<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Watchdog Transparency Blog - Most recent 5 featured articles</title>
        <description>Most recent 5 articles categorized as 'Featured'</description>
        <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com</link>
        <atom:link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.featured.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 13:01:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>


        
        <item>
            <title>We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>Coronavirus</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed concerns about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>featured</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections.  An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/indicators/unemployment/&quot;&gt;skyrocketing &lt;/a&gt;unemployment.  To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;permitted &lt;/a&gt;companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>Red Flags</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Is it Safer to Invest in China or the U.S.?</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>gray swan event</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;The China based coffee company Luckin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt; a massive fraud on April 2nd, and only five days later, another China based company TAL Education, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1499620/000110465920044459/tm2015354d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales.  A decade ago, a wave of Chinese companies were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20&quot;&gt;exposed &lt;/a&gt;as frauds, which damaged China’s reputation.  The confluence of Luckin’s fraud with news that the Chinese lied about coronavirus has damaged China’s reputation once again as many people have come to believe that investing in Chinese companies is too risky.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-06T16:01:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_it%20it%20safer%20to%20invest%20in%20china%20or%20us.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>BorgWarner Wants to Dump Delphi.  Will Delphi’s Resistance be Futile?</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>Coronavirus</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;With the coronavirus shutting down entire industries and raising the possibility of an extended recession, pending mergers are in peril, and mergers overall will become disfavored as companies lose their appetite for risk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-04-08T09:31:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/borger.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/</guid>
        </item>
        

    </channel>
</rss>

