<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Watchdog Transparency Blog - Most recent 5 featured articles</title>
        <description>Most recent 5 articles categorized as 'Featured'</description>
        <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com</link>
        <atom:link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.featured.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 09:26:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>

        <item>
            <title>
                Hunter Biden: Was He Paid Appropriately as an Independent Director?
            </title>
            <author>John Cheffers</author>
            <category>featured</category>
            <description>
                <p><em>Burisma is a private company and Reuters <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trump-whistleblower-burisma-factb/factbox-burisma-the-obscure-ukrainian-gas-company-at-the-heart-of-u-s-political-row-idUSKBN1W91UG">estimates</a> that it only brings in $400 million a year in revenue. In our analysis, we would expect an independent director like Hunter Biden to make between $55,000—$83,000 a year at Burisma. If Hunter made $83,333 a month as reported by Reuters, then he made over 12 times what a typical independent director at a private company would make.</em></p>
            </description>
            <pubDate>2019-11-15T05:48:00-05:00</pubDate>
            <link>
                https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/
            </link>
            <enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/hunter_biden.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">
                https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/
            </guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Kraft Heinz: Warren Buffet's Dunkirk</title>
            <author>John Cheffers</author>
            <category>featured</category>
            <description>
                <p>Every investor makes mistakes when it comes to valuing an acquisition. However, the dramatic decline in market value of Kraft Heinz Co. (“KHC”) is not simply about failing to properly value KHC, or failing to manage the Company to meet growth expectations, it is about a collapse of confidence in the reliability of financial disclosures. Warren Buffet’s well-earned reputation as a great fundamental analyst cannot be questioned, but he rarely gets caught up with investments that present evidence of ethical and transparency challenges. And if he does, he is known to fix them quickly. KHC is the exception to this rule and it is a failure of such magnitude that it could over-shadow Buffet’s long-term reputation as a champion of good governance.</p>
            </description>
            <pubDate>2019-09-16T16:42:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>
                https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/
            </link>
            <enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/dundirk.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">
                https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/
            </guid>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Early Retirement for Target's CFO</title>
            <author>Joseph Burke</author>
            <category>featured</category>
            <description>
                <p>Updated November 21, 2019: We are updating our original blog on Target. First, we note that Ms. Cathy Smith, stepped-down officially on November 1, 2019 and her replacement was named at the same time. Specifically, her replacement is a Target insider. At a time we believe a new and fresh perspective about Target’s PPE is needed, Target went the other way and appointed Michael J. Fiddelke, 43, as Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. Mr. Fiddelke appears to have originally joined Target as a 29 year-old and has stayed loyal to Target since then.</p>
            </description>
            <pubDate>2019-11-21T16:21:00-05:00</pubDate>
            <link>
                https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-concerns-target/
            </link>
            <enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Target.png" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">
                https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-concerns-target/
            </guid>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Under Armour III: Major CFO Change Was a Warning Sign of Litigation</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
                
                    <category>featured</category>
                

                <description>&lt;p&gt;CFOs play an outsized role in the financial health of a company.  When a CFO leaves abruptly or under bad circumstances, that event can have far reaching implications.  Lawrence “Chip” Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was as damaging as it was sudden and mysterious.  Within a year after being brought in from as an outsider, he had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691717000008/january312017form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;resigned&lt;/a&gt; for “personal reasons.”  In his wake there was litigation, an SEC investigation only recently brought to light, and—of course—more litigation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>2020-03-25T09:26:00-04:00</pubDate>
                <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/</guid>
            </item><item>
                <title>Under Armour II: CAM Raises the Specter of “Channel Stuffing”</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
                
                    <category>Red Flags</category>
                

                <description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; piece on Under Armour (UA) we looked at how a dramatic increase in non-audit fees by PriceWaterhouseCoopers (PWC) was a sign of financial problems and a leading indicator of litigation. We also briefly examined UA’s SEC investigation, which was first reported on by the Wall Street Journal.  This investigation has remained somewhat mysterious and UA has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/under-armour-says-its-accounting-practices-have-been-entirely-appropriate-after-wsj-story-2019-11-15&quot;&gt;denied&lt;/a&gt; any wrongdoing.  Thanks to the newly required disclosures of Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), we are getting some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>2020-03-17T14:48:00-04:00</pubDate>
                <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/clothes_stack.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/</guid>
            </item><item>
                <title>Under Armour I: Troubling Spike in Non-Audit Fees Went Ignored</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
                
                    <category>Leading Indicators</category>
                

                <description>&lt;p&gt;Under Armour still has not recovered from a serious blow it suffered in early November 2019 when the Wall Street Journal reported that the company had been under investigation by the SEC for its accounting practices.  One element of the story that rattled investors was that the investigation had been going on since July &lt;em&gt;of 2017&lt;/em&gt;, yet it had not been addressed in a transparent way by management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>2020-03-13T11:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
                <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/under_armour_non_audit_fees.png" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/</guid>
            </item><item>
                <title>UPDATE Nine Critical Days in Hunter Biden’s Time on the Burisma Board</title><author>Brian Lawe</author>
                
                    <category>featured</category>
                

                <description>&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: AG Bondi’s Presentation Adds More Facts and Raises More Questions&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>2020-01-17T06:18:00-05:00</pubDate>
                <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/oligarch.png" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/</guid>
            </item><item>
                <title>The Practice of Reverse Factoring Raises Transparency Concerns</title><author>Olga Usvyatsky</author>
                
                    <category>featured</category>
                

                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here at Watchdog, we are firm believers in transparency, and we take a critical look at any accounting procedures which tend to make financial disclosures opaque.  This guest blog on reverse factoring was contributed by Olga Usvyatsky, a former VP of Research at Audit Analytics.  She has a distinguished library of blogs and op-eds on accounting, buy-side research, and data analysis. Ms. Usvyatsky is currently enrolled as a PhD in Accounting student at Boston College, where she earned her MS in Accounting degree.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>2020-01-07T12:37:00-05:00</pubDate>
                <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/reverse_factoring.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/</guid>
            </item>

    </channel>
</rss>

