<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-17T09:59:02-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: Fraud Enabled by Slack Standards</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: Fraud Enabled by Slack Standards" /><published>2020-06-16T15:41:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-16T15:41:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/">&lt;p&gt;Luckin Coffee engaged in one of the most brazen frauds in history. It is easy to blame the fraud on the business environment in China fostered by the CCP. But this fraud could not have occurred if not for systemic weaknesses in the Western capital markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Enron scandal, Sarbanes Oxley was passed to create stringent new standards that would deter future frauds. Auditors were supposed to play a key role in enforcing these new stringent standards. Publicly traded companies had to pay their independent auditors to offer an opinion on whether the internal controls of a company were effective (requiring the auditors to test management’s financial reporting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, the Obama administration signed bipartisan legislation relieving some companies of the obligation to get this opinion from their auditors. This change lowered the costs associated with taking a company public, and eased access to capital for many businesses. The White House &lt;a href=&quot;https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/blog/2012/04/05/jobs-act-encouraging-startups-supporting-small-businesses&quot;&gt;promised&lt;/a&gt; that this bill “will help encourage startups and support &lt;em&gt;our nation’s&lt;/em&gt; small businesses.” (emphasis added) But this law did not just apply to American businesses, it applied to all businesses, including those in foreign countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem? If an American company takes advantage of the relaxed requirements and commits fraud, they take a significant risk that they will ultimately be exposed and go to jail or get sued. But when a well-connected company in an emerging market, like China, engages in fraud, there is no &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;recourse&lt;/a&gt; for investors. It is even &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;possible&lt;/a&gt; that some level of fraud is encouraged by the people in power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging more investment in American businesses might be an important enough public policy goal to justify the increased risk of fraud that comes with loosening standards, but there is no such public policy justification for loosening standards for companies in emerging markets with structurally weak regulatory systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Congress Lowered Standards in 2012&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congress wanted to increase economic growth by easing access to capital markets for companies that are were often considered too small to take public. To create this ease of access, they created a new category of company, called an Emerging Growth Company (EGC) in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/112/hr3606/summary#libraryofcongress&quot;&gt;JOBS Act&lt;/a&gt; in 2012. Generally, an EGC is one that has less than a billion dollars in revenue and less than $700 million in equity. If a company remains under the revenue threshold, it can keep its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/smallbusiness/goingpublic/EGC&quot;&gt;EGC&lt;/a&gt; status for up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EGC is only required to provide two years of audited statements (instead of three), and less extensive disclosure on executive compensation, and it can delay compliance with new accounting standards. But perhaps the biggest advantage of EGC status is an exemption from receiving a SOX 404(b) opinion, where the independent auditor attests that management’s “internal controls” over financial reporting are effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;internal controls&lt;/a&gt;” are the first line of defense against fraud and human error. Management is supposed to install a system that aids employees in routinely recording the economic activity of the company in a way that is both accurate and comprehensible.  The controls should also ensure that neither employees nor management misuses company assets or manipulates results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management has an inherent interest in creating effective internal controls over its employees, but not necessarily for itself.   In fact, management often has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-complaint-cites-watchdog-researchs-analysis/&quot;&gt;conflict of interest&lt;/a&gt;. The Enron scandal is just one example of how management can easily succumb to the temptation to manipulate results. Policymakers created the SOX 404(b) attestation requirement so that independent auditors would look over the shoulders of management and help ensure that management’s internal controls were effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost for a SOX 404(b) opinion varies, but it can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schgroup.com/resource/blog-post/sarbanes-oxley-404b-compliance-a-refresher-of-the-initial-questions-you-should-be-asking/&quot;&gt;exceed&lt;/a&gt; $2 million a year, especially at the early stages of implementation. The high cost is due to the independent auditor testing and evaluating the internal controls on financial reporting throughout the year, a time consuming and expensive process (although likely much lower in a labor market like China). This extensive year-round testing makes concealing a large-scale fraud far more difficult for management.  Luckin’s auditor Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/luckin-coffee-anatomy-of-an-auditor&quot;&gt;uncoverd &lt;/a&gt;the fraud, and would have probably have detected the inflated revenues and costs even earlier if it had been testing the internal controls throughout the year.   However, Luckin was classified as an EGC, and therefore, EYHM did not offer an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746919003174/a2238747z424b4.htm&quot;&gt;opinion&lt;/a&gt; on their internal controls and did not do the requisite testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;The Company is not required to have, nor were we engaged to perform, an audit of its internal control over financial reporting.&lt;/strong&gt; As part of our audits we are required to obtain an understanding of internal control over financial reporting but not for the purpose of expressing an opinion on the effectiveness of the Company’s internal control over financial reporting. &lt;strong&gt;Accordingly, we express no such opinion&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SOX 404(b) Attestation Has a Real Impact on the Quality of Internal Controls&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though SOX was passed with the idea that it would cover every company, implementation for small issuers (those with less than $75 million in market cap) were initially given an exemption, and eventually &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;permanently&lt;/a&gt; exempted by the Dodd Frank Act in 2010. An investigation was done by the Government Accountability Office (GAO) in 2012 to see if the SOX 404(b) requirement had any effect on the quality of internal controls. The GAO studied restatement rates between companies that had met the SOX 404(b) requirement (either by law or voluntarily) and those that did not; the results indicated that companies without the SOX 404(b) requirement had weaker controls and therefore filed more restatements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LK%20GAO%20EGC%206.16.png&quot; alt=&quot;LK GAO EGC 6.16.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This indicates that the SOX 404(b) attestation requirement improves the quality of the internal controls at a company.&lt;/strong&gt; In its conclusion the GAO report (which used data provided by Audit Analytics) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;concluded&lt;/a&gt; that the SOX 404(b) attestation “may be useful for investors in gauging the reliability of a company’s financial reporting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By permitting EGCs an exemption to the SOX 404(b) attestation, Congress may have unintentionally lowered the quality of internal controls. Luckin is just one particularly bad example. Consider it this way, if a company makes a big splash with an IPO, and the company is too big to be considered a “small” issuer (with less than $75 million in market cap), then it probably needs &lt;em&gt;extra&lt;/em&gt; scrutiny, not less.  Instead EGCs get a pass. We are troubled about the implications of EGC status in the West. But we are positively alarmed by the implications of EGC status in Chinese companies, where real enforcement is effectively &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;impossible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin took advantage of its EGC status to forego a SOX 404(b) auditor attestation, but they are not alone. Our analysts compared all Chinese companies trading on the Nadsaq, NYSE, and OTC exchanges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/China%20EGC%20numbers.png&quot; alt=&quot;China EGC numbers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysts determined that 53% of listed Chinese companies listed on the Nasdaq, NYSE, and OTC exchanges were classified as EGCs. The collective market cap for these companies is over $65 billion. This may only represent a little less than 5% of the total value of all Chinese based companies traded on U.S. exchanges, but it is still a significant sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have been quick to blame the auditors Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP for not uncovering this fraud earlier. But can people really blame EYHM when it was Congress who loosened the restrictions so that EYHM would not vigorously test and evaluate the internal controls at Luckin? (The issues surrounding EY in this story are very complex and we will give them their own treatment another time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EGCs essentially have no oversight until the auditor arrives to conduct the year-end audit. &lt;strong&gt;That means the current bill passed by the Senate&lt;/strong&gt; that would delist companies whose auditors are not subject to inspection by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;PCAOB&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;would not have stopped the fraud at Luckin&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;even if the CCP acquiesced to inspections&lt;/strong&gt; by the regulator. As it stands now, foreign companies in emerging markets that are considered EGCs have a one-year period where they can fabricate numbers before the auditors come to check their books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public policy makers should be concerned that other foreign companies like Luckin may attempt to use EGC status to run short term scams on the capital markets.  It would be a good step to insist that every company from an emerging market meet the SOX 404(b) requirement before listing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="China" /><category term="Sarbanes Oxley" /><category term="EGC" /><summary type="html">Luckin Coffee engaged in one of the most brazen frauds in history. It is easy to blame the fraud on the business environment in China fostered by the CCP. But this fraud could not have occurred if not for systemic weaknesses in the Western capital markets.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/fraud_luckin_standard.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/fraud_luckin_standard.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: Clash Over the PCAOB</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: Clash Over the PCAOB" /><published>2020-06-15T16:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-15T16:31:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/">&lt;p&gt;In April, just as the America was in the grip of the coronavirus originating from Wuhan, Luckin Coffee initially reported that it had discovered a fraud by the COO fabricating over half of the company’s revenue. We wrote an in-depth &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; arguing the fraud was far more pervasive. Since then, Luckin has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920063497/a20-20057_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt;, the WSJ wrote an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/behind-the-fall-of-chinas-luckin-coffee-a-network-of-fake-buyers-and-a-fictitious-employee-11590682336&quot;&gt;exposé&lt;/a&gt; detailing far more extensive fraud than originally reported, the CEO was also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920059927/a20-19256_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;implicated&lt;/a&gt; by Luckin, and now Luckin’s chairman and founder is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2020/06/08/why-luckin-coffee-stock-dropped-today.aspx&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; facing charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin’s massive fraud hints at systemic problems in the Chinese markets. At the root, there is a fundamental difference in how financial information is perceived in the West to how it is perceived by the Chinese Communist Party (CCP). The West holds that financial information should be shared with the investing public, and there are several safeguards to ensure that the information is accurate. For the CCP, financial information is a tool used to meet the goals of the Party. Luckin’s fraud raises the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/2018-06-05/block-says-chinese-equities-are-sin-stocks-video&quot;&gt;possibility&lt;/a&gt; that the CCP has allowed or even encouraged Chinese companies to bilk money out of Western investors as a point of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;policy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, this story has reignited a dormant dispute between China and the U.S. about the regulatory oversight of Chinese auditors. Even though some Chinese audit firms in China are registered with the PCAOB, including affiliates of the Big 4, the CCP has not permitted the PCAOB to conduct investigations of any of its auditors. We consider this so significant that our reports assign a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/&quot;&gt;red flag&lt;/a&gt; to any company whose auditor is not subject to meaningful supervision by the PCAOB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the fraud at Luckin, the Senate unanimously passed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/bill-that-could-delist-chinese-companies-from-us-stock-exchanges-to-see-swift-passage-in-house-analyst-says-2020-05-21&quot;&gt;bill &lt;/a&gt;that would delist any companies from U.S. exchanges whose auditors were not subject to inspection by the PCAOB. As a practical matter, this could result in the delisting of Chinese companies worth over a trillion dollars and trigger a big kerfuffle in U.S.-Sino relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;China’s Longstanding Refusal to Allow Oversight of Their Auditors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Enron scandal, Congress created the PCAOB.  The PCAOB ia a quasi-independent regulator that provides oversight of audit firms; every publicly traded company on a U.S. exchange must have an auditor registered with the PCAOB. The PCAOB conducts inspections of these auditors and can deregister them if they do not meet professional standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCAOB’s influence has expanded internationally, as many countries have &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/International/Pages/RegulatoryCooperation.aspx&quot;&gt;agreements&lt;/a&gt; where the PCAOB will conduct joint inspections with the regulators from other countries to assure every nation has the same high standards for its auditors. China has never agreed to allow these inspections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead the CCP has steadily tightened its grip on the profession. In 2012, the CCP &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/business/la-xpm-2012-may-10-la-fi-china-auditing-rules-20120511-story.html&quot;&gt;ordered&lt;/a&gt; the Big Four affiliates to phase in Chinese nationals to replace foreigners in senior management. And just this year, the CCP passed a law &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/u-s-moves-to-audit-chinese-firms-market-frets-over-what-comes-next-11590485401&quot;&gt;outlawing&lt;/a&gt; cooperating with foreign regulators without express permission. It is very likely that many of the senior partners in these affiliates are Party members, potentially undermining their professional integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China’s refusal to allow PCAOB inspections first came to a head after systemic fraud was revealed in Chinese companies that had accessed U.S. markets via reverse merger. Oftentimes these were shell companies without any actual operations. Even the most cursory oversight would have prevented many of these companies from defrauding investors. In the wake of the reverse merger wave, there was a huge outcry from investors to have more oversight of Chinese firms. The CCP flatly refused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Impotence in the Face of CCP Defiance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2012, concerns over the lack of oversight were coming to a head. The SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/francinemckenna/2011/10/21/auditors-in-china-a-whole-lot-of-posturing-going-on/#cede5ff3f239&quot;&gt;sued&lt;/a&gt; the Big Four affiliates in China for their refusal to hand over their work papers for inspection. However, the affiliates had never promised to hand over their work papers for inspection because it is the policy of the CCP that these papers were “state secrets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Westerners may have scoffed at this idea, but for an authoritarian regime like the CCP, all information is the state’s business. The CCP will never permit accurate and truthful numbers to be recorded and transmitted to its own people and to the West; even something as innocuous as a balance sheet can cause a revolution because truth always poses a danger to propagandists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC and PCAOB did not have the clout to force the CCP to change its position, which left them with a dilemma. Either they could take decisive action and potentially delist all the Chinese companies listed on the U.S. exchanges and deprive every multinational company of the ability to have its Chinese operations audited by a registered affiliate, or they could largely give in while making a few face-saving gestures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC gave in.  No one should have been surprised either, the public policy implications of enforcing the rules were too broad. Decisions concerning international relations are public policy decisions that require leadership in Washington. The administration at that time had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/08/opinion/chinas-rise-isnt-our-demise.html&quot;&gt;expressed&lt;/a&gt; support for closer investment links with China, rendering untenable any course of action that would have alienated the CCP. So, the SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/pressrelease/2015-25.html#:\~:text=SEC%20Imposes%20Sanctions%20Against%20China%2DBased%20Members%20of%20Big%20Four,for%20Refusing%20to%20Produce%20Documents&amp;amp;text=The%20Securities%20and%20Exchange%20Commission,to%20investigations%20of%20potential%20fraud.&quot;&gt;settled&lt;/a&gt; their case for $2 million and the PCAOB signed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://upload.news.esnai.com/2013/0617/1371444412766.pdf&quot;&gt;Memorandum of Understanding&lt;/a&gt; that allowed Chinese firms to register in exchange for vague promises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, those vague promises never amounted to anything. Recently, with the new administration, the SEC and the PCAOB seemed to be more willing to discuss their concerns with China. They issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-vital-role-audit-quality-and-regulatory-access-audit-and-other&quot;&gt;joint&lt;/a&gt; statement warning investors that Chinese firms were not subject to proper oversight, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/regulators-revive-china-audit-dispute-but-miss-prime-opportunity-to-fully-explain-why-2018-12-12&quot;&gt;failed&lt;/a&gt; to full explain the issues involved or do anything to correct the problem. This Caveat Emptor attitude is incongruous with current American customs and law, since economic liberalism and the robber barons it spawned have been confined to the dustbin of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for several years Chinese audit firms have been permitted to register with the PCAOB, even though they are not subject to inspections. This has worked well for Chinese companies, who get a premium price for listing on U.S. exchanges, and it has worked well for Chinese audit firms who register with the PCAOB since they also can charge a &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3111973&quot;&gt;premium&lt;/a&gt;. Whenever a fraud is revealed, individual investors are left holding the bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without leadership from Washington on this issue, nothing could change. There had been some talk over the years, but it had not yielded any fruit. For example, Sen. Marco Rubio &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/you-cant-trust-a-chinese-audit-11559687739&quot;&gt;touted&lt;/a&gt; the EQUITABLE Act last year, a bill he introduced that would have potentially delisted Chinese companies if their auditors were not subject to inspection. But the bill languished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one small step that SEC and the PCAOB took after the Luckin story broke was to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-kingsoft-cloud-ipo/kingsoft-sets-terms-for-u-s-listing-first-major-ipo-since-coronavirus-crisis-idUSKBN22G2JB&quot;&gt;require&lt;/a&gt; companies in China to disclose the fact that their auditors are not subject to inspections by the PCAOB in all relevant financial statements.  Buyer Beware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leadership in Washington?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That changed in May, when the Senate &lt;em&gt;unanimously&lt;/em&gt; passed a bill that would delist Chinese companies unless the CCP permits the PCAOB to oversee their auditors. Frankly, we were shocked when this bill was passed because it takes real steps to address a real problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed this bill passed because of the confluence of two stories: first, the emergence of the coronavirus from Wuhan coupled with credible reports that the CCP’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2020/05/06/finally-the-world-is-catching-on-to-chinas-coronavirus-lies/&quot;&gt;lies&lt;/a&gt; had made the impact of the virus worse, and second, the disclosure of a massive fraud at Luckin. Public opinion turned decisively &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/global/2020/04/21/u-s-views-of-china-increasingly-negative-amid-coronavirus-outbreak/&quot;&gt;against&lt;/a&gt; China, creating the perfect environment for this bill to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unclear if this ostensibly bipartisan bill will be introduced and passed in the House of Representatives. The moment has passed. Reports on riots have finally displaced the unceasing coverage of the coronavirus which had monopolized the airwaves for months. The CCP looks as if it will arrest Charles Lu, the chairman and founder of Luckin, since people were not satisfied with the COO as a scapegoat (nor with the CEO who was served up a month later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a powerful lobby that would like to see this bill scrapped, or at least neutered either in its final form or its enforcement. Many investors know that the CCP will not budge on this issue, but they are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2020/05/22/read-before-selling-all-us-listed-chinese-stock.aspx&quot;&gt;guessing&lt;/a&gt; that Washington will fold. If there is a change in the White House in November it is unlikely that this bill, and the hardline on the CCP that it represents, will last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Issue Unaddressed by the Bill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bill may be helpful for investors, but it omits a crucially important issue. Francine Mckenna, an independent reporter whose work is now available on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, has pointed out more than &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/regulators-revive-china-audit-dispute-but-miss-prime-opportunity-to-fully-explain-why-2018-12-12&quot;&gt;once&lt;/a&gt; that multinational companies like Pfizer and Walmart rely on Chinese audit firms to conduct the audits of their Chinese operations. This means that there are potential &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-chinese-blind-spot-in-u-s-companies-financials-1532170801?mod=article_inline&quot;&gt;blind-spots&lt;/a&gt; in the audits of some of the biggest and most important companies in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns about the Chinese operations of multinational companies are warranted, and the senate bill does nothing to address that issue. However, this problem may already have an informal albeit makeshift solution. Even though the Chinese audit firms are supposed to do everything locally, it is likely that they &lt;a href=&quot;http://retheauditors.com/2012/07/09/what-the-sec-and-pcaob-fail-to-acknowledge-about-chinese-fraud/&quot;&gt;consult&lt;/a&gt; with their U.S. counterparts when doing a multinational audit. This probably allows the Big Four to exercise some influence over their foreign affiliates in China, even if the official story is that no “sensitive” work-papers ever cross borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shockingly, the Senate has passed a bill that could actually protect investors. However, there is undoubtedly pressure from pro-China lobbyists to scrap the essence of the bill in exchange for some token victory. This victory could be the arrest of Charles Lu or perhaps some “corrupt” CCP officials who supported him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the bill passes, it may not have the effect intended. Chinese companies incorporated in the U.S. or in Tax Havens and only attached to the Chinese operations through contractual agreements (most “Chinese” companies already have one of these “VIE” arrangements) may be permitted to stay on the exchanges without any PCAOB oversight of their auditors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the U.S. wants to really ensure that Chinese companies have proper oversight, Washington must continue to lead and show resolve. However, the stories that drove the passage of this bill are already fading from memory and Washington is a place where resolve is in short supply…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="Legislation" /><summary type="html">In April, just as the America was in the grip of the coronavirus originating from Wuhan, Luckin Coffee initially reported that it had discovered a fraud by the COO fabricating over half of the company’s revenue. We wrote an in-depth report arguing the fraud was far more pervasive. Since then, Luckin has been delisted, the WSJ wrote an exposé detailing far more extensive fraud than originally reported, the CEO was also implicated by Luckin, and now Luckin’s chairman and founder is reportedly facing charges.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_America%20Runs%20From%20Luckin_Clash%20Over%20PCAOB.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_America%20Runs%20From%20Luckin_Clash%20Over%20PCAOB.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Symantec Complaint Cites Watchdog Research’s Analysis</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-complaint-cites-watchdog-researchs-analysis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Symantec Complaint Cites Watchdog Research’s Analysis" /><published>2020-06-09T14:20:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T14:20:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-complaint-cites-watchdog-researchs-analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-complaint-cites-watchdog-researchs-analysis/">&lt;p&gt;In February 2018, we published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-flashback-what-happened/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; calling out the management of Symantec for a perceived lack of candor in the way they handled a whistleblower report of accounting irregularities and a subsequent SEC investigation. In particular, we honed-in on Symantec’s failure to disclose any material weakness in their internal controls and their dubious claim that a $12 million adjustment in revenue in 2018 was immaterial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis was quoted in a securities lawsuit, &lt;em&gt;Felix v. Symantec Corp.&lt;/em&gt; (N. D. Cal.) Here is the entire quote as it appears in the complaint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Symantec%20Complaint.png&quot; alt=&quot;Symantec Complaint.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Symantec’s Questionable Revenue Recognition Methods&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MarketWatch’s Francine Mckenna, an independent reporter who now has her own website, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/companies-are-using-ghost-revenue-to-calculate-executive-bonuses-2017-11-06&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; in November 2017 that Symantec was using non-GAAP methods to add back in deferred revenue after an acquisition. After that report, a whistle-blower came forward and accused Symantec of inappropriately adjusting revenue to boost executive compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This non-GAAP accounting allegedly allowed Symantec’s management to pull out saved revenue and add it in when it suited their purposes. The plaintiff in this case accuses Symantec’s executives of deferring revenue when results were good and adding it back in when results were poor. This would potentially have allowed executives to hit certain compensation benchmarks and greatly increase how much money they were paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these accusations are true, then this is a great example of how performance bonuses can create a conflict of interest for management. The same people responsible for accurately and truthfully reporting the financial condition of the company also stand to personally benefit the most from potential manipulation of the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using deferred revenue is only one potential path that executives can take to manipulate results and enrich themselves. In another post we discussed how UA may have been manipulating revenue by “&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;channel stuffing&lt;/a&gt;.” A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.terry.uga.edu/articles/ceos_are_turning_a_negative_into_a_payout_study_finds/&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; also indicated that some executives have been timing the release of bad news so that their company stock prices are artificially lowered when they receive their stock options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management’s conflict of interest reinforces the crucial role that independent board members play as watchdogs for the company. It is crucial that board members are truly independent from management, by both the letter and spirit of the law, so that they can deter and discover any manipulation in financial reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the Litigation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we wrote our analysis of Symantec, we wanted to promote transparency and responsibility for investors, not to aide in litigation per se. But plaintiff’s attorneys can also serve as watchdogs to protect the interests of investors and we consider it a compliment that our reports and independent analysis are being cited in securities litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Gray Swan Event Factor and Watchdog Reports are tools that allow investors to understand the inherent risks in their investments and potentially hold management accountable. It is our hope that if management is tempted to massage or manipulate the numbers for their own gain, that they will be deterred by potential scrutiny from independent board members, auditors, activist shareholders, regulators, plaintiff’s attorneys, and Watchdog Research. This accountability for management is crucial to protect the financial health of our companies and is in the best interests of all shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Symantec" /><category term="Litigation" /><category term="Revenue Recognition" /><summary type="html">In February 2018, we published a report calling out the management of Symantec for a perceived lack of candor in the way they handled a whistleblower report of accounting irregularities and a subsequent SEC investigation. In particular, we honed-in on Symantec’s failure to disclose any material weakness in their internal controls and their dubious claim that a $12 million adjustment in revenue in 2018 was immaterial.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/symantec_manipulation.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/symantec_manipulation.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Symantec FLASHBACK “What happened?”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-flashback-what-happened/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Symantec FLASHBACK “What happened?”" /><published>2020-06-08T10:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-08T10:33:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-flashback-what-happened</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-flashback-what-happened/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We originally published this report in February 1, 2019 to FactSet. We are now republishing it on our blog since it was referenced and quoted in a securities lawsuit against Symantec, which has since changed its name to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/cgi-bin/browse-edgar?action=getcompany&amp;amp;CIK=0000849399&amp;amp;owner=exclude&amp;amp;count=40&quot;&gt;NortonLifeLock Inc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symantec Announced Earnings: On-time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last three quarters Symantec has been posting non-timely filings with the SEC. On January 31, 2019, as planned, they announced their earnings. We expect they are now on-schedule to make regular SEC filings. And that’s a good thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watchdog’s Concerns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were called and asked to look at Symantec ahead of its 3rd quarter earnings call January 31. We see a company that had a whistleblower identify a revenue recognition fraud problem. We see a company that the SEC is still investigating with potential for major civil litigation (e.g. fines). We see a company under shareholder class action litigation for securities fraud, but a company that appears to have made no material reserves for either the SEC litigation or class action suits. We see a company with massive intangibles and goodwill on its balance sheet, with no reasonable history of impairments. We heard several analysts’ question inconsistencies related to Symantec’s revenue on its Jan. 31 earnings call. The CFO also just announced his resignation. The next CFO will be the fifth in five years. We also read about new but conflicting officer-level roles including Chief Accounting Officer and Chief Compliance Officer. And most surprising, amidst all these challenges, this company has consistently reported effective disclosure controls and no material weaknesses in their accounting even AFTER they disclosed their revenue recognition breach and after they issued their 10k five months late!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symantec should remember what every mom and dad teaches their kids about reputation being the most important thing to have. Right now, trust and reputation are the most important things for Symantec and its investors. That trust and reputation took a beating May 10, 2018 when Symantec’s stock plunged 33% in one day based on a whistle blower’s accounting concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symantec’s accounting breach was announced on May 10, 2018 with this disclosure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“ …in connection with concerns raised by a former employee regarding the company’s public disclosures, including commentary on historical financial results; its reporting of certain non-GAAP measures…The Audit Committee has retained independent counsel and other advisers to assist in its investigation… It is unlikely that the investigation will be completed in time for the company to file its annual report on Form 10-K…&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Audit Committee apparently did its job investigating and disclosing SYMC’s failure in properly accounting for $12 million in wrongly recognized revenue, (Press Release Sept. 24, 2018) we still find fault with Symantec’s Auditor, CEO and CFO, who all failed to acknowledge what are plainly ineffective internal controls and material weaknesses in Symantec’s reporting systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our readers know management must attest to its own internal controls each quarter (302 statements) and the company’s auditor must also attest to the company’s internal controls once a year (404b statements). Each quarter since the May 10, 2018 breach announcement, SYMC’s CEO and CFO have stated they have “effective controls” in place, as they did most recently Nov. 11, 2018:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Based on such evaluation, our Chief Executive Officer and our Chief Financial Officer have concluded that our disclosure controls and procedures were effective at the reasonable assurance level as of the end of the period covered by this report.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SYMC filed their annual report five months late on Oct. 26, 2018, after acknowledging a revenue recognition breach, yet its auditor KPMG also gave the company an “effective” controls statement (and did NOT amend or restate it):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Also in our opinion, the Company maintained, in all material respects, effective internal control over financial reporting as of March 30, 2018…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If reputation matters, &lt;em&gt;and it does&lt;/em&gt;, both filing five months late and false revenue recognition are indicators for any CEO, CFO or auditor to admit to glaring failures and weakness with their company’s internal controls. Further regarding the $12 million revenue recognition breach: We note management and the auditor did not require SYMC to file any restatements and they have not announced any out-of-period adjustments regarding the issue. You would expect that a $12 million revenue recognition fraud would be reported at least as an out-of-period adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any irregularities in accounting are material because they raise questions about the potential for failure or weakness in the personnel and/or systems used for a company’s accounting. In this case, it might seem a $12 million revenue recognition issue would be immaterial. But that would be false. Symantec reported $49 million in operating income in 2018. If the $49 million was reduced by the $12 million, that still means the $12 million had an impact of 20% on operating income – excluding any millions spent on the investigation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not the only watchdogs concerned about SYMC’s reputation and the false revenue recognition issue. The SEC’s last letters to/from SYMC were chockfull of issues. See [infra].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, we know from Symantec’s Sept. 24, 2018 announcement concluding their internal investigation, that the SEC IS continuing its own investigation into the revenue recognition breach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“As previously disclosed in our public filings, the Audit Committee has recently completed its internal investigation. In connection with the Audit Committee Investigation, we voluntarily contacted the SEC in May 2018. &lt;strong&gt;The SEC commenced a formal investigation and we continue to cooperate with that investigation.&lt;/strong&gt; ”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC could level fines or officer suspensions once their investigation concludes. Outside investors have also filed multiple class action and derivative lawsuits against the company. The company disclosed the suits in their 10q’s, but they appear to not have any material reserves set aside for the suits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Several securities class action and derivative lawsuits were filed against us following our announcement on May 10, 2018 …If any of the lawsuits related to our Audit Committee Investigation are decided adversely, we may be liable for significant damages … At this stage, we are unable to assess whether any material loss or adverse effect is reasonably possible as a result of these lawsuits or estimate the range of any potential loss.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 11, 2018 SYMC lost $4 billion in market cap. Yet it is accruing ZERO for lawsuits. How difficult is it to assume the company should be accruing a significant amount to potentially settle pending lawsuits for an acknowledged issue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We keep mentioning a management’s reputation for accounting disclosures is vitally important. Symantec’s balance sheet shows why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember those old accounting classes when you first heard about “Goodwill”? You probably learned “Goodwill” was the cost of an acquisition above the book value and beyond the amount attributed to specific intangibles. In essence, ‘Goodwill” is nothing more than a management judgement call. If you are relying on management’s judgement about goodwill and that goodwill is HUGE, you better trust management’s judgement. Symantec’s management assigned $10.8 billion (yes, billion) of their total $16.2 billion in assets to goodwill plus intangibles (67%). More interesting, goodwill and intangibles account for 75% of the total market cap value of Symantec. Can you trust that management got that number right? Could or should they be making adjustments (impairments) to goodwill based on the known weak internal controls and revenue recognition issues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this: Symantec disclosed one recent $29 million impairment to its Property, Plant and Equipment assets. A $29 million impairment on total PPE of $778 million is 3.7%. Now imagine the reasonable case where SYMC realizes the revenue recognition issue emanated from one of its recent large acquisitions. As such, they would rationally think to make an impairment of goodwill for that company’s goodwill. What if they took a 3.7% impairment on the $4 billion assigned to goodwill for Blue Coat? That would equal a $148 million impairment. Such an impairment would represent 3x their 2018 operating income of $49 million!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, Symantec’s valuation and reputation took a massive hit on May 10, 2018 and it has yet to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It likely will NOT recover and management will not restore its market value until they step-up and take full responsibility for the revenue recognition fraud at the company. That will mean disclosing ineffective financial controls and building a culture that demands rigor and the highest ethics and reliability for their financial controls and reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Symantec" /><category term="Goodwill" /><category term="Lawsuits" /><category term="Revenue Recognition" /><summary type="html">We originally published this report in February 1, 2019 to FactSet. We are now republishing it on our blog since it was referenced and quoted in a securities lawsuit against Symantec, which has since changed its name to NortonLifeLock Inc.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/symantec.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/symantec.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armor Goodwill Impairment Due to Coronavirus or Preexisting Conditions?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armor-goodwill-impairment-due-to-coronavirus-or-preexisting-conditions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armor Goodwill Impairment Due to Coronavirus or Preexisting Conditions?" /><published>2020-06-03T10:23:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T10:23:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armor-goodwill-impairment-due-to-coronavirus-or-preexisting-conditions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armor-goodwill-impairment-due-to-coronavirus-or-preexisting-conditions/">&lt;p&gt;In our previous piece “&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;Birds of a Feather: How to Tell a Gray Swan from a Black Swan&lt;/a&gt;,” we discussed how difficult it may be to spot when a company disingenuously blames an impairment of goodwill on the effects of the coronavirus, as opposed to righfuly blaming it on preexisting conditions at the company. We then &lt;em&gt;specifically&lt;/em&gt; mentioned Under Armour’s (UA) Latin American reporting unit as one to watch because PwC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm&quot;&gt;highlighted&lt;/a&gt; the goodwill impairment testing of that specific reporting unit as requiring particularly “&lt;em&gt;challenging, subjective, or complex judgements&lt;/em&gt;” in its Critical Audit Matters (CAMs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did not have much confidence in management’s valuation which estimated that the fair market value of the Latin American reporting unit exceeded the carrying value by 19%. In fact, we said, “&lt;em&gt;UA seems like they are trying to impress us with the precision of their measurements and soundness of their methods, but our experience tells us that these numbers are more showmanship than science.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not easy to valuate goodwill, small changes in variables can have a big impact, and those variables are often subjective. Weighing the variables properly requires a great deal of judgement. Because they can be so subjective, valuations are easier to massage or manipulate. Accusations of manipulated valuations lie at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;heart&lt;/a&gt; of a recent derivative suit concerning Kraft Heinz’s massive $15.4 billion impairment filed in early 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would a company want to massage or manipulate its valuation of goodwill? Because large impairments can be an indication that a company is not performing well and that its internal projections are predicting slower growth or decline in the future.  A big impairment usually invites bad press and scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the opportunity presented by the present moment. The fact that we just endured a black swan event that has shaken many companies to their core is a perfect opportunity because all bad news can be blamed on the black swan event. A company massaging its numbers can declare an impairment of goodwill and blame it on the coronavirus, even if they ought to have declared an impairment well before the coronavirus ever reared its ugly head in Wuhan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wrote our piece specifically mentioning Under Armor’s Latin American reporting unit on April 1st; on May 11th, it made the following disclosure in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000033/ua-20200331.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q&lt;/a&gt; on May 11th:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Goodwill Impairment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As a result of the impacts of COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;, the Company determined that sufficient indicators existed to trigger the performance of an interim goodwill impairment analysis for all of the Company’s reporting units as of March 31, 2020. The Company performed discounted cash flow analyses and &lt;strong&gt;determined that the estimated fair values of the Latin America reporting unit&lt;/strong&gt; and the Canada reporting unit, within the North America operating segment, &lt;strong&gt;no longer exceeded its carrying value, resulting in an impairment of goodwill&lt;/strong&gt;. The Company recognized goodwill impairment charges of $51.6 million for these reporting units for the three months ended March 31, 2020.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of that $51.6 million, $36.2 million was attributable to the Latin American reporting unit. That reporting unit originally had $46.7 million in goodwill, which means that over 75% of the goodwill was written off. How much of this write off was due to COVID-19? It is possible that the lockdowns accounted for some of the issues leading to the impairment, but good due diligence shows that UA already had preexisting issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many companies are operating in the same gray zone as UA? According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/an-update-on-cams/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, 16.6% of all CAMs as of May 20th 2020 are concerned with intangible assets and goodwill. That means there are potentially hundreds of companies whose valuations of goodwill have been highlighted by their auditors as particularly challenging, subjective, or complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of these companies will file an impairment in the first or second quarter? And how many will blame it on the coronavirus? If you a retail investor and want to know what the companies in your portfolio are doing, then get the Watchdog Report for free and do your own due diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Goodwill" /><category term="Impairment" /><summary type="html">In our previous piece “Birds of a Feather: How to Tell a Gray Swan from a Black Swan,” we discussed how difficult it may be to spot when a company disingenuously blames an impairment of goodwill on the effects of the coronavirus, as opposed to righfuly blaming it on preexisting conditions at the company. We then specifically mentioned Under Armour’s (UA) Latin American reporting unit as one to watch because PwC highlighted the goodwill impairment testing of that specific reporting unit as requiring particularly “challenging, subjective, or complex judgements” in its Critical Audit Matters (CAMs).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/covid-19.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/covid-19.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kraft Heinz: Complaint Alleges Fundamental Corporate Governance Problems, Accounting Shenanigans, and Insider Trading</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kraft Heinz: Complaint Alleges Fundamental Corporate Governance Problems, Accounting Shenanigans, and Insider Trading" /><published>2020-05-29T13:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-29T13:55:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/">&lt;p&gt;Kraft Heinz (KHC) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000020/february2019form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a massive $15.4 billion impairment in February, 2019 to its goodwill and intangible assets.  This impairment was essentially an admission by management major components of the combined company were worth billions less than recorded on the balance sheet.  It was also an admission that 3G Capital (3G) and Warren Buffett’s much touted merger of Kraft and Heinz was a failure.   In the aftermath, Warren Buffett &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/buffett-criticizes-others-for-using-non-standard-accounting-metricsbut-he-does-too-2019-02-26&quot;&gt;admitted &lt;/a&gt;that he had overpaid for his 27% of combined company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHC’s impairment crushed share prices and has led to lawsuits, rapid executive bloodletting, an SEC investigation, and other deleterious events.  We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about the KHC bus-crash last September and argued that KHC’s core problem was a loss of investor trust and a poor management ethos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a carefully researched complaint has brought new revelations that support our initial thesis.  The Complaint is built on the public record, as well as information the plaintiffs have been able to request as shareholders (like board and committee minutes, and some other non-public financial information). Initially filed on March 25th, much of the complaint had been redacted because of KHC’s request for confidentiality.  However, thanks to a challenge to the confidentiality filed by Francine Mckenna of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, KHC has narrowed their scope of requested redactions considerably.  The amended plaintiff’s derivative claim accusing 3G Capital of insider trading revolves around accusations of poor corporate governance and manipulation of accounting concerning goodwill testing and impairment for the benefit of 3G and its executives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHC was formed in 2015 in a merger arranged by 3G and Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway.  3G is a Brazilian firm that became one of the largest and most successful private equity firms in the world after it used a series of acquisitions to create AB InBev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the acquisition of Tim Horton’s in 2014, 3G has partnered with Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway on a number of acquisitions.  In these joint ventures, Berkshire Hathaway has bankrolled much of the operation, while 3G has seized control and implemented its management philosophy of zero-based budgeting to cut costs and boost profit margins.  This partnership was generally considered successful, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/antoinegara/2015/07/06/kraft-heinz-will-prove-the-power-of-warren-buffetts-dealmaking-partnership-with-3g-capital/#4bc95ed11a4c&quot;&gt;reportedly &lt;/a&gt;making 3G Warren Buffett’s partner of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate Governance Disaster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mutual Pledges of Loyalty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a company has serious accounting-related problems, usually it also has serious problems in its corporate governance structure.  After the merger that created Kraft Heinz, the company had 11 board members, 5 were appointed by the former board of Kraft, and the other six were evenly divided between representatives of 3G and Berkshire Hathaway.  This gave 3G and Berkshire Hathaway a controlling interest in Kraft Heinz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint draws attention to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000095015716001605/sc13g.htm&quot;&gt;13G&lt;/a&gt; disclosure made by 3G Capital and Berkshire Hathaway where they acknowledged a shareholder agreement to support each other’s nominees to the board and not take any actions to remove the other’s board members.  This effectively created a mutual pledge of loyalty between 3G Capital and Berkshire Hathaway as shareholders.  Even though this agreement does not violate the law, it created a conflict of interest that deprived the board of effective independent members and compromised the loyalty of these directors to the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agreements between shareholders are common, and the law permits them because shareholders do not (usually) owe any duty to each other, or the company, or the board.  However, in this case, the main shareholders (3G and Berkshire Hathaway) were entities whose partners also comprised more than half of the board of directors.  Additionally, and this is key, 3G’s partners were in control of the operations of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go over the basics of corporate governance. Every corporation has a board of directors that oversees the management of the company.  Each member of the board owes the corporate entity a fiduciary duty to the corporate entity to make decisions for the benefit of the shareholders, not for the benefit of management.  A fiduciary duty is a legal term of art defined as an affirmative duty to act on behalf of a person or corporation in good faith, with reasonable care and undivided loyalty.  The duty of loyalty requires board members put the interests of the corporation before all other interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mutual pledge of loyalty by Berkshire Hathaway and 3G undermines the loyalty that the partners are supposed to have toward KHC. It is hard to believe the partners at 3G and Berkshire Hathaway would effectively pledge mutual loyalty to each other as shareholders of KHC in one room, and then walk into another room and act as independent watchdogs monitoring 3G’s management of KHC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint also highlights issues with board independence and asserts that seven of the members had disabling connections to 3G Capital.  The Nasdaq stock exchange requires that the majority of directors on the board be independent so that it is not beholden to management and can act as effective watchdog.  Even if all these directors technically qualified as independent, their connections to 3G, which was in control of management, violated the spirit of Nasdaq rules concerning independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Core Accusation of Manipulation and Insider Trading in the Complaint&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core this case is about whether 3G Capital and its partners manipulated the accounting related to the company’s goodwill in a way that delayed disclosing bad news, and used that delay to sell their holdings at a price they knew was overvalued. This case revolves around the interpretation of ASC 350, an accounting rule that tells companies when and how to test their intangible assets like goodwill for impairment.  The FASB issued ASU 2017-04 simplifying the test for goodwill impairment and allowed companies to adopt it early.  KHC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;adopted &lt;/a&gt;the revised rule on April 1, 2018, so we will focus on the new test for impairment, not the previous version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have criticized this rule &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.  Whenever companies have a merger or acquisition, the tangible and intangible assets are accounted for, and where the market price of the company exceeds the book value of the company’s assets the excess is recorded as “goodwill” on the balance sheet. To ensure that the amount recorded as goodwill really represents something substantive and defensible, companies are required to test their goodwill value every year as well on the occurrence of a triggering event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they evaluate the fair market value of their companies (often granularly reporting unit by reporting if there is more than one), and secondly, they compare this to the book value.  If the book value exceeds the fair value, then the company writes down, or impairs, the goodwill.  If there is not that much “cushion” between the fair value and the carrying value and the goodwill is at substantial risk for an impairment, then the company is required to disclose that risk to investors.  There is no bright line for the amount of “cushion” but in 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745918000015/form10-k2017.htm&quot;&gt;KHC &lt;/a&gt;used 10% as its threshold.  This threshold was not unusual at the time, as some of KHC’s peers, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1103982/000119312518037332/d466496d10k.htm&quot;&gt;Mondelez &lt;/a&gt;used the same standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASC 350 testing for an impairment to goodwill and other intangible assets is at the center of this case.  The question is when should it have occurred, and what should the results have been?  When KHC disclosed the massive impairment they made a case that the impairment was properly recorded in the 4th Quarter, since that is when it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000020/february2019form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;claims &lt;/a&gt;the circumstances arose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the fourth quarter of 2018, in connection with the preparation of our year-end financial statements, we assessed the changes in circumstances that occurred during the quarter to determine if it was more likely than not that the fair values of any reporting units or indefinite-lived intangible assets were below their carrying amounts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While there was no single determinative event, the consideration in totality of several factors that developed during the fourth quarter of 2018 led us to conclude that it was more likely than not that the fair values of certain reporting units and indefinite-lived intangible assets were below their carrying amounts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint argues that the 3G Capital partners managing KHC knew that the company was in trouble well before the 4th quarter.   We made this point ourselves in our original post, although we pointed to sales that were virtually flat in 2017 and 2018, (2017’s poor results were obscured by a $7 billion benefit from the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act signed by Trump). 
The Complaint looks at KHC’s repeated downward adjustments to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/ebitda.asp&quot;&gt;EBITDA &lt;/a&gt;projections to argue that KHC was aware of serious problems by the end of the second quarter.  EBITDA is a financial metric that measures earnings before taxes, interest expense, depreciation, or amortization costs are realized.  The Plaintiff put together a table of KHC’s revisions to EBITDA in 2018:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/KHC%20EBITDA.png&quot; alt=&quot;KHC EBITDA.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: City of Hollywood v. Kraft Heinz, Motion for Confidential Treatment, Exhibit A (18)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular attention is also given to the Audit Committee and Board meetings at the end of the second quarter.  In those meetings management revised EBITDA projections down by $248 million from earlier revisions for a total decline from the beginning of the year of $727 million.  They also disclosed that the SEC made a request that KHC not destroy accounting-related documents due to a pending investigation.  The management at KHC also told the Audit Committee that it had tested some of its international segments, and that two of them required an impairment because their book value exceeded the carrying value by $265 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, KHC’s management’s valuations of the U.S. reporting units (the same ones subject to a $15.4 billion impairment six months later) did not indicate that those units either required an impairment or that they were at significant risk of an impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint alleges that KHC manipulated the valuations of these segments by using outdated and rosy estimates of future earnings, as well as discount rates on future cash flows that were not high enough.  The Complaint also states that KPMG, which assisted in the required annual testing of goodwill, was also using stale projections from earlier in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff asserts that an increase in the discount rates by a mere .5% would have resulted in KHC being required to issue a warning to investors that certain segments were at risk for impairment. As they stood, these segments were measured at just over the threshold for 10% that would have required a warning. This accusation of manipulation lies at the heart of their case, and if it were to go to trial both sides would provide experts to argue the reasonableness of their position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Valuations Often Speculative and Subjective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have access to the underlying financial information that went into this valuation so we cannot make any determination if the allegations of manipulation in the Complaint are true.  But it is worth noting that these valuations are often subjective, unreliable, and easily manipulated.
In their 2018 2nd quarterly report KHC discussed how these valuations were subject to lots of estimates and guesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some of the more significant assumptions inherent&lt;/strong&gt; in estimating the fair values include the estimated future annual net cash flows for each reporting unit (including net sales, cost of products sold, SG&amp;amp;A, working capital, and capital expenditures), income tax rates, and a discount rate that appropriately reflects the risk inherent in each future cash flow stream … &lt;strong&gt;Estimating the fair value of individual reporting units requires us to make assumptions and estimates regarding our future plans&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as industry and economic conditions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the minutes of the Audit Committee Meeting on July 31st, 2018, Kraft Heinz auditor PwC (which had audited both Kraft and Heinz before the merger) warned that management had made some “close call judgements” about the valuations of certain reporting units.  Those warnings appear to be consistent with the PwC’s Critical Audit Matters (CAMs) disclosures made this year.  Auditors are required to disclose any portion of management’s financial reporting that the auditors found particularly challenging, subjective, or complex, and therefore potentially less reliable, as CAMs.  PwC highlighted KHC’s goodwill and intangible asset impairment testing as CAMs for FY 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the potential valuations KHC could have selected given the “play in the numbers,”  it is clear that KHC selected a valuation that allowed them to avoid making an impairment or even warning of a substantial risk of one occurring. &lt;strong&gt;There is no bright-line rule for telling investors when there is a substantial risk of impairment, but KHC changed its threshold after it recorded the massive impairment.  Prior to it, it would disclose only if the “cushion” was below 10%, but afterwards they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;doubled &lt;/a&gt;the “cushion” to 20%.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3G Capital Trims Stake in KHC Before Second Quarter Results Released&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board met on August 2nd.  The CEO, Hees, shared with the board the poor results up to that point, and lowered projections for the end of the year.  Just four days later, on August 6th, 3G trimmed its holdings from 29% to 22% of KHC’s ownership, selling $1.2 billion worth of stock.  Selling at $59.80 a share, 3G netted at least $653 million more than they would have if they sold after the impairment was announced in February 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/KHC%20Chart%20Complaint.png&quot; alt=&quot;KHC Chart Complaint.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3G’s sale was suspicious under the best of circumstances.&lt;/strong&gt;  The firm had orchestrated the merger creating KHC, it was in control of the operations of KHC, and it had three members sitting on the board (plus four other board members with substantial connections).  If 3G smelled something rotten in KHC, then something must have been rotten. Was this decision to sell based on insider information, or was it done properly based on the information disclosed in the 10-Q on August 3rd?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Kraft Heinz" /><category term="Goodwill" /><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="Litigaiton" /><summary type="html">Kraft Heinz (KHC) announced a massive $15.4 billion impairment in February, 2019 to its goodwill and intangible assets. This impairment was essentially an admission by management major components of the combined company were worth billions less than recorded on the balance sheet. It was also an admission that 3G Capital (3G) and Warren Buffett’s much touted merger of Kraft and Heinz was a failure. In the aftermath, Warren Buffett admitted that he had overpaid for his 27% of combined company. KHC’s impairment crushed share prices and has led to lawsuits, rapid executive bloodletting, an SEC investigation, and other deleterious events. We wrote about the KHC bus-crash last September and argued that KHC’s core problem was a loss of investor trust and a poor management ethos.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/conclusion-of-the-contract-3100578_640.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/conclusion-of-the-contract-3100578_640.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Research: Gray Swan Event Factor is Predictive of Stock Return</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Research: Gray Swan Event Factor is Predictive of Stock Return" /><published>2020-05-22T15:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T15:33:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joseph Burke PhD. and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, have produced two white papers for Watchdog Research that show that companies with higher Gray Swan Event Factors have a lower return on investment. This is because accounting-related risks are not properly priced into the market, potentially giving investors who use this valuable tool an edge over the broader market.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, we wrote a series of blog posts on Tesla. These posts highlighted some potential red flags, like turmoil at the CFO and director positions. They also criticized opaque disclosures and the SolarCity debacle. Naively, we believed this would likely hamper Tesla’s appeal to investors, but we were wrong. Really, really, wrong!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla growth from 11/6/19 to 5/20/20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the chart makes obvious, if you had sold your shares when our last blog was posted on November 6th, 2019, then you really missed out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a fact, buyers and sellers determine stock prices. A company’s stock price will not necessarily go down just because their business practices raise numerous red flags, or it suffers a gray swan event (like a financial restatement, securities suit, C-suite change, or material weakness disclosure).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this begs the question, does doing due diligence on management, accounting issues, litigation and other similar red flags have any value for investors? Many investment firms don’t think so, they don’t spend any time tracking or weighing the effects of gray swan events because it’s too much work. How do we know this? We spent months calling and asking them. Instead most firms get their due diligence research from the investment brokers &lt;em&gt;selling the stocks&lt;/em&gt; and assume that the impact of these events is priced into the stock already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our new white papers show that these events are not priced in, and that companies that are more likely to experience a gray swan event perform worse than their peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key Results from Gray Swan Event Factor Research Papers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Burke and Dr. Yarbrough produced two research reports to examine the predictive power of our Gray Swan Event Factor. In one report, they created a portfolio of the 42 companies that had a Gray Swan Event Factor exceeding 10% on January 1st, 2019 and compared the performance of that portfolio to the performance of the S&amp;amp;P 500 with a hypothetical $1,000 investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20%20image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20 image2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of 2019, the portfolio of companies with a large Gray Swan Event Factor lagged further and further behind the market as investors eventually priced in these adverse events. In fact, these companies suffered a loss while the S&amp;amp;P 500 gained well over $200 on its hypothetical investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note is that no large cap companies had a Gray Swan Event Factor over 10%. In their second white paper, Dr. Burke and Dr. Yarbrough made a far more detailed analysis. They put companies into three categories, small cap, mid cap, and large cap. They then divided companies into four tranches according to their Grey Swan Event Factor score: low risk as 0-2%, medium risk as 2-5%, and high risk as 5-10%, and extremely high risk as &amp;gt;10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping in mind that no large cap companies earned a score of over 10%, lets look at the results of a hypothetical $1,000 investment made in January 2019 by GSEF for large cap companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20%20image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20 image3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As can be seen here, the high-risk companies did significantly worse than their peers by the end of 2019, returning a loss during a year when the S&amp;amp;P 500 would have returned nearly $300 dollars on the investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research demonstrates that there is significant value in properly assessing and weighing accounting-related risks. Investors could potentially short high-risk stocks, or they could filter high-risk stocks out of their portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is of course a great deal more information in these white papers, if you would like to read them for yourself, then send us an email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send the author of this piece John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Gray Swan Event Factor" /><category term="White Paper" /><summary type="html">Joseph Burke PhD. and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, have produced two white papers for Watchdog Research that show that companies with higher Gray Swan Event Factors have a lower return on investment. This is because accounting-related risks are not properly priced into the market, potentially giving investors who use this valuable tool an edge over the broader market.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/New%20Research.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/New%20Research.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs from Luckin: The Fraud</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs from Luckin: The Fraud" /><published>2020-05-22T12:44:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T12:44:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/">&lt;p&gt;We originally wrote this post on Luckin Coffee over a month ago on April 27th, 2020.  Since then the story has significantly developed. Since we wrote this piece, Luckin has changed its story and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920059927/a20-19256_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;admitted&lt;/a&gt; that its CEO was involved in the massive fraud and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;delayed&lt;/a&gt; releasing its annual report.  The WSJ has also written a devastating &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/behind-the-fall-of-chinas-luckin-coffee-a-network-of-fake-buyers-and-a-fictitious-employee-11590682336&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; that confirmed our suspicions that many of the expenses were fabricated and that Charles Lu, the chairman, sat at the center of a complicated web of related party transactions that began before the IPO. Luckin has also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920063497/a20-20057_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt; from the Nasdaq, hopefully for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shockingly, it has also spurred action in Washington, with the Senate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/senate-could-vote-on-bill-that-could-delist-chinese-companies-from-us-stock-exchanges-2020-05-19&quot;&gt;passing&lt;/a&gt; a bill that could potentially delist every Chinese company unless the Chinese Communist Party releases its iron grip on information and allows the PCAOB to inspect its audit firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Senate bill, if signed into law, would be a serious escalation in the ongoing dispute between the U.S. and the Chinese Communist Party. We are going to closely examine potential problems in Sino-American business relations in a series of in-depth posts.  But to understand why a fraud at a Chinese coffee company has sparked an international conflict, read our original analysis…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Fraud at Luckin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Executive Summary. If one tallies all the money lost in the West from the Luckin fraud, which went either to Luckin, or directly to its chairman Charles Lu, before the stock was shorted, this amounts to $2.165 billion. If one additionally includes money from short positions, and other potentially undisclosed and improper insider trading, the total could be far higher. Thus, from issues of sheer scale, the fraud requires careful attention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For many years, there have been credible &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2020/02/10/804501991/chinese-hackers-charged-in-alleged-cyber-theft-of-145-million-americans-data&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; that elements of the CCP have sponsored selective looting of intellectual property from Western companies, through cyber hacking and other scams, and that similarly, the CCP has protected the perpetrators from prosecution. Can this alternative be ruled out in the case of Luckin?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ‘downside’, which must be protected against, would be extremely serious. If elements of the CCP have aided and abetted Chinese companies in defrauding Western investors on a grand scale, then there are significant implications for the US legislators, regulators, and gatekeepers for the capital markets and their relationships with the CCP. The implications range all the way from the relatively small-scale, such as whether a US company’s important supply chain should be located solely in China, all the way up to policy questions about the relationship, going forward, between economic engagement and civil liberties in China.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The evidence raises the colorable claim that Luckin’s fraud involved further bad actors, and greater coordination, than a renegade COO—the current official explanation. Watchdog Research believes that the currently available information more than justifies an investigation, by investigative journalists and competent US public authorities, to rule out if possible the worst-case hypothesis, that Luckin was a scam from the beginning, where its public statements, capital raising, revenue projections, expense disclosures, and borrowings came together in an orchestrated, fraudulent scheme to fleece billions of dollars from greedy Western investors hungry for big returns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It must be kept in mind that, according to official communist ideology, the system of free markets is itself corrupt and inherently a system of greed, and the destabilization of such markets can only serve to promote an eventual communist revolution. To exploit the ‘capitalist system’ to the advantage of communism, on this ideology, is regarded as a positive good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 2nd 2020, Luckin Coffee, which had been a darling for American investors since its IPO in 2019, and which had attracted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1061165/000106116520000006/sc13gluckincoffee.htm&quot;&gt;support&lt;/a&gt; from institutional investors like Lone Pine Capital, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that its COO and some employees had fabricated expenses and revenue. TAL Education Group, another company based in China, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1499620/000110465920044459/tm2015354d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales numbers just five days later. These stories quickly gained prominence in the news, in part because of corresponding stories about the CCP’s blatant &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/02/us/politics/cia-coronavirus-china.html&quot;&gt;lies&lt;/a&gt; about the numbers of infections and deaths from the Wuhan flu in China. Indeed, it has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/5-million-left-wuhan-before-coronavirus-quarantine-2020-1&quot;&gt;become clear&lt;/a&gt; that the Chinese government allowed 5 million visitors to leave Wuhan for other parts of the world, after it knew about the virus and had blocked travel from Wuhan to other parts of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The confluence of these stories about the virus and the CCP, and about two prominent Chinese companies, produced a widespread negative reaction, with many investors gaining a newfound &lt;a href=&quot;https://finanz.dk/luckin-debacle-shakes-investor-faith-in-new-yorks-china-listings/page/2/&quot;&gt;skepticism&lt;/a&gt; about reported financial results in China. New stories that the CCP has almost certainly been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/coronavirus-covid-19-origins-investigation-wuhan-lab-accident/&quot;&gt;covering&lt;/a&gt; up the origins of the Wuhan flu serve only to deepen skepticism of the reliability of regulatory and oversight institutions in China, and standards of transparency and fairness. The SEC and DOJ have had no ability to prosecute frauds in China, and the CCP seems intent on covering them up, creating a dangerous dynamic. With no fear of punishment or disgorgement, it is reasonable to suppose that criminals in China have been emboldened to commit fraud on Western investors. As mentioned, on communist ideology, it is not clear, to say the least, that such fraud would even be identified as ‘wrong.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional Wisdom on the Fraud&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The massive Luckin fraud was first revealed by the activist short-seller Muddy Waters, which published a report by an anonymous author detailing the fraud. This triggered an investigation by Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP (EYHM). When EYHM learned of the fraud, they reportedly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yicaiglobal.com/news/exclusive-auditor-anti-fraud-team-led-to-luckin-confession-sources-say&quot;&gt;pressured&lt;/a&gt; Luckin to come clean. When Luckin did make its report, there began a massive sell-off, and a halt on trading, for the short-term at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Share price of Luckin Coffee for 2020, which is mapped to Watchdog Flags on the interactive Watchdog website&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;own disclosure&lt;/a&gt; states that the COO was responsible for initiating the fraudulent overreporting of revenue by over $300 million for 2019, which was more than half of the company’s reported revenue that year. This furthers a narrative that the pressure to meet expectations after the company’s IPO in May of last year motivated the COO and his underlings to inflate sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official story is of course not the only reasonable hypothesis. We find this narrative highly unpersuasive on its face. It seems doubtful that the COO could have pulled off fabricating more than half of Luckin’s revenue, and made “substantial” changes to expenditures, without the knowledge of the CFO or CEO. And it is implausible that a fraud so massive began only after the IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close look at the available evidence suggests that, possibly, it was Luckin’s top executives who benefited most from this fraud. Moreover, there are indications that at some point, if not from the beginning, the company’s primary purpose changed from serving coffee to scamming Western investors. Enough evidence already exists, we believe, to justify an investigation to determine the true scope of Luckin’s fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this represent an Enron moment? Are truly large questions necessarily raised by this fraud, about how US securities regulators, auditors, exchanges, underwriters and Congressional representatives should respond?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digging into the Anonymous Report&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carson Block’s Muddy Waters has become renowned for eviscerating Chinese companies, ever since Carson Block kickstarted his career by publishing a damaging &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/id/43765929&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; on Orient Paper. Since then, Muddy Waters has issued numerous reports which resulted in serious losses for Chinese companies and even delisting, making Muddy Waters a wealthy and powerful short seller. However, in the case of Luckin, Muddy Waters claims not to have written the report, but to have received it from an anonymous source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1LKOYMpXVo1ssbWQx8j4G3-strg6mpQ7F/view&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; published by Muddy Waters was not created by amateurs. It included thousands of hours of footage shot by 92 full-time and 1,418 part-time staff in 38 separate cities. The costs for producing this report would have easily run into the millions, which raises the question of who funded this report. Muddy Waters could have funded it and be lying. It could also have been Starbucks that paid for it, looking to kneecap a potential competitor. Perhaps it was a Chinese firm that received an inside scoop and wanted to benefit from the short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core claim of the report is that reported sales numbers simply did not match actual customer volume, such that 70%-90% of sales were inflated. Luckin apparently rigged its ordering system to skip numbers so make it more difficult if not impossible to discover the manipulation. The report appears to have obtained a screenshot of instructions sent to employees telling them to ignore the discrepancies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Text.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Text.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings were confirmed when Luckin admitted through its financial restatement that its COO had started inflating sales in May 2019. The restatement also indicated that some costs and expenses had been substantially inflated. But the report contains other red flags which indicate that it may have been the chairman of Luckin, Charles Zhengyao Lu, and his associates, who were ultimately responsible for the fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indicia of a Larger Fraud in the Anonymous Report&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous report pointed out a red flag, which had been buried in the fine print of the Luckin’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746920000079/a2240174zf-1.htm&quot;&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt;, filed on January 7th, 2020, which is this: Charles Lu, Luckin’s chairman, Jenny Zhiya Qian, the CEO, and Sunying Wong (who is &lt;a href=&quot;https://luckincoffee.info/2020/04/07/goldman-sachs-usd-520-million-ruixing-stock-pledge-loan-default/&quot;&gt;alleged&lt;/a&gt; to be the sister of Charles Lu, a fact not disclosed in the SEC filing) pledged 49% of their collective shares to underwrite loans. The anonymous report argued that pledging shares for personal loans allowed Charles Lu and his associates effectively to cash out their ownership without panicking other shareholders. This theory appeared to be confirmed, when Goldman Sachs reported that Charles Lu defaulted on his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.morningstar.com/news/dow-jones/202004071246/loan-to-luckin-chairman-could-cost-banks-millions-wsj&quot;&gt;$518 million&lt;/a&gt; loan only a few days after the fraud was revealed, which looks like a smoking gun for his involvement in the fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous report also claimed that Luckin engaged in related party transactions with companies that were controlled by Charles Lu and his associates. Luckin’s SEC filings disclosed it received advertising services from a company that is affiliated with Charles Lu. But the anonymous report claims not only that Charles Lu understated his relationship with advertising companies, but also that he controlled additional companies that provided coffee vending machines and food products to Luckin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a related party transaction, a person in control of two companies can syphon off money for himself, by having the one company overpay for goods or services to the other company, pocketing for himself the difference of overpayment. The report accuses Luckin of inflating its advertising costs by over 150% and of dramatically inflating the cost of its coffee vending machines. One way of hiding such overcharges on related party transactions is to increase revenue falsely, to make it look as though revenue is increasing apace, with all the extra expenditures. Thus, there needs to be an investigation to determine if Luckin’s fraud started with fabricating expenses, instead of fabricating revenue. There should also be an investigation of the cost of building and outfitting new stores, one of Luckin’s largest expenditures, to see if that cost was inflated as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous report also accuses the founding partner of Centurium Capital of being an old friend of Charles Lu because of its investment in one of Charles Lu’s other companies. Centurium Capital was one of the early investors in Luckin, contributing over $180 million in 2018. On January 8th, 2020, it made over $230 million by selling 20% of its holdings in Luckin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/chinas-centurium-capital-to-reach-first-close-at-%242-bln%3A-sources-2020-03-05&quot;&gt;netting $50&lt;/a&gt; million on its initial investment. One could argue that the sale was not suspicious, after all, because Centurium retained 80% of its holdings. However, if an investing firm believed it was in on the ground floor of the Chinese Starbucks, would it sell 20% of its holdings? Besides, the percentages do not really matter that much: what really matters is how much money they were putting in their pockets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report contains many other claims, but the existence of the report itself indicates that there may be a larger conspiracy here, something we believe is obvious. There are two reasonable inferences that can be drawn from the mere existence of this report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;em&gt;Someone on the inside of Luckin leaked this information&lt;/em&gt;. There is no chance anyone would have spent several months and millions of dollars to create this report on a hunch. They had to know what they would find before they started looking, and the report was merely to document the fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;Certain members of the CCP were aware of this report before it came out&lt;/em&gt;. China is an authoritarian &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifesitenews.com/news/chinese-govt-uses-smartphones-to-track-citizens-deny-service-to-those-deemed-threat-to-society&quot;&gt;surveillance state&lt;/a&gt;, which uses advanced technology to track and grade all of its citizens movements, all the time. It would be exceedingly difficult for any group to spend millions of dollars, and hire over 1,500 people to conduct surveillance, without the CCP knowing about it. Additionally, the authors of the report must have known that exposing the CCP to potential embarrassment could easily cost them everything. Therefore, it is unlikely that the authors would have hired so many people in this endeavor without sufficient ‘comfort,’ taking the form of knowledge and permission of suitably placed CCP authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the origin of the report itself, and who knew about it, needs to be investigated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Springtime for Luckin; Winter for Western Investors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its peak in January, Luckin had a market cap of over &lt;a href=&quot;https://ycharts.com/companies/LK/market_cap&quot;&gt;$12 billion&lt;/a&gt; (reaching $50.4 per share on January 19, 2020). Now it stands at $1 billion, but only because the halt in trading has kept it from falling still lower. However, it is unlikely that the people responsible will face any punishment because most of that money belonged to Western investors. For over a decade, the CCP has employed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/06/us/politics/china-hacking-cyber.html&quot;&gt;state sponsored hackers&lt;/a&gt;, tasked with stealing information, intellectual property, and technology from Western governments and companies. These groups do not restrict themselves to stealing sensitive information: they also steal plenty of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.knowbe4.com/chinese-state-sponsored-phishing&quot;&gt;money&lt;/a&gt;. Elements of the CCP have long sponsored the looting of Western companies and protected the perpetrators from any consequences, provided they get some of the benefit themselves, and their long-term interests are not threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This broader context is important, because if Charles Lu purchased the patronage of certain elements of the CCP, then one must consider the possibility that the launch of Luckin, from the start, was a scam to defraud Western investors; and, if not from the beginning, then whether it turned into such a scheme, when it became clear to those on the inside, after the IPO in April 2019, that growth at the pace that investors were expecting would be untenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin was founded in 2018, and in June it received $200 million in investments from a private equity firm in Singapore and two Chinese firms, Centurium Capital and Joy Capital. In November, it raised another $200 million from the same investors. Up to this point, Luckin had mostly been in the business of building stores (over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/luckin-coffee-ipo-stock-price-51558054869&quot;&gt;2,370&lt;/a&gt; of them in about a year), and it had little revenue to show for it. By this time, Charles Lu probably had gained the patronage of some important Party officials. Indeed, to have built so many shops, in such a short period of time, in a country so tightly controlled by Party officials, would otherwise have been impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2019, foreign investments started to roll in. Luckin received $150 million from Blackrock in pre-IPO fundraising. Then, in May, Luckin generated over $645 million from its IPO. By November, the company had made two fraudulent quarterly reports, which showed rising revenues and associated expenses, while also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465919065621/a19-23472_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;claiming&lt;/a&gt; the number of its stores had risen to 3,680:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%203d%20quarter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin 3d quarter.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One must consider that Charles Lu, after his lock-up on shares came to an end in November 2019, potentially wished to use these fraudulent results to pledge shares as collateral for a $518 million loan. In January 2020, Luckin raised over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920003929/a20-3405_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;$850 million&lt;/a&gt; more in shares and bond offerings, even though they claimed to retain, still, over $650 million in cash and cash equivalents after the third quarter. As mentioned, Centurium Capital, whose founding partner is allegedly affiliated with Charles Lu, sold over $230 million in holdings, just a few weeks before Muddy Waters published its anonymous report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not know if Centurium was able to extricate any more capital out of Luckin. However, a thorough investigation is necessary, to see which other investors bailed just prior to the publication of the report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin’s share price was initially resilient, but it plummeted when the fraud was confirmed. The short sellers made a killing, estimated at about &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/news/luckin-coffee-short-sellers-1-152036003.html&quot;&gt;$1.1 billion&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, an investigation into the Luckin fraud also needs to discover who benefited from the short besides Muddy Waters, to see if in particular if there are any related parties that benefited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Timeline.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final tally of cash flowing into China is this: $150 million taken from Blackrock; $1.5 billion raised from public offerings; $518 million in a personal loan to Charles Lu; and an unknown amount of proceeds from share and short sales. Moreover, Western investors lost a company that was valued at $12 billion as recently as January 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Was the COO Responsible?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the evidence, it is hard to believe that Charles Lu and the other executives were unaware of the fraud. A look at the company’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465919065621/a19-23472_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;unaudited&lt;/a&gt; third quarter results indicates that they claim that about $300 million was spent on operating costs for that quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total operating expenses&lt;/strong&gt; were RMB2,132.5 million (US$298.3 million), representing an increase of 193.6% from RMB726.4 million in the third quarter of 2018. The increase in operating expenses was the result of business expansion. Meanwhile, operating expenses as a percentage of net revenues decreased to 138.3% in the third quarter of 2019 from 301.7% in the third quarter of 2018, mainly driven by increased economies of scale and the Company’s technology-driven operations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that the revenue number for this company was almost completely fabricated, one has reason to doubt every number in these statements. Luckin reported approximately a billion dollars in total expenses for 2018 and the first three quarters of 2019. Given that this number is likely overstated, perhaps by hundreds of millions of dollars, and that Luckin did make some revenue, the company ought to have been swimming in cash, and anyone with access to company accounts would have noticed something was wrong. Yet we are expected to believe that the COO and a few other employees conducted this fraud without the knowledge of the CFO, the CEO, or Charles Lu. A far more reasonable hypothesis is that much of this money ended up in the pockets of Charles Lu and associates through related party transactions, and significant amounts probably greased the palms of important CCP officials as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the CCP and the Western media have uncritically accepted Luckin’s offering of its COO as a sacrificial scapegoat. It does not appear that the CCP is investigating Charles Lu and his family members—someone might comment mordantly that when the CCP is displeased with a business owner, that person often simply &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/news/china-billionaires-ceo-disappearing-missing-station-sanctioned-abductions-beijing-security-agencies-a7564896.html&quot;&gt;disappears&lt;/a&gt;. Some doctors who blew the whistle on the coronavirus are still &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/china-coronavirus-whistleblowers-speak-out-vanish-2020-2&quot;&gt;missing&lt;/a&gt;. Since Charles Lu is still with us and apparently flourishing, it is probably because officials at the CCP are pleased with his contributions to the Party. For all we know, he is being hailed a hero, and there is some &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WBYeats1865/status/1245730490234982400&quot;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; supporting this idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are these idle speculations, or colorable claims that require investigating, because of the potential downside? But none of the uses of funds, or relationship between expenditures and revenues, makes any sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Revealing the Fraud as an Exit Strategy: Cui bono?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The craziest part of this fraud, if perpetrated as we suspect by Charles Lu and his patrons in the CCP, is that they could have made even more money by revealing it. As we said, it is likely that someone inside of Luckin leaked information to the writers of the anonymous report, and by extension to Muddy Waters. Who had motive? Sure, it might have been some midlevel manager who wanted cash. But if we look at the sequence of events, the possibility that it was actually Charles Lu and his associates becomes a more plausible explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carson Block’s firm Muddy Waters has shown how lucrative it can be to expose fraud. Why wouldn’t fraudsters themselves, then, give it a try? Did any of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/news/luckin-coffee-short-sellers-1-152036003.html&quot;&gt;$1.1 billion&lt;/a&gt; that short-sellers made on Luckin go into the pockets of Charles Lu, or members of the CCP? Moreover, there would be no risk or exposure to them, if the CCP had never had an interest in pursuing the case, because foreign banks and investors would have no recourse and no methods of enforcement. Neither the SEC nor the DOJ can investigate, and Chinese laws prevent foreigners from taking effective measures (such as taking control of the operations of the company, or seizing and selling off property and equipment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCP has played an active role in looting Western governments and companies for years. And their willingness to allow fraud has created an environment where investors are exposed to every type of fraud. We know for certain that Luckin inflated revenues. But Charles Lu also appears to have taken out a $518 million dollar loan without any intention of repaying it. He also may have used related party transactions to syphon money out of the company and encouraged friends to sell in January before the fraud was revealed. But that is just the fraud that is well substantiated by available evidence. Fraud is not carried out in plain sight: it comes to light only when something compels disclosure. The available evidence likely represents only the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can rule out that, after Luckin’s cash disappears (perhaps to buy coffee vending machines from a company allegedly owned by Charles Lu), and the firm declares bankruptcy—what can rule out that, on that day, the people involved in this scam are able to buy up again all the property, inventory, and equipment, for pennies on the dollar, and try something similar once more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Muddy Waters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could some of this conjecture be false? Yes, and Muddy Waters might have some inside information that could reinforce or dispel our thesis. But without cooperation from the CCP, some questions will never be answered. We hope that Muddy Waters would participate in any investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet one is reasonably troubled by the ethics of Muddy Waters’ short selling activism. Indeed, they are incentivized to expose fraud, which is good. But they are also incentivized to let a fraud go on for as long as possible, to allow the stock price to climb as high as possible, before pulling out the rug. Do they have some sort of moral obligation to warn investors at the first sign of trouble? Perhaps they think that any investor foolish enough to invest money in China gets what he or she deserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Conclusion *&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is compelling enough evidence that Charles Zhengyao Lu and his associates, not the COO, are principally responsible for fabricating numbers and stealing an enormous amount of money from foreign investors out of Luckin Coffee. And, if that is true, then it is at least a possibility, which needs examination, that the executives were the ones who leaked details of the fraud and had it released, after they had raised additional capital so that they could short the stock. Considering the astonishing, meteoric rise of Luckin, and the amount of money in play (billions), is it possible that Charles Lu and his associates made substantial contributions to certain CCP officials every step of the way, allowing them to get off scot free?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most troubling part about this story is the implications it has for the future of permitting Chinese firms unfettered access to Western capital markets. If Chinese companies are able to loot Western investment houses, and all the people they represent, without fear of reprisal or personal responsibility, because segments of the CCP have given fraudsters free reign to steal as much money as they can get their hands on, then we will see frauds like this happen again and again. Yet institutions in the West seem impotent in the face of the CCP. We believe strongly that this fraud cannot be allowed to go uninvestigated by regulators and financial press alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; do to protect &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; money? Perhaps the next time you think you see a Chinese unicorn—you should run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About our Watchdog Transparency Blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watchdog Research is a new resource covering issues associated with the reliability of financial disclosures now available to all institutional and advisory firms. Three years in the making, it draws proprietary analyst driven data from multiple sources and provides that information in a concise, timely and interactive way. In our Blog we utilize highly experienced analysts and forensic accountants to take a critical look at particular public company disclosures and focus on issues surrounding transparency, reliability, and accuracy. It you are looking for cheerleading, you have come to the wrong place. We rely on information from the best sources available to gain insight into companies and make predictions about what will happen in the future. Nothing in business is certain, so sometimes we will be wrong, but we will always be an independent voice telling you the truth as we see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send the author of this piece John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>John_Cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="CCP" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="Fraud" /><summary type="html">We originally wrote this post on Luckin Coffee over a month ago on April 27th, 2020. Since then the story has significantly developed. Since we wrote this piece, Luckin has changed its story and admitted that its CEO was involved in the massive fraud and delayed releasing its annual report. The WSJ has also written a devastating piece that confirmed our suspicions that many of the expenses were fabricated and that Charles Lu, the chairman, sat at the center of a complicated web of related party transactions that began before the IPO. Luckin has also been delisted from the Nasdaq, hopefully for good.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/America%20Runs%20from%20Luckin-%20I.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/America%20Runs%20from%20Luckin-%20I.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers" /><published>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;concerns &lt;/a&gt;about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the coronavirus, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;allowed&lt;/a&gt; public companies to delay releasing their annual or quarterly reports by up to 45 days. This order initially went into effect on March 4th, after large accelerated filers (companies with more than 700 million in public float) had already submitted their annual reports. However, large accelerated filers were due to report their first quarter results on May 11th, giving these big companies a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to see how many large accelerated filers were choosing to file their 10-Qs late. Our analysis showed that as of May 19th, &lt;em&gt;only 27 U.S. based companies&lt;/em&gt; had failed to file their 10-Qs due to disruptions from the coronavirus. We arrived at this number by eliminating foreign filers (who have different reporting obligations and dates) and by eliminating companies that failed to file because they were acquired or stated their failure to file was due to internal control problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is significant that so few companies decided to file late. We decided to look deeper to see what made these companies the exceptions. We were not surprised to see Party City (PRTY) on this list. In addition to having its stores closed, long term social distancing practices could destroy their prospects for recovery; its stock has taken such a beating that it was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1592058/000119312520107068/d901922dex991.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt;. But for other companies it is less clear why they were unable to file. For example, Entercom Communications (ETM), which owns radio stations and other digital content, has only reported a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1067837/000119312520142278/d910419dex991.htm&quot;&gt;4% loss in net revenue&lt;/a&gt; for its first quarter, hardly cataclysmic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20Filers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late Filers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found that about 14 of these companies had offered their first quarter results to their investors in an earnings call and concurrent press release. We are not quite sure what to make of this. On one hand, it seems commendable that they are keeping investors appraised of what is going on, but if they can pull together an accurate earnings call, then why can’t they file their 10-Qs on time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20filers%20press%20release.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late filers press release.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interesting Specific Examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circor International (CIR)&lt;/strong&gt;. This industrial valve manufacturer failed to timely file their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000023/circorformnt10-kv10.htm&quot;&gt;10-k&lt;/a&gt; this year because of internal control issues and a cybersecurity breach.  Now they are claiming that the coronavirus is the reason for their late 10-Q. They also filed two of their quarterly reports late in 2019. This company sells manufactures valves and other products for the industrial, aerospace and defense, and energy sectors. This is probably the clearest cut case of a company making a dubious assertion that its filing delay is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000070/cir8-k42920.htm&quot;&gt;due&lt;/a&gt; to the coronavirus as opposed to preexisting internal issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MFA Financial (MFA)&lt;/strong&gt;. This Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT) provided an interesting reason why they could not &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1055160/000105516020000018/mfa-8k05062020.htm&quot;&gt;timely&lt;/a&gt; file their quarterly report, “&lt;em&gt;Company’s management has had to devote significant time and attention to address [the impact of coronavirus], which have diverted management resources from completing tasks necessary to file the Company’s Quarterly Report…&lt;/em&gt;.” The other two REITs who failed to file in a timely manner cited the need for accounting staff to work at home as a reason for the delay. In contrast, it appears MFA’s management simply did not make time to file their 10-Q because the SEC has allowed them to put it on the backburner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credit Acceptance Corp (CACC).&lt;/strong&gt; MFA was not the only company to say its management was too busy to file a 10-Q. CACC had a near identical &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000042/cacc8k20200420.htm&quot;&gt;disclosure&lt;/a&gt;, claiming management was just too busy assessing the potential impact of the coronavirus. For context, CACC specializes in offering subprime loans on vehicles, which some people find &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2019/12/12/787337997/the-big-business-of-subprime-auto-loans&quot;&gt;unsavory&lt;/a&gt;. Even though almost every other company is trying to increase and preserve liquidity to survive the shutdowns, CACC is in the process of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000036/cacc8k20200305.htm&quot;&gt;repurchasing&lt;/a&gt; up to 3 million shares, reducing their cash position. We also can’t help but point out the irony of CACC filing their 10-Q late on the flimsiest of excuses while also issuing this statement on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creditacceptance.com/coronavirus-response&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; “…Credit Acceptance is unable to support payment deferrals, and your payments will continue to be due on your scheduled monthly due date….” Considering the current predicament of many of the low-income recipients of these predatory loans, we don’t know how CACC shareholders can sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every investor wants to know if management is reliable and is dedicated to transparency. When management is opaque, it makes an investment far riskier. The best way to assess the trustworthiness of a management team is to see what kind of choices they make. The coronavirus has presented management teams with lots of choices, and we should watch them carefully as they make their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Late Filings" /><summary type="html">In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed concerns about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?" /><published>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/">&lt;p&gt;To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections.  An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/indicators/unemployment/&quot;&gt;skyrocketing &lt;/a&gt;unemployment.  To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;permitted &lt;/a&gt;companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some companies this may simply be a welcome respite during a difficult time, but we are concerned that some companies may use this as an opportunity to prevent investors from seeing just how badly things are going until it is too late. However, the SEC has also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-clayton-hinman&quot;&gt;encouraged &lt;/a&gt;companies to reveal how the shutdowns are effecting them and to speculate about how they will bounce back from the disaster. The SEC has assured companies concerned about incurring liability for these speculative statements that they will not be “second guessed by the SEC.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect the SEC has created two divergent paths for companies, some will file on time and may include extensive disclosures, but others may take the opportunity to delay reporting for as long as possible, perhaps in hope that by the time the 45 day period runs out, they will be able to report some good news (if they don’t declare bankruptcy first).  We believe that the strongest indicator for which path companies will take is their financial health before the lockdowns.  This would be consistent with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/coronavirus-uncertainties-contribute-to-going-concern-uncertainties/&quot;&gt;findings&lt;/a&gt; from Audit Analytics that the companies who initially received going concern warnings from auditors, where the coronavirus was named as a substantial factor, had already received going concern warnings before the pandemic even started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already expressed concern that some companies might use the coronavirus as a pretext to write off goodwill that was junk before the lockdowns, but we became concerned that some companies might abuse the delay allowance when we saw that Luckin Coffee was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;delaying &lt;/a&gt;its annual report due to the coronavirus.  The disclosure did not even refer to the massive fraud it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;unveiled &lt;/a&gt;less than a month earlier, or the firing of its CEO that was announced a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. large accelerated filers, companies with a public float of over $700 million, were required to file their annual statements before March 1st, so they were unable to take advantage of the ability to file late.  But smaller companies and foreign issuers with later deadlines were able to take advantage to file late if they wanted and many of them did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LateFilings%20graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;LateFilings graph.png&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/impacts-of-covid-19-on-late-filings/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most large accelerated filers are due to file their quarterly statements this week, which is giving the markets their first real insight as to the effects of the coronavirus on the world’s biggest businesses.  For example, the Kraft Heinz Company, (one of our favorite &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;subjects&lt;/a&gt;) has benefited from the shutdowns with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745920000061/khc-20200328.htm&quot;&gt;boost &lt;/a&gt;in revenue, as we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;predicted&lt;/a&gt;.  They also wrote off $226 million in goodwill, but that was apparently from consolidating their reporting into three segments instead of four and not from the coronavirus (how KHC’s figured that its new international segment is worth $226 million less than the sum of its component parts is anyone’s guess).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, Hertz filed its 10-Q in a timely fashion, but it did not have such good news to report.  The rental car industry, which has high fixed costs and relies primarily on people traveling to earn revenue has been hit hard by the shutdowns.  Hertz issued a going concern warning in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/47129/000165785320000049/hghthcq12020form10-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q&lt;/a&gt; that it cannot continue to make necessary payments without more revenue as it is burning through its cash. Currently, one of its biggest debts is in forbearance but that deal is set to end on May 22nd, and Hertz has been unable to offer any assurances that a deal will be struck.  The debtors could potentially seize their collateral, including vehicles in Hertz’s fleet, hurting the company’s ability to recover when the lockdowns end. It is good that Hertz is sharing this crucial information for investors at such a critical time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, some companies have opted to delay their filings.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920010302/fooh20200510_nt10q.htm&quot;&gt;One &lt;/a&gt;such company is HF Food Group (HFFG) which primarily serves Chinese takeout restaurants.  Although not a large accelerated filer, this company had the dubious distinction of earning a higher Gray Swan Event Factor score than any other publicly traded company as of April 8th.  Their high score was mostly attributable to two recent mergers, including one consummated in November 2019.  The company also disclosed in its 10-K, filed on March 16th, 2020, that it identified a material weakness in its internal controls.  HF was also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/hf-foods/&quot;&gt;targeted&lt;/a&gt; by a short seller and had a securities &lt;a href=&quot;http://securities.stanford.edu/filings-case.html?id=107365&quot;&gt;lawsuit &lt;/a&gt;filed against it in March, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920009194/ex_184193.htm&quot;&gt;replaced &lt;/a&gt;its CFO on May 4th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those curious about our Grey Swan Event Factor analysis, here is the analysis for HFFG:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Latefilings%20GSEF.png&quot; alt=&quot;Latefilings GSEF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is it that HFFG was able to put out a timely annual report but has needed to delay its quarterly report due to the coronavirus?  Is it possible that this delay has more to do with material weaknesses in the internal controls and turmoil at the executive level, rather than the coronavirus? To its credit (and unlike Luckin Coffee), HFFG has released some information indicating that it has been suffering an adverse impact from the shutdowns, with net sales declining from $209 million to $175.8 million year over year.  Still, investors will not really be able to assess the big picture until the quarterly results are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this mess is over, the SEC ought to study the effect of its policy.  Did the delayed filings really help companies who were suffering from the coronavirus? Or were they mostly used by companies who would have filed late anyways?  And was any real benefit to companies worth the loss of crucial information for investors at such a critical time?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC" /><category term="Late Filings" /><category term="GSEF" /><summary type="html">To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections. An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and skyrocketing unemployment. To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has permitted companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>