<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-25T10:26:04-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Under Armour III: Major CFO Change Was a Warning Sign of Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour III: Major CFO Change Was a Warning Sign of Litigation" /><published>2020-03-25T09:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T09:26:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;CFOs play an outsized role in the financial health of a company.  When a CFO leaves abruptly or under bad circumstances, that event can have far reaching implications.  Lawrence “Chip” Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was as damaging as it was sudden and mysterious.  Within a year after being brought in from as an outsider, he had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691717000008/january312017form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;resigned&lt;/a&gt; for “personal reasons.”  In his wake there was litigation, an SEC investigation only recently brought to light, and—of course—more litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already taken a closer look at some of the finer details on this story; we looked at how UA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;spike &lt;/a&gt;in non-audit fees was a leading indicator of financial distress and litigation, and we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;looked&lt;/a&gt; at how UA’s comment letters and recent CAM disclosure lend credence to a theory, supported by Francine Mckenna’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/what-might-be-driving-the-criminal&quot;&gt;reporting&lt;/a&gt;, that UA may be under investigation for “channel stuffing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears in UA’s case that the rounds of litigation and the SEC investigation were a direct result of Molloy’s departure.  Molloy’s departure in 2017, understood in its proper context, was a leading indicator of the financial troubles and litigation that UA would suffer in 2019—&lt;em&gt;over two years later&lt;/em&gt;.  Molloy’s story is interesting, but we wanted to look further into the numbers and see if this was a unique circumstance, or if it was emblematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with at every CFO change that was marked as a red flag in our reports from 2014-2018.  Then we looked at the likelihood that that CFO change would coincide with a Securities Class Action (SCA) lawsuit in the same year.  Here were our results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20Same%20Year.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO Same Year.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This result is not that surprising, since oftentimes the same issues that cause a CFO to resign abruptly are the same issues that provide fodder for a lawsuit. In a previous post we had analyzed ten years of data (which explains the small variation in the numbers) to determine the likelihood of a SCA lawsuit arising in the same year as a red-flag CFO change, and this is what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20same%20year%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO same year by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This result is also interesting, although not surprising.  The bigger companies have more public scrutiny, so if their CFO unexpectedly departs, a SCA is far more likely to occur; or if a SCA is filed upon learning of some problem, the CFO is more likely to be fired.  In the case of UA, litigation followed closely behind both the resignation of Molloy in 2017 and the departure of the founder Kevin Plank as CEO in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CFO Change as a Leading Indicator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear from the numbers that a red-flag CFO change in any given year corresponds with an increased risk of a SCA lawsuit during that year, especially for big companies.  But that warning is often too late, since litigation can come hot on the heels of an early CFO resignation.  We ran the same analysis to see if red-flag CFO changes have been a leading indicator of a more litigation in the following year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20followingyr.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO followingyr.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have a statistically significant correlation, demonstrating that a red-flag CFO change is a leading indicator of SCA litigation in the following year.  Moreover, the risk is greater for large cap companies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20followingyr%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO followingyr by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more interesting point is that the results of a similar study on red-flag CEOs did not yield the same results.  CEO departures did correlate with an increased risk of SCA litigation for the same year, &lt;em&gt;but not for the following year&lt;/em&gt;.  This makes sense, since an abrupt CFO change probably relates to the financial health of a company, but a CEO can be removed abruptly for all sorts of other reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UA’s Issues Emblematic of Other Red-Flag CFO Departures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers we have presented indicate that UA’s problems with SCA litigation following the resignation of Molloy is emblematic, and not a fluke or exception.  The UA example is helpful because it gives a window as to what is going on behind these numbers.  When something dramatic like a unexpected CFO departure occurs and the company offers little or no explanation as to what is going on, it is more likely that there is a major problem going on that will trap the company in expensive litigation.  The best course of action for these companies is to be fully transparent and address their issues head-on so that their problems do not linger for years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="CFO Change" /><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Leading Indicators" /><summary type="html">CFOs play an outsized role in the financial health of a company. When a CFO leaves abruptly or under bad circumstances, that event can have far reaching implications. Lawrence “Chip” Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was as damaging as it was sudden and mysterious. Within a year after being brought in from as an outsider, he had resigned for “personal reasons.” In his wake there was litigation, an SEC investigation only recently brought to light, and—of course—more litigation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/litigation_ua-3.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/litigation_ua-3.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armour II: CAM Raises the Specter of “Channel Stuffing”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour II: CAM Raises the Specter of “Channel Stuffing”" /><published>2020-03-17T14:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-17T14:48:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/">&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; piece on Under Armour (UA) we looked at how a dramatic increase in non-audit fees by PriceWaterhouseCoopers (PWC) was a sign of financial problems and a leading indicator of litigation. We also briefly examined UA’s SEC investigation, which was first reported on by the Wall Street Journal.  This investigation has remained somewhat mysterious and UA has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/under-armour-says-its-accounting-practices-have-been-entirely-appropriate-after-wsj-story-2019-11-15&quot;&gt;denied&lt;/a&gt; any wrongdoing.  Thanks to the newly required disclosures of Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), we are getting some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to news reports, the SEC began its investigation into UA in July of 2017.  The report indicated that there was shuffling sales from quarter to quarter to make the company look healthier.  An extensive report by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/retheauditors&quot;&gt;Francine Mckenna&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/about?utm_source=menu-dropdown&quot;&gt;“The Dig”&lt;/a&gt; raised the possibility that UA may have been “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/channelstuffing.asp&quot;&gt;channel stuffing&lt;/a&gt;” by sending retailers more product than they can sell (a practice more likely when a transaction is not truly at arms-length).  The speculation is that UA would push its inventory on retailers during a traditionally slower time of year, thereby boosting sales, and then record the loss of the returned merchandise in a more profitable time of year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear from the investigation whether or not there has been any “channel stuffing,” but there are a few pieces of evidence that suggest UA has not been completely transparent in their accounting and may have to pay a price at the end of this investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lawrence Molloy Left in January 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molloy, an outsider, was appointed the CFO in January 2016.  In January 2017, he announced his resignation for “personal reasons.”  The short tenure, the non-explanation, and the fact that the outsider Molloy was replaced with a long-time loyalist in David E. Bergman (joined in 2004) suggests that Molloy had a serious disagreement in how the company’s finances should be managed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Correspondence with the SEC in May 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting detail from the Wall Street Journal story is that this investigation by the SEC has been ongoing since July of 2017.  Right around that time, our report flagged the release of an SEC comment letter correspondence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we looked at the letter itself, we found that the SEC first &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/app/view-comment-letter.php?cl_fkey=edgar/data/1336917/0000000000-17-015141.txt&quot;&gt;contacted&lt;/a&gt; UA on May 1st, 2017 with questions about the factors that had led to material increases in revenue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;we note you do not quantify the impacts of these factors or fully describe the specific new products lines or offerings that have caused the increase. Please expand your discussion to fully describe the specific reasons and factors contributing to the material changes in revenue…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC wanted to know how much revenue growth was due to new product lines. UA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000119312517187248/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; on May 30th, amongst other things was that “… &lt;em&gt;the Company is not readily able to quantify the impact of unit sales growth of existing versus new product offerings.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It strikes us as odd that UA would not know how much revenue they were receiving from new product offerings.  The SEC might have found it strange as well.  This exchange shows that the SEC was taking a critical view of UA’s revenue recognition methods, and the SEC may not have been satisfied with UA’s explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plank, Founder and CEO, Stepped Aside in October 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not unusual for a founder of a company to step aside from the day-to-day operations of a company, but the timing here is suspicious.  Plank’s departure came a few weeks before the Wall Street Journal broke its story about the SEC investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PWC’s Critical Audit Matter Disclosure Highlights Issues with Sales Returns and Allowances&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting firms are now required to disclose CAMs as a part of their report on a company.  These disclosures require the firm to highlight areas in the accounting that required particularly challenging, complex, or subjective judgements by the auditor.  Our report indicates that UA already has a red flag CAM concerning its Reserve for Customer Returns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Under%20Armour%20CAM%20redflag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Under Armour CAM redflag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we looked at the filing, PWC explained that the company had recorded $219 million in this reserve for returns and markdowns.  And they offered this by way of explanation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal considerations for our determination that performing procedures relating to the reserve for customer returns is a critical audit matter are there was significant judgment by management in estimating the customer returns reserve, which in turn led to a high degree of auditor judgment, effort, and subjectivity in performing procedures and evaluating the significant assumptions used in developing the estimate, including the amount of outstanding returns that have not yet been received by the Company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC has reportedly been investigating since July of 2017 and yet the increased scrutiny has not spurred UA to solve the issue, as PWC issued this CAM for 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that this “reserve” represents the value of merchandise that the company estimates will be returned to the company, effectively adjusting the final sales numbers.  To understand the magnitude of the issue we took a closer look at some of these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm#ia59c9d23542e4b489dc58de46d9acdd9_25&quot;&gt;numbers&lt;/a&gt; (edited for formatting):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20sales%20returns%20numbers.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA sales returns numbers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sales returns and allowances and allowance for doubtful accounts amounts are significantly less this year than in years past.  This could indicate that UA has been changing how it interacts with its retailers, pushing product less aggressively so that the retailers are less likely to overbuy and then return product.  Additionally, the number has fluctuated greatly over the past three years, from which we can infer that PWC would probably have flagged the sales returns consistently if it had been required to relay CAMs in years past.  Regardless, the fact that PWC highlighted these numbers as being particularly subjective is not comforting for investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Typical was UA’s CAM?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close examination of UA’s financial statements reveals how invaluable new CAMs disclosures are in understanding the story behind the numbers, but the CAMs have more to offer.  They can also help us draw comparisons with other companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/an-updated-overview-of-cams/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; shows that CAMs relating to revenue (including sales returns and allowances) account for about 15% of all CAMS issued so far.  Our analysts wanted to see how typical it is for a company to have a CAM that falls under the category of Sales Returns and Allowances.  Currently, more than 1900 companies have filed CAMs.  We narrowed by only looking at CAMs related to Sales Returns and Allowances.  This narrowed our pool to only 74 companies.  Here are the results broken down by industry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CAMS%20by%20industry.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CAMS by industry.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No other apparel companies have had CAMs concerning the sales and returns allowances.  However we discovered several limitations in this sort of analysis due to the CAMs disclosure requirement &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Standards/Auditing/Pages/AS3101.aspx&quot;&gt;incremental&lt;/a&gt; roll-out.  Currently, only large accelerated filers are required to file CAMs for 2019, and not every company has filed yet.  There are 11 apparel manufacturers who will be required to file CAMs this year, but so far only 3 have done so.  It is too early to draw any real conclusions, but we are excited about how this new disclosure will open the door to new and better insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Last Word on “Channel Stuffing”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Channel Stuffing” is considered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fbi.gov/news/stories/executives-sentenced-in-750-million-fraud-scheme&quot;&gt;serious crime&lt;/a&gt;, and executives have received lengthy prison sentences for wire or mail fraud because of it.  But to convict, the DOJ would need to prove the requisite intent (i.e. a purpose to defraud), and the fact that the investigation has been going on for almost three years indicates that the DOJ does not have a smoking gun.  UA may be entirely innocent of “channel stuffing.”   We won’t really know until the DOJ or UA brings all the details to light.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Channel Stuffing" /><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><category term="Critical Audit Matters" /><summary type="html">In our first piece on Under Armour (UA) we looked at how a dramatic increase in non-audit fees by PriceWaterhouseCoopers (PWC) was a sign of financial problems and a leading indicator of litigation. We also briefly examined UA’s SEC investigation, which was first reported on by the Wall Street Journal. This investigation has remained somewhat mysterious and UA has denied any wrongdoing. Thanks to the newly required disclosures of Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), we are getting some clarity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/clothes_stack.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/clothes_stack.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armour I: Troubling Spike in Non-Audit Fees Went Ignored</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour I: Troubling Spike in Non-Audit Fees Went Ignored" /><published>2020-03-13T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-13T11:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/">&lt;p&gt;Under Armour still has not recovered from a serious blow it suffered in early November 2019 when the Wall Street Journal reported that the company had been under investigation by the SEC for its accounting practices.  One element of the story that rattled investors was that the investigation had been going on since July &lt;em&gt;of 2017&lt;/em&gt;, yet it had not been addressed in a transparent way by management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was reported that Under Armour has allegedly been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/03/business/under-armour-sec-justice-dept.html&quot;&gt;shifting&lt;/a&gt; its sales in between quarters to appear healthier.  Companies with seasonal sales often try unconventional and even counter-productive methods to boost traditionally slow quarters and smooth out their numbers, but the ongoing SEC investigation indicates that something more sinister is at play here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For it’s part, Under Armour has said it did nothing wrong.  However, a court found these troubling allegations substantial enough to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm&quot;&gt;revive &lt;/a&gt;a securities lawsuit that it previously had dismissed with prejudice because of the new evidence presented.  Now Under Armour is facing three suits over the matter, and the one certainty of this litigation is that it will be expensive for Under Armour (and their D+O underwriter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Non-Audit Fees Increased Dramatically at Under Armour&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever a story like this gets broken, people always want to look back and see if there were any leading indicators or warning signs. In our opinion a lack of transparency is the most important sign that a company could be in trouble. When a company like Under Armour is going through a lot of turmoil and they attempt to paper over and obscure the problem instead of hitting it straight on, then we get concerned that there are deeper problems festering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors did have some indications that something was wrong at Under Armour. The company went through a tremendous amount of turmoil in their management team in 2016-2017.  Lawrence Molloy replaced a long-time CFO in January 2016, then &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691717000008/january312017form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; his resignation for “personal reasons” about a year later.  If Molloy was experiencing health issues, they didn’t stop him from finding work shortly thereafter, or from serving on the board of &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.sprouts.com/leadership-bios/lawrence-p-molloy/&quot;&gt;Sprouts&lt;/a&gt; during that time.  When highly paid executives start leaving for “personal reasons,” that raises a red flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volatility at the executive level does not necessarily indicate something is wrong; it can be a sign of health if a company has become moribund.  However, those rapid changes at the executive level in 2017 were followed a dramatic 267% increase in Non-Audit fees paid to PWC for 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Under%20Armour%20Non-Audit%20Fees.png&quot; alt=&quot;Under Armour Non-Audit Fees.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that Under Armour’s accounting disclosures are not particularly complex, and that their traditional audit fees had been hovering around the 25th quartile for several years and had actually decreased significantly in 2018, this dramatic increase in non-audit fees signaled that Under Armour was wrestling with significant issues. 
Our Analysts looked back at the period from 2014-2018 and found that a high non-audit fee that raises a yellow flag in our reports corresponded with a statistically significant increase in the risk of securities litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Under%20Armour%20Non-audit%20Fee%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Under Armour Non-audit Fee Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If high non-audit fees are generally a leading indicator of securities litigation, a dramatic one-year increase in non-audit fees would be an even more compelling sign of financial distress.  Here Under Armour’s 268% increase in non-audit fees, paired with unexplained turmoil on the executive level, provided ample notice that trouble was on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Fraud" /><category term="Non-Audit Fees" /><category term="SEC" /><category term="Leading Indicators" /><category term="Red Flag" /><summary type="html">Under Armour still has not recovered from a serious blow it suffered in early November 2019 when the Wall Street Journal reported that the company had been under investigation by the SEC for its accounting practices. One element of the story that rattled investors was that the investigation had been going on since July of 2017, yet it had not been addressed in a transparent way by management.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/under_armour_non_audit_fees.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/under_armour_non_audit_fees.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">UPDATE Nine Critical Days in Hunter Biden’s Time on the Burisma Board</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UPDATE Nine Critical Days in Hunter Biden’s Time on the Burisma Board" /><published>2020-01-17T06:18:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-17T06:18:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/">&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: AG Bondi’s Presentation Adds More Facts and Raises More Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the Trump administration and the US Department of Justice wants to conduct a meaningful inquiry into the circumstances surrounding Burisma, Joe and Hunter Biden and the loss of billions of dollars associated with the failure of Privat Bank and aid to Ukraine, it must subpoena the records of Boise Schiller concerning Hunter Biden, Zlochevsky, and Burisma, and it must subpoena the IMF records concerning Burisma, PrivatBank and Kolomoisky. If the Senate ends up being dragged into this investigation, it will have to do the same as the only real question that exists that matters is whether Trump was correct to be concerned about corruption in Joe and Hunter Biden’s dealings with Burisma and Ukraine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This an update to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/&quot;&gt;lengthy piece&lt;/a&gt; from last week on Hunter Biden’s potential conflicts of interest and ethical/moral issues he faced during his board tenure. In this fast-paced story, more evidence has come to light about the connection between Bursima to Ihor Kolomoisky and his theft of 5.5 billion from PrivatBank, and a conflict of interest for Hunter concerning his employment at Boise Schiller. Let’s jump in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump’s defense lawyer and former Florida Attorney General Pam Bondi made a presentation during the Senate trial where she made the case showing it was reasonable for the President to raise the issue of investigating Hunter Biden’s role at Burisma with the Ukrainian President Zelensky. Ms. Bondi did not address everything our original blog below addressed, but we are adding her new information to our blog to paint a more damning position for Hunter’s role as a board member at Burisma. We have no personal animosity toward Hunter. Our company acts as a watchdog (WatchdogResearch.com) on proper board governance, transparency, risks and disclosures. Our focus remains on Hunter’s failures in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already argued that Hunter’s role was not really to serve as an independent director. It is far more likely that Zlochevsky brought him on so the Biden name would provide a firewall, preventing the Ukranian government from seizing the energy company either as a wartime measure, or as a way of rewarding those loyal to the new regime. There remains a great deal of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/ukraine-gas-company-burisma-holdings-joe-bidens-son-hunter-explained-2019-9&quot;&gt;confusion&lt;/a&gt; as to what role he actually played at the company. Burisma &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/5980032-Burisma-Announces-Hunter-Biden-s-Appointment-to.html&quot;&gt;initially&lt;/a&gt; reported on May 12, 2014, that he would be in charge of the legal unit. But as Ms. Bondi’s presentation showed, Hunter told the NY Times that he never served in that capacity and Hunter’s lawyer issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; denying it. Hunter undoubtedly denied this claim because serving as an executive head of the “legal unit” would be antithetical to his supposed position as an independent board member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Senate Ought to Subpoena Records From the IMF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our last piece we pointed out that Hunter Biden was on the Board when Ihor Kolomoisky, one of Ukraine’s most powerful Oligarchs, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kyivpost.com/article/content/reform-watch/prosecutors-put-zlochevsky-multimillionaire-ex-ecology-minister-on-wanted-list-377719.html&quot;&gt;purchased 45%&lt;/a&gt; of a company believed to be Burisma’s subsidiary. Kolomoisky was the owner of PrivatBank, the largest private banks in Ukraine at the time. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/&quot;&gt;OCCRP&lt;/a&gt;, Kolomoisky also stole &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/investigations/oligarchs-weaponized-cyprus-eranch-of-ukraines-largest-bank-to-send-5-billion-abroad&quot;&gt;$5.5 billion&lt;/a&gt; (5% of the Ukraine’s GDP) out of PrivatBank in 2016, which lead to the IMF to bail the bank out, and creating an urgent need for loan guarantees from the U.S.  Make no mistake, U.S. taxpayers paid for this bailout. Kolomoisky allegedly stashed and laundered this money through other entities that he owned at the time. It is possible that some of this money went through his newly owned interest in Burisma or its subsidiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PrivatBank was implicated in a money laundering scheme in 2014 where it allegedly laundered over $2 billion from Russia and brought it into Europe. PrivatBank’s reported purchase of a subsidiary of Burisma has all the hallmarks of a money laundering scheme, especially considering Zlochevsky had just had $23 million &lt;a href=&quot;https://johnsolomonreports.com/the-ukraine-scandal-timeline-democrats-and-their-media-allies-dont-want-america-to-see/&quot;&gt;frozen&lt;/a&gt; by the British fraud office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have previously discussed how Hunter was paid 12X the typical salary for an independent board member at a small private company.  But Ms. Bondi helped us see which bank was handling Burisma’s payments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/update_9_days_burisma.png&quot; alt=&quot;update_9_days_burisma.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that Burisma held its accounts at PrivatBank, showing another link between the two companies and the two Oligarchs, Zlochevsky and Kolomoisky. Why is this connection relevant to impeachment? It has been widely reported Joe Biden insistence that Shokin be fired had nothing to do with Burisma and that he was fired because of his failure to investigate the massive theft of IMF money by Kolomoisky. That version of the story doesn’t hold much water when Kolomoisky is potentially closely affiliated with Burisma and may have used it as a vehicle to launder money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more point about Kolomoisky. He is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/13/world/europe/ukraine-ihor-kolomoisky-russia.html&quot;&gt;closely&lt;/a&gt; tied to President Zelensky. Although Kolomoisky seems more like his patron, Zelensky said in an interview “He is my business partner, not my boss.”  Zelensky’s statement is not very reassuring.  Is it so surprising that Trump was hesitant to send more money to the Ukraine? In that interview, Zelensky was all but admitting that he was receiving money from Kolomoisky, and if you read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/investigations/oligarchs-weaponized-cyprus-eranch-of-ukraines-largest-bank-to-send-5-billion-abroad&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; it is clear that he received significant assistance in the form of free advertising and promotion from Kolomoisky’s television station.  Wasn’t it reasonable for Trump to be hesitant about sending US aid to an administration potentially beholden to an Oligarch accused by the IMF of massive fraud, one who already have been implicated in laundering Russian money through its Lativian subsidiary of PrivatBank?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case for impeachment relies on the idea that no reasonable person could have believed that there was corruption going on with Burisma and the Bidens. The Democrats have called the notion “absurd.” In reality, the case that there was corruption at Burisma is unassailable, and it is also indisputable that Hunter Biden’s position on the board may implicate him in attempts to hide potential corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money is fungible, and it is difficult to know exactly where all the money flowed.  But it is certainly worth investigating, and if the Senate wants to quickly get to the bottom of it, it needs to subpoena every IMF record on Kolomoisky, Zlochevsky, PrivatBank, and Burisma and its subsidiaries. Those records will show whether there was a legitimate reason to investigate Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Senate Ought to Subpoena Records from Boise Schiller&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bosie Schiller has been associated with the Biden family for at least a decade, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsfllp.com/news-events/bsf-achieves-dismissal-of-claims-against-family-members-of-vice.html&quot;&gt;represented&lt;/a&gt; them before Hunter worked for Boise.  In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/&quot;&gt;last piece&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed the potential for a conflict of interest between Hunter Biden active role on the board of Burisma and his continued role at Boise. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://johnsolomonreports.com/the-ukraine-scandal-timeline-democrats-and-their-media-allies-dont-want-america-to-see/&quot;&gt;reporting&lt;/a&gt; of John Solomon has demonstrated that this conflict was not simply potential, but that it happened. Hunter was announced as a board member in May of 2014 after being asked to join in April. Prior to that, Hunter had been working for Burisma on behalf of his firm Boise Schiller Flexner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Hunter’s attorney, “Burisma agreed to pay the legal expenses of Boies Schiller to support Hunter in developing corporate reform initiatives.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribd.com/document/436048670/Burisma-Holdings-Accounting-Ledger&quot;&gt;Records&lt;/a&gt; show that Boise billed Burisma $250,000 for a retainer in May 2014, and then an additional $33,000 in September when that presumably did not cover all of Hunter’s expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not the big legal fees that raise eyebrows, even though it seems Hunter &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;subbed out&lt;/a&gt; most of the work to Nardello &amp;amp; Co. which was paid about $55,000 for its work. It is the fact that Burisma started paying Hunter’s investment firm in April, around the time that it asked Hunter to join the board as an independent director. Burisma then paid Hunter $83,000 a month ($1 million/year) to serve as an independent board member starting in May, the same month it gave Boise a $250,000 retainer for the work being done by Hunter Biden on behalf of Boise. If these records are accurate then Hunter was double dipping, at least initially, as both a consultant and as an “independent” board director which is a glaring conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boise Schiller is at risk here too; they allowed this unethical behavior by one of their attorneys. There is a cauldron of conflicts here for Boise Schiller as they had to consider the implications for Burisma, Zlochevsky, Hunter Biden, the Biden family, and any duties of loyalty that may have come with government contracts or legal obligations to report ongoing crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boise is one of the world’s most powerful firms, with some of the brightest and most astute lawyers. There is certainly an extensive file on Burisma, Hunter Biden, and Zlochevsky, including the reports that they put together. There may even be internal memos about the risks posed to the firm for this conflict. There were certainly internal discussions after it was widely reported. The Senate must subpoena all of the documents related to Zlochevsky, Burisma, Hunter Biden, and any other related documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is of course more to this story. Like the fact that Devon Archer failed to serve his full five year term and quietly left the board after he became implicated in an unrelated but massive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/litigation/litreleases/2016/lr23535.htm&quot;&gt;Ponzi&lt;/a&gt; scheme. Or the fact that the other well-connected Board member, the former president of Poland, Aleksander Kwasniewski, was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/24/world/europe/manafort-gusenbauer-hapsburg-ukraine-indictment.html&quot;&gt;connected&lt;/a&gt; with the ousted Pro-Russian Regime and Paul Manafort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be understandable for the Senators to dismiss the impeachment against President Trump without going any further, but if they want to get to the truth, then any roadmap should start with subpoenaing Boise and the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our original post is below…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;But Burisma’s owner, Mykola Zlochevsky, has been under investigation in Britain and in Ukraine. It should be plain to Hunter Biden that any connection with a Ukrainian oligarch damages his father’s efforts to help Ukraine. This is not a board he should be sitting on.&lt;/em&gt;“ &lt;strong&gt;New York Times Op Ed, December 12, 2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;… if President Trump honestly believed that there was a corrupt arrangement with Hunter Biden that was not fully investigated by the Obama Administration, the request for an investigation is not corrupt, notwithstanding its inappropriateness. The Hunter Biden contract has been widely criticized as raw influence peddling. I have joined in that criticism. For many years, I have written about the common practice of companies and lobbyists attempting to curry favor with executive branch officials and members of Congress by giving windfall contracts or jobs to their children. This is a classic example of that corrupt practice.&lt;/em&gt;“ &lt;strong&gt;Jonathan Turley, Esq. Testimony before House Judiciary Committee December 5, 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog Research, we publish reports and blogs focused on publicly traded company transparency, honest and full public disclosures and gray swan events. Professional investors and D&amp;amp;O insurance industry executives pay to subscribe to our reports because we expose the hidden risks and troubling issues that often cause a stock to lose value. As a public service, we do offer our reports to individual investors for free from our website. Our reports cover 6,500+ public companies, mostly in the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, such as with this blog, we have the opportunity to apply our insights and skills to other situations that need a healthy dose of transparency and our rock-solid analysis. We have been watching the developments in the impeachment of Donald Trump with great interest. The articles of impeachment have been delivered to the Senate and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/trump-impeachment-trial-in-senate-likely-to-start-tuesday-january-21-and-last-3-to-5-weeks-sources-say/&quot;&gt;full trial&lt;/a&gt; in the Senate is imminent. There has been talk that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/01/06/us/politics/bolton-testify-impeachment-trial.html&quot;&gt;John Bolton&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/biden-lays-out-his-objections-to-impeachment-subpoena-demand-11577558319&quot;&gt;Joe Biden&lt;/a&gt; may participate as witnesses, but the most consequential witness that we have not heard from is Hunter Biden. President Trump’s discussion with the President of Ukraine regarding Hunter Biden’s role as an independent board member of Burisma is the key issue to the impeachment case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already written a report on Hunter Biden’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;unusually high&lt;/a&gt; compensation for his position at Burisma, which is a topic he would probably rather avoid.  Our team has investigated Hunter Biden’s tenure at Burisma and found nine specific days in Hunter’s tenure at Burisma that might either prove he was an active, appropriate board member or he was instead a passive board member paid a whopping sum because he had a unique last name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason why it is crucial that the Senate get comprehensive answers from Hunter about Burisma and these nine days is because the Russians just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/01/13/us/politics/russian-hackers-burisma-ukraine.html&quot;&gt;hacked&lt;/a&gt; Burisma. The most effective way to prevent the Russians from interfering with the election by spreading potentially false damaging information about Hunter’s time at Burisma, is for Hunter to immediately disclose all his relevant documents from Burisma and provide complete and comprehensive testimony. For instance, how did Hunter act during the nine days we discuss below?  Did he fulfill his professional board-level responsibilities or did he simply rubber-stamp everything and allow Burisma to operate with little input or oversight? The answer will prove whether Donald Trump’s instincts were right or wrong to raise the issue of Hunter Biden with the president of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why we have taken such a keen interest in Hunter’s time at Burisma is because it gives us the chance to apply principles of good governance to a real-life example (actually Hunter’s story is less real life and more HBO movie). There is much that can be learned from Hunter Biden’s misfortune. And if you serve on a foreign board and your days start looking as bad as Hunter Biden’s, we would strongly recommend taking your career in another direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day One - The Day the NY Times Demanded Hunter Biden’s Resignation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffet famously admonishes his operating executives to apply “the newspaper test” to their actions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I ask the managers to judge every action they take — not just by legal standards, though obviously that’s the first test — but also by what I call the ‘newspaper test.’ If a manager expresses uncertainty, I ask them how they would feel about any given action if they know it was to be written up the next day in their local newspaper by a smart but pretty unfriendly reporter.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good test and one Hunter could apply on December 12, 2015, when the NY Times ran an editorial entitled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/12/opinion/joe-biden-lectures-ukraine.html&quot;&gt;Joe Biden Lectures Ukraine.&lt;/a&gt;”. It is worth quoting the relevant portion on Hunter Biden here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sadly, the credibility of Mr. Biden’s message may be undermined by the association of his son with a Ukrainian natural-gas company, Burisma Holdings, which is owned by a former government official suspected of corrupt practices. A spokesman for the son, Hunter Biden, argues that he joined the board of Burisma to strengthen its corporate governance. That may be so. But Burisma’s owner, Mykola Zlochevsky, has been under investigation in Britain and in Ukraine. It should be plain to Hunter Biden that any connection with a Ukrainian oligarch damages his father’s efforts to help Ukraine. This is not a board he should be sitting on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you hail from a staunchly democrat-party family, and your father serves as VP of the United States and the NY Times (one of your biggest press advocates dares to call for your resignation, you should probably listen.  Imagine the discussions taking place on that day in the Biden, Obama and Kerry households, not to mention just about all of Ukraine, Russia, China, US intelligence agencies, State department, Attorney General’s office, Congress, and a host of other political, personal and readers of the NY Times.  How could any son of a VP be so belligerent, obtuse or desperate as to not resign immediately?  Was receiving more than a million dollars a year for virtually no-show job, being paid by a pro-Russian, on-the-lam Ukrainian Oligarch worth it?  In our opinion, this had to be the worst of nine days in the life of Hunter Biden and Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Two -The Day Hunter Discovered of a UK Investigation into Burisma’s owner Mykola Zlochevsky:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 28, 2014, most likely right after Hunter joined the board, the UK’s Serious Fraud Office &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfo.gov.uk/2014/04/28/money-laundering-investigation-opened/http://&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; it was launching a criminal investigation into possible money laundering undertaken by Burisma’s owner Mykola Zlochevsky. The UK Guardian wrote an in-depth review of the case &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/apr/12/the-money-machine-how-a-high-profile-corruption-investigation-fell-apart&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Ultimately the case fell apart because of corruption in the Ukranian prosecutor’s office (someone there wrote to the UK court saying that Zlovchevsky was not under investigation, a bald lie which was probably the result of a bribe).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the launching of the investigation, mere days after he joined the board should have been a red flag for Hunter Biden that should have led to his initiating an internal board investigation into potential claims of misuse of funds by Zlochevsky or any of his staff who reported to him.  At a minimum Hunter should have demanded Burisma hire an independent, well-regarded law firm to do a review of the case to advise the board on actions it should take.  Hunter should also have insisted Zlochevsky cooperate fully with the UK in their efforts.  Any resistance by Zlochevsky in this regard should have led to Hunter to ‘resign loudly.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Three - The Day Hunter Learned Burisma’s Owner Was a Fugitive of the Ukrainian Government:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime after October of 2014, Hunter Biden learned that Zlochevsky, Burisma’s owner, was a fugitive wanted by the Ukrainian government. Although it was not until January 16, 2015, approximately nine months after Hunter Biden joined the Burisma board, that the government of Ukraine publicly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kyivpost.com/article/content/reform-watch/prosecutors-put-zlochevsky-multimillionaire-ex-ecology-minister-on-wanted-list-377719.html&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; Zlochevsky’s fugitive status. Zlovchevsky was under investigation for (amongst other things) of using his previous position as Ecology Minister to grant Burisma and its subsidiaries valuable licenses to extract oil and gas that were not granted to competitors. He also had been considered a lackey for Yanukovitch, Putin’s puppet and the former president of Ukraine whose ouster had started the ongoing war with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A point for context. Hunter Biden’s role as an independent board member required him to act as a fiduciary for Burisma. This means he owed the company a duty to act diligently, loyally, and in good faith to advance the interests of the company. What is in the best interest of the owner is not always what is in the best interests of the company, and we can find no clearer example of that than here in the case of Burisma. With Zlovchevsky on the lam, it was the responsibility of the Board to come clean with the government of Ukraine and restore Burisma. However, Hunter was not truly able to do any of this, especially since Zlovchevsky remained the sole owner and his people remained in charge. Since Hunter could not have discharged his duties as an independent board member, he should have resigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team struggled to justify Hunter’s decision to stay on the board. At best, we concluded that Hunter Biden might have stayed IF he had taken steps to approach the Ukrainian government (and given notice to his father and appropriate US security interests) to place Burisma into receivership or something like it. Receivership is an equitable remedy where a court appoints an independent guardian or trustee to oversee the company’s operations. Having a court or government take over a company in such turmoil is not unusual. It happens fairly often in the US through banking and insurance company regulators. Mostly these government takeovers occur to protect creditors in bankruptcy, but it can be used in other extraordinary circumstances, such as during war-time, which we would argue apply here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Hunter or other board members had taken such steps to put Burisma into receivership or remove themselves from the board or had engaged an outside regulator or appointed receiver, these high-paid board members would almost certainly have lost their lucrative board seats and ongoing cash payments. As farfetched as it may sound, given the wild-west nature of Ukraine at the time, they may even have faced threats of bodily harm. Is it reasonable to believe that after joining the board of Burisma that Hunter stayed on because he felt like he had no choice? It’s doubtful, since Hunter never visited Ukraine, and may even have been entitled to Sercret Service proteciton.  We must also not forget that during his board years he was facing extraordinary expenses in the US from a divorce, drug addiction issues, and other expensive personal challenges. It seems likely that Hunter’s primary reason for remaining on the board was for the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Four - The Day Burisma made an Large Sale of Operating Subsidiary Assets to Another Corrupt Ukrainian Oligarch Kolomoisky:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kyiv Post &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kyivpost.com/article/content/reform-watch/prosecutors-put-zlochevsky-multimillionaire-ex-ecology-minister-on-wanted-list-377719.html&quot;&gt;ran a story&lt;/a&gt;, noting that in July 2014 Burisma’s owner, Zlochevsky, sold up to a 45% equity share in at least one of Burisma’s subsidiaries (not Burisma itself) to the Ukrainian oligarch Ihor Kolomoisky, a reputed billionaire whom at that time owned the largest bank in Ukraine (PrivatBank). It is not known how much the sale generated for Burisma (vs. directly for Zlochevsky). It is also not known whether the funds to purchase the 45% interest came from Kolomosky himself or from PrivatBank. However, we do know both Kolomoisky and Zlochevsky would later flee the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, Kolomoisky controlled the Ukrainian bank PrivatBank.  PrivatBank, later nationalized by Ukraine, was the vehicle through which as much as $&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/investigations/oligarchs-weaponized-cyprus-eranch-of-ukraines-largest-bank-to-send-5-billion-abroad&quot;&gt;5.5 billion&lt;/a&gt; of IMF money was stolen. As reported by the OCCRP, “The central mechanism in the scheme was a series of insider loans to companies Kolomoisky and [his partner] controlled.”  Considering that Kolominisky held a considerable stake in Burisma’s subsidiaries, Hunter and the board would have needed to investigate to ensure that none of the stolen money was being hidden in Burisma through its subsidiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the money is often quoted in any fraud case. Given that the US is the primary provider of capital to the IMF, it would be wise for Joe Biden use his influence to force the IMF to follow the money from the IMF to Kolomoisky.  From there it could have gone to Burisma through its subsidiaries, and then to Zlovchevsky. If it had gone to Zlovchevsky and Burisma, then by association some could have benefited Hunter Biden, Devon Archer and the former President of Poland Aleksander Kwasniewski who were paid excessively high as board members. At the time, Hunter Biden should have forced Burisma to trace funds going in and out of Burisma, and those going in and out of the hands of Zlovchevsky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the Burisma equity sale to Kolomoisky: this sale reportedly occurred in the summer of 2014, after Hunter had joined the board. The board of directors would have needed to be intimately involved in a decision of this import, and Hunter should have received documentation and an opportunity to vote on it. At a minimum, Hunter Biden should have insisted on proper valuation of the subsidiary interests and demanded a thorough legal review of the transaction. This legal review should have investigated the buyer, and if it was Ihor Kolomoisky, or any of the Ukrainian oligarchs who had by then been named in corrupt practices cases, Hunter should have interceded to stop any further sale discussions and told other board members it would be appropriate to invite US or IMF regulators to weigh-in on their concerns about Kolomoisky. He definitely should have discussed this with his father, and Secretary of State Kerry.  This sale has all the hallmarks of a seriously corrupt transaction.  And as Hunter stated in his recent television interview, he understood that he had been asked to sit on the board because his name was Biden. This should have translated into a two-way street, as Burisma should have expected Hunter to be regularly discussing key Burisma and US and Ukrainian national security issues with his father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Five - The Day Ukraine’s Top Prosecutor was Fired&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PrivatBank was also a banking vehicle that indirectly processed US aid and/or loan guarantees to Ukraine. The IMF loss of billions (in part guaranteed by the US) was central to the IMF loudly demanding Ukraine fire its lead investigator Shokin, presumably for not investigating Kolomoisky and PrivatBank. Shokin has denied the IMF allegations and countered that the primary reason for his firing was his investigation into Burisma and by extension Hunter Biden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least in part because of IMF demands, as is well known, in March 2016 VP Joe Biden subsequently made $1 billion in US funding support for Ukraine contingent on Ukraine firing Shokin. Shokin was then fired and the US funds/guarantees were released. Thus, two years after Hunter joined the board we see evidence of a link between Joe Biden, his son Hunter, Burisma, missing funds, PrivatBank, Kolomoisky, the firing of Shokin and US national security interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of why Shokin was fired, the effect was to chill any ongoing investigations of Burisma and by extension, Zlovchevsky.  The subsequent prosecutor dropped the case, even though it was widely known that there was corruption at Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Six - The Day Hunter Learned his Business Partner Devon Archer Was Banned By SEC from Board Memberships:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunter’s fiduciary duties to the company should not only have created independence from the oligarch Zlovchevsky and his management team, but from the other directors as well. Part of the responsibilities of a board member is to assure the independence of the other directors. Now there was already a potential conflict. As discussed in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;previous report&lt;/a&gt;, both Hunter Biden and Devon Archer were overpaid compared to their peers. But the former President of Poland Aleksander Kwasniewski also was making &lt;a href=&quot;https://polandin.com/44767911/former-polish-president-and-the-ukrainian-investigation-into-biden&quot;&gt;a million euro a year&lt;/a&gt;. Unsurprisingly, these overpaid members would cause more problems during their tenure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 11, 2016, approximately two years after Hunter joined Burisma’s board with Devon Archer, the SEC filed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/litigation/litreleases/2016/lr23535.htm&quot;&gt;litigation release&lt;/a&gt; stating that it was seeking to bar Devon Archer from serving on any SEC regulated company boards and announcing the Southern District of New York was pursuing criminal charges against Devon Archer. Based upon our experience analyzing SEC cases, it is very likely that word of this investigation into Archer and his cohorts would have first become known to Archer and his business partners Christopher Heinz and Hunter Biden, in at least mid-2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no need to mince words here: Devon Archer, a long-time associate and friend of Hunter Biden was accused by the SEC of running a $43 million Ponzi scheme. In the history of US fraud cases, Ponzi schemes are considered among the worst financial swindles. And here it happened to Hunter Biden’s a friend, business associate, and fellow board member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, Hunter Biden should have demanded Devon Archer’s immediate resignation from the Burisma board and requested a full outside counsel review of Devon Archer’s SEC complaint to learn of what, if any risk Burisma was exposed to while Devon Archer served on its board. We note that back in the States, Hunter and Devon’s other politically connected partner, Chris Heinz, the step-son of ex-US Secretary of State John Kerry, seemed to make the appropriate actions to disassociate himself with Devon Archer (and Hunter Biden) when this news broke. By mid-2015, through his step-son, then Secretary John Kerry and most likely VP Joe Biden would have also become aware of the reputational risks facing Heinz and Hunter Biden through their close relationship with Archer. So in short, Christopher Heinz considered this news to be so disconcerting that he disassociated himself from all business matters, likely taking a significant financial loss in the action. Hunter continued his financial and reputational relationship with Archer, a move that is consistent with his refusing to give up his million dollar board-ship at Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Seven -The Day Hunter Learned One of His Other “Independent” Fellow Board Member Was Connected to Paul Manafort and Manafort’s alleged Payoffs and Diversions of Funds Schemes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 24, 2018, another New York Times story &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/24/world/europe/manafort-gusenbauer-hapsburg-ukraine-indictment.html&quot;&gt;ran&lt;/a&gt; linking then President Donald Trump’s ex-campaign manager Paul Manafort to illegal lobbying work tied to Hunter Biden’s Burisma co-board member named Aleksander Kwasniewski. Manafort illegal lobbying had been done on behalf of Putin’s puppet Yanukovych, whose removal had sparked the war in Ukraine. Kwasniewski was well known to Hunter Biden. Kwasniewski was the ex-President of Poland and allegedly &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;played an instrumental role&lt;/a&gt; in recruiting Hunter to the Burisma board in 2014. We say allegedly because Hunter had already been providing expert advice to Burisma and Zlochevsky through his employment with the Boies law firm. Manafort was subsequently found guilty of the violations for his work with Kwasniewski. Manafort was sentenced to 7.9 years in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When exactly Hunter knew of the connection between Kwasniewski and Manafort is unclear. But he certainly knew after the NY Times article hit. And when that happened, Hunter would immediately understand the intersection of the Trump campaign, his role on Burisma’s board, his close links with the Polish ex-president, Manafort and the potential impact his role might have on his father’s potential participation in the 2020 campaign. Joe Biden announced his candidacy a year later, April 25, 2019. Here again, our team could find no reasonable alternative for Hunter Biden other than his immediate resignation from Burisma’s board. Yet, he did not resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Eight - The Day Hunter Agreed to Serve in April 2014 – Overlooking a Cauldron of Conflicts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Hunter Biden agreed to serve on the board of Burisma, he was counsel at Boies, Schiller Flexner, LLP, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;advising Burisma on board practices&lt;/a&gt;. This paid professional role demonstrates Hunter Biden presented himself as an expert in proper independent board member actions. As such, Hunter Biden should have been expected to do the following before joining the Burisma board:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review financial documents&lt;/strong&gt;, including: Audited financial statements for Burisma; Previous board minutes for the last two years; Reviewing Burisma’s equity holders (cap table); Reviewing Burisma’s corporate charter, tax practices, subsidiaries and partnerships, along with all legal documents related to those. If any of these documents were withheld from Hunter that would have been a major red-flag leading to his refusal to serve on the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask for other board member bios and conflicts&lt;/strong&gt;, including: The names, roles, compensation, external conflicts and all written or oral agreements between Burisma and any existing board members regarding any possible conflicts of interest. Any questionable board members should have been interviewed and their backgrounds reviewed thoroughly for conflicts. Hunter should have insisted on an understanding that he, and all board members, should recuse themselves from any conflicted votes they might take while serving on the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company Legal Review&lt;/strong&gt;: Hunter should have asked for, and received, a review of legal issues from Burisma’s outside counsel before joining the board. This review should have included a three-year review of any Ukrainian regulatory requests made to Burisma and any violations or accusations made against the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conduct a war footing review&lt;/strong&gt;:  Before agreeing to serve, Hunter should have also met with US government entities, including his own father, to discuss the importance of the role of Burisma to Ukraine’s war activities with Russia (Recall Russia invaded Ukraine in February 2014) and to uncover any known or suspected corruption at the company.   Reuters reported that the owner of Burisma, Zlochevsky, worked as a deputy secretary of Ukraine’s National Security and Defense Council from 2012-2014.  Russia invaded in February of 2014 and the pro-Russian Ukrainian political leadership, including then Ukraine President Yanukovich, were all deposed after street uprisings in 2014.  We note this because it raises serious questions about Zlochevsky’s alignment or opposition to US national security interests at the time Hunter joined the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear it was certainly an odd choice to ask Hunter Biden to join the Burisma board. He had no oil or gas expertise and no expertise in Ukraine. War had just broken out between Russia and Ukraine and his father was just appointed as the top US diplomat covering Ukraine. There were strong reasons NOT to join. Yet, his joining may not sound as crazy as it first seems. To explain why, we need to briefly discuss the relevancy of Hunter Biden serving on the Amtrak board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senator Joe Biden was known as “Senator Amtrak.” He rode Amtrak trains to and from work in DC and often shepherded Amtrak spending legislation through Congress. Amtrak was Hunter Biden’s only other for-profit board member role. Amtrak board members require approval by Congress and Hunter Biden &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/CHRG-109shrg65181/html/CHRG-109shrg65181.htm&quot;&gt;got that approval&lt;/a&gt; in 2006. In other words, it took an act of Congress to approve Hunter working on a board heavily tied to his father’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to be clear here: We do believe Hunter properly acted as an independent board member for Amtrak. We could find no financial or personal relationship conflicts for him on that board. As such, we believe he acted ethically and appropriately, other than possibly being incompetent in his management and oversight of Amtrak. His compensation at Amtrak was minimal. His relationship with his father, who was NOT on the Amtrak board, actually lent credence to the idea that Hunter would act as an independent watchdog over Amtrak because Hunter could go to his father to leverage benefits solely for Amtrak. Benefits to Amtrak are exactly what an independent board member would seek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to paraphrase Sen. Lloyd Benson’s quip: Burisma is no Amtrak.  None of the favorable Amtrak-board elements existed for Hunter when he served on the Burisma board. Hunter Biden was paid &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;excessively for his Burisma board role&lt;/a&gt;. He also seemed to be paid for consulting work which breaks a cardinal rule for independence. There was also the danger that any steps his father took which may have been admirable, but nonetheless aided Burisma directly or indirectly (e.g. the firing of Investigator Shokin discussed later), would be perceived as mostly working to benefit Burisma’s owner. The optics of benefiting Zlovchevsky would be damning. He was a known Ukrainian oligarch who had served in the pro-Russian regime that had just been overthrown in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these elements are negative, we do not automatically subscribe to the belief that Hunter’s relationship to his father necessarily precluded his seat on Burisma’s board. If Hunter was open and honest with his father, the US State Department and Burisma’s owner and other board members regarding his allegiances to US national security interests we can see potential benefits in his placement – but never at one million a year. Any potential benefits we might identify, however, seem to be precluded by Joe Biden’s insistence that he and his son never spoke about Hunter’s activities and relationship with Burisma and its pro-Russian owner and sympathetic board members. But there could have been benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a long-standing business practice to encourage executives to accept cross-board membership as a way to help one company learn from another company. For instance, Disney’s CEO Robert Iger sat on the board of Apple for seven years until it became clear that Apple would enter Disney’s space. With that as context and the Amtrak precedent, one can understand why the Obama administration may have viewed the Hunter Biden-Burisma board role as a positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular supplies of natural gas would be a requirement for fighting the war with Russia. The US would obviously like to have a “connected” insider at Burisma rather than be blind to Burisma’s operations. From this viewpoint, it makes logical sense that Hunter may have been a benefit to US interests at Burisma. Except, again, his compensation at Burisma was exceedingly high and his Burisma role was far different than Amtrak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, Boies Schiller Conflicts&lt;/strong&gt;: Before joining the board, Hunter should have also requested a review about accepting a board role at Burisma, by Boies Schiller’s internal compliance officer to identify any and all conflicts of interest that could arise from Hunter’s joining the Burisma board while serving as of counsel at Boies. This review may well have required Boies to sever its relationship with either or both Hunter Biden and Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe the potential conflicts and implications from Hunter Biden’s role at Burisma and Boies arising are so significant that Boies may have exposed itself to liability from claims arising from an independently operated Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Nine - The Day Hunter Actually Became a Board Member and Receiving His First Monthly $83,000 Check:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Solomon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://https://johnsolomonreports.com/the-ukraine-scandal-timeline-democrats-and-their-media-allies-dont-want-america-to-see/&quot;&gt;timeline&lt;/a&gt; shows that Boise was receiving payments for services while Hunter was on the Board, and that Hunter was receiving consulting fees from Burisma while still working for Boise before being announced as a board member.  This is a big no-no.  Hunter ought to have undertaken efforts to end any conflicted relationship with Boies, Schiller &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; taking the position. It was a violation of his sole duty of allegiance to Burisma for him to accept payments from, Boies, Schiller during his time on the Burisma board. Likewise, Hunter should have suggested a review of Burisma’s outside auditor, specifically requesting the company seek new auditor bids from well-established, international auditing firms like Deloite, Price-Waterhouse, EY or KPMG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We note that The New Yorker &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2019/07/08/will-hunter-biden-jeopardize-his-fathers-campaign&quot;&gt;ran a piece&lt;/a&gt; claiming Boies, Schiller produced a report within three months of Hunter joining the board of Burisma. The report claimed Boies was “unable to identify any information to date regarding any current government investigation into Zlochevsky or Burisma,” and that Burisma was “vulnerable to investigation for financial crimes” or “perceived abuse of power.” It would be crucial to understand when Hunter received this report, and what, if anything he did with it or what his part was in preparing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summing It All Up:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burisma is like a Charles Dickens story, written to expose the worst kinds of crony capitalism, government cronyism, war, corruption, adverse national security interests, political shenanigans and old fashioned human greed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to put into words how stunning it has been to review all of the adverse situations that Hunter Biden encountered as a member of the board at Burisma. Undoubtably his tenure will provide the Senate with many avenues for questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Russians have hacked Burisma’s records it is crucial that Hunter’s copies of the records are subpoenaed and any problematic transactions are dragged out into the light of day before they are leaked online in a misinformation campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps the most pressing question is why did Hunter choose to join and then remain on the Burisma board for so long? What obstacles did his exorbitant salary place in the way of advancing both Ukrainian and US national security interests?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It certainly is true, as we originally pointed out in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;first blog&lt;/a&gt;, that Hunter Biden was being paid a large amount of money for sitting on the Burisma board. But it seems implausible that the son of one of our current political luminaries, a past VP of the United States and the current top nominee for his party’s presidential candidacy, would participate in the sordid world of Burisma solely for financial gain. Unfortunately, we draw a blank on any other way to reasonably justify Hunter’s decision.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>brian_lawe</name></author><category term="Hunter Biden" /><category term="Corruption" /><summary type="html">UPDATE: AG Bondi’s Presentation Adds More Facts and Raises More Questions</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/oligarch.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/oligarch.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Practice of Reverse Factoring Raises Transparency Concerns</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Practice of Reverse Factoring Raises Transparency Concerns" /><published>2020-01-07T12:37:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-07T12:37:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here at Watchdog, we are firm believers in transparency, and we take a critical look at any accounting procedures which tend to make financial disclosures opaque.  This guest blog on reverse factoring was contributed by Olga Usvyatsky, a former VP of Research at Audit Analytics.  She has a distinguished library of blogs and op-eds on accounting, buy-side research, and data analysis. Ms. Usvyatsky is currently enrolled as a PhD in Accounting student at Boston College, where she earned her MS in Accounting degree.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key factors in assessing a company’s business is understanding its sources of liquidity. After all, the most prevalent reason for a company to go out of business or declare a bankruptcy is running out of cash. Conversely, a not-yet-profitable company may stay afloat for an arbitrarily long period of time, and even consider an IPO, provided their investors are ready to foot the (pre-IPO) bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liquidity comes in many shapes and sizes, ranging from cash received from sales to taking on debt. Supply chain financing is a one of form of liquidity management that has received some extra publicity lately from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.muddywatersresearch.com/research/nmc/mw-is-short-nmc/&quot;&gt;prominent&lt;/a&gt; short seller, who claimed that NMC Health plc used an obscure reverse factoring agreement was to understate debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is Reverse Factoring?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at how the unusual accounting around reverse factoring (also known as supply chain financing) works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, the company that has accounts payable to a supplier may want to extend the terms payable on their invoices. One way to achieve this is to ask the supplier to use a third-party financial institution to buy the company’s obligations, and then settle these obligations with the financial institution. When the cost of such transaction is low, it looks like a win-win situation for the company and the supplier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting example is Masco Corp (MAS). In response to the SEC comment letter, the company  described how a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/62996/000006299619000038/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;supply chain finance program&lt;/a&gt; was used to increase accounts payable days to above 70.  In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/62996/000006299619000063/a2019q3masco10-q093020.htm&quot;&gt;quarterly report&lt;/a&gt; for the nine months ended September 30, 2019 Masco stated that the “amounts settled through the program and paid to participating financial institutions were $181 million and $188 million for our continuing operations during the nine-month periods ended September 30, 2019 and 2018, respectively.” As of September 30, 2019, the company had $879 million of outstanding accounts payable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problematic Issues with Reverse Factoring&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of supply chain financing appears to be on the rise. Yet, there is little regulatory guidance around the way supply chain financing transactions are accounted for or disclosed. This means that companies can report these transactions as either debt or liabilities. A company might not want to report the transaction as debt because of existing debt covenants that prevent the taking on of new debt. Additionally, some companies will choose to report the transactions as debt and others as liabilities, creating diversity in financial statements that make it difficult to compare peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue appears to be significant enough to prompt the Big Four to author an &lt;a href=&quot;https://fasb.org/cs/BlobServer?blobkey=id&amp;amp;blobnocache=true&amp;amp;blobwhere=1175836059659&amp;amp;blobheader=application%2Fpdf&amp;amp;blobheadername2=Content-Length&amp;amp;blobheadername1=Content-Disposition&amp;amp;blobheadervalue2=667317&amp;amp;blobheadervalue1=filename%3DAR-2019.UNS.020.BIG_4_ACCOUNTING_FIRMS.pdf&amp;amp;blobcol=urldata&amp;amp;blobtable=MungoBlobs&quot;&gt;open letter&lt;/a&gt; to regulators requesting additional guidance. From the investors point of view, it is a noticeable event. The letter implies that the Big Four, which audit &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/who-audits-public-companies-2019-edition/&quot;&gt;more than 90%&lt;/a&gt; of large accelerated filers, are facing challenges determining the appropriate accounting treatment of these reverse factoring transactions during the year-end auditing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The letter also expressed concerns that the transactions may not be even disclosed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“…because there are no specific disclosure requirements in U.S. GAAP related to these types of programs, there has been limited disclosure of such programs provided in practice”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These concerns are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.moodys.com/research/Moodys-Reverse-factorings-rising-popularity-comes-with-high-but-hidden--PBC_1195322&quot;&gt;shared&lt;/a&gt; by the rating agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, the SEC is stepping up its scrutiny of supply-chain finance programs. In the past few months, the SEC issued comments to issuers requesting to clarify accounting treatment and provide more transparent disclosures (see, for example, comments to Keurig Dr Pepper (KDP) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1418135/000141813519000056/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1418135/000141813519000075/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the main objective of the reverse factoring agreements is to improve working capital and liquidity. Yet, lack of transparent disclosure and limited information about such transactions, along with increased regulatory scrutiny, pose additional risks for the investors that need to be taken into consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Watchdog Blog Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:  Our team is made up of current and former Big Four CPAs, Public Company CFOs, Litigation Specialists, Lawyers, Accounting Educators, Ethicists, Regulators,  Entrepreneurs, and yes, even a few overly opinionated Harvard MBAs.  Our mission is to write blogs that promote transparency in corporate disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We offer free report to retail investors and the press on our home page.  If you want our reports for a commercial purpose, call our subscription manager, at 813-670-2060.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, call our content manager John Cheffers at 239-240-9284 or send an email to jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>olga_usvyatsky</name></author><category term="reverse factoring" /><category term="transparency" /><category term="MAS" /><category term="disclosures" /><category term="red flag" /><summary type="html">Here at Watchdog, we are firm believers in transparency, and we take a critical look at any accounting procedures which tend to make financial disclosures opaque. This guest blog on reverse factoring was contributed by Olga Usvyatsky, a former VP of Research at Audit Analytics. She has a distinguished library of blogs and op-eds on accounting, buy-side research, and data analysis. Ms. Usvyatsky is currently enrolled as a PhD in Accounting student at Boston College, where she earned her MS in Accounting degree.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/reverse_factoring.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/reverse_factoring.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Early Retirement for Target’s CFO</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-concerns-target/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early Retirement for Target's CFO" /><published>2019-11-21T16:21:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-21T16:21:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-concerns-target</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-concerns-target/">&lt;p&gt;Updated November 21, 2019:
We are updating our original blog on Target.
First, we note that Ms. Cathy Smith, stepped-down officially on November 1, 2019 and her replacement was named at the same time. Specifically, her replacement is a Target insider.  At a time we believe a new and fresh perspective about Target’s PPE is needed, Target went the other way and appointed Michael J. Fiddelke, 43, as Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer.  Mr. Fiddelke appears to have originally joined Target as a 29 year-old and has stayed loyal to Target since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our view, as we outlined originally, is that Target should be evaluating a serious impairment of its physical retail stores.   Such an action will take courage because any impairment would likely be a very serious hit to Target’s assets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be easier to believe such courage would come from an outsider with a track record of tackling difficult accounting realities rather than a long-time insider.   Mr. Fiddelke was Target’s most recent Senior Vice President of Operations and was previously the Senior Vice President, Merchandising Capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, we were also disappointed to note that Target LOWERED its audit fees last year.  Given the physical retail environment’s economic challenges, it seems illogical that audit services would be reduced.  Consider that Target’s competitors are increasing audit fees:  Walmart. Audit fees up 47.7%, Costco audit fees up 35.2 %, TJ Maxx audit fees up 40.6%.  Yet, Target’s audit fees are down 19.3%?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Armour recently was investigated by the SEC because of serious accounting issues.  We note this because, by our analysis, Under Armour was starving its auditor’s of resources.  We get concerned when we see any company reducing audit fees at a time when they are likely grappling with complicated accounting issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continue to see massive retail store closures and write-downs. Business Insider reports on this as a “retail apocalypse” with 9,100 retail stores closing in the US this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be looking forward to seeing what Target’s auditor (Ernst &amp;amp; Young) publishes as Target’s Critical Audit Matters.  We would hope there will be a significant discussion on valuing PPE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 10, 2019, Target’s CFO Cathy Smith resigned after serving in her role for less than four years.  We wish her well in her retirement, but with all the turmoil happening in retail we take a skeptical view of any 54 year-old CFO suddenly “retiring.” at one of the world’s top retail corporations.  Is there something else going on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watchdog’s Concerns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by giving kudos to Amazon which has no physical stores (sans Whole Foods) and  earned its top position by stealing market share from brick-and-mortar physical stores like Target, Sears and others.  We also note Sears filed for bankruptcy in October, 2018, which means the likely shutdown of all, or most, of the 425 Sears and Kmart physical stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Target revenue for the last five years has been negative.  Even without adjusting for inflation, Target’s revenue for 2018 was lower than 2014’s revenue.  Since revenue is derived from its physical stores, it is clear the physical stores are not as productive as they once were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you sensing the theme here?  It has to do with physical stores.  Every retail CFO in the USA should be closely valuing the true worth of their physical retail assets.  Doing so won’t be pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accounting terms, the polite term for a serious write down of any balance sheet asset is called an “asset impairment.”  An asset impairment happens when management states the previous asset value on their books is wrong.  Who determines it is wrong?  The CFO, auditors, CEO and/or board members.    To then correct the discrepancy between the older value and newly assessed value, you file an asset impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Target has 1,850 physical stores which now appear vulnerable to a major asset impairment write-down.  The retail market has changed and the changes are negative for physical stores.  Now may be the time to lower store asset values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does Target value long-lived assets?  Their 10k released March 14, 2018, Target states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Long-lived assets are reviewed for impairment whenever events or changes in circumstances indicate that the carrying amounts may not be recoverable…Fair value is measured using discounted cash flows or independent opinions of value, as appropriate. We recorded impairments of $91 million, $43 million, and $54 million in 2017, 2016, and 2015, respectively…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We note that Target has disclosed an average of only $85 million in impairments a year over the last five years – on a PPE base of $18 billion in non-land  PPE assets.  That’s about a 0.5% in impairment value.  Looking at TGT’s peers, we note Walmart took a $569m impairment when closing Sam’s stores and Sears took over $1bn in impairments in the last four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Target has consistently identified its disclosure controls “as effective,” starting in May 2010, TGT has added non-standard language ten times disclosing its efforts to implement an ERP system (three disclosures were over the last three quarters). The most recent disclosure came in the November 2018 10Q disclosing it is moving from “mainframe” computers to a more “modern” platform.  This does not inspire confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most likely there are serious internal discussions going on at Target about the asset value of stores. The CFO resignation and Auditor (EY-1931) fees might be evidence of a fissure at Target.  From 2017 to 2018 outside audit fees shot up 20.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our concerns about a possible impairment are valid, one might look at a CFO retirement as a delaying tactic or evidence of accounting disclosure conflicts within management.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joseph_burke</name></author><category term="Target" /><category term="CFO" /><summary type="html">Updated November 21, 2019: We are updating our original blog on Target. First, we note that Ms. Cathy Smith, stepped-down officially on November 1, 2019 and her replacement was named at the same time. Specifically, her replacement is a Target insider. At a time we believe a new and fresh perspective about Target’s PPE is needed, Target went the other way and appointed Michael J. Fiddelke, 43, as Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. Mr. Fiddelke appears to have originally joined Target as a 29 year-old and has stayed loyal to Target since then.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Target.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Target.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hunter Biden: Was He Paid Appropriately as an Independent Director?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hunter Biden: Was He Paid Appropriately as an Independent Director?" /><published>2019-11-15T05:48:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-15T05:48:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Burisma is a private company and Reuters &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trump-whistleblower-burisma-factb/factbox-burisma-the-obscure-ukrainian-gas-company-at-the-heart-of-u-s-political-row-idUSKBN1W91UG&quot;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; that it only brings in $400 million a year in revenue.  In our analysis, we would expect an independent director like Hunter Biden to make between $55,000—$83,000 a year at Burisma.  If Hunter made $83,333 a month as reported by Reuters, then he made over 12 times what a typical independent director at a private company would make.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunter Biden has been in the spotlight in recent weeks for his involvement on the board of the Ukrainian company Burisma.   The appearance of possible corruption exists for Hunter Biden’s term as director because his father was serving as vice president and playing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-09-25/here-s-what-we-know-about-joe-and-hunter-biden-in-ukraine&quot;&gt;key role&lt;/a&gt; in U.S. diplomacy in Ukraine during the early part of Hunter’s tenure.  Vice President Biden has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2019/09/27/flashback_2018_joe_biden_brags_at_cfr_meeting_about_withholding_aid_to_ukraine_to_force_firing_of_prosecutor.html&quot;&gt;publicly&lt;/a&gt; stated his quid-pro-quo tactic of withholding critically needed US financial support unless Ukraine fired an investigator who was, or had been, investigating Burisma.  Vice President Biden proudly announced the Ukrainians delivered by firing the prosecutor and replacing him with someone who dropped many of the charges against Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/29/business/media/fact-check-biden-ukraine-burisma-china-hunter.html&quot;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, Hunter joined the board of Burisma in 2014, shortly after his father was appointed as the lead US diplomat overseeing Ukraine.  The company was then mired in a corruption scandal.  Hunter has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2019/10/15/hunter-biden-speaks-out-amid-ukraine-controversy-admits-mistake/3983320002/&quot;&gt;stated&lt;/a&gt; that he was “focused on governance,” and other people &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-hunter-biden-ukraine/what-hunter-biden-did-on-the-board-of-ukrainian-energy-company-burisma-idUSKBN1WX1P7&quot;&gt;familiar&lt;/a&gt; with his role have said that he would provide advice on legal issues, corporate finance, and strategy, although he did so remotely and never visited Ukraine.   It has also been widely reported that Hunter did not have experience in Ukraine or in the oil and gas industry, and Hunter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2019/10/15/hunter-biden-speaks-out-amid-ukraine-controversy-admits-mistake/3983320002/&quot;&gt;stated&lt;/a&gt; that he would “probably not” have been offered a seat on the board if his father were not the vice-president.  Since Hunter was only added to Burisma’s board because of his father’s position, Hunter’s appointment looks like corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunter did have some previous board experience.  He served on the board of non-profits as well on Amtrak’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://edition.cnn.com/2014/10/17/politics/who-is-hunter-biden/index.html&quot;&gt;board&lt;/a&gt; for several years.  Undoubtedly, Hunter Biden would have been familiar with the SEC’s rules on proper board governance.  Given Hunter’s statement about focusing on governance at Burisma, it seems that his goal was to implement best practices at Burisma to help them clean up corruption.  Hunter was not the sole new Burisma board member added at the time.  His business partner, Devon Archer, also joined the board with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why Hunter’s participation on the board matters:  A company’s board of directors is the last internal line of defense to ensure proper business ethics are followed at a company.  In effect, both Hunter Biden and Devon Archer were serving as watchdogs for Burisma.  But who was watching the watchdogs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There Are Some Wrinkles in the Story&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we can make a comparison of Biden’s compensation to other independent directors at other companies, there are a few wrinkles that need to be addressed. The first wrinkle is that it is not clear how much Hunter was paid.  The New York Times &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/29/business/media/fact-check-biden-ukraine-burisma-china-hunter.html&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that he made $50,000 a month, or $600,000 annually. However, Reuters &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-hunter-biden-ukraine/what-hunter-biden-did-on-the-board-of-ukrainian-energy-company-burisma-idUSKBN1WX1P7&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that Hunter and Devon Archer’s firm Seneca Bohai LLC received two payments of $83,333 monthly, which it then distributed to Hunter and Devon Archer.  Reuters said that its source had seen records of those payments for 18 separate months.  If those payments were made consistently throughout Biden’s 5-year tenure, then those payments would amount to $1 million annually for a total of $5 million.   So, was Biden paid $600,000 or a $1 million annually?  Without more definitive evidence it is impossible to know. It is also possible that both are correct, and that he had a salary of $50,000 a month, and also received an additional $83,333 for a least 18 months of his tenure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It remains an open question as to whether Biden received any stock options in Burisma.  While everyone has focused on cash-compensation, it is often the gains on stock options which richly reward board membership.  To our knowledge, no one has reported (or asked) about stock options for Hunter Biden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the cash payments to Hunter’s firm present another wrinkle, that Hunter’s role at the company is not clear.  Those payments were made out to Hunter and Devon Archer’s firm Seneca Bohai LLC for “consulting services.”  There has also been a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/firm-hired-by-ukraines-burisma-tried-to-use-hunter-biden-as-leverage-documents-show-11573009615&quot;&gt;story&lt;/a&gt; in the Wall Street Journal that indicates a consulting firm was attempting use Hunter Biden’s name to get a meeting with the State Department and improve Burisma’s image in Washington.  It is not clear if Hunter was aware that his name was being used, but if this firm was indeed acting at his direction, that would certainly qualify as more then “consulting services” and would appear to be more like lobbying efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Consulting” payments to Seneca Bohai also do not square with Hunter and Devon Archer’s roles as independent directors at Burisma.  Federal securities &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/240.10A-3&quot;&gt;law &lt;/a&gt;prohibits any person from serving as an independent director if they “accept directly or indirectly any consulting, advisory, or other compensatory fee…” 17 CFR § 240.10A-3(b)(1)(ii).  Obviously, US law does not apply to a private foreign entity because they are not subject to federal securities law.  However, that squares the circle by putting Hunter Biden in the position of both claiming he was focused on good governance as a board member while also ignoring US best practices for board members.  By accepting “consulting” payments AND board compensation, Hunter Biden was potentially breaking a cardinal rule created to promote good governance and stop corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hunter May Have Been Paid Over 12X a Typical Salary for His Position&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that the payments to Seneca Bohai were for board member compensation to Hunter Biden (and Devon Archer).  Was Hunter Biden’s compensation as an independent director out of line? Our review of large cap public companies showed that independent board members typically receive a cash retainer of about $100,000 a year, with additional fees for serving as chair or serving on specific committees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Harvard &lt;a href=&quot;https://corpgov.law.harvard.edu/2017/08/01/board-pay-not-just-a-public-company-concern/&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; published in 2017 provides additional context.  That study showed directors at public companies typically receive more than half of their compensation from equity compensation, whereas at private companies, independent directors typically receive almost all compensation in cash.  Public companies typically pay more than private companies, but private companies give directors more cash as seen in this table from the study:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Biden%20image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Biden image1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burisma is a private company and Reuters &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trump-whistleblower-burisma-factb/factbox-burisma-the-obscure-ukrainian-gas-company-at-the-heart-of-u-s-political-row-idUSKBN1W91UG&quot;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; that it only brings in $400 million a year in revenue, meaning that we would expect an independent director for Burisma to make between $55,000—$83,000 a year.  If Hunter made $83,333 a month as reported by Reuters, then he made over 12 times what a typical independent director at a private company would make.  If he made $50,000 a month, as reported by the New York Times, then he would have made over 7 times as much as a typical private company director.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Hunter Biden was paid the same amount as an independent director of a large public company, then he would expect to make approximately $265,000 a year.  That hefty sum is still only a little more than a quarter of what Reuters reported as Hunter’s annual salary.  If the New York Times’ more conservative estimate of Hunter’s income is used, then he still made more that double what an independent director would make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was Hunter Biden overpaid? Yes. If he was an independent director, then certainly. If he received the money for consulting, then it would be hard to argue that he was overpaid, but it would be easy to argue that his claims of being an independent director “focused on governance” are a sham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joe and Hunter Biden story has many layers.  However, from a corporate governance perspective it highlights the importance of transparency and oversight for good governance.  Having directors who are familiar with the rules but only pay lip service to good governance is a failure.  To stop corruption, directors need deep integrity.  It seems Hunter Biden did not bring that to Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested in our Reports on Public Companies?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a free trial to our whole library of reports &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/free-trial&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Watchdog?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watchdog Research, Inc. is an independent research provider that publishes Watchdog Reports. Our reports contain warning signs, red flags, material disclosures, and peer analysis for use in valuation, risk analysis, due diligence research, and idea generation. Watchdog Reports are designed to assist investment professionals fulfill their fiduciary obligations and to help investors, executives, board members, regulators and educators learn what they need to know about publicly traded companies. Watchdog Research, Inc. utilizes over 75 specialists and analysts to provide accurate and timely information to our readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Watchdog Blog Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:  Our team is made up of current and former Big Four CPAs, Public Company CFOs, Litigation Specialists, Lawyers, Accounting Educators, Ethicists, Regulators,  Entrepreneurs, and yes, even a few overly opinionated Harvard MBAs.  Our mission is to write blogs that promote transparency in corporate disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 813-670-2060.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, call our content manager John Cheffers at 239-240-9284 or send an email to jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Hunter Biden" /><category term="Good Governance" /><category term="Corruption" /><category term="Quid Pro Quo" /><category term="overpaid" /><summary type="html">Burisma is a private company and Reuters estimates that it only brings in $400 million a year in revenue. In our analysis, we would expect an independent director like Hunter Biden to make between $55,000—$83,000 a year at Burisma. If Hunter made $83,333 a month as reported by Reuters, then he made over 12 times what a typical independent director at a private company would make.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/hunter_biden.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/hunter_biden.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tesla Part VI: Is Musk Truskworthy? Or Will Investors be Gored in the Latest Running of the Bulls?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-vi-is-musk-truskworthy-or-will-investors-be-gored-in-the-latest-running-of-the-bulls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tesla Part VI: Is Musk Truskworthy? Or Will Investors be Gored in the Latest Running of the Bulls?" /><published>2019-11-11T11:24:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-11T11:24:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-vi-is-musk-truskworthy-or-will-investors-be-gored-in-the-latest-running-of-the-bulls</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-vi-is-musk-truskworthy-or-will-investors-be-gored-in-the-latest-running-of-the-bulls/">&lt;p&gt;Tesla’s stock price is notoriously volatile.  When a profit was recorded in the third quarter, the stock jumped from about $250 a share to over $310 a share.  This volatility reflects the volatility of Musk himself, who has gotten himself into so much trouble with his twitter account that he has agreed to have a lawyer act as his twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/tesla-ceo-elon-musk-stricter-twitter-babysitter/&quot;&gt;babysitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our blog is focused on integrity of financial reporting and understanding the culture of management is the key to understanding whether a company’s reports are reliable.  If there is a lack of integrity in the management culture, then there will be a lack of integrity in the financial reporting.  Musk sets the tone for the management culture at Tesla.  He is the founder, CEO, biggest shareholder, biggest promoter, and is intimately involved in operations of the company.  So, does Musk foster a culture of transparency and reliability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Musk’s Troubles with Twitter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musk has been embroiled in more than one &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-48238576&quot;&gt;controversy&lt;/a&gt; on twitter, but the most expensive troubles have come from false or misleading statements about Tesla that have affected the stock price.    Musk set off a firestorm when he announced in August of 2018 that funding was secured for a buyout to take the company private at $420 a share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musk said this tweet came from discussions he had with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2018/08/13/elon-musk-confirms-his-bid-to-take-tesla-private-backed-by-saudi-arabias-sovereign-wealth-fund/&quot;&gt;Saudi&lt;/a&gt; backed fund, but later admitted that he picked the number 420 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/sec-says-elon-musks-420-price-point-was-a-weed-reference-2018-9&quot;&gt;specifically &lt;/a&gt;as a reference to smoking weed.  The SEC was not amused and sued Musk for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/dantedisparte/2018/09/29/elon-musk-versus-the-sec-when-a-tweet-costs-40-million/#4a4c7ed61556&quot;&gt;fraud&lt;/a&gt;. Within a month Musk was embroiled in yet &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2018-09-07/tesla-chief-accounting-officer-leaves-citing-level-of-scrutiny&quot;&gt;another&lt;/a&gt; controversy when he smoked weed on a popular podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of September, Musk had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/elon-musk-settlement-with-sec-costs-him-tesla-chairmanship-and-20-million-fine-2018-09-29&quot;&gt;settled&lt;/a&gt; the matter with the SEC; he personally paid a $20 million fine, and Tesla also paid a $20 million fine.  In addition, he agreed to step down as chairman of the board for at least three years.  The settlement also required Musk to seek legal pre-approval for tweets that could affect the company’s share price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By February of 2019, Musk was in trouble &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/04/26/elon-musk-sec-agree-to-guidelines-on-twitter-use/&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, this time for posting a tweet saying that Tesla would produce 500,000 vehicles in 2019, which he soon corrected.  The SEC wanted Musk to be held in contempt, but the parties negotiated a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/tesla-ceo-elon-musk-stricter-twitter-babysitter/&quot;&gt;deal&lt;/a&gt; whereby Musk essentially reagreed to seek legal preapproval for tweets that could affect the company’s share price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The punishments meted out by the SEC are little more than slaps on the wrist for a billionaire like Musk, but they serve as a warning to shareholders that Musk’s statements about the company are not reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tesla’s Management Follows Musk’s Lead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A company’s financial reports are nothing more than statements by the management of the company, expressing their opinion about the company.  Standardized formats, technical language, and spreadsheets do not magically transform these statements into objective facts.  Those statements are only facts if they are true.  So, has Tesla’s management done a good job of telling the truth, or have they followed Musk’s lead and made allegedly exaggerated, misleading, or false statements?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Part &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iv-solarcity-the-zombie-that-musk-cant-get-away-from/&quot;&gt;IV&lt;/a&gt; of our series on Tesla we looked at Tesla’s statement that the acquisition of SolarCity would benefit both companies, when SolarCity was in a liquidity crisis in retrospect has been little more than dead weight.   Tesla also may have misdirected shareholders by unveiling a new solar roof technology and promising to start production soon to get approval for the SolarCity acquisition.  Three years later, Tesla is yet to deliver on the promise of the solar roof.  In Part &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-v-is-teslas-financial-reporting-reliable/&quot;&gt;V&lt;/a&gt; we looked at Tesla’s statement to the SEC that the loss of its electric vehicle tax credit would have no material impact on sales.  That statement has been proven demonstrably false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only does Tesla’s management have a history of unreliable statements, but they also have some of the most complex accounting disclosures in the manufacturing industry.  The combination of complexity and unreliability is a volatile combination, almost as volatile as Musk himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our last post on Tesla (for now at least), but we hope that it hammers home the critical point that the reliability and integrity of financial reporting and the culture of the management are inextricable.  Concerns about the reliability of financial reporting are concerns about the culture of management.  Likewise, concerns about the culture of management are concerns about the reliability and integrity of financial reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For investors to make informed decisions, they need to look beyond the last quarterly report and gain some perspective honesty of management and the integrity of financial reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the Report for Yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/Watchdog%20Report%20for%20Tesla,%20Inc.%20-%20TSLA%2011.6.19.pdf&quot;&gt;Watchdog Report for Tesla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a free trial to our whole library of reports &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/free-trial&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Watchdog?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watchdog Research, Inc. is an independent research provider that publishes Watchdog Reports. Our reports contain warning signs, red flags, material disclosures, and peer analysis for use in valuation, risk analysis, due diligence research, and idea generation. Watchdog Reports are designed to assist investment professionals fulfill their fiduciary obligations and to help investors, executives, board members, regulators and educators learn what they need to know about publicly traded companies. Watchdog Research, Inc. utilizes over 75 specialists and analysts to provide accurate and timely information to our readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Watchdog Blog Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:  Our team is made up of current and former Big Four CPAs, Public Company CFOs, Litigation Specialists, Lawyers, Accounting Educators, Ethicists, Regulators,  Entrepreneurs, and yes, even a few overly opinionated Harvard MBAs.  Our mission is to write blogs that promote transparency in corporate disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 813-670-2060.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, call our content manager John Cheffers at 239-240-9284 or send an email to jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Musk" /><category term="Reliablity" /><category term="Tesla" /><category term="tsla" /><summary type="html">Tesla’s stock price is notoriously volatile. When a profit was recorded in the third quarter, the stock jumped from about $250 a share to over $310 a share. This volatility reflects the volatility of Musk himself, who has gotten himself into so much trouble with his twitter account that he has agreed to have a lawyer act as his twitter babysitter.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/tesla_IV_risk.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/tesla_IV_risk.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tesla Part V: Is Tesla’s Financial Reporting Reliable?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-v-is-teslas-financial-reporting-reliable/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tesla Part V: Is Tesla’s Financial Reporting Reliable?" /><published>2019-11-06T12:45:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-06T12:45:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-v-is-teslas-financial-reporting-reliable</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-v-is-teslas-financial-reporting-reliable/">&lt;p&gt;Tesla supporters have been reveling in the third quarter results that showed Tesla turning an operating profit for the first time this year.  Tesla’s stocks have shot up dramatically based on the good news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Teslapt5%20image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Teslapt5 image1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wave of enthusiasm started when Tesla released their financial statements for the third quarter.  Implicit in this enthusiasm is a trust in the integrity of the financial reporting, and a trust of the management team that has issued the report.  But should investors place their trust in Tesla’s financial reporting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our previous posts on Tesla suggest that the answer is no. Specifically in Part &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iv-solarcity-the-zombie-that-musk-cant-get-away-from/&quot;&gt;IV&lt;/a&gt; we looked at the unreliability of Tesla’s statements concerning their acquisition of SolarCity, where management’s conflicts of interest seemed to supersede valid business interests.  Parts &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-i-another-cfo-change-increases-the-probability-of-more-problems-at-tesla/&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-ii-just-how-unusual-is-it-for-four-directors-to-decline-reelection-in-the-same-year/&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iii-the-smart-money-is-getting-out-of-tesla/&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt; looked at things that would provide an inference that insiders and institutional investors have lost confidence in the reliability of Tesla’s reporting.  But we are going to go further, by looking at Tesla’s reliability light of the complexity of their accounting, their virtue signaling impairment, and their statements to the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accounting Complexity Leaves Investors in the Dark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking at the reliability of the financial reporting of any company, it is always a good idea to look the Watchdog Report graph on accounting disclosure complexity.  Tesla’s is particularly worrisome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Teslapt5%20image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Teslapt5 image2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look behind the graph. The SEC has made a serious effort to make all company disclosures &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/page/osdhistoryandrulemaking&quot;&gt;accessible&lt;/a&gt; to the public by requiring the use of standardized formats and standardized language.  As part of this effort, the SEC also requires companies to submit these filings in an XBRL format, so it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/structureddata/what-is-structured-data&quot;&gt;simpler&lt;/a&gt; for software to provide meaningful analysis without too much manual work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a practical matter, when a company makes a filing, they mark it with a set of standardized XBRL tags.  However, sometimes a company needs to use “custom” XBRL tags because their data does not fit into the standard language or format.  Our graph represents how often a company introduces these “custom” tags in comparison with their industry peers. Here is a look at the specific numbers for Tesla:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Teslapt5%20image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Teslapt5 image3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a company uses more custom language or formats than its peers, its disclosures are more complex, unusual, and hard to understand.  When the financial statements are hard to understand, then you must pin your hopes on the honesty and competency of the management team making the disclosures.  That is inherently risky, because management collects bigger checks when they report that all is well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our graph lets you know in seconds that Tesla’s reporting is difficult to understand because it has unusual terms or formats.  So, if you are going to put money in something you don’t understand, then you need a lot of faith in the management team.  Should you put your faith in Tesla’s management?  We haven’t forgotten about Tesla’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-i-another-cfo-change-increases-the-probability-of-more-problems-at-tesla/&quot;&gt;revolving&lt;/a&gt; door at CFO, where the current occupant is only 34 years old and has never worked anywhere besides Tesla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Will Tesla’s Critical Audit Matters (CAMs) Tell Us About the Complexity at Tesla?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will learn more when their auditors file their &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Standards/Auditing/Pages/AS3101.aspx&quot;&gt;Critical Audit Matters&lt;/a&gt; (CAMs) at year-end, and we get a sense of what parts of the business pose difficulties for the auditors.  With accounting complexity ranking this highly, we suspect that the CAM disclosure will name more issues that most of Tesla’s peers.  It will also be interesting to see which &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/progress-of-critical-audit-matters-cams/&quot;&gt;parts&lt;/a&gt; of their business pose the most difficulty for auditors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tesla’s Virtue Signaling Impairment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have noted this phenomenon before, at &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;Kraft Heinz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt;.  When a company issues an impairment on a loss that is immaterial, it concerns us because it is a sign that management wants to reassure investors that their internal controls and accounting methods are rigorous.  Such reassurances tend to make our team wary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Tesla reported a $&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000156459019003165/tsla-10k_20181231.htm&quot;&gt;13.3&lt;/a&gt; million impairment for a commercially infeasible product.  Keep in mind that Tesla valued SolarCity at $2.6 billion dollars in value, but was winding &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2017/10/18/solarcity-teslas-solar-boondoggle.aspx&quot;&gt;down&lt;/a&gt; its operations within a year.   Tesla unveiled the solar roof tile in 2016 and promised to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000156459017009968/tsla-10q_20170331.htm&quot;&gt;start&lt;/a&gt; production in 2017, a promise that they did not keep, but a promise that they made yet &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000156459019038256/tsla-10q_20190930.htm&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt; this quarter.  And what about the $5.8 billion in solar systems that SolarCity had leased to customers that made up the bulk of their assets, what happened to those?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did Tesla incur any losses associated with the acquisition of SolarCity that would require a write off?  With their complex accounting, including many unconventional lease agreements and tax credits, it’s impossible to tell.  In the third quarter, approximately $50 million of Tesla’s profit was due to a change in its provision for warranty, a one-off adjustment.  Will there be more major one-off adjustments, either up or down, for the final quarter this year?  Who knows?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tesla Denies a Loss of Almost a Billion Dollars in Tax Benefits is Material&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/businesses/plug-in-electric-vehicle-credit-irc-30-and-irc-30d&quot;&gt;IRS&lt;/a&gt; allows purchasers of electronic vehicles to apply a $7,500 credit to their taxes, this provides the manufacturer a benefit of effectively reducing the price of their vehicle by $7,500.  However, once a manufacture sells 200,000 vehicles, the credit phases out over the next year.  Tesla hit the 200,000 mark in 2018, and on January 1st, 2019, the phaseout began.  The credit was cut to $3,750 for the first six months, and then went down to $1,875 and will be completely phased out at the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC sent Tesla a letter asking to estimate any material effect this phase-out will have on sales.  Tesla’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000156459018021925/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;response&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We respectfully advise the Staff that we have not expected, and currently do not expect, any impact of the scheduled phase-out of the federal tax credit over the course of 2019 on our vehicle demand or sales to be material&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was this gusto, or obfuscation?  In 2018, Tesla sold approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autonews.com/sales/us-sales-rise-22-dec-saar-hits-2018-high&quot;&gt;182,400&lt;/a&gt; vehicles in the U.S. in 2018, meaning it benefited from $1,368,000,000 billion in government tax credits.  In the first six months of 2019, when the credit was still $3,750 credit, Tesla sold approximately  &lt;a href=&quot;https://cleantechnica.com/2019/09/08/why-2nd-half-of-2019-will-be-better-for-tesla-than-1st-half-part-1/&quot;&gt;83, 875&lt;/a&gt; vehicles in the U.S., benefiting from approximately $314,000,000 million in tax credits. Now that the credit has dropped to $1,875, the amount of government benefits they will receive will be even smaller.  Keep in mind that other manufacturers can still &lt;a href=&quot;https://mashable.com/article/tesla-electric-vehicles-federal-tax-credit/&quot;&gt;receive&lt;/a&gt; the benefit of the credit, making other all electric alternatives to Tesla more attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in 2018 Tesla told the SEC it did not expect the loss of the credit to have a material impact on sales, but after losing a billion dollars in the first half of 2019, Musk said that the step down in the credit was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eenews.net/stories/1060814477&quot;&gt;complicating&lt;/a&gt; growth in the U.S.  The third quarter results show that Tesla had $2 billion &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000156459019038256/tsla-10q_20190930.htm&quot;&gt;less&lt;/a&gt; in third quarter sales in the U.S. than it did in the third quarter of 2018.  This is partly due to a reduction Tesla has made in the prices of its cars, to offset the phasing out of the tax credit.  Tesla has joined with other manufacturers to lobby for an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-autos-electric-taxcredit-exclusive/u-s-bill-to-boost-electric-car-tax-credits-could-rev-gm-tesla-idUSKCN1RM1NG&quot;&gt;extension&lt;/a&gt; of the tax credit, but the current administration seems hostile to the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the loss of the tax credit has really hurt Tesla’s domestic sales this year.  Not only have they lost the benefit of the credit, but that same benefit now is giving Tesla’s competitors an advantage in selling their vehicles.  Tesla knew this would have a material effect.  This is same company that professes to have such rigorous controls and accounting procedures that they reported a $13.3 million impairment.    Yet they did not inform their shareholders of the expected loss of sales, and then doubled down by making a statement to the SEC that turned out to be demonstrably false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla has some of the most complex accounting disclosures in the manufacturing sector, and that leaves investors in the hands of management.  But has management proven that it is committed to transparency?  If you look at their statements to the SEC and their acquisition of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iv-solarcity-the-zombie-that-musk-cant-get-away-from/&quot;&gt;SolarCity&lt;/a&gt;, it seems the answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the Report for Yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/Watchdog%20Report%20for%20Tesla,%20Inc.%20-%20TSLA%2011.6.19.pdf&quot;&gt;Watchdog Report for Tesla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a free trial to our whole library of reports &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/free-trial&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Watchdog?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watchdog Research, Inc. is an independent research provider that publishes Watchdog Reports. Our reports contain warning signs, red flags, material disclosures, and peer analysis for use in valuation, risk analysis, due diligence research, and idea generation. Watchdog Reports are designed to assist investment professionals fulfill their fiduciary obligations and to help investors, executives, board members, regulators and educators learn what they need to know about publicly traded companies. Watchdog Research, Inc. utilizes over 75 specialists and analysts to provide accurate and timely information to our readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Watchdog Blog Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:  Our team is made up of current and former Big Four CPAs, Public Company CFOs, Litigation Specialists, Lawyers, Accounting Educators, Ethicists, Regulators,  Entrepreneurs, and yes, even a few overly opinionated Harvard MBAs.  Our mission is to write blogs that promote transparency in corporate disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 813-670-2060.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, call our content manager John Cheffers at 239-240-9284 or send an email to jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Musk" /><category term="Tesla" /><category term="TSLA" /><category term="Reliablity" /><category term="accounting complexity" /><summary type="html">Tesla supporters have been reveling in the third quarter results that showed Tesla turning an operating profit for the first time this year. Tesla’s stocks have shot up dramatically based on the good news.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/tesla_V.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/tesla_V.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tesla Part IV: SolarCity—The Zombie That Musk Can’t Get Away From</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iv-solarcity-the-zombie-that-musk-cant-get-away-from/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tesla Part IV: SolarCity—The Zombie That Musk Can’t Get Away From" /><published>2019-11-01T10:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-11-01T10:34:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iv-solarcity-the-zombie-that-musk-cant-get-away-from</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iv-solarcity-the-zombie-that-musk-cant-get-away-from/">&lt;p&gt;In Parts &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-i-another-cfo-change-increases-the-probability-of-more-problems-at-tesla/&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-ii-just-how-unusual-is-it-for-four-directors-to-decline-reelection-in-the-same-year/&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/tesla-part-iii-the-smart-money-is-getting-out-of-tesla/&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt;, we took a deeper look at their recent CFO change, their loss of four Directors, and the loss of the confidence of some of their biggest institutional investors.  In each of these indicators there is a possible inference that insiders at the company know about something rotten in Tesla that is obscured from the ordinary shareholders.  In this post we will take a deep dive into the SolarCity acquisition and look at the reliability of Musk and Tesla’s statements surrounding the acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A company’s commitment to transparency is important for the long-term health of any company, but it is particularly important during an acquisition because of the complexity of the accounting and the need for judgement calls from management concerning the value of control and synergies.  It is no surprise that &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/progress-of-critical-audit-matters-cams/&quot;&gt;17%&lt;/a&gt; of the Critical Audit Matters (CAMs) disclosed by auditors so far have concerned business combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The SolarCity Acquisition: Vertical Integration or a Bailout?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000119312516627916/d185582dex991.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that it had made an all-stock offer to acquire SolarCity on June 20, 2016.  SolarCity was one of the leading solar panel installation companies in the country.  Everyone expects a merger to be announced with certain ritualized glowing rhetoric and grand promises and Tesla’s announcement was no exception:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We would be the world’s only vertically integrated energy company offering end-to-end clean energy products to our customers…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We would be able to maximize and build on the core competencies of each company…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Culturally, this is a great fit. Both companies are driven by a mission of sustainability, innovation, and overcoming any challenges that stand in the way of progress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note, right from the start, is that Musk was the Chairman of the Board of both companies.  At the beginning of 2016, he owned &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000119312516543341/d133980ddef14a.htm#toc133980_41&quot;&gt;26.5%&lt;/a&gt; of Tesla and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1408356/000119312516736379/d231493ddefm14a.htm#toc241192_22&quot;&gt;21.9%&lt;/a&gt; of SolarCity.  There were other &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000119312516697498/d241192ds4.htm#toc241192_14&quot;&gt;connections&lt;/a&gt;, as board members of both companies are partners in other ventures together and both the CEO and CTO of SolarCity were close relatives of Musk.  In short, there were far too many connections between SolarCity and Tesla for this transaction to occur at arm’s length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there is a potential conflict of interest in a merger like this, there is a greater need for transparency because the courts may look skeptically at the transaction if it goes badly.  Tesla made its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tesla.com/blog/tesla-and-solarcity&quot;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; on its blog, and the story they told their investors was that 1) this merger would create the world’s only vertically integrated sustainable energy company, and 2) that a merger with SolarCity would benefit Tesla financially in the short term and long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine the first claim.  The vertical integration was announced repeatedly and with much pomp, but the claim is really a stretch.  Solar panels are rationally related to electric cars, but did the merger help Tesla make cars that were cheaper or better? No, this integration came from selling a potential source of energy for their vehicles.  Would Ford vertically integrate, using the same logic, if they bought Exxon?&lt;br /&gt;
After the merger, Tesla separated out its new residential energy storage product and paired it with SolarCity to create a new business segment.  So, in truth, Tesla diversified its business and their claim of vertical integration was mere puffery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Look Back at SolarCity Prior to the Merger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting aside the puffery, let’s look at the claim that the purchase of SolarCity would benefit Tesla.  At first glance, this claim seemed plausible at the time, since SolarCity had almost $2 billion in equity on their balance sheet, stemming mostly from the $5.8 billion in lease and to be leased solar system assets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a closer look at SolarCity’s income and cash flow statements from 2016, provides some crucial context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Teslapt4%20image%201.png&quot; alt=&quot;Teslapt4 image 1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SolarCity was able to dramatically increase its revenues in the two years before the merger, but only at great expense.  Not only were installation costs high, but the company also had teams selling the product door-to-door.  Sales and marketing accounted for nearly half of the companies operating expenses.  Considering that gross profits need to exceed operating expenses and interest expenses to keep a company in the black, SolarCity had no prospects of short-term profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because SolarCity operated at a perpetual net loss, it relied on debt and government subsidies to keep afloat.  To boost sales, SolarCity offered a no money down installation of solar panels to potential customers, but it would retain ownership of the panels and lease them to the customers.  This also allowed them to take advantage of something called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/IF10479.pdf&quot;&gt;Investor Tax Credit&lt;/a&gt; (ITC).  SolarCity’s description of how it used the ITC is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[R]egulations enable the ITCs to be separated from the ownership of the property and allow the transfer of these ITCs.  Under the lease pass-through fund arrangements, the Company can make a tax election to pass through the ITCs to the fund investor, who is the legal lessee of the property. The Company is therefore able to monetize the ITCs to investors who can utilize them in return for cash payments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, SolarCity’s business model was to purchase and install solar systems at great expense and recoup the costs over time with a combination of income from leases and cash payments for the accompanying tax credits.  But this strategy was failing SolarCity. The cash flow statements show that SolarCity spent over $1.6 billion in 2015 and 2016 on purchasing solar systems that were leased and to be leased, but that those cash outflows did not generate much revenue, with only $293 million in 2015 and $422 million in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Teslapt4%20image%202.png&quot; alt=&quot;Teslapt4 image 2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of the merger in 2016, SolarCity had $5.8 billion in assets attributable to leased solar systems, more than half of their total assets. Those leases only produced $422 million in revenue.  After the acquisition Tesla &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2018-05-01/tesla-s-the-biggest-reason-why-rooftop-solar-leasing-is-fading&quot;&gt;discontinued&lt;/a&gt; offering to lease solar panels with no money down.  By doing so, it essentially put an end to SolarCity’s business model, and it’s not hard to see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there were real concerns about the long-term viability of SolarCity because the ITC tax credit that spawned the solar business has been set to start phasing out for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seia.org/initiatives/solar-investment-tax-credit-itc#targetText=A%20tax%20credit%20is%20a,of%20investment%20in%20solar%20property.&amp;amp;targetText=After%202021%2C%20the%20residential%20credit,to%20a%20permanent%2010%20percent&quot;&gt;residential&lt;/a&gt; homes this year.  This tax credit has little hope of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.greentechmedia.com/articles/read/the-solar-industry-wants-a-tax-credit-extension-should-it-get-one&quot;&gt;extension&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Warning Signs at the Time of the Merger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these issues, there have also been reports that SolarCity was having trouble raising debt and that Musk’s other company Space X had purchased &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2019/09/23/tesla-solarcity-claims-detailed-in-newly-unsealed-court-docs.html&quot;&gt;$167&lt;/a&gt; million in bonds to keep the company afloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also serious concerns raised about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equities.com/news/tesla-and-solar-city-s-ridiculous-valuations&quot;&gt;valuations&lt;/a&gt; provided by the banks involved.  A number of concerns were raised, but there were two that stood out.  First, Tesla’s bank Lazard used Goldman Sachs to estimate their cash flows, but SolarCity’s bank Evercore used &lt;em&gt;SolarCity’s&lt;/em&gt; estimates for cash flows.   The second point was that Evercore used 6-8% percent perpetual growth for Tesla and 3-5% perpetual growth for SolarCity in its terminal value, which is problematic because it assumed growth that was higher than that of the economy &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also some suspicious behavior by Tesla.  In 2016, just a few weeks before shareholders voted on the merger with SolarCity, Musk announced that Tesla would begin installing complete solar roofs, where the individual tiles would act as solar panels. The tiles used in this announcement were &lt;a href=&quot;https://ftalphaville.ft.com/2019/08/28/1566985766000/The-great-Tesla-solar-roof-distraction/&quot;&gt;fake&lt;/a&gt;. Tesla was not ready to bring the product to market, and in the three years since the unveiling, only a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utilitydive.com/news/what-happened-to-the-tesla-solar-roof/550942/&quot;&gt;handful&lt;/a&gt; have been installed.  In context, the unveiling of the solar tiles seems like misdirection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to have confidence in Musk and his management team’s commitment to transparency when they use fake props to unveil an idea for a flashy new product right at the time when shareholders ought to be doing their due diligence for a vote on a merger that raises serious conflict of interest concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Musk and his Friends Won at the Expense of Other Tesla Holders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it seems SolarCity was a dog and Tesla paid $2.6 billion dollars for it. We would argue that SolarCity was worth far less than $2.6 billion, perhaps nothing, perhaps it was only a liability.  Since Musk and his friends owned stock in both companies, they were better off than Tesla owners who did not own SolarCity prior to the merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per the terms of the merger, each share of SolarCity stock was exchanged for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000119312516665620/d200129d8k.htm&quot;&gt;shares&lt;/a&gt; of Tesla stock.  If SolarCity was worth nothing, then most Tesla owners had their ownership diluted by the acquisition, except for Musk and his friends.  Take Musk for example, before the deal Musk had approximately 37 million shares representing 19% of the ownership of Tesla (his shares had been diluted by an offer earlier that year).  When the deal was completed, when Tesla &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1318605/000119312516773705/d292845d8k.htm&quot;&gt;registered&lt;/a&gt; approximately 2 million additional shares, of which Musk received approximately 400,000, or twenty percent, representing his 20 percent stake in SolarCity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predictably, the merger has led to securities litigation.  And this suit may have legs, as discovery is well underway, and trial is set for March 2020.  Musk has already been deposed for the case, and has admitted that he was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-09-09/musk-deposed-in-class-action-lawsuit-over-tesla-solarcity-merger&quot;&gt;involved&lt;/a&gt; in the discussions surrounding the merger, and that he was well aware of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2019/10/28/musk-deposition-stockholders-v-tesla-solarcity.html&quot;&gt;liquidity crisis&lt;/a&gt; facing SolarCity at the time. His recusal from the actual vote may not matter, as the suit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2019/03/19/tesla-and-elon-musk-lawsuits-overview.html&quot;&gt;alleges&lt;/a&gt; that 6 out of the 7 members of the board benefited from the merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likely that the case will resolve before trial, but the fact that this litigation has progressed so far lends further credence to the idea that this merger was a raw deal for Tesla shareholders.  As a corporate Watchdog, what concerns us about this merger is the possibility that Musk, along with his friends and relations, were not transparent about why they wanted to merge the companies, and that they benefited while Tesla’s shareholders were left with a smaller slice of the pie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the Aftermath of the Merger SolarCity has Proven It Was a Dog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the benefit of hindsight, even the most skeptical assessments of SolarCity were understated.  After the merger Tesla broke into two segments, automotive and energy generation and storage.  Energy generation and storage includes sales associated with Tesla’s Powerwall system, (a battery that will power your home in case of an outage), as well the solar panel systems that were originally sold by SolarCity.  Overall revenues for the segment have increased every year, but that has mostly been due to the popularity of the Powerwall system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less than two years after the merger, Tesla began &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-tesla-solar-exclusive/exclusive-tesla-to-close-a-dozen-solar-facilities-in-nine-states-documents-idUSKBN1JI013&quot;&gt;cutting&lt;/a&gt; positions at SolarCity.  It ended door to door sales, only offering the product &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2019/03/09/is-this-the-final-nail-in-the-coffin-for-teslas-so.aspx&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;, and ended a deal with Home Depot that accounted for half of its solar panel sales.  There have been other hiccups with the solar panel technology, with Walmart &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/8/20/20825566/walmart-tesla-solar-panel-fire-lawsuit-negligence&quot;&gt;suing&lt;/a&gt; Tesla for no fewer than seven fires started by defectively manufactured solar panels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a presence in stores, and with installations declining &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/f/613541/teslas-trumpeted-solar-shingles-are-a-flop/#targetText=In%20the%20more%20than%20two,or%20provide%20overall%20installation%20numbers.&quot;&gt;steadily&lt;/a&gt; every year, it seems that SolarCity is truly dead just three years after the merger, along with the dream of a “vertically integrated” all-electric experience for the consumer.  Musk and his friends promised the shareholders a dream and delivered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/f/613541/teslas-trumpeted-solar-shingles-are-a-flop/&quot;&gt;flop&lt;/a&gt;, at least so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Tesla’s supporters have had their patience rewarded, Musk announced earlier this year that 2019 would be the year of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://buffalonews.com/2019/07/30/elon-musk-says-tesla-hopes-to-rapidly-ramp-solar-roof-production-in-buffalo/&quot;&gt;solar roof&lt;/a&gt;.  He has offered the third iteration of the solar roof tiles to rekindle their zeal, at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextweb.com/plugged/2019/10/27/tesla-launches-solar-roof-tiles-v3-now-ready-for-primetime/&quot;&gt;$21&lt;/a&gt; per square foot for the experimental technology, when a conventional roof ranges from $3.5 to $5.5 per square foot.  True believers need to act now and install this monstrously expensive roof before the $8,500 Investor Tax Credit for solar installation beings to phase out next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the first announcement of the solar tile seems to have been made to sell the merger with SolarCity and not the tile, we wonder if this announcement is more misdirection for some other issue at Tesla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**SolarCity’s Enduring Legacy, A Boondoggle in Buffalo **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before SolarCity was acquired, Musk struck a deal with Governor Cuomo to have the State pay &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2019/08/28/cuomos-buffalo-billion-tainted-tesla-solar-city-faces-audit/&quot;&gt;$750&lt;/a&gt; million to SUNY, who would build and furnish a factory according to SolarCity’s specifications, and SolarCity would pay any additional amount required.  This was a part of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2018/07/12/former-cuomo-crony-found-guilty-in-buffalo-billion-corruption-case/&quot;&gt;scandal ridden&lt;/a&gt; government attempt to revitalize the city of Buffalo.  Tesla had promised that this factory would lead the industry in manufacturing solar tiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla’s accounting for this gift from the State of New York has undergone some changes.   Initially, when SolarCity was the original lessor, it put the factory on the books as if they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1408356/000156459017003084/scty-10k_20161231.htm&quot;&gt;owned&lt;/a&gt; it because of their potential exposure to cost overruns if SUNY were to waste money and leave SolarCity on the hook.  This project was valued on the books at over $800 million accounting for almost half of the equity on the books at the time of acquisition. That changed in the first quarter of this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Following the adoption of ASC 842, we no longer recognize the build-to-suit asset and related depreciation expense or the corresponding financing liability and related amortization for Gigafactory 2 in our consolidated financial statements.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla now recognizes the property on the balance sheet as a right-of-use asset.  The accounting for this gift is opaque, but that is nothing compared their lack of transparency about the status of the solar tiles that the factory is supposed to be churning out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10k 2016: We currently expect to commence production in the summer of 2017 at our Gigafactory 2 in Buffalo, New York, and begin customer installations of the solar roof later in 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q3 2017: We … plan to produce Solar Roof tiles at Gigafactory 2.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10k 2017: We recently commenced Solar Roof production at our Gigafactory 2 in Buffalo, New York, and are beginning to install them in customers’ homes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q2 2018:  We are also continuing to iterate on our Solar Roof product design and production and installation processes before ramping production…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10k 2019: We have been installing this product at a slow pace to gather learnings about our design and installation processes, and plan to ramp the production of Solar Roof with significantly improved manufacturing capabilities during 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q3 2019: … we are planning to scale over the remainder of 2019 and into 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reuters reported in May of 2019 that only &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-tesla-solar-exclusive/exclusive-teslas-solar-factory-is-exporting-most-of-its-cells-document-idUSKCN1SL1H5&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt; homes in California with solar tiles were hooked up to the grid.  Musk owns &lt;a href=&quot;http://money.com/money/4993071/elon-musk-spent-72-million-on-his-homes-in-bel-air-heres-what-his-lavish-life-looks-like/&quot;&gt;four&lt;/a&gt; homes in California.  Perhaps with the launch of its third iteration of the Solar Roof, Tesla will have more success, perhaps not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more problems with the factory than just the fact that the main product it is supposed to produce has been a flop.  Part of its deal with New York was that Tesla would employ 1450 employees there by April of 2020, and there currently are only 800 employees working there.  Tesla will need to pay  $41.2 million to SUNY every year that if fails to meet this benchmark.  Tesla has partnered with Panasonic and considered moving the production of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/roadshow/news/tesla-buffalo-gigafactory-supercharger-v3-energy-storage/&quot;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; products to the factory to boost employment there, but that cost more than paying the fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Workers there have &lt;a href=&quot;https://cleantechnica.com/2019/02/11/the-latest-news-from-the-tesla-gigafactory-2-in-buffalo-isnt-good/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that production is virtually non-existent and that employees sit around on their phones unless the press is scheduled to visit, in which case they block off unused parts of the factory and try to look busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that Tesla has kept SolarCity’s Buffalo factory open largely for show.  This has saved face for Musk and his management team but has probably cost Tesla an enormous amount of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of the merger, there was plenty evidence that SolarCity was not worth the trouble.  It bled cash, it had no hope of running an operating profit, and the tax credits it depended on were set to phase out in a few short years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the merger, even more evidence has come out supporting the idea that SolarCity was a dog, and that Tesla was aware of this fact when it went through with the deal.  In fact, the “launch” of the solar tile weeks before the shareholder vote seems to be deliberate misdirection.  The simplest explanation for all this evidence is that Musk and his friends had a serious conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transparency is critical to the long-term health of a company, because the accountability it brings helps management make good decisions, even when they are hard and humiliating.  The ongoing boondoggle in Buffalo is emblematic of the legacy wrought by Tesla’s lack of transparency surrounding the merger.  The question arises, if Musk and his friends aren’t committed to transparency, then what else might they be hiding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the Report for Yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/Watchdog%20Report%20for%20Tesla,%20Inc.%20-%20TSLA.pdf&quot;&gt;Watchdog Report for Tesla&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a free trial to our whole library of reports &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/free-trial&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Watchdog?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watchdog Research, Inc. is an independent research provider that publishes Watchdog Reports. Our reports contain warning signs, red flags, material disclosures, and peer analysis for use in valuation, risk analysis, due diligence research, and idea generation. Watchdog Reports are designed to assist investment professionals fulfill their fiduciary obligations and to help investors, executives, board members, regulators and educators learn what they need to know about publicly traded companies. Watchdog Research, Inc. utilizes over 75 specialists and analysts to provide accurate and timely information to our readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Watchdog Blog Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note:  Our team is made up of current and former Big Four CPAs, Public Company CFOs, Litigation Specialists, Lawyers, Accounting Educators, Ethicists, Regulators,  Entrepreneurs, and yes, even a few overly opinionated Harvard MBAs.  Our mission is to write blogs that promote transparency in corporate disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 813-670-2060.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, call our content manager John Cheffers at 239-240-9284 or send an email to jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Tesla" /><category term="SolarCity" /><category term="Buffalo Billion" /><category term="Conflict of Interest" /><category term="Vertical Integration" /><summary type="html">In Parts I, II, and III, we took a deeper look at their recent CFO change, their loss of four Directors, and the loss of the confidence of some of their biggest institutional investors. In each of these indicators there is a possible inference that insiders at the company know about something rotten in Tesla that is obscured from the ordinary shareholders. In this post we will take a deep dive into the SolarCity acquisition and look at the reliability of Musk and Tesla’s statements surrounding the acquisition.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/solar.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/solar.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>