<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-03T09:19:57-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">WEX Exemplifies Accounting Challenges that Accompany Mergers</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/wex-exemplifies-accounting-challenges-that-accompany-mergers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WEX Exemplifies Accounting Challenges that Accompany Mergers" /><published>2020-08-03T08:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T08:18:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/wex-exemplifies-accounting-challenges-that-accompany-mergers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/wex-exemplifies-accounting-challenges-that-accompany-mergers/">&lt;p&gt;WEX Inc (WEX) is a company, headquartered in Maine, that provides payment solutions. Over the years they have grown and expanded the number of services that they offer by going on a acquisition/merger spree. They have engaged in at least one merger or acquisition every year since 2015, and they accelerated this trend in 2019 with four mergers or acquisitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mergers have expanded the company, but they have also given them chronic internal control issues, leading to extensive irregularities in their accounting. A brief look at WEX’s Watchdog Report shows that their recent financial reporting has been riddled with red and yellow flags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WEX%20Flags.png&quot; alt=&quot;WEX Flags.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Ups and Downs of Mergers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appeal of a merger is that it is a relatively easy way to gain market share, reduce competition, and gain economies of scale. Additionally, many companies seek to capture synergistic value, where a firm not only gains the value of the two previously existing companies but also a new value that arises out of the combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies usually experience diminishing returns on their organic growth strategies associated with their core business over time, and that puts a great deal of pressure on companies to come up with alternative strategies to stimulate growth. Companies will often acquire businesses in the hopes that it will provide additional growth, but acquisitions pose their own difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers have waxed and waned in popularity over the last thirty-five years. As a &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/&quot;&gt;rule&lt;/a&gt;, companies are more eager to engage in mergers when the economy is strong/bubbling and are less inclined during harder times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Mergers%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mergers Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acquisition Accounting Challenges&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting scandals are often rooted in a merger or acquisition. The accounting challenges go beyond the technical problems posed by reconciling two different sets of books, it has to do with reconciling two different management cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron/&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; on Cronos Group highlighted the problems that arose because of a clash of cultures arising from a big investment by the tobacco giant Altria in the small Canadian pot wholesaler. But combining cultures is not the potential pitfall. Even when one entity completely devours the other and displaces the management team, as occurred in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;Kraft Heinz&lt;/a&gt;, the imposition of a new corporate culture on an existing structure can create serious challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turmoil in management can lead to problems with internal controls, fostering an environment that allows for incompetence or even fraud. Our research has shown that mergers are associated with management turnover, material weaknesses in the internal controls, restatements, and other reporting irregularities that we quantify in our Gray Swan Event Factor. Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has also shown that companies with a higher Gray Swan Event Factor tend to have lower returns on investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;WEX’s Chronic Internal Control Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WEX began its current acquisition spree in 2015. Since then it has acquired or merged with at least one company every year. In 2019, WEX accelerated this trend by acquiring/merging with four companies. Concurrently, WEX has experienced serious internal control problems and material weaknesses in their financial reporting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WEX%20controls%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;WEX controls chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of the beginning of 2020, WEX appears to have remediated its material weaknesses, but more trouble lies ahead. WEX did not include the four companies it acquired in 2019 in its assessment of its internal controls:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Company acquired Noventis, Inc. on January 24, 2019, Pavestone Capital, LLC on February 14, 2019, Discovery Benefits, Inc. on March 5, 2019, and Go Fuel Card on July 1, 2019. Management excluded these four businesses from its assessment of the effectiveness of the Company’s internal control over financial reporting as of December 31, 2019. These exclusions were in accordance with Securities and Exchange Commission guidance that an assessment of a recently acquired business’s internal control over financial reporting may be omitted from management’s report on internal control over financial reporting in the year of acquisition of the business. These four businesses represented, in aggregate, approximately 8.3% of the Company’s total consolidated assets (excluding goodwill and intangibles, which are included within the scope of the assessment) and 8.9% of total consolidated revenues, as of and for the year ended December 31, 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering WEX’s track record, we can expect many more internal control problems stemming from its 2019 acquisitions.  The potential internal control issues stemming from its four mergers last year have greatly increased the company’s Gray Swan Event Factor, which is a metric we use to quantify the risk of an accounting-related problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Pandemic Spoils the Appetite for Acquisitions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers often decline when the economy hits a rough patch, but the current pandemic appears to have decimated Corporate America’s appetite for mergers. We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/&quot;&gt;discussed&lt;/a&gt; this phenomenon when BorgWarner looked like it would back out of its deal with Delphi (although they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.borgwarner.com/newsroom/press-releases/2020/05/06/borgwarner-and-delphi-technologies-enter-into-amendment-to-transaction-agreement&quot;&gt;appear&lt;/a&gt; to have patched things up). After the pandemic struck, WEX &lt;a href=&quot;https://seekingalpha.com/news/3571322-enett-optal-fight-wexs-attempt-to-nix-deal&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; also planned on ditching the mergers it had planned for this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the economy is experiencing this downturn, accounting related risks have loomed larger. WEX gorged itself on mergers in 2019, hopefully an economic recovery will buoy the company when it starts to experience the first signs of indigestion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Mergers" /><category term="featured" /><category term="WEX" /><category term="Mergers" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><summary type="html">WEX Inc (WEX) is a company, headquartered in Maine, that provides payment solutions. Over the years they have grown and expanded the number of services that they offer by going on a acquisition/merger spree. They have engaged in at least one merger or acquisition every year since 2015, and they accelerated this trend in 2019 with four mergers or acquisitions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/WEX%20picture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/WEX%20picture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SEC Comment Letters and Accounting Problems Plague Contura Energy, Inc. “CTRA”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-and-accounting-problems-plague-contura-energy-inc-ctra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEC Comment Letters and Accounting Problems Plague Contura Energy, Inc. “CTRA”" /><published>2020-07-24T12:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T12:19:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-and-accounting-problems-plague-contura-energy-inc-ctra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-and-accounting-problems-plague-contura-energy-inc-ctra/">&lt;p&gt;CTRA is a company that mines and processes coal before selling it to powerplants and steel producers. 2020 has brought some unexpected challenges for all energy producing companies, as demand has fallen sharply. According to the U.S. Energy Information Association, demand for coal is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eia.gov/outlooks/steo/report/coal.php#:\~:text=EIA%20forecasts%20that%20U.S.%20coal%20exports%20will%20decrease,by%2032%25%20to%2063%20MMst.&amp;amp;text=Based%20on%20an%20assumed%20increase,for%20U.S.%20coal%20in%20India.&quot;&gt;down 37%&lt;/a&gt; from last year. But CTRA is not merely struggling with the fallout of the pandemic, there recent disclosures have raised a bevy of red flags related to their accounting and internal controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repetitive SEC Comment Letters Raise a Red Flag&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our friend and occasional guest contributor, Olga Usvyatsky CPA , drew our attention to CTRA’s recent SEC Comment Letters. These letters concern Item 101(c)(1)(vii) of Regulation S-K, which requires a company to disclose the names of any customers that account for more than 10% of revenue, &lt;em&gt;if the loss of that customer would have a materially adverse effect on the company.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CTRA does not disclose the list of its customers, even though one of their clients &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000095010319008988/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;accounted&lt;/a&gt; for 16.7% of revenue, and their top ten consumers account for 60%. When the SEC first asked about this issue in June of 2019, CTRA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000095010319008248/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt; that the market for coal was highly liquid, and therefore the loss of any one customer would not be material because they would easily be replaced. Markets tend to be liquid when demand consistently outpaces supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CTRA does not explain in their comment letter why the market for coal is highly liquid, but we will take them at their word that this is usually the case, even with a limited consumer base. Thereafter CTRA included their dependence on a few large customers in their risk factor section, although they continued to omit the names of its customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remarkably, in May 2020 the SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000000000020003775/filename1.pdf&quot;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;the exact same question&lt;/em&gt; they had asked in June of 2019. The most reasonable explanation for this repetition is that the SEC staff members believe the impact of the coronavirus out to have changed CTRA’s response. Yet CTRA gave this response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Given the fluid nature of the commodity market for coal products sold by the Company, we do not think a loss of any such customer &lt;strong&gt;would have a material adverse effect&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;on the&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;long-term financial results&lt;/strong&gt; or prospects of our business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Company respectfully advises the Staff that &lt;strong&gt;in a customary business environment&lt;/strong&gt; the coal market exhibits high levels of liquidity given the nature of the commodity. Our sales force is experienced in moving coal sales volumes from one account to another as required by market conditions, either with established customers or new customers.&lt;/em&gt;(emphasis added)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two parts of this statement are problematic, so we will take each in turn. The first problem is that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/229.101&quot;&gt;regulation&lt;/a&gt; asks for the names of customers if their loss would be material. It does not qualify this requirement by stating that the loss must be material in the “long-term.” Here CTRA qualifies their statement by saying the loss of any one customer would not be material “on the long-term financial results.” But what about the impact right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in a relatively illiquid market the loss of an important customer might not have a material effect in the “long-term.” Could CTRA replace a lost customer within a day? A week? A month? A quarter? A year? A decade? In the “long-term” it is possible that coal power plants will be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/fernandezelizabeth/2020/03/26/the-us-comes-one-step-closer-to-producing-commercial-fusion-power/#43744d8a6a35&quot;&gt;replaced&lt;/a&gt; with fusion power plants. Lots of things can happen if you stretch out your time horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that amid this coronavirus we are not in a “customary business environment.” As stated earlier, demand has fallen over 37% from last year. Cratering demand means that the market is losing its liquidity. We know that the price of coal is falling because of excess supply, making it more difficult for CTRA to resell their coal on similar terms if one of their big customers scales back use or ceases operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know that CTRA expects this collapse in price to continue for some time in the future. In their latest quarterly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000170471520000021/contura0331202010-q.htm&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, CTRA wrote off $33 million dollars in mines which are not viable at the current price point, and their estimates for the future do not show them recovering:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[D]ue to declines in metallurgical and thermal coal pricing which reduced forecasted margins at certain locations to amounts below those required for full recoverability, the Company determined that indicators of impairment were present for four long-lived asset groups…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just when will things go back to a “customary business environment?” Hopefully, it will in the “long-term.” As for the SEC, they seem satisfied with CTRA’s response since they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000000000020005481/filename1.pdf&quot;&gt;completed&lt;/a&gt; their review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;CTRA’s Parts Ways with KPMG over Internal Control Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, CTRA dismissed their auditor KPMG and replaced them with RSM US LLP. KPMG had given the company an adverse opinion in their annual &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000170471520000010/contura1231201910-k.htm&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; for 2019. KPMG highlighted material weaknesses in the risk assessment process was ineffective and their staff was not properly trained in certain control procedures. As a result, there are substantial questions concerning the company’s valuations of its coal inventory, as well as what it reported about its procurement process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of proper internal controls greatly increases the risk that the financial statements could be restated due to error or fraud. It also opens the company to potential litigation if the financial statements turn out to be false. Perhaps the best protection that CTRA currently has against litigation is the fact that their share price has already hit rock bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CTRA%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;CTRA chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has hit all energy companies hard, and hopefully the impacts of this virus will be relatively short lived. This may be a great time to buy energy companies if you believe demand will recover over time, and the stock prices will follow. However, investors should be aware of potential accounting issues that can hinder a company’s stock price. With its auditor changes and internal control issues, CTRA is facing far more challenges on its road to recovery than just recovering from the impact of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><category term="CTRA" /><category term="Auditor Change" /><category term="Coronavirus" /><summary type="html">CTRA is a company that mines and processes coal before selling it to powerplants and steel producers. 2020 has brought some unexpected challenges for all energy producing companies, as demand has fallen sharply. According to the U.S. Energy Information Association, demand for coal is down 37% from last year. But CTRA is not merely struggling with the fallout of the pandemic, there recent disclosures have raised a bevy of red flags related to their accounting and internal controls.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CTRA%20picture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CTRA%20picture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Party is Over at “CRON”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Party is Over at “CRON”" /><published>2020-07-17T14:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-17T14:56:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When CRON &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000030/q3exhibit991fs.htm&quot;&gt;restated&lt;/a&gt; the third quarter results for 2019, it attributed the restatement to “accounting errors.” Accounting errors? No kidding! Over a quarter of the company’s supposed revenue went up in smoke.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cronos Group, Inc “CRON” is headquartered in Canada and sells cannabis and its derivative products wholesale. They sell the “medicinal” kind of cannabis in Canada, Israel, and Colombia, where it is legal. And in the U.S., they sell CBD oil and other cannabis derivatives that contain negligible amounts of THC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON was listed on the Nasdaq in May of 2018 and was initially listed as a foreign entity with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;Emerging Growth Company&lt;/a&gt; (EGC) status. Last March, the tobacco giant Altria &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000117184319001610/exh_991.htm&quot;&gt;invested&lt;/a&gt; $1.8 billion in CRON. Under the terms of the deal Altria received 45% of the stock with a warrant to purchase another 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Altria’s cash and valuable experience, CRON seemed poised to dominate the pot market, but there was a catch. Altria’s investment meant that starting in 2020, CRON’s accounting would be subject to more scrutiny. They would no longer qualify as an EGC, or as foreign filer, meaning their accounting would need to comply with GAAP and their auditor KPMG would be required to test their internal controls throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON’s accounting did not hold up well to the extra scrutiny. In March, CRON restated revenue for 2019 and revealed material weaknesses in their internal controls. As can be seen from our Gray Swan Event Factor table, these revelations indicate that CRON will face significant challenges going forward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CRON%20GSEF.png&quot; alt=&quot;CRON GSEF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Restatement Cancels Revenue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 2nd, CRON filed an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000012/cronos12b-25.htm&quot;&gt;incomplete&lt;/a&gt; annual report, citing an internal effort to properly account for revenue from certain wholesale transactions. On March 17th, CRON &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000017/pressrelease-200317.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that it would need to restate its previously issued financial information by canceling C$7.6 million (approximately $5.6 million U.S.) in recorded sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their unaudited 2019 third quarter results, CRON had claimed to have brought in C$31,111 million in gross revenue (approximately $23 million in U.S. dollars). After revealing that over $5 million in sales &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;never occurred&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, they reported that their annual gross revenues were only $25.6 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When CRON &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000030/q3exhibit991fs.htm&quot;&gt;restated&lt;/a&gt; the third quarter results from 2019, it attributed the problem to “accounting errors… due to three wholesale transactions… that were inappropriately accounted for as revenue.” Accounting errors? No kidding! Over a quarter of the company’s supposed revenue a at that time simply did not exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to believe management’s contention that this overstatement was due to an “accounting error” and not outright manipulation and fraud. After all, it beggars belief that the CFO and CEO would be unaware of the details of these &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; wholesale transactions that accounted &lt;em&gt;for a quarter&lt;/em&gt; of the company’s revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;EGCs Internal Controls and Material Weaknesses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON brought on KPMG in May 2018 after it was listed on the Nasdaq. The management at CRON probably wanted to increase investor confidence by hiring a Big 4 firm with lots of experience. But as an EGC, CRON did not have to comply with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;SOX 404(b)&lt;/a&gt;, so KPMG did not test the company’s internal controls throughout the year or offer an opinion of the effectiveness of those controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all changed in 2020, when CRON lost its EGC status after Altria’s investment. The internal investigation that eventually revealed these “accounting errors” was conducted at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000012/cronos12b-25.htm&quot;&gt;direction&lt;/a&gt; of the Audit Committee, indicating that KPMG may have discovered the suspicious transactions while testing the internal controls and alerted the Audit Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KPMG also filed a Critical Audit Matter (CAM) for the revenue recognition related to the company’s wholesale purchases. Auditors are required to file CAMs in their annual report to disclose when a matter requires particularly challenging, complex, or subjective judgements. Investors should pay attention to CAMs because they indicate which numbers in the annual report may be “subjective,” and therefore easier to manipulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, KPMG identified three material weaknesses in the internal controls for the financial reporting of CRON. The weaknesses related to risk assessment, lack of segregation between purchase and sale responsibilities, and an inability to ensure that “non-routine transactions” that &lt;em&gt;deviated from contract terms&lt;/em&gt; were properly authorized and recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Did CRON Add Over $5 Million with an “Accounting Error”?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its CAM disclosure, KPMG specifically pointed to non-monetary transactions where CRON simultaneously purchased and sold inventory with a vendor. Cron would trade dried cannabis flowers for cannabis resin in a “non-monetary transaction.” The company states that no revenue should be recognized from these transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we read the tea leaves, it appears that someone at CRON engaged in three “non-routine transactions” with their vendor, deviating from the terms of the sales contract and recording large amounts of revenue from the transactions, when they actually were non-monetary “trades” that raised no revenue. Additionally, whomever was responsible for this apparently did not record the transaction properly or notify the CEO or CFO of what they were doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bizarrely, the CFO and CEO didn’t notice or ask any questions, which is weird because these non-monetary transactions would not have brought in any new cash, even though they apparently accounted for $5 million in gross sales. The SEC seems interested in how this could have happened; they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/exclusive-pot-company-cronos-receives-sec-inquiry-2020-03-19?mod=bnbh&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; asked CRON to preserve documents concerning the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corporate Governance Problems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a merger, there can be all sorts of problems that arise when bringing together two different management teams. Altria’s investment created a similar problem at CRON. Altria &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000119312519076836/d690389dex992.htm&quot;&gt;added&lt;/a&gt; four new members to the board and brought in Jeffery Barbato as CFO in April 2019. The first “accounting error” occurred in the second quarter of 2019 so that it was Altria’s Barbato that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000156459019030406/cron-ex994_7.htm&quot;&gt;certified&lt;/a&gt; both of the quarterly statements containing over $5 million in “accounting errors”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also interesting that Bruce Gates, added to the board by Altria and Chairman of the Compensation Committee, resigned the same day that the restatement was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000019/form8kb.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt;. If that wasn’t fishy enough, the explanation for his departure was that he was “going to focus on other increased professional responsibilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON may have been happy to take Altria’s money, but Altria is a big tobacco company, not a charity. The team members Altria brought in may have been putting a lot of pressure on CRON to accelerate growth. That pressure, coupled with inadequate internal controls, may have created the perfect environment for “accounting errors.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current situation for the top brass of CRON is untenable, expect major changes this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;KPMG Cleaning up the Accounting…For a Price&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON has given over $2 million to KPMG for its services in 2020. That’s 7% of revenue! In total, they have spent &lt;a href=&quot;https://seekingalpha.com/article/4345058-cronos-group-inc-cron-ceo-mike-gorenstein-on-q1-2020-results-earnings-call-transcript?page=6&quot;&gt;$4.4 million&lt;/a&gt; on the internal review costs related to the restatement. It is likely that they will spend much more as the remediation efforts continue and the litigation costs pile up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One bright spot for CRON is that KPMG appears to have helped reduce the complexity of CRON’s disclosures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CRON%20Complexity%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;CRON Complexity Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial disclosures decrease in complexity when companies use fewer custom XBRL tags. It appears that CRON has made an effort in 2020 to put their disclosures into more standard and accessible language. It is likely that KPMG has been assisting them in this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON is a posterchild for the why the U.S. should reconsider allowing Emerging Growth Companies to forego the SOX 404(b) auditor attestation requirement. We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;discussed&lt;/a&gt; this problem when looking at Luckin’s fraud. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, when the SEC further scaled back the number of companies required to comply with SOX 404(b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the auditor is not testing the internal controls of a company throughout the year, there is very little incentive for management to develop proper internal controls over financial reporting. This creates the perfect environment for the manipulation of financial results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If investors want to protect themselves from potential machinations by management, they should demand that their companies get an auditor to attest to the internal controls, even when they are exempt from SOX 404(b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Watchdog Spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Emerging Growth Companies" /><category term="CRON" /><category term="Errors" /><summary type="html">When CRON restated the third quarter results for 2019, it attributed the restatement to “accounting errors.” Accounting errors? No kidding! Over a quarter of the company’s supposed revenue went up in smoke.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/next-green-wave-JPI6SKrd-Rw-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/next-green-wave-JPI6SKrd-Rw-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Slacker Standards: SEC Exempts Even More Companies From 404(b)</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slacker Standards: SEC Exempts Even More Companies From 404(b)" /><published>2020-07-14T07:29:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-14T07:29:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is scant evidence that 404(b) is scaring companies away from the public marketplace, but there is evidence that the sort of companies that just got an exception from 404(b) were the ones who needed it most.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC issued a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/rules/final/2020/34-88365.pdf&quot;&gt;rule&lt;/a&gt; that took effect on April 27th, 2020 that exempted even more companies from the auditor attestation requirement of SOX Section 404(b). The SEC accomplished this by adjusting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/rules/final/2020/34-88365.pdf&quot;&gt;definitions&lt;/a&gt; of “accelerated” and “large accelerated” filers. We have &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt; discussed 404(b) when looking at Luckin Coffee, and we decried how the loosening of 404(b) by the JOBS Act allowed Luckin’s fraud to go undetected. But this new regulation merits a deeper discussion of 404(b) and its implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) was legislation passed in the wake of the Enron and WorldCom scandals. Its purpose was to end corporate fraud empowering watchdogs and gatekeepers to restrain the impulse of management to manipulate financial reporting. One of the key measures was 404(b), which required &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; publicly traded company to have an independent auditor attest that the “internal controls” of the company were effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;internal controls&lt;/a&gt;” are the first line of defense against fraud and human error. Management is supposed to install a system that aids employees in routinely recording the economic activity of the company in a way that is both accurate and comprehensible. The controls should also ensure that neither employees nor management misuses company assets or manipulates results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every Watchdog Report flags potential issues raised with regards to the internal controls raised by the independent auditor or management. We have discussed them before in our examinations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg/&quot;&gt;HFFG&lt;/a&gt;. However, Watchdog Reports do not currently flag companies that are not required to comply with 404(b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 404(b) attestation requires the independent auditor to do some due diligence. The auditors must test the internal controls of the company throughout the year, instead of just reviewing financial statements at the end of the year. This is a time-intensive process and estimates by the SEC put the average cost at over $200,000 a year. This process improves internal controls and creates a powerful deterrent against fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whittling Away at 404(b)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that 404(b) is a significant regulatory burden. When the measures were first passed, Small Reporting Companies, (SRCs) with less than $75 million in public float were not required to implement 404(b) right away but were given an extension. The extension was made permanent by the Dodd Frank Act in 2010 so that SRCs would &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be required to get a 404(b)auditor attestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, President Obama signed the bipartisan JOBS Act. This bill created a new classification, the Emerging Growth Company (EGC). A company can qualify as an EGC for up to five years after going public if it has less than 1 billion in revenue and less than 700 million in public float. A company that fits the criteria does not have to comply with certain regulations, including 404(b). According to Audit Analytics, 1,394, or around 20% of the 6,644 publicly registered companies qualify for EGC status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAO put out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; in 2013 using Audit Analytics’ data to conduct a review of 404(b) and found that the auditor attestation improved internal controls and decreased the chances of damaging restatements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LK%20GAO%20EGC%206.16.png&quot; alt=&quot;LK GAO EGC 6.16.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now under President Trump, the SEC has changed the definitions of “accelerated” and “large accelerated” filers to reduce the number of companies that must comply with 404(b). This change is commensurate with a change in the definition of Smaller Reporting Companies that was &lt;a href=&quot;https://corpgov.law.harvard.edu/2018/07/21/amended-definition-of-smaller-reporting-company/&quot;&gt;made&lt;/a&gt; in 2018. The result of all these rule changes is a complex set of classifications, where the status of a company changes based on its revenue and public float. This table from an &lt;a href=&quot;https://corpgov.law.harvard.edu/2020/04/04/secs-carve-out-from-sox-404b-for-low-revenue-companies/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; published by Harvard Law is the best representation we have found of the current state of the classifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SRC%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;SRC Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies that are classified as Accelerated filers or as Large Accelerated filers are required to comply with 404(b). The companies that are most affected by this new rule change are companies with relatively low revenue, who nevertheless carry up to $700 million in public float, because they no longer need to comply with 404(b). The SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://corpgov.law.harvard.edu/2018/07/21/amended-definition-of-smaller-reporting-company/&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; that 966 companies would be affected by the rule change, with 161 of them having revenues under $100 million but public float between $250-700 million. The SEC Chair Jay Clayton (who recently announced his departure), specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/sec-proposes-eliminating-auditor-checks-on-controls-at-low-revenue-biotechs-2019-05-09?mod=hp_econ&quot;&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt; bio-tech and healthcare companies as intended beneficiaries of the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New Rule Defies Good Sense&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new carveouts are designed to encourage more private companies to enter the public market by reducing regulatory burdens that may deter some from entering. However, there is scant evidence that 404(b) is scaring companies away from the public marketplace, but there is evidence that the sort of companies that just got an exception from 404(b) were the ones who needed it most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFOs were asked to name the obstacles that were keeping them from going public; the CFOs &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooleypubco.com/2017/06/26/whats-up-with-the-declining-number-of-ipos/&quot;&gt;provided&lt;/a&gt; all sorts of answers, however, concerns about regulatory compliance were at the &lt;em&gt;bottom&lt;/em&gt; of the list. In contrast, a 2011 survey of CEOs of public companies that found 92% stated that compliance costs were a significant barrier to completing an IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What explains this disparity? Compliance with 404(b) is both expensive and time-consuming, and since these companies were &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; public, the CEOs may just have been griping. This is a bit like asking a graduate if the loans they took out for their degree was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a strong narrative that burdensome regulations have contributed to a decline in IPOs, but there are other &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooleypubco.com/2017/06/26/whats-up-with-the-declining-number-of-ipos/&quot;&gt;probable&lt;/a&gt; explanations. Nor is it reasonable to assume that the high watermark for public companies in 1996 represents a benchmark of a healthy marketplace that we should strive towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francine Mckenna wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/sec-proposes-eliminating-auditor-checks-on-controls-at-low-revenue-biotechs-2019-05-09?mod=hp_econ&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; for MarketWatch in 2019 that highlighted data from Audit Analytics indicating that the 404(b) requirement for these soon-to-be-exempted companies provided a lot of value for investors. Companies with revenues under $100 million received 176 adverse opinions on their internal controls from their independent auditors from 2014-2019, that represented 70% of adverse opinions for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; public companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main beneficiary of this new rule is pharmaceutical companies that do not have much revenue but are attracting lots of public investment. The losers are investors who have now lost an important watchdog in these pharmaceutical start-ups. This will only enable companies to play fast and loose with investors money as they doll themselves up to spur an acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final Note on the SEC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a split on this rule, with Commissioner Lee dissenting. She stated, “Eliminating the auditor attestation removes a critical gatekeeping function that we know works to improve the reliability of financial reporting for investors.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably is not the last time the SEC will choose to reduce the scope of 404(b), since there appears to be broad bipartisan support for rolling back the protections it offers for investors. Commissioner Pierce is in favor of making 404(b) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-peirce-accelerated-filer-2020-03-12&quot;&gt;optional&lt;/a&gt; for all companies. If the SEC continues to strip away the burdens placed on corporations by Sarbanes Oxley, it will strip away the corresponding protections for investors as well. The SEC would do well to remember its job is to &lt;em&gt;enforce&lt;/em&gt; the laws passed by Congress, including Sarbanes Oxley, not to minimize them by changing the definitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="Sarbanes Oxley" /><category term="404(b)" /><summary type="html">There is scant evidence that 404(b) is scaring companies away from the public marketplace, but there is evidence that the sort of companies that just got an exception from 404(b) were the ones who needed it most.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SEC%20404(b).jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SEC%20404(b).jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Watchdog Spotlight on HF Food Group “HFFG”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watchdog Spotlight on HF Food Group “HFFG”" /><published>2020-07-07T10:07:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-07T10:07:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In March HFFG was accused of siphoning off investors money to buy a stable of super-cars, but their problems started well before those allegations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG is a food distributor that primarily serves Asian restaurants in the Southeast, Pacific, and Mountain West regions of the U.S. HFFG currently has the dubious distinction of having our highest Gray Swan Event Factor (GSEF) score by far at 17.43%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with our GSEF score, we calculate it by estimating the likelihood of certain “gray swan” events, and then estimate the potential impact of those events. Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has demonstrated that this risk has not been properly priced into the marketplace, mostly because no one is doing the due diligence necessary to account for it. In fact, most firms rely on the analysts &lt;em&gt;selling the stock&lt;/em&gt; to conduct this research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/HFFG%20GSEF%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;HFFG GSEF Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cascading Bad News for HFFG&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG seems to be suffering from a series of escalating problems. They reported serious material weaknesses in their financial reporting for FY 2018, just a few months before announcing a merger with B&amp;amp;R Global (B&amp;amp;R), another larger Chinese restaurant food distributor for an ostensible value of $400 million. B&amp;amp;R’s shareholders were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919021487/fooh20191104_8k.htm&quot;&gt;awarded&lt;/a&gt; approximately 60% of the ownership of the surviving company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, the company had to contend with the coronavirus and a scathing &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/hf-foods/&quot;&gt;short-seller report&lt;/a&gt; by Hindenburg Research, as well as a securities lawsuit based on that report. HFFG was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920010302/fooh20200510_nt10q.htm&quot;&gt;late&lt;/a&gt; in releasing its first quarter results, and when those &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920011101/fooh20200331_10q.htm&quot;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; came out, they included a whopping $338 million impairment to goodwill. Before the impairment, the company had a goodwill balance of $406 million, which represented almost the entire &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919014692/fooh20190719_prem14a.htm&quot;&gt;value&lt;/a&gt; of the consideration provided by HFFG in the merger. This impairment wiped out approximately 83% of that value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Restatement Incoming?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our statistical analysis, HFFG has a nearly 60% chance of a filing a restatement in the next 12 months. One of the biggest factors in that calculation is recurring material weaknesses in HFFG’s financial reporting. HFFG reported serious material weaknesses in both their annual reports for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919006198/fooh20181231_10k.htm&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920005276/fooh20191231_10k.htm&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;. In 2018, they disclosed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The material weakness related to the &lt;strong&gt;deficiency in the ability of our in-house accounting professionals to generate financial statements in the form required by applicable SEC requirements&lt;/strong&gt;. Control deficiencies are related to the lack of proper documentation to evidence the review of customer orders and purchase orders, and lack of proper documentation to evidence customers’ acknowledgement of transaction amounts and account balances&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the annual report for 2019, the HFFG admitted that little progress had been made, “&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the Company does not have in-house accounting personnel with sufficient knowledge of US GAAP and SEC reporting experiences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find this strange.  Why haven’t they hired someone over the past year with the ability to follow GAAP? Is it so difficult to find an experienced and qualified person to lead the in-house accounting staff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also note that because HFFG is classified as an Emerging Growth Company, its auditor does not offer an opinion as to the effectiveness of its internal controls. But considering that HFFG’s auditors do not understand how to apply Generally Accepted Accounting Principles, we can venture a guess as to what their auditor’s opinion would be if they gave one. HFFG’s problems are a great example of how the lack of the SOX 404(b) requirement lowers the quality of internal controls, which we have written about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If HFFG can hire someone who understands GAAP, it is likely that they will need to revise the financial results from prior years. They will also need to simplify the financial reporting. This relatively small food distributor makes unusually complex accounting disclosures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/HFFG%20Complexity%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;HFFG Complexity Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC has made a serious effort to make all company disclosures &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/page/osdhistoryandrulemaking&quot;&gt;accessible&lt;/a&gt; to the public by requiring the use of standardized formats and standardized language. As part of this effort, the SEC also requires companies to submit these filings in an XBRL format, so it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/structureddata/what-is-structured-data&quot;&gt;simpler&lt;/a&gt; for software to provide meaningful analysis without too much manual work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a practical matter, when a company makes a filing, they mark it with a set of standardized XBRL tags. However, sometimes a company needs to use “custom” XBRL tags because their data does not fit into the standard language or format. This graph represents how often a company introduces these “custom” tags in comparison with their industry peers. A relatively high number of custom tags indicate that a company’s disclosures are complex and opaque.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extensive Related Party Transactions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG’s material weaknesses also related to the review of their purchase orders. This potentially raises revenue recognition questions, raising a possibility that someone at the company could be engaging in accounting shenanigans. We have written about this issue before, when discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;Under Armour’s&lt;/a&gt; potential channel stuffing issues. Although not proof of manipulation, it is very concerning that HFFG has a “&lt;em&gt;lack of proper documentation to evidence the review of customer orders and purchase orders&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG also has a high number of related party transactions. HFFG disclosed that it made sales of over $19 million and made purchases of over $40 million in related party transactions in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920005276/fooh20191231_10k.htm&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt; alone. HFFG also recorded many other types of related party transactions, including advances both to related suppliers and from related customers, a $55 million term loan guarantee, and related lease transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the company loaned over $8 million to entities either owned by the Chairman- and co-CEO Zhou Min Ni or his son; Ni initially guaranteed the loans before he “purchased” them with over 632,746 shares. But Ni also had to put an additional 208,806 shares into escrow, and he will lose all or part of those shares if the average closing price of the stock is below $13.30 for the 250 days leading up to September 30th, 2020. Considering that the stock price dropped below $13.30 in March and has stayed consistently below $10.00 since, Ni has a very strong incentive to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that will make the share price recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/HFFG%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;HFFG Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Accusations by Hindenburg Research&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindenburg Research is an activist short-seller in the mode of Muddy Waters founded by &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/about-us/&quot;&gt;Nate Andersen&lt;/a&gt;. In March, this short seller published a report on HFFG which included assertions based on public information as well as non-public information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core claim made by Hindenburg was that the merger between HFFG and B&amp;amp;R was not conducted at “arm’s length” as stated by the relevant &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919014692/fooh20190719_prem14a.htm&quot;&gt;disclosures&lt;/a&gt;, but that both of these companies were previously part of the same Chinese investment group. Unfortunately, many of underlying documents supporting Hindenburg’s contention are in Chinese and are not easily verified. One interesting fact that seems to support Hindenburg’s assertion is that the two companies were neatly divided into east and west divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key assertion in Hindenburg’s report is that the chairman and co-CEO Zhou Min Ni has been using the related party transactions to inappropriately siphon money out of the company. Hindenburg asserts that background checks of these related parties reveal that no fewer than 17 super-cars with total value of over $3.5 million were registered to these entities. Hindenburg also provides photos, supposedly from the Instagram account of Ni’s son Raymond, of Raymond showing off this collection of super-cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this report was published, the Rosen Law Firm filed a class action Complaint against HFFG in the Central California District Court. The complaint closely mirrors the report by Hindenburg research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The C-Suite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporate governance problems are often at the root of accounting-related issues. Chaos in the C-suite translates into chaos throughout the organization. HFFG has had an unusual structure post-merger. Zhou Min Ni and Xiao Mou “Peter” Zhang, formerly the heads of HFFG and B&amp;amp;R respectively, are now co-CEOs. Adding to the confusion, three different people have held the office of CFO at HFFG since last March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers often hurt companies in the short run because the difficulty of combining systems and cultures cost more than the “synergies.” Even if both companies were previously affiliated, as Hindenberg Research asserts, the fact that Peter Zhang and Zhou Min Ni are sharing the position of CEO will raise a plethora of issues. Additionally, HFFG’s inability to develop effective internal controls for the past two years does not bode well for achieving “synergies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Goodwill Impairment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;anticipated&lt;/a&gt; that the outbreak of the coronavirus would cause many companies to test their goodwill, and that this would lead to a rash of impairments. We also anticipated that some companies would disingenuously use the pandemic as cover to write off junk goodwill. So, did HFFG write off the goodwill because they needed to, or did they write it off because it was a convenient excuse?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG’s $338 million impairment may not be earth shattering in an absolute sense, but relative to its size it is exceptionally large. When Kraft Heinz wrote off $15 billion in intangible assets and goodwill, that wiped out about 12% of the company’s assets and reduced equity by 23%. By comparison, HFFG’s impairment wiped out 35% of the total assets, and eliminated over half of the equity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this merger was consummated in December 2019. At that time HFFG paid a premium for B&amp;amp;R and recorded over $400 million in goodwill from the deal. However, the assumptions underpinning the purchase price have changed, as 83% of that value has now been erased. But was this justified?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all depends on whether you trust management to perform accurate valuations. Valuations are more of an art than a science because they require a great deal of estimates and assumptions about the future. But how can you properly evaluate the future during a black swan event? When they were conducting their valuations in March and April, they did not know what the effects of the coronavirus would be, nor how long those effects would persist. The effects could end soon, or they may &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the irony, the pandemic is so disruptive that it constitutes a triggering event, causing every company to test their goodwill for impairment, but it is also so disruptive that it makes the future predictions critical for a proper valuations &lt;em&gt;highly subjective&lt;/em&gt;. If Hindenburg’s assertions about self-dealing turn out to be accurate, then it would be reasonable to believe that there was an ulterior motive for this impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did HFFG make reasonable assumptions in their valuation estimates? We cannot be sure, but since their financial reporting is unreliable, given their lack of expertise with GAAP and chronic internal control issues, we find it likely that these valuations are riddled with problematic assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG has had a difficult year so far. The merger certainly has posed a difficult set of challenges, made worse by the management team’s material weaknesses in their financial reporting. They are already enduring one securities lawsuit and have made a massive impairment. But if our research is correct this is only the opening salvo and 2020 probably has a lot more in store for HFFG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Watchdog Spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="HFFG" /><category term="Material Weaknesses" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="Impairment" /><summary type="html">In March HFFG was accused of siphoning off investors money to buy a stable of super-cars, but their problems started well before those allegations.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Chinese%20Food.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Chinese%20Food.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: Underwriting Shmunderwriting</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-underwriting-shmunderwriting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: Underwriting Shmunderwriting" /><published>2020-06-26T12:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T12:58:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-underwriting-shmunderwriting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-underwriting-shmunderwriting/">&lt;p&gt;Before a company offers its stock to the public in an IPO, it is supposed to undergo an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/330/321612.pdf&quot;&gt;extensive&lt;/a&gt; vetting process. Part of this process is called underwriting, and it involves having investment banks act as intermediaries between the company and the public. The investment bankers conduct a substantial factual investigation of the company and its prospectus so that it can accurately price the stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/business/banking-finance/article/3078667/credit-suisse-out-tencent-backed-wedoctors-hong-kong-ipo&quot;&gt;underwriters&lt;/a&gt; for Luckin’s IPO were Credit Suisse, Morgan Stanley, China International Capital and Haitong. This consortium of influential investment banks certainly had the resources to conduct a proper investigation of Luckin, but did they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less than a year after its IPO, Luckin Coffee revealed a massive fraud that implicated its COO, CEO, and its founder and Chairman. It is unclear just when this fraud began, but a WSJ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/behind-the-fall-of-chinas-luckin-coffee-a-network-of-fake-buyers-and-a-fictitious-employee-11590682336&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; found evidence of fraudulent transactions predating the IPO by at least a month. This means that it is likely that Luckin was fabricating numbers while the underwriters were still supposed to be conducting their investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think that the revelation of this fraud would spell bad news for the consortium of banks which underwrote the false prospectus, but that is probably not true. Generally, when plaintiffs pursue a securities fraud case they rely on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/240.10b-5&quot;&gt;Section 240.10b-5&lt;/a&gt;. However, the Supreme Court’s decisions over the years have neutered this as a private cause of action against defendants who are considered “aiders and abettors” to fraud, like investment banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Effectively Immune from Private Suit?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underwriters received a boon from the Supreme Court in &lt;em&gt;Central Bank v. First Interstate, 511, U.S. 164 (1994)&lt;/em&gt;, when it decided that civil liability did not extend to “aiders and abettors” of fraud in the sales of securities (ending decades of tradition to the contrary). This decision was reinforced by &lt;em&gt;Stoneridge Investment Partners v. Scientific-Atlanta, 552 U.S. 148 (2008)&lt;/em&gt; by holding that third parties are not liable for participating in corporate wrongdoing if they did not directly mislead investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Supreme Court decisions have provided underwriters effective immunity from many securities lawsuits. This creates a moral hazard that encourages carelessness on the part of the underwriters because they do not bear the costs if their clients commit fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most significant results from the &lt;em&gt;Central Bank&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Stoneridge&lt;/em&gt; was the result in &lt;em&gt;California Regents v. Merrill Lynch.&lt;/em&gt; In that &lt;a href=&quot;https://caselaw.findlaw.com/us-5th-circuit/1140930.html&quot;&gt;suit&lt;/a&gt;, the Enron shareholders sued Merrill Lynch for assisting Enron in cooking the books by disguising loans as purchases so that executives at Enron would hit certain benchmarks for their compensation. The 5th Circuit dismissed the suit because Merrill Lynch and the other investment banks did not have a duty to investors and had made no false statements &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; to investors. The Supreme Court denied certiorari, thereby ensuring that Enron’s investors were left holding the bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court went even further in &lt;em&gt;Janus Capital Group, Inc. v. First Derivative Traders, 564 U. S. 135 (2011)&lt;/em&gt; to hold that a party does not “make” a statement unless they have ultimate authority over that statement. This would appear to have created an airtight defense for underwriters and other potential aiders and abettors for securities fraud under rule 10b-5. These legal protections create troubling incentives that undermine the underwriter’s role as gatekeepers for the capital markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recently the water has been muddied. In &lt;em&gt;SEC v. Tambone, 550 F. 3d 106 (1st Cir. 2008)&lt;/em&gt;, the first circuit held that underwriters can be held responsible for making false statements in the prospectus by implication because their duty to investigate the company and verify the facts in the prospectus. In Lorenzo v. SEC, (2018), the Supreme Court contradicted earlier decisions by deciding that persons did not need to make false statements, so long as they participated in the fraud “scheme.” Some enterprising plaintiff’s attorney could attempt to bring a case under Section 10-b5 against the banking consortium by arguing either an implied misstatement of fact via &lt;em&gt;Tambone&lt;/em&gt;, or “scheme” via &lt;em&gt;Lorenzo&lt;/em&gt;, but the odds would be stacked against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1933 Securities Act does allow underwriters to be sued in a private cause of action for false statements under a different section, but those claims are different, and the underwriters can raise “due diligence” as a complete defense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Due Diligence Standard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the consortium can show they took “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/230.176&quot;&gt;reasonable care&lt;/a&gt;” and conducted a reasonable investigation of Luckin, then they will have a complete defense.  Determining whether the consortium actually exercised due diligence would be a fact-intensive inquiry, with the consortium providing pallets of documents supporting their contention that the investigation was reasonable. But at its core, due diligence requires independent verification, and it is hard to imagine the banking consortium truly verified the information in the prospectus in such a massive fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underwriters should rely on experts, like auditors, but they should not take an auditor’s report at face value. In an article on the topic posted to &lt;a href=&quot;https://corporate.findlaw.com/finance/underwriter-due-diligence-in-securities-offerings.html&quot;&gt;FindLaw&lt;/a&gt;, the authors make this point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Underwriters should … carefully scrutinize the auditor’s report and letters to management to determine whether potential problem areas were uncovered during the audit. Moreover, underwriters should look at general financial issues – including profits and revenue, budget concerns and the internal audit controls the issuer has in place – to reach a sufficient comfort level with the issuer’s overall financial condition. “&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see if substance will triumph over style in a court’s analysis of the consortium’s due diligence. Another wrinkle for potential litigation is that many of the events occurred in China, so a proper fact-finding investigation may not even be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is concerning that the WSJ’s investigation uncovered fraudulent transactions prior to the IPO as well as a web of related party transactions revolving around Charles Lu. The underwriters could also potentially have discovered this information before signing off on the prospectus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;SEC is Last Line of Defense&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-luckin-investigation/u-s-sec-investigates-luckin-coffee-over-accounting-scandal-wsj-idUSKBN22B1D6&quot;&gt;declared&lt;/a&gt; an investigation into Luckin’s fraud, and they might take a look at the banking consortium’s due diligence practices. One thing to note is that the SEC &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; bring a 10b-5 case against an entity that aids and abets a fraud. The publicity surrounding this case and the SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-luckin-investigation/u-s-sec-investigates-luckin-coffee-over-accounting-scandal-wsj-idUSKBN22B1D6&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; into Luckin raises the possibility that Credit Suisse and Morgan could be charged with aiding and abetting Luckin’s fraud, but once again a lack of information coming out of China may hamper any investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underwriters for Luckin’s stock will probably be sued because there is nowhere else for the defrauded investors to make a recovery. If there is a case, it will revolve around the idea of due diligence and we will see if substance triumphs over style in the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this may be a chance for something bigger. The Supreme Court could get a chance to walk back its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.gwu.edu/sites/g/files/zaxdzs2351/f/downloads/Klock_Stoneridge.pdf&quot;&gt;maligned&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Stonebridge&lt;/em&gt; decision. Something must be done to change the incentives at play here for the big investment banks, because if the incentives don’t change, regular people will continue to pay the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Underwriters" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="Due Dilligence" /><summary type="html">Before a company offers its stock to the public in an IPO, it is supposed to undergo an extensive vetting process. Part of this process is called underwriting, and it involves having investment banks act as intermediaries between the company and the public. The investment bankers conduct a substantial factual investigation of the company and its prospectus so that it can accurately price the stock.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/luckin_bank_fraud.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/luckin_bank_fraud.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: Insider Trading and Stock Pledging</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-insider-trading-and-stock-pledging/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: Insider Trading and Stock Pledging" /><published>2020-06-22T09:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-22T09:55:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-insider-trading-and-stock-pledging</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-insider-trading-and-stock-pledging/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You might think that foreign companies would be held to the same standards as U.S. companies, but that is not true, not at all.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC ostensibly enforces its insider trading laws vigorously. Under the Trump Administration, they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.perkinscoie.com/en/news-insights/u-s-agencies-step-up-insider-trading-enforcement-against-foreign.html&quot;&gt;increasingly pursued&lt;/a&gt; foreign actors, especially the Chinese, for suspected insider trading. The SEC considers its enforcement of the insider trading rules to be a crucial part of its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/rules/final/33-7881.htm#P225_88637&quot;&gt;function&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[P]rohibitions against insider trading in our securities laws play an essential role in maintaining the fairness, health, and integrity of our markets. We have long recognized that the fundamental unfairness of insider trading harms not only individual investors but also the very foundations of our markets, by undermining investor confidence in the integrity of the markets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 16 of the Exchange Act seeks to deter improper insider trading by requiring directors, officers, and shareholders who hold over 10% of a company’s shares to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/smallbusiness/goingpublic/officersanddirectors&quot;&gt;disclose&lt;/a&gt; most transactions of their stock within two business days. However, foreign private issuers like Luckin are exempt. This is no secret as Luckin warned in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746919003174/a2238747z424b4.htm&quot;&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Because we qualify as a foreign private issuer under the Exchange Act, we are exempt from certain provisions of the securities rules&lt;/strong&gt; and regulations in the United States that are applicable to U.S. domestic issuers, including … the sections of the Exchange Act requiring insiders to file public reports of their stock ownership and trading activities and liability for insiders&lt;/em&gt;* who profit from trades made in a short period of time … As a result, you may not be afforded the same protections or information that would be made available to you were you investing in a U.S. domestic issuer. (emphasis added)*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign private issues are only required to include their insider trading information in their annual reports—&lt;em&gt;once a year&lt;/em&gt;—compared to &lt;em&gt;two business days&lt;/em&gt; for U.S. companies. Has Charles Lu or any other insiders dumped their stock? We do not know, as Luckin has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920073381/a20-12062_3nt20f.htm&quot;&gt;delayed&lt;/a&gt; releasing their annual report. When initially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;announcing&lt;/a&gt; this delay in late April, they claimed it was due to the impact of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public policymakers need to reconsider whether we should be willing to lower our disclosure requirements to encourage foreign companies to access our capital markets. You might think that foreign companies would be held to the same standards as U.S. companies, but that is not true, not at all. A good way for policymakers to prevent foreign insider trading in the first place would be to end the Section 16 exemption for foreign private issuers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology Ought to Make Enforcement Simple&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In years past foreign companies faced significant obstacles in complying with the same rules as U.S. companies, but this is no longer the case. It is easier to Zoom with someone in China than to walk to your neighbor’s house and ask for a stick of butter. All trading can be done &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketplace.org/2020/03/23/nyse-stocks-trading-floor-closed-electronic/&quot;&gt;electronically&lt;/a&gt;, which means that enforcing stricter disclosure requirements for foreign companies is feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exchanges could require that directors, executives, and their proxies register and forbid any trading through unregistered entities. That way insider trades would be flagged and easy to check against disclosures. Attempts to circumvent the system using unregistered proxies would be prosecuted. Perhaps there is a better way to ensure compliance; however, it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; too much to ask for foreign companies to meet the same standards as U.S. companies to get access to U.S. capital markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Problems with Pledged Stock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not know if Luckin’s insiders traded on insider information, but we do know that Charles Lu, his sister, and the CEO cashed in their ownership interest by pledging shares for a $&lt;a href=&quot;https://money.usnews.com/investing/news/articles/2020-05-22/banks-pursue-luckin-coffee-chairmans-assets-after-loan-default&quot;&gt;518&lt;/a&gt; million dollar loan. They defaulted on this loan a few days after the fraud was revealed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin disclosed these pledges in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746920000183/a2240425z424b4.htm&quot;&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt; for its second offering in January, 2020, although they did not reveal how much money was raised through the loans. Insiders are often hesitant to sell stock for a number of reasons, including the need to disclose the sale on SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/about/forms/form4.pdf&quot;&gt;Form 4&lt;/a&gt; within two business days, so, sometimes they will pledge their shares as collateral for a loan. This allows them to retain title to the stock and does not change ownership unless they default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an insider pledges some or all their holdings, they do not need to report that within two business days under SEC Form 4 because there has been no change in the &lt;em&gt;ownership&lt;/em&gt; of the stock and pledged shares are specifically not considered &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/240.16a-1&quot;&gt;derivative securities&lt;/a&gt;. Insiders are only required to disclose whether they have pledged their shares under &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/229.403&quot;&gt;Regulation S-K Item 403(b)&lt;/a&gt; once a year in a footnote. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfo.com/compensation/2012/11/iss-targets-hedging-pledging-of-company-stock/&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; of the Russell 3000 index showed that one or more executives at 15% of companies had used their shares as collateral for loans, and that the average amount of these loans was more than $57 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, these stock pledges have created problems. When directors or executives take out these loans, they risk being forced to put up additional stock as collateral if the price of the company stock declines. For &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052702304070304577394040890661820&quot;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;, Green Mountain Coffee’s founder and chairman of the board initially put up 46% of his shares as collateral for loans, but was forced to increase that amount to 78% when the company’s stock price took a nose-dive. He was eventually forced to sell his shares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently the CEO of Wirecard, Markus Braun, resigned after Wirecard revealed that $2 billion of its supposed cash did not exist.   Braun had &lt;a href=&quot;https://world-news-monitor.com/money/finance/2020/06/21/wirecard-ceo-in-a-world-of-pain-as-banks-force-margin-call-on-e150mm-stock-pledged-loan/&quot;&gt;apparently &lt;/a&gt;pledged a little less than half of his personal stake in the company for a 150 million Euro loan.  This loan undoubtedly put a lot of personal pressure on Braun to  keep stock prices stable as investigative journalists  started reporting on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/19c6be2a-ee67-11e9-bfa4-b25f11f42901&quot;&gt;irregularities &lt;/a&gt; at Wirecard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These loans can create an enormous conflict of interest for directors and executives. A director who is heavily leveraged could push for a stock buy-back to boost share prices when the stock is in trouble, depleting cash reserves and exposing the company and its stakeholders to unnecessary risk.  Or to boost share price through outright fraud. Many companies craft &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.wsj.com/cfo/2013/05/20/executive-use-of-company-stock-as-loan-collateral-scrutinized/&quot;&gt;policies&lt;/a&gt; that either restrict the practice of pledging, or simply ban it outright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with Dodd-Frank, the SEC has implemented a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/rules/final/2018/33-10593.pdf&quot;&gt;rule&lt;/a&gt; that requires companies to disclose their policies concerning stock pledges in their annual proxy statement, and to say they do not have a policy if they do not have one. Every SEC registrant will need to follow this rule starting on July 1, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insider stock sales and insider stock pledges, we juxtapose these issues to raise a point. Why are they treated differently? The SEC requires insider sales to be reported within 2 days because that information is highly relevant for the investing public, and it is relevant as soon as it happens, not just when the proxy statement is released annually. The same logic applies for stock pledges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is completely mystifying why foreign companies have less rigorous insider trading disclosure requirements than U.S. firms. With advances in technology, there is no reason why a company located in Columbia should be treated differently than a company in Colorado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, policymakers should reconsider how stock pledges are treated under the current law. If an insider takes on a large loan and pledges a large amount of their stock as collateral, shouldn’t the other investors know right away?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Insider Trading" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Insider Trading" /><category term="Stock Pledging" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="Congress" /><summary type="html">You might think that foreign companies would be held to the same standards as U.S. companies, but that is not true, not at all.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/luckin_stock_drop.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/luckin_stock_drop.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: Corporate Governance Failures</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-corporate-governance-failures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: Corporate Governance Failures" /><published>2020-06-18T10:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-18T10:25:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-corporate-governance-failures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-corporate-governance-failures/">&lt;p&gt;Luckin Coffee’s  massive fraud was discovered by its auditors, EY’s Chinese affiliate, Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP. The affiliate  probably would have discovered the fraud earlier if not for Luckin’s status as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;Emerging Growth Company&lt;/a&gt;, but in this post we turn our attention to Luckin’s board of directors, who ought to serve as the first line of defense against fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarbanes Oxley introduced extensive corporate governance &lt;a href=&quot;http://nasdaq.cchwallstreet.com/NASDAQTools/PlatformViewer.asp?selectednode=chp%5F1%5F1%5F3%5F3%5F8%5F3&amp;amp;manual=%2Fnasdaq%2Fmain%2Fnasdaq%2Dequityrules%2F&quot;&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt; to check management’s impulses and protect from fraud. At the heart of these rules is the involvement of “independent directors” on every company’s board of directors. What makes “independent directors” independent is that they are not beholden to management and have the best interests of the corporation in mind when making decisions. These “independent directors” sit on important committees and provide oversight of the management team and can take decisive action to correct problems they discover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there is a big fraud at a company, you can be certain that there are flaws in the corporate governance. Some companies violate governance rules while others violate their &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;spirit&lt;/a&gt;. But in the case of foreign filers, like Luckin, some companies do not even have to abide by the same governance rules as U.S. companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Loophole in Corporate Governance Requirements for Foreign Filers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, to trade on the Nasdaq, the majority of directors on the board must be independent. In principle, a director is independent if they do not have personal or financial ties that management can leverage to make the director beholden to management. Additionally, the company must have an audit committee of three members, all of whom must be independent, and one of whom must be financially sophisticated (with a background in accounting or something similar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin did not have a majority of independent directors, in fact, of the eight members of the board, only two, Thomas P. Meier and Sean Shao were held out as independent directors. Foreign companies have always had a little-known exception to the requirement for a majority of board members to be independent &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; that rule contradicted local law. Foreign companies were permitted to request this exemption. Few firms applied initially because it was difficult to get a law firm to sign off on the request and there was no guarantee the regulators would grant such a request. So, companies petitioned for a change in the rule. This rule was relaxed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clm.com/publication.cfm?ID=23&quot;&gt;2005&lt;/a&gt;, foreign firms no longer needed to request an exemption, instead they could just declare that they were taking one and relying on “home country practice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change was not made in the best interests of investors, since foreign companies have legal and language barriers that make performing due diligence difficult. Unsurprisingly, Luckin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746919003174/a2238747z424b4.htm&quot;&gt;opted&lt;/a&gt; to diminish the role on the board for these watchdogs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Listing Rules of the NASDAQ generally require that a majority of an issuer’s board of directors must consist of independent directors. However, &lt;strong&gt;the Listing Rules of the NASDAQ permit foreign private issuers like us to follow “home country practice” in certain corporate governance matters. We rely on this “home country practice” exemption and do not have a majority of independent directors serving on our Board of Directors&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no “home country practice” exemption for the Audit Committee however, which raises an important question, how could the audit committee have missed this fraud? How could the audit committee have missed a fabrication of more than half of the annual revenue? Or a substantial change costs and expenses? One contributing factor is that the rules allow companies to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/info/smallbus/gbfor25_2006/goingpublic.pdf&quot;&gt;phase-in&lt;/a&gt; independent directors after an IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only two of the three audit committee members were independent. One member, Mr. Erhai Liu, was the founder and manager of Joy Capital and heavily invested in Luckin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Were These “Independent Directors” Even Independent?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also appears that Luckin broke the rules. The “independent” directors were Thomas P. Meier, the former president and CEO of Frankee Coffee Systems and Sean Shao. When Thomas Meier was still leading Frankee coffee systems, they and another manufacturer obtained a contract with Luckin in 2018 that was &lt;a href=&quot;https://alltechasia.com/luckin-coffees-blue-partner-alliance-fuels-its-bold-10000-shop-target/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; to quintuple sales for the manufacturer. It is possible that serving in that role ought to have disqualified Mr. Meier from qualifying as an independent director since the Nasdaq does not consider independent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(D) a director who is, or has a Family Member who is, a partner in, or a controlling shareholder or an executive officer of, any organization to which the company made, or from which the company received, payments for property or services in the current or any of the past three fiscal years that exceed 5% of the recipient’s consolidated gross revenues for that year, or $200,000 ($1 million if the listed company is also listed on the New York Stock Exchange), whichever is more…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Meier left his position at Frankee in March 2019 to join Luckin as an independent director. Given the large contract with Luckin, it is likely that he ought to have been disqualified under the Nasdaq rules because he was an executive at Frankee Coffee Systems which likely had a contract with Luckin which exceeded both 5% of the revenue and $200,000. About three weeks after Luckin disclosed its fraud on April 21st, he resigned as an “independent” director and member of the audit committee. There was no explanation for his departure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other independent director, Sean Shao, has extensive experience as an independent director. He worked at Deloitte Touche Tohmatsu CPA Ltd for almost a decade before taking up the role of independent director at many companies. One of his longest tenures was with Agria Corporation from 2008-2017, where he was an independent director and chairman of the corporate governance committee. In 2018, Agria settled with the SEC for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2018-276&quot;&gt;fraud&lt;/a&gt; relating to its operations in China from 2010-2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not uncommon for former auditors at the Big 4 to parlay their experience into lucrative careers as independent directors, but there is something about this kind of serial board membership that seems unsavory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more difficult for the exchanges and regulators to effectively monitor foreign based firms for a host of reasons. That makes it critical for foreign firms to have effective independent directors to act as watchdogs and prevent fraud. However, the current rules permit these foreign firms more latitude than U.S. firms. If regulators want to make meaningful steps to bolster protections for investors in the wake of the Luckin fraud, then this would be a great place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="Loopholes" /><summary type="html">Luckin Coffee’s massive fraud was discovered by its auditors, EY’s Chinese affiliate, Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP. The affiliate probably would have discovered the fraud earlier if not for Luckin’s status as an Emerging Growth Company, but in this post we turn our attention to Luckin’s board of directors, who ought to serve as the first line of defense against fraud.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/luckin_management.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/luckin_management.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: Fraud Enabled by Slack Standards</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: Fraud Enabled by Slack Standards" /><published>2020-06-16T15:41:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-16T15:41:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/">&lt;p&gt;Luckin Coffee engaged in one of the most brazen frauds in history. It is easy to blame the fraud on the business environment in China fostered by the CCP. But this fraud could not have occurred if not for systemic weaknesses in the Western capital markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Enron scandal, Sarbanes Oxley was passed to create stringent new standards that would deter future frauds. Auditors were supposed to play a key role in enforcing these new stringent standards. Publicly traded companies had to pay their independent auditors to offer an opinion on whether the internal controls of a company were effective (requiring the auditors to test management’s financial reporting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, the Obama administration signed bipartisan legislation relieving some companies of the obligation to get this opinion from their auditors. This change lowered the costs associated with taking a company public, and eased access to capital for many businesses. The White House &lt;a href=&quot;https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/blog/2012/04/05/jobs-act-encouraging-startups-supporting-small-businesses&quot;&gt;promised&lt;/a&gt; that this bill “will help encourage startups and support &lt;em&gt;our nation’s&lt;/em&gt; small businesses.” (emphasis added) But this law did not just apply to American businesses, it applied to all businesses, including those in foreign countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem? If an American company takes advantage of the relaxed requirements and commits fraud, they take a significant risk that they will ultimately be exposed and go to jail or get sued. But when a well-connected company in an emerging market, like China, engages in fraud, there is no &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;recourse&lt;/a&gt; for investors. It is even &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;possible&lt;/a&gt; that some level of fraud is encouraged by the people in power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouraging more investment in American businesses might be an important enough public policy goal to justify the increased risk of fraud that comes with loosening standards, but there is no such public policy justification for loosening standards for companies in emerging markets with structurally weak regulatory systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Congress Lowered Standards in 2012&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congress wanted to increase economic growth by easing access to capital markets for companies that are were often considered too small to take public. To create this ease of access, they created a new category of company, called an Emerging Growth Company (EGC) in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/112/hr3606/summary#libraryofcongress&quot;&gt;JOBS Act&lt;/a&gt; in 2012. Generally, an EGC is one that has less than a billion dollars in revenue and less than $700 million in equity. If a company remains under the revenue threshold, it can keep its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/smallbusiness/goingpublic/EGC&quot;&gt;EGC&lt;/a&gt; status for up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EGC is only required to provide two years of audited statements (instead of three), and less extensive disclosure on executive compensation, and it can delay compliance with new accounting standards. But perhaps the biggest advantage of EGC status is an exemption from receiving a SOX 404(b) opinion, where the independent auditor attests that management’s “internal controls” over financial reporting are effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;internal controls&lt;/a&gt;” are the first line of defense against fraud and human error. Management is supposed to install a system that aids employees in routinely recording the economic activity of the company in a way that is both accurate and comprehensible.  The controls should also ensure that neither employees nor management misuses company assets or manipulates results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management has an inherent interest in creating effective internal controls over its employees, but not necessarily for itself.   In fact, management often has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/symantec-complaint-cites-watchdog-researchs-analysis/&quot;&gt;conflict of interest&lt;/a&gt;. The Enron scandal is just one example of how management can easily succumb to the temptation to manipulate results. Policymakers created the SOX 404(b) attestation requirement so that independent auditors would look over the shoulders of management and help ensure that management’s internal controls were effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost for a SOX 404(b) opinion varies, but it can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schgroup.com/resource/blog-post/sarbanes-oxley-404b-compliance-a-refresher-of-the-initial-questions-you-should-be-asking/&quot;&gt;exceed&lt;/a&gt; $2 million a year, especially at the early stages of implementation. The high cost is due to the independent auditor testing and evaluating the internal controls on financial reporting throughout the year, a time consuming and expensive process (although likely much lower in a labor market like China). This extensive year-round testing makes concealing a large-scale fraud far more difficult for management.  Luckin’s auditor Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/luckin-coffee-anatomy-of-an-auditor&quot;&gt;uncoverd &lt;/a&gt;the fraud, and would have probably have detected the inflated revenues and costs even earlier if it had been testing the internal controls throughout the year.   However, Luckin was classified as an EGC, and therefore, EYHM did not offer an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746919003174/a2238747z424b4.htm&quot;&gt;opinion&lt;/a&gt; on their internal controls and did not do the requisite testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;The Company is not required to have, nor were we engaged to perform, an audit of its internal control over financial reporting.&lt;/strong&gt; As part of our audits we are required to obtain an understanding of internal control over financial reporting but not for the purpose of expressing an opinion on the effectiveness of the Company’s internal control over financial reporting. &lt;strong&gt;Accordingly, we express no such opinion&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SOX 404(b) Attestation Has a Real Impact on the Quality of Internal Controls&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though SOX was passed with the idea that it would cover every company, implementation for small issuers (those with less than $75 million in market cap) were initially given an exemption, and eventually &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;permanently&lt;/a&gt; exempted by the Dodd Frank Act in 2010. An investigation was done by the Government Accountability Office (GAO) in 2012 to see if the SOX 404(b) requirement had any effect on the quality of internal controls. The GAO studied restatement rates between companies that had met the SOX 404(b) requirement (either by law or voluntarily) and those that did not; the results indicated that companies without the SOX 404(b) requirement had weaker controls and therefore filed more restatements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LK%20GAO%20EGC%206.16.png&quot; alt=&quot;LK GAO EGC 6.16.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This indicates that the SOX 404(b) attestation requirement improves the quality of the internal controls at a company.&lt;/strong&gt; In its conclusion the GAO report (which used data provided by Audit Analytics) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;concluded&lt;/a&gt; that the SOX 404(b) attestation “may be useful for investors in gauging the reliability of a company’s financial reporting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By permitting EGCs an exemption to the SOX 404(b) attestation, Congress may have unintentionally lowered the quality of internal controls. Luckin is just one particularly bad example. Consider it this way, if a company makes a big splash with an IPO, and the company is too big to be considered a “small” issuer (with less than $75 million in market cap), then it probably needs &lt;em&gt;extra&lt;/em&gt; scrutiny, not less.  Instead EGCs get a pass. We are troubled about the implications of EGC status in the West. But we are positively alarmed by the implications of EGC status in Chinese companies, where real enforcement is effectively &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;impossible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin took advantage of its EGC status to forego a SOX 404(b) auditor attestation, but they are not alone. Our analysts compared all Chinese companies trading on the Nadsaq, NYSE, and OTC exchanges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/China%20EGC%20numbers.png&quot; alt=&quot;China EGC numbers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysts determined that 53% of listed Chinese companies listed on the Nasdaq, NYSE, and OTC exchanges were classified as EGCs. The collective market cap for these companies is over $65 billion. This may only represent a little less than 5% of the total value of all Chinese based companies traded on U.S. exchanges, but it is still a significant sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have been quick to blame the auditors Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP for not uncovering this fraud earlier. But can people really blame EYHM when it was Congress who loosened the restrictions so that EYHM would not vigorously test and evaluate the internal controls at Luckin? (The issues surrounding EY in this story are very complex and we will give them their own treatment another time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EGCs essentially have no oversight until the auditor arrives to conduct the year-end audit. &lt;strong&gt;That means the current bill passed by the Senate&lt;/strong&gt; that would delist companies whose auditors are not subject to inspection by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;PCAOB&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;would not have stopped the fraud at Luckin&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;even if the CCP acquiesced to inspections&lt;/strong&gt; by the regulator. As it stands now, foreign companies in emerging markets that are considered EGCs have a one-year period where they can fabricate numbers before the auditors come to check their books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public policy makers should be concerned that other foreign companies like Luckin may attempt to use EGC status to run short term scams on the capital markets.  It would be a good step to insist that every company from an emerging market meet the SOX 404(b) requirement before listing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="Auditor Opinions" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="China" /><category term="Sarbanes Oxley" /><category term="EGC" /><summary type="html">Luckin Coffee engaged in one of the most brazen frauds in history. It is easy to blame the fraud on the business environment in China fostered by the CCP. But this fraud could not have occurred if not for systemic weaknesses in the Western capital markets.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/fraud_luckin_standard.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/fraud_luckin_standard.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: Clash Over the PCAOB</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: Clash Over the PCAOB" /><published>2020-06-15T16:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-15T16:31:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/">&lt;p&gt;In April, just as the America was in the grip of the coronavirus originating from Wuhan, Luckin Coffee initially reported that it had discovered a fraud by the COO fabricating over half of the company’s revenue. We wrote an in-depth &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; arguing the fraud was far more pervasive. Since then, Luckin has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920063497/a20-20057_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt;, the WSJ wrote an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/behind-the-fall-of-chinas-luckin-coffee-a-network-of-fake-buyers-and-a-fictitious-employee-11590682336&quot;&gt;exposé&lt;/a&gt; detailing far more extensive fraud than originally reported, the CEO was also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920059927/a20-19256_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;implicated&lt;/a&gt; by Luckin, and now Luckin’s chairman and founder is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2020/06/08/why-luckin-coffee-stock-dropped-today.aspx&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; facing charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin’s massive fraud hints at systemic problems in the Chinese markets. At the root, there is a fundamental difference in how financial information is perceived in the West to how it is perceived by the Chinese Communist Party (CCP). The West holds that financial information should be shared with the investing public, and there are several safeguards to ensure that the information is accurate. For the CCP, financial information is a tool used to meet the goals of the Party. Luckin’s fraud raises the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/2018-06-05/block-says-chinese-equities-are-sin-stocks-video&quot;&gt;possibility&lt;/a&gt; that the CCP has allowed or even encouraged Chinese companies to bilk money out of Western investors as a point of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;policy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, this story has reignited a dormant dispute between China and the U.S. about the regulatory oversight of Chinese auditors. Even though some Chinese audit firms in China are registered with the PCAOB, including affiliates of the Big 4, the CCP has not permitted the PCAOB to conduct investigations of any of its auditors. We consider this so significant that our reports assign a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/&quot;&gt;red flag&lt;/a&gt; to any company whose auditor is not subject to meaningful supervision by the PCAOB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the fraud at Luckin, the Senate unanimously passed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/bill-that-could-delist-chinese-companies-from-us-stock-exchanges-to-see-swift-passage-in-house-analyst-says-2020-05-21&quot;&gt;bill &lt;/a&gt;that would delist any companies from U.S. exchanges whose auditors were not subject to inspection by the PCAOB. As a practical matter, this could result in the delisting of Chinese companies worth over a trillion dollars and trigger a big kerfuffle in U.S.-Sino relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;China’s Longstanding Refusal to Allow Oversight of Their Auditors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Enron scandal, Congress created the PCAOB.  The PCAOB ia a quasi-independent regulator that provides oversight of audit firms; every publicly traded company on a U.S. exchange must have an auditor registered with the PCAOB. The PCAOB conducts inspections of these auditors and can deregister them if they do not meet professional standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCAOB’s influence has expanded internationally, as many countries have &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/International/Pages/RegulatoryCooperation.aspx&quot;&gt;agreements&lt;/a&gt; where the PCAOB will conduct joint inspections with the regulators from other countries to assure every nation has the same high standards for its auditors. China has never agreed to allow these inspections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead the CCP has steadily tightened its grip on the profession. In 2012, the CCP &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/business/la-xpm-2012-may-10-la-fi-china-auditing-rules-20120511-story.html&quot;&gt;ordered&lt;/a&gt; the Big Four affiliates to phase in Chinese nationals to replace foreigners in senior management. And just this year, the CCP passed a law &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/u-s-moves-to-audit-chinese-firms-market-frets-over-what-comes-next-11590485401&quot;&gt;outlawing&lt;/a&gt; cooperating with foreign regulators without express permission. It is very likely that many of the senior partners in these affiliates are Party members, potentially undermining their professional integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China’s refusal to allow PCAOB inspections first came to a head after systemic fraud was revealed in Chinese companies that had accessed U.S. markets via reverse merger. Oftentimes these were shell companies without any actual operations. Even the most cursory oversight would have prevented many of these companies from defrauding investors. In the wake of the reverse merger wave, there was a huge outcry from investors to have more oversight of Chinese firms. The CCP flatly refused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Impotence in the Face of CCP Defiance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2012, concerns over the lack of oversight were coming to a head. The SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/francinemckenna/2011/10/21/auditors-in-china-a-whole-lot-of-posturing-going-on/#cede5ff3f239&quot;&gt;sued&lt;/a&gt; the Big Four affiliates in China for their refusal to hand over their work papers for inspection. However, the affiliates had never promised to hand over their work papers for inspection because it is the policy of the CCP that these papers were “state secrets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Westerners may have scoffed at this idea, but for an authoritarian regime like the CCP, all information is the state’s business. The CCP will never permit accurate and truthful numbers to be recorded and transmitted to its own people and to the West; even something as innocuous as a balance sheet can cause a revolution because truth always poses a danger to propagandists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC and PCAOB did not have the clout to force the CCP to change its position, which left them with a dilemma. Either they could take decisive action and potentially delist all the Chinese companies listed on the U.S. exchanges and deprive every multinational company of the ability to have its Chinese operations audited by a registered affiliate, or they could largely give in while making a few face-saving gestures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC gave in.  No one should have been surprised either, the public policy implications of enforcing the rules were too broad. Decisions concerning international relations are public policy decisions that require leadership in Washington. The administration at that time had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/08/opinion/chinas-rise-isnt-our-demise.html&quot;&gt;expressed&lt;/a&gt; support for closer investment links with China, rendering untenable any course of action that would have alienated the CCP. So, the SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/pressrelease/2015-25.html#:\~:text=SEC%20Imposes%20Sanctions%20Against%20China%2DBased%20Members%20of%20Big%20Four,for%20Refusing%20to%20Produce%20Documents&amp;amp;text=The%20Securities%20and%20Exchange%20Commission,to%20investigations%20of%20potential%20fraud.&quot;&gt;settled&lt;/a&gt; their case for $2 million and the PCAOB signed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://upload.news.esnai.com/2013/0617/1371444412766.pdf&quot;&gt;Memorandum of Understanding&lt;/a&gt; that allowed Chinese firms to register in exchange for vague promises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, those vague promises never amounted to anything. Recently, with the new administration, the SEC and the PCAOB seemed to be more willing to discuss their concerns with China. They issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-vital-role-audit-quality-and-regulatory-access-audit-and-other&quot;&gt;joint&lt;/a&gt; statement warning investors that Chinese firms were not subject to proper oversight, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/regulators-revive-china-audit-dispute-but-miss-prime-opportunity-to-fully-explain-why-2018-12-12&quot;&gt;failed&lt;/a&gt; to full explain the issues involved or do anything to correct the problem. This Caveat Emptor attitude is incongruous with current American customs and law, since economic liberalism and the robber barons it spawned have been confined to the dustbin of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for several years Chinese audit firms have been permitted to register with the PCAOB, even though they are not subject to inspections. This has worked well for Chinese companies, who get a premium price for listing on U.S. exchanges, and it has worked well for Chinese audit firms who register with the PCAOB since they also can charge a &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3111973&quot;&gt;premium&lt;/a&gt;. Whenever a fraud is revealed, individual investors are left holding the bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without leadership from Washington on this issue, nothing could change. There had been some talk over the years, but it had not yielded any fruit. For example, Sen. Marco Rubio &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/you-cant-trust-a-chinese-audit-11559687739&quot;&gt;touted&lt;/a&gt; the EQUITABLE Act last year, a bill he introduced that would have potentially delisted Chinese companies if their auditors were not subject to inspection. But the bill languished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one small step that SEC and the PCAOB took after the Luckin story broke was to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-kingsoft-cloud-ipo/kingsoft-sets-terms-for-u-s-listing-first-major-ipo-since-coronavirus-crisis-idUSKBN22G2JB&quot;&gt;require&lt;/a&gt; companies in China to disclose the fact that their auditors are not subject to inspections by the PCAOB in all relevant financial statements.  Buyer Beware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leadership in Washington?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That changed in May, when the Senate &lt;em&gt;unanimously&lt;/em&gt; passed a bill that would delist Chinese companies unless the CCP permits the PCAOB to oversee their auditors. Frankly, we were shocked when this bill was passed because it takes real steps to address a real problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed this bill passed because of the confluence of two stories: first, the emergence of the coronavirus from Wuhan coupled with credible reports that the CCP’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2020/05/06/finally-the-world-is-catching-on-to-chinas-coronavirus-lies/&quot;&gt;lies&lt;/a&gt; had made the impact of the virus worse, and second, the disclosure of a massive fraud at Luckin. Public opinion turned decisively &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/global/2020/04/21/u-s-views-of-china-increasingly-negative-amid-coronavirus-outbreak/&quot;&gt;against&lt;/a&gt; China, creating the perfect environment for this bill to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unclear if this ostensibly bipartisan bill will be introduced and passed in the House of Representatives. The moment has passed. Reports on riots have finally displaced the unceasing coverage of the coronavirus which had monopolized the airwaves for months. The CCP looks as if it will arrest Charles Lu, the chairman and founder of Luckin, since people were not satisfied with the COO as a scapegoat (nor with the CEO who was served up a month later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a powerful lobby that would like to see this bill scrapped, or at least neutered either in its final form or its enforcement. Many investors know that the CCP will not budge on this issue, but they are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2020/05/22/read-before-selling-all-us-listed-chinese-stock.aspx&quot;&gt;guessing&lt;/a&gt; that Washington will fold. If there is a change in the White House in November it is unlikely that this bill, and the hardline on the CCP that it represents, will last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Issue Unaddressed by the Bill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bill may be helpful for investors, but it omits a crucially important issue. Francine Mckenna, an independent reporter whose work is now available on &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, has pointed out more than &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/regulators-revive-china-audit-dispute-but-miss-prime-opportunity-to-fully-explain-why-2018-12-12&quot;&gt;once&lt;/a&gt; that multinational companies like Pfizer and Walmart rely on Chinese audit firms to conduct the audits of their Chinese operations. This means that there are potential &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-chinese-blind-spot-in-u-s-companies-financials-1532170801?mod=article_inline&quot;&gt;blind-spots&lt;/a&gt; in the audits of some of the biggest and most important companies in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns about the Chinese operations of multinational companies are warranted, and the senate bill does nothing to address that issue. However, this problem may already have an informal albeit makeshift solution. Even though the Chinese audit firms are supposed to do everything locally, it is likely that they &lt;a href=&quot;http://retheauditors.com/2012/07/09/what-the-sec-and-pcaob-fail-to-acknowledge-about-chinese-fraud/&quot;&gt;consult&lt;/a&gt; with their U.S. counterparts when doing a multinational audit. This probably allows the Big Four to exercise some influence over their foreign affiliates in China, even if the official story is that no “sensitive” work-papers ever cross borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shockingly, the Senate has passed a bill that could actually protect investors. However, there is undoubtedly pressure from pro-China lobbyists to scrap the essence of the bill in exchange for some token victory. This victory could be the arrest of Charles Lu or perhaps some “corrupt” CCP officials who supported him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the bill passes, it may not have the effect intended. Chinese companies incorporated in the U.S. or in Tax Havens and only attached to the Chinese operations through contractual agreements (most “Chinese” companies already have one of these “VIE” arrangements) may be permitted to stay on the exchanges without any PCAOB oversight of their auditors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the U.S. wants to really ensure that Chinese companies have proper oversight, Washington must continue to lead and show resolve. However, the stories that drove the passage of this bill are already fading from memory and Washington is a place where resolve is in short supply…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Legislation" /><category term="China" /><category term="featured" /><category term="China" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="Legislation" /><summary type="html">In April, just as the America was in the grip of the coronavirus originating from Wuhan, Luckin Coffee initially reported that it had discovered a fraud by the COO fabricating over half of the company’s revenue. We wrote an in-depth report arguing the fraud was far more pervasive. Since then, Luckin has been delisted, the WSJ wrote an exposé detailing far more extensive fraud than originally reported, the CEO was also implicated by Luckin, and now Luckin’s chairman and founder is reportedly facing charges.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_America%20Runs%20From%20Luckin_Clash%20Over%20PCAOB.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_America%20Runs%20From%20Luckin_Clash%20Over%20PCAOB.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>