<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-29T15:21:46-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Kraft Heinz: Complaint Alleges Fundamental Corporate Governance Problems, Accounting Shenanigans, and Insider Trading</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kraft Heinz: Complaint Alleges Fundamental Corporate Governance Problems, Accounting Shenanigans, and Insider Trading" /><published>2020-05-29T13:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-29T13:55:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/">&lt;p&gt;Kraft Heinz (KHC) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000020/february2019form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a massive $15.4 billion impairment in February, 2019 to its goodwill and intangible assets.  This impairment was essentially an admission by management major components of the combined company were worth billions less than recorded on the balance sheet.  It was also an admission that 3G Capital (3G) and Warren Buffett’s much touted merger of Kraft and Heinz was a failure.   In the aftermath, Warren Buffett &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/buffett-criticizes-others-for-using-non-standard-accounting-metricsbut-he-does-too-2019-02-26&quot;&gt;admitted &lt;/a&gt;that he had overpaid for his 27% of combined company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHC’s impairment crushed share prices and has led to lawsuits, rapid executive bloodletting, an SEC investigation, and other deleterious events.  We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about the KHC bus-crash last September and argued that KHC’s core problem was a loss of investor trust and a poor management ethos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a carefully researched complaint has brought new revelations that support our initial thesis.  The Complaint is built on the public record, as well as information the plaintiffs have been able to request as shareholders (like board and committee minutes, and some other non-public financial information). Initially filed on March 25th, much of the complaint had been redacted because of KHC’s request for confidentiality.  However, thanks to a challenge to the confidentiality filed by Francine Mckenna of The Dig, KHC has narrowed their scope of requested redactions considerably.  The amended plaintiff’s derivative claim accusing 3G Capital of insider trading revolves around accusations of poor corporate governance and manipulation of accounting concerning goodwill testing and impairment for the benefit of 3G and its executives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHC was formed in 2015 in a merger arranged by 3G and Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway.  3G is a Brazilian firm that became one of the largest and most successful private equity firms in the world after it used a series of acquisitions to create AB InBev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the acquisition of Tim Horton’s in 2014, 3G has partnered with Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway on a number of acquisitions.  In these joint ventures, Berkshire Hathaway has bankrolled much of the operation, while 3G has seized control and implemented its management philosophy of zero-based budgeting to cut costs and boost profit margins.  This partnership was generally considered successful, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/antoinegara/2015/07/06/kraft-heinz-will-prove-the-power-of-warren-buffetts-dealmaking-partnership-with-3g-capital/#4bc95ed11a4c&quot;&gt;reportedly &lt;/a&gt;making 3G Warren Buffett’s partner of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate Governance Disaster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mutual Pledges of Loyalty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a company has serious accounting-related problems, usually it also has serious problems in its corporate governance structure.  After the merger that created Kraft Heinz, the company had 11 board members, 5 were appointed by the former board of Kraft, and the other six were evenly divided between representatives of 3G and Berkshire Hathaway.  This gave 3G and Berkshire Hathaway a controlling interest in Kraft Heinz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint draws attention to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000095015716001605/sc13g.htm&quot;&gt;13G&lt;/a&gt; disclosure made by 3G Capital and Berkshire Hathaway where they acknowledged a shareholder agreement to support each other’s nominees to the board and not take any actions to remove the other’s board members.  This effectively created a mutual pledge of loyalty between 3G Capital and Berkshire Hathaway as shareholders.  Even though this agreement does not violate the law, it created a conflict of interest that deprived the board of effective independent members and compromised the loyalty of these directors to the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agreements between shareholders are common, and the law permits them because shareholders do not (usually) owe any duty to each other, or the company, or the board.  However, in this case, the main shareholders (3G and Berkshire Hathaway) were entities whose partners also comprised more than half of the board of directors.  Additionally, and this is key, 3G’s partners were in control of the operations of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go over the basics of corporate governance. Every corporation has a board of directors that oversees the management of the company.  Each member of the board owes the corporate entity a fiduciary duty to the corporate entity to make decisions for the benefit of the shareholders, not for the benefit of management.  A fiduciary duty is a legal term of art defined as an affirmative duty to act on behalf of a person or corporation in good faith, with reasonable care and undivided loyalty.  The duty of loyalty requires board members put the interests of the corporation before all other interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mutual pledge of loyalty by Berkshire Hathaway and 3G undermines the loyalty that the partners are supposed to have toward KHC. It is hard to believe the partners at 3G and Berkshire Hathaway would effectively pledge mutual loyalty to each other as shareholders of KHC in one room, and then walk into another room and act as independent watchdogs monitoring 3G’s management of KHC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint also highlights issues with board independence and asserts that seven of the members had disabling connections to 3G Capital.  The Nasdaq stock exchange requires that the majority of directors on the board be independent so that it is not beholden to management and can act as effective watchdog.  Even if all these directors technically qualified as independent, their connections to 3G, which was in control of management, violated the spirit of Nasdaq rules concerning independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Core Accusation of Manipulation and Insider Trading in the Complaint&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core this case is about whether 3G Capital and its partners manipulated the accounting related to the company’s goodwill in a way that delayed disclosing bad news, and used that delay to sell their holdings at a price they knew was overvalued. This case revolves around the interpretation of ASC 350, an accounting rule that tells companies when and how to test their intangible assets like goodwill for impairment.  The FASB issued ASU 2017-04 simplifying the test for goodwill impairment and allowed companies to adopt it early.  KHC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;adopted &lt;/a&gt;the revised rule on April 1, 2018, so we will focus on the new test for impairment, not the previous version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have criticized this rule &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.  Whenever companies have a merger or acquisition, the tangible and intangible assets are accounted for, and where the market price of the company exceeds the book value of the company’s assets the excess is recorded as “goodwill” on the balance sheet. To ensure that the amount recorded as goodwill really represents something substantive and defensible, companies are required to test their goodwill value every year as well on the occurrence of a triggering event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they evaluate the fair market value of their companies (often granularly reporting unit by reporting if there is more than one), and secondly, they compare this to the book value.  If the book value exceeds the fair value, then the company writes down, or impairs, the goodwill.  If there is not that much “cushion” between the fair value and the carrying value and the goodwill is at substantial risk for an impairment, then the company is required to disclose that risk to investors.  There is no bright line for the amount of “cushion” but in 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745918000015/form10-k2017.htm&quot;&gt;KHC &lt;/a&gt;used 10% as its threshold.  This threshold was not unusual at the time, as some of KHC’s peers, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1103982/000119312518037332/d466496d10k.htm&quot;&gt;Mondelez &lt;/a&gt;used the same standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASC 350 testing for an impairment to goodwill and other intangible assets is at the center of this case.  The question is when should it have occurred, and what should the results have been?  When KHC disclosed the massive impairment they made a case that the impairment was properly recorded in the 4th Quarter, since that is when it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000020/february2019form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;claims &lt;/a&gt;the circumstances arose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the fourth quarter of 2018, in connection with the preparation of our year-end financial statements, we assessed the changes in circumstances that occurred during the quarter to determine if it was more likely than not that the fair values of any reporting units or indefinite-lived intangible assets were below their carrying amounts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While there was no single determinative event, the consideration in totality of several factors that developed during the fourth quarter of 2018 led us to conclude that it was more likely than not that the fair values of certain reporting units and indefinite-lived intangible assets were below their carrying amounts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint argues that the 3G Capital partners managing KHC knew that the company was in trouble well before the 4th quarter.   We made this point ourselves in our original post, although we pointed to sales that were virtually flat in 2017 and 2018, (2017’s poor results were obscured by a $7 billion benefit from the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act signed by Trump). 
The Complaint looks at KHC’s repeated downward adjustments to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/ebitda.asp&quot;&gt;EBITDA &lt;/a&gt;projections to argue that KHC was aware of serious problems by the end of the second quarter.  EBITDA is a financial metric that measures earnings before taxes, interest expense, depreciation, or amortization costs are realized.  The Plaintiff put together a table of KHC’s revisions to EBITDA in 2018:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/KHC%20EBITDA.png&quot; alt=&quot;KHC EBITDA.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: City of Hollywood v. Kraft Heinz, Motion for Confidential Treatment, Exhibit A (18)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular attention is also given to the Audit Committee and Board meetings at the end of the second quarter.  In those meetings management revised EBITDA projections down by $248 million from earlier revisions for a total decline from the beginning of the year of $727 million.  They also disclosed that the SEC made a request that KHC not destroy accounting-related documents due to a pending investigation.  The management at KHC also told the Audit Committee that it had tested some of its international segments, and that two of them required an impairment because their book value exceeded the carrying value by $265 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, KHC’s management’s valuations of the U.S. reporting units (the same ones subject to a $15.4 billion impairment six months later) did not indicate that those units either required an impairment or that they were at significant risk of an impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint alleges that KHC manipulated the valuations of these segments by using outdated and rosy estimates of future earnings, as well as discount rates on future cash flows that were not high enough.  The Complaint also states that KPMG, which assisted in the required annual testing of goodwill, was also using stale projections from earlier in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff asserts that an increase in the discount rates by a mere .5% would have resulted in KHC being required to issue a warning to investors that certain segments were at risk for impairment. As they stood, these segments were measured at just over the threshold for 10% that would have required a warning. This accusation of manipulation lies at the heart of their case, and if it were to go to trial both sides would provide experts to argue the reasonableness of their position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Valuations Often Speculative and Subjective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have access to the underlying financial information that went into this valuation so we cannot make any determination if the allegations of manipulation in the Complaint are true.  But it is worth noting that these valuations are often subjective, unreliable, and easily manipulated.
In their 2018 2nd quarterly report KHC discussed how these valuations were subject to lots of estimates and guesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some of the more significant assumptions inherent&lt;/strong&gt; in estimating the fair values include the estimated future annual net cash flows for each reporting unit (including net sales, cost of products sold, SG&amp;amp;A, working capital, and capital expenditures), income tax rates, and a discount rate that appropriately reflects the risk inherent in each future cash flow stream … &lt;strong&gt;Estimating the fair value of individual reporting units requires us to make assumptions and estimates regarding our future plans&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as industry and economic conditions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the minutes of the Audit Committee Meeting on July 31st, 2018, Kraft Heinz auditor PwC (which had audited both Kraft and Heinz before the merger) warned that management had made some “close call judgements” about the valuations of certain reporting units.  Those warnings appear to be consistent with the PwC’s Critical Audit Matters (CAMs) disclosures made this year.  Auditors are required to disclose any portion of management’s financial reporting that the auditors found particularly challenging, subjective, or complex, and therefore potentially less reliable, as CAMs.  PwC highlighted KHC’s goodwill and intangible asset impairment testing as CAMs for FY 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the potential valuations KHC could have selected given the “play in the numbers,”  it is clear that KHC selected a valuation that allowed them to avoid making an impairment or even warning of a substantial risk of one occurring. &lt;strong&gt;There is no bright-line rule for telling investors when there is a substantial risk of impairment, but KHC changed its threshold after it recorded the massive impairment.  Prior to it, it would disclose only if the “cushion” was below 10%, but afterwards they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;doubled &lt;/a&gt;the “cushion” to 20%.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3G Capital Trims Stake in KHC Before Second Quarter Results Released&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board met on August 2nd.  The CEO, Hees, shared with the board the poor results up to that point, and lowered projections for the end of the year.  Just four days later, on August 6th, 3G trimmed its holdings from 29% to 22% of KHC’s ownership, selling $1.2 billion worth of stock.  Selling at $59.80 a share, 3G netted at least $653 million more than they would have if they sold after the impairment was announced in February 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/KHC%20Chart%20Complaint.png&quot; alt=&quot;KHC Chart Complaint.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3G’s sale was suspicious under the best of circumstances.&lt;/strong&gt;  The firm had orchestrated the merger creating KHC, it was in control of the operations of KHC, and it had three members sitting on the board (plus four other board members with substantial connections).  If 3G smelled something rotten in KHC, then something must have been rotten. Was this decision to sell based on insider information, or was it done properly based on the information disclosed in the 10-Q on August 3rd?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Kraft Heinz" /><category term="Goodwill" /><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="Litigaiton" /><summary type="html">Kraft Heinz (KHC) announced a massive $15.4 billion impairment in February, 2019 to its goodwill and intangible assets. This impairment was essentially an admission by management major components of the combined company were worth billions less than recorded on the balance sheet. It was also an admission that 3G Capital (3G) and Warren Buffett’s much touted merger of Kraft and Heinz was a failure. In the aftermath, Warren Buffett admitted that he had overpaid for his 27% of combined company. KHC’s impairment crushed share prices and has led to lawsuits, rapid executive bloodletting, an SEC investigation, and other deleterious events. We wrote about the KHC bus-crash last September and argued that KHC’s core problem was a loss of investor trust and a poor management ethos.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/conclusion-of-the-contract-3100578_640.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/conclusion-of-the-contract-3100578_640.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Research: Gray Swan Event Factor is Predictive of Stock Return</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Research: Gray Swan Event Factor is Predictive of Stock Return" /><published>2020-05-22T15:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T15:33:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joseph Burke PhD. and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, have produced two white papers for Watchdog Research that show that companies with higher Gray Swan Event Factors have a lower return on investment. This is because accounting-related risks are not properly priced into the market, potentially giving investors who use this valuable tool an edge over the broader market.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, we wrote a series of blog posts on Tesla. These posts highlighted some potential red flags, like turmoil at the CFO and director positions. They also criticized opaque disclosures and the SolarCity debacle. Naively, we believed this would likely hamper Tesla’s appeal to investors, but we were wrong. Really, really, wrong!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla growth from 11/6/19 to 5/20/20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the chart makes obvious, if you had sold your shares when our last blog was posted on November 6th, 2019, then you really missed out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a fact, buyers and sellers determine stock prices. A company’s stock price will not necessarily go down just because their business practices raise numerous red flags, or it suffers a gray swan event (like a financial restatement, securities suit, C-suite change, or material weakness disclosure).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this begs the question, does doing due diligence on management, accounting issues, litigation and other similar red flags have any value for investors? Many investment firms don’t think so, they don’t spend any time tracking or weighing the effects of gray swan events because it’s too much work. How do we know this? We spent months calling and asking them. Instead most firms get their due diligence research from the investment brokers &lt;em&gt;selling the stocks&lt;/em&gt; and assume that the impact of these events is priced into the stock already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our new white papers show that these events are not priced in, and that companies that are more likely to experience a gray swan event perform worse than their peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key Results from Gray Swan Event Factor Research Papers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Burke and Dr. Yarbrough produced two research reports to examine the predictive power of our Gray Swan Event Factor. In one report, they created a portfolio of the 42 companies that had a Gray Swan Event Factor exceeding 10% on January 1st, 2019 and compared the performance of that portfolio to the performance of the S&amp;amp;P 500 with a hypothetical $1,000 investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20%20image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20 image2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of 2019, the portfolio of companies with a large Gray Swan Event Factor lagged further and further behind the market as investors eventually priced in these adverse events. In fact, these companies suffered a loss while the S&amp;amp;P 500 gained well over $200 on its hypothetical investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note is that no large cap companies had a Gray Swan Event Factor over 10%. In their second white paper, Dr. Burke and Dr. Yarbrough made a far more detailed analysis. They put companies into three categories, small cap, mid cap, and large cap. They then divided companies into four tranches according to their Grey Swan Event Factor score: low risk as 0-2%, medium risk as 2-5%, and high risk as 5-10%, and extremely high risk as &amp;gt;10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping in mind that no large cap companies earned a score of over 10%, lets look at the results of a hypothetical $1,000 investment made in January 2019 by GSEF for large cap companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20%20image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20 image3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As can be seen here, the high-risk companies did significantly worse than their peers by the end of 2019, returning a loss during a year when the S&amp;amp;P 500 would have returned nearly $300 dollars on the investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research demonstrates that there is significant value in properly assessing and weighing accounting-related risks. Investors could potentially short high-risk stocks, or they could filter high-risk stocks out of their portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find these results interesting and want to learn more, simply email us and we will provide you with Dr. Burke and Dr. Yarbrough’s white papers free of charge or any commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send the author of this piece John Cheffers, our Director of Research and Associate General Counsel, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Gray Swan Event Factor" /><category term="White Paper" /><summary type="html">Joseph Burke PhD. and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, have produced two white papers for Watchdog Research that show that companies with higher Gray Swan Event Factors have a lower return on investment. This is because accounting-related risks are not properly priced into the market, potentially giving investors who use this valuable tool an edge over the broader market.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/New%20Research.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/New%20Research.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs From Luckin: II</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs From Luckin: II" /><published>2020-05-22T12:52:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T12:52:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-ii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-ii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is the second part in a three-part series on Luckin Coffee. The post below was completed this on May 6th, 2020, while the story was still developing. Since we wrote this piece, Luckin has changed its story and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920059927/a20-19256_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;admitted&lt;/a&gt; that its CEO was involved in the massive fraud and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;delayed&lt;/a&gt; releasing its annual report. It has also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920063497/a20-20057_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt; from the Nasdaq, spelling death for the company. It has also spurred action in Washington, with the Senate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/senate-could-vote-on-bill-that-could-delist-chinese-companies-from-us-stock-exchanges-2020-05-19&quot;&gt;passing&lt;/a&gt; a bill that could potentially delist every Chinese company unless the Chinese Communist Party releases its iron grip on information and allows the PCAOB to inspect its audit firms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Senate bill, if signed into law, would be a serious escalation in the ongoing dispute between the U.S. and the Chinese Communist Party. This is a ten page report detailing many of the vulnerabilities of the U.S. systems to Chinese fraud.  We touch on the inability of the PCAOB to inspect audit firms, which is the subject of the Senate bill, but we cover many other topics as well.  If you want to take a deep dive into understanding how a fraud at a Chinese coffee company could spark an international conflict, read our original analysis…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part II: Impotence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is evidence to suggest Luckin Coffee’s executives—aided and abetted by segments of the CCP— schemed to steal billions from Western investors in one of the largest security fraud cases this decade. Corporate fraud may be a systemic problem in China, but the Western institutions that are supposed to act as gatekeepers to our capital markets appear to have been powerless before the CCP. It is remarkable that the NASDAQ; Luckin’s auditors, Ernst &amp;amp; Young; Credit Suisse and other securities underwriters; the SEC; the PCAOB; and the DOJ were all impotent to stop the fraud at Luckin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, however, it is Congress and the Executive branch that have left American investors vulnerable to fraud sanctioned by the CCP, by neutering all of the normal gatekeepers and watchdogs. &lt;em&gt;This must change.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Appeal of Growth in the Far East&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the time of the California gold-rush, Horace Greeley told Americans to go West, and many did, looking for quick and easy money. Some struck it rich, but many lost everything. Today, American investment houses, tired of stagnant growth in the United States, are rushing to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/cabf76d4-c5a1-11e9-a8e9-296ca66511c9&quot;&gt;pour &lt;/a&gt;billions into Chinese companies, trying to tap into a growing market of 1.3 billion people. Investors are looking to strike it rich by throwing millions of dollars at the next Alibaba. But, all too often, promising companies have &lt;a href=&quot;http://bassiounigroup.com/reverse-takeover-how-fraudulent-chinese-companies-are-deceiving-u-s-investors/&quot;&gt;turned out &lt;/a&gt;to be wholesale frauds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The allure of rapid growth is irresistible to many investors. When Luckin marketed itself as the “Chinese Starbucks,” Western investors fell in love with the idea and heaped over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-luckin-investigation-timeline/luckin-coffees-journey-from-hot-startup-to-5billion-share-wipeout-idUSKBN21L1HW&quot;&gt;$1.5 billion &lt;/a&gt;into Luckin through their public offerings. The stock price rose as high as $50 a share, fueled mostly by hype and enthusiasm, to $12 billion in market capitalization by mid-January 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As China began to suffer from an outbreak of the coronavirus, many investors saw a concurrent stock decline as a great opportunity &lt;a href=&quot;https://investorplace.com/2020/04/luckin-coffee-lk-stock-will-be-a-post-coronavirus-buy/&quot;&gt;to&lt;/a&gt; buy. Even when short seller Muddy Waters took a position on Luckin&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/luckin-coffee-stock-muddy-waters-citron-research-short-sellers-fraud-claim-51580495986&quot;&gt;, and&lt;/a&gt; revealed on January 31st that it had received an anonymous report accusing the company of fraud, investors &lt;a href=&quot;https://investorplace.com/2020/04/luckin-coffee-lk-stock-will-be-a-post-coronavirus-buy/&quot;&gt;were&lt;/a&gt; still high on Luckin. Its stock price remained resilient&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;—until&lt;/a&gt; Luckin disclosed its massive fraud on April 2nd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our first piece, we argued that the official story on Luckin’s fraud—that the COO and a few other employees were responsible—was extremely difficult to believe. It seems far more probable that the chairman Charles Lu and his associates arranged a massive fraud, the full scope of which we cannot be sure of yet. One must also suspect that elements of the CCP assisted Luckin and the fraud every step of the way, and that they are now helping to cover up and understate the fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been some pushback. Given China’s history of reverse merger scams&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20&quot;&gt;, the&lt;/a&gt; recent reports of fraud at Luckin and TAL Education, and stories that the CCP has been lying extensively about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-04-01/china-concealed-extent-of-virus-outbreak-u-s-intelligence-says&quot;&gt;coronavirus,&lt;/a&gt; have led many Western investors to dump Chinese stock. The implications of this moment for Chinese companies and the overall market are hard to overstate. The CCP is apparently so alarmed about the potential implications, that it took the extremely unusual step of making an overture to the SEC and the PCAOB &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/30/business/luckin-coffee-china-fraud-wall-street.html&quot;&gt;in the&lt;/a&gt; wake of Luckin’s collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCP has reason to worry. Chinese companies on the U.S. exchanges have already lost over $200 billion due to market downturn and investor concerns. And there is plenty of money still at stake here: our analysts have found that, even with a $200 billion decline, the current value of Chinese companies on the U.S. exchanges is over a *trillion *dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20market%20table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin market table.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many institutions in the United States have a strong incentive to paper over fundamental problems in giving Chinese firms access to the U.S. capital markets. Companies want access to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/021015/how-many-multinational-corporations-operate-china.asp&quot;&gt;growing &lt;/a&gt;market. Investment houses are prospecting for higher growth and better margins. Underwriters collect their fees. The exchanges make money for every company listed, creating a powerful incentive to list Chinese firms, regardless of any chronic problems these Chinese firms may have. The NASDAQ alone makes $37,000–$155,000 per &lt;a href=&quot;https://listingcenter.nasdaq.com/assets/2018_All_Inclusive_Annual_Fee.pdf&quot;&gt;listing&lt;/a&gt; annually from each of the approximately 145 Chinese-based firms that trade on its Global and Capital Markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Chinese%20companies%20by%20Exchange.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Chinese companies by Exchange.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Communist Party or China Inc.?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Has China become China Inc., the largest corporation in the world, with monopolistic subsidiaries covering every sector of China’s economy, reaching out to compete worldwide? Is China an ideologically-driven communist regime, in its own cold war with the West? For the past two decades, the CCP, and its allies here in the U.S., have told us that China is not ideological, and that it is worth investing and partnering with China. But the CCP’s cover-up of the coronavirus, and its stating outwardly that &lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/bf685dcf52125be54e030834ab7062a8&quot;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; virus could not spread person-to-person, while hoarding medical supplies and allowing citizens to flee to foreign countries, has upended this conventional wisdom on China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the untrustworthiness and potential hostility of the CCP, it is incredible that U.S. exchanges, underwriters, lawmakers, and regulators would permit Chinese companies, under the influence of the CCP, to have access to our capital markets, while not meeting the same reporting and accountability standards demanded of American firms. Yet that is what is happening, and the fraud at Luckin is proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Enron scandal rocked the United States, the Sarbanes-Oxley Act (“SOX”) introduced tough standards and better oversight, intended to prevent large-scale corporate fraud. However, since that time, standards have consistently been relaxed, first in the Dodd-Frank Act of 2010, and then by the JOBS Act in 2012. These measures have loosened certain standards for domestic and foreign firms. Additionally, institutions meant to provide oversight, like the SEC and PCAOB, wilted when they encountered stiff resistance from the CCP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Congress Lowered Standards by Creating “Emerging Growth Company” Status&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congress wanted to increase economic growth by easing access to capital markets for companies that had been considered too small to take public. To foster this ease of access, they created a new category of company, called an Emerging Growth Company (EGC) in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/112/hr3606/summary#libraryofcongress&quot;&gt;JOBS Act &lt;/a&gt;of 2012. Generally, an EGC is one that has less than $1 billion in revenue and less than $700 million in equity. If a company remains under the revenue threshold, it can keep its EGC status &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/smallbusiness/goingpublic/EGC&quot;&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; up to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EGC is required to provide only two years of audited statements, instead of three, and less extensive disclosure on executive compensation. It can also delay compliance with new accounting standards. But perhaps the biggest advantage of EGC status is an exemption from receiving a SOX 404(b) opinion, where the independent auditor attests that management’s “internal controls” over financial reporting are effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;“internal&lt;/a&gt; controls” are the public’s first line of defense against fraud and human error. Management is supposed to install a system that aids employees in routinely recording the economic activity of the company. This recording must be accurate, comprehensible to others, and designed so that neither employees nor management can misuse company assets or manipulate results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management has an incentive to create effective internal controls for its employees, but not necessarily for management itself. The Enron scandal showed that management could easily succumb to a temptation to manipulate results for its own benefit. Hence, policymakers created the SOX 404(b) attestation requirement, so that independent auditors would look over the shoulders of management and help ensure that management’s internal controls were effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost for a “SOX 404(b)” opinion varies, but it can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schgroup.com/resource/blog-post/sarbanes-oxley-404b-compliance-a-refresher-of-the-initial-questions-you-should-be-asking/&quot;&gt;exceed &lt;/a&gt;$2 million a year, especially at the early stages of implementation. The high cost is due to the independent auditor’s testing and evaluating the internal controls on financial reporting throughout the year, a time-consuming and expensive process (although likely much lower in a labor market like China). This extensive year-round testing makes concealing a large-scale fraud far more difficult for management. It seems likely that Luckin’s auditor, Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP (“EYHM”), would have detected the inflated revenues and costs if it had been testing the internal controls throughout the year. However, Luckin was classified as an EGC, and, therefore, EYHM &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746919003174/a2238747z424b4.htm&quot;&gt;did not&lt;/a&gt; offer an opinion on internal controls and did not do the requisite testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Company is not required to have, nor were we engaged to perform, an audit of its internal control over financial reporting.&lt;/em&gt; As part of our audits we are required to obtain an understanding of internal control over financial reporting but not for the purpose of expressing an opinion on the effectiveness of the Company’s internal control over financial reporting. &lt;em&gt;Accordingly, we express no such opinion.”&lt;/em&gt; (emphasis added)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SOX was passed with the idea that it would cover every company. However, its implementation for small issuers (those with less than $75 million in market cap) was initially delayed, and then permanently shelved under the Dodd Frank Act in 2010. Yet does the SOX 404(b) attestation have any real impact on&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt; the quality of&lt;/a&gt; internal controls? An investigation was done by the Government Accountability Office (GAO) in 2012 to see whether the SOX 404(b) requirement had any effect on the quality of internal controls. The GAO studied restatement rates of companies that had met the SOX 404(b) requirement (either by law or voluntarily) as compared with those that did not. The results indicated that companies without the SOX 404(b) requirement had weaker controls and therefore filed more restatements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20GAO%20chart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin GAO chart.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, as the chart shows, SOX 404(b) attestation requirement improves the quality of the financial reporting at a company. The GAO report &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;concluded &lt;/a&gt;that the SOX 404(b) attestation was potentially “useful for investors in gauging the reliability of a company’s financial reporting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By permitting EGCs an exemption to the SOX 404(b) attestation, Congress may have unintentionally lowered the quality of internal controls, and Luckin would be just one particularly bad example. Consider it this way: if a company makes a big splash with an IPO, so that it is too big to be considered a “small” issuer (that is, with less than $75 million in market cap), then it probably needs &lt;em&gt;extra&lt;/em&gt; scrutiny. A rapidly growing company, hungry for capital, probably needs &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; scrutiny, not less. Instead, EGCs get a pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are troubled enough by the implications of EGC status in the West: but we are positively alarmed by the implications of EGC status in Chinese companies, where real enforcement is effectively impossible. Luckin was not alone in taking advantage of EGC status to forego a SOX 404(b) auditor attestation. Our analysts compared all Chinese companies trading on the NASDAQ, NYSE, and OTC exchanges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20EGC%20table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin EGC table.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysts found that 53% of listed Chinese companies listed on the NASDAQ, NYSE, and OTC exchanges were classified as EGCs. The collective market cap for these companies is over $65 billion. Although this represents a little less than 5% of the total value of all Chinese-based companies traded on the exchanges, it is still a significant sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have been quick to blame the auditors Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP for not uncovering this fraud earlier. But can people really blame EYHM, when it was Congress which loosened the restrictions, so that EYHM would not vigorously test and evaluate the internal controls at Luckin? (The issues surrounding EY in this story are very complex: we will give them separate treatment in Part III of this series).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the NASDAQ , it should be concerned that other companies similar to Luckin may be trading on their exchanges, and it would be a good step for it to insist that all Chinese-based companies be required to meet the SOX 404(b) requirement before listing. If the NASDAQ is hesitant to make this change on its own, it should use its powerful lobby in Washington to push Congress into mandating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Foreign Companies Like Luckin Have Lax Insider Trading Disclosure Requirements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC enforces its insider trading laws vigorously. Under the Trump Administration, they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.perkinscoie.com/en/news-insights/u-s-agencies-step-up-insider-trading-enforcement-against-foreign.html&quot;&gt;increasingly pursued &lt;/a&gt;foreign actors, especially the Chinese, for suspected insider trading. The SEC considers its enforcement of the insider trading rules to be a crucial part of its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/rules/final/33-7881.htm#P225_88637&quot;&gt;function&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;”[P]rohibitions against insider trading in our securities laws play an essential role in maintaining the fairness, health, and integrity of our markets. We have long recognized that the fundamental unfairness of insider trading harms not only individual investors but also the very foundations of our markets, by undermining investor confidence in the integrity of the markets.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section 16 of the Exchange Act seeks to deter improper insider trading by requiring directors, officers, and shareholders who hold over 10% of a company’s shares to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/smallbusiness/goingpublic/officersanddirectors&quot;&gt;disclose &lt;/a&gt;most transactions of their stock within two business days. However, foreign private issuers like Luckin are exempt. This is no secret, as Luckin even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746919003174/a2238747z424b4.htm&quot;&gt;warned&lt;/a&gt; investors about it in its prospectus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Because we qualify as a foreign private issuer under the Exchange Act, we are exempt from certain provisions of the securities rules and regulations in the United States that are applicable to U.S. domestic issuers, including … the sections of the Exchange Act requiring insiders to file public reports of their stock ownership and trading activities and liability for insiders who profit from trades made in a short period of time … As a result, you may not be afforded the same protections or information that would be made available to you were you investing in a U.S. domestic issuer.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign private issues are only required to include their insider trading information in their annual reports—&lt;em&gt;once a year&lt;/em&gt;—compared to &lt;em&gt;two business days&lt;/em&gt; for U.S. companies. Has Charles Lu or any other insiders dumped their stock? We do not know, as Luckin has delayed releasing their annual report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;announcing &lt;/a&gt;this delay in late April, they claimed it was due to the impact of the coronavirus: they made no mention of problems stemming from the massive fraud they disclosed less than a month earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public policymakers need to reconsider whether it makes sense to lower our disclosure requirements for insider trading, as a means of encouraging foreign companies to gain access our capital markets. The Trump administration’s focus on foreign insider trading provides some comfort. However, enforcement actions can be effective only if foreign investors keep assets within reach of the authorities. Policymakers therefore need to prevent foreign insider trading in the first place, by ending Section 16 exemption for foreign private issuers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Responsible is the Nasdaq for Slack in its Rules?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Sarbanes-Oxley was passed, the SEC set forth certain minimum standards for listing and trading on the NASDAQ, NYSE, and OTC exchanges. These rules were formulated with input from the exchanges themselves, private companies, regulators, auditors, academics, and other stakeholders. Sometimes, Congress will weigh in as well and tweak the system to advance certain public policy goals, as they did with Dodd-Frank in 2010 and the JOBS act in 2012. The SEC assists in promulgating rules which form a minimum standard, or a floor. But he NASDAQ and the NYSE as private entities can impose higher standards, which accounts for slight &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freewritings.law/wp-content/uploads/sites/24/2019/02/NYSE-vs-Nasdaq-Listing-Standards.pdf&quot;&gt;variations &lt;/a&gt;in the listing requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NASDAQ and the NYSE have some discretion, so they bear some responsibility if slack in their standards enables a fraud. Admittedly, Congress is the main entity that has occupied the field. Nonetheless, the exchanges have much power and influence, and they should be advocating for strong standards to protect investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Luckin Flouted Corporate Governance Requirements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarbanes-Oxley introduced extensive corporate governance rules to check management’s impulses and protect from fraud. The NASDAQ cooperates with the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority (“FINRA,” another &lt;a href=&quot;http://nasdaq.cchwallstreet.com/NASDAQTools/PlatformViewer.asp?selectednode=chp%5F1%5F1%5F3%5F3%5F8%5F3&amp;amp;manual=%2Fnasdaq%2Fmain%2Fnasdaq%2Dequityrules%2F&quot;&gt;quasi-private&lt;/a&gt; oversight entity) in implementing these rules. A key component of these reforms was to require the involvement of “independent directors” in public companies, that is, directors who lack personal or financial ties which management can leverage to make the director beholden to management. The law requires that these independent directors be put in important positions to act as watchdogs for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, to trade on the NASDAQ, the majority of directors on the board must be independent. Additionally, the company must have an audit committee of three members, all of whom must be independent, and one of whom must be financially sophisticated (that is, with a background in accounting or something similar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there is large-scale fraud at a company, one can be certain that there are flaws in corporate governance. Generally, there are two types of problems: (1) rules which are insufficient, because they allow companies to skirt around the spirit of the law, while staying within the letter of it, and (2) companies that simply break the rules. Luckin had both problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin did not have a majority of independent directors. In fact, of the eight members of the board, only two, Thomas P. Meier and Sean Shao, were held out as independent directors. The NASDAQ has allowed foreign companies an exemption if the majority independence rule contradict local law. It also permitted foreign companies to request an exemption, if the requirement was against the generally accepted business practice for that specific country. But because few foreign firms were able to gain an exemption under this standard, they petitioned for a change in the rule. Indeed, the rule was&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clm.com/publication.cfm?ID=23&quot;&gt; relaxed&lt;/a&gt; in 2005, so that, instead of needing to request an exemption, firms could just declare that they were taking one. The change towards relaxation was not made in the best interests of investors, but rather it was because foreign companies can have legal and language barriers that make performing due diligence difficult. Unsurprisingly, Luckin opted to diminish the role on its board for these watchdogs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Listing Rules of the NASDAQ generally require that a majority of an issuer’s board of directors must consist of independent directors. However, the Listing Rules of the NASDAQ permit foreign private issuers like us to follow “home country practice” in certain corporate governance matters. We rely on this “home country practice” exemption and do not have a majority of independent directors serving on our Board of Directors.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no such exemption for the Audit Committee, however, which raises an important question: how could the audit committee have missed this fraud? How could the audit committee have missed a fabrication of more than half of the annual revenue with substantial changes in costs and expenses? One contributing factor is that the rules allow companies to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/info/smallbus/gbfor25_2006/goingpublic.pdf&quot;&gt;phase-in &lt;/a&gt;independent members after an IPO. Only two of the three audit committee members were independent, and one member, Mr. Erhai Liu was the founder and manager of Joy Capital, a firm that was heavily invested in the company. In sum, Luckin gamed the rules, using the foreign exception to the majority independent director rule, and the phase-in period for the audit committee, to reduce the scope of these independent directors’ roles as watchdogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But possibly Luckin also broke the rules. The directors which it held out as “independent” were Thomas P. Meier, the former president and CEO of Frankee Coffee Systems, and Sean Shao. However, when Mr. Meier was still leading Frankee coffee systems, they and another manufacturer obtained a contract with Luckin, in 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://alltechasia.com/luckin-coffees-blue-partner-alliance-fuels-its-bold-10000-shop-target/&quot;&gt;that was&lt;/a&gt; reported to quintuple sales. It seems plausible that serving in that role ought to have disqualified Mr. Meier from qualifying as an independent director. After all, NASDAQ does not consider independent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“(D) &lt;em&gt;a director who is&lt;/em&gt;, or has a Family Member who is, a partner in, or a controlling shareholder or &lt;em&gt;an executive officer of, any organization to which the company made&lt;/em&gt;, or from which the company received, &lt;em&gt;payments for property&lt;/em&gt; or services &lt;em&gt;in the current or any of the past three fiscal years that exceed 5% of the recipient’s consolidated gross revenues for that year, or $200,000&lt;/em&gt; ($1 million if the listed company is also listed on the New York Stock Exchange), &lt;em&gt;whichever is more&lt;/em&gt;… (emphasis added)”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Meier left his position at Frankee in March 2019 to join Luckin as an independent director. Given the large contract with Luckin, apparently he should have been disqualified under the NASDAQ rules, as he was an executive at Frankee Coffee Systems, which had a contract with Luckin, which likely exceeded both 5% of revenue and $200,000. About three weeks after Luckin disclosed its fraud on April 21st, Mr. Meier resigned as an “independent” director and member of the audit committee. There was no explanation for his departure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other independent director, Sean Shao, has extensive experience as an independent director. He worked at Deloitte Touche Tohmatsu CPA Ltd for almost a decade before taking up the role of independent director at many companies. One of his longest tenures was with Agria Corporation, from 2008-2017, where he was an independent director and chairman of the corporate governance committee. In 2018, Agria settled with the SEC for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2018-276&quot;&gt;fraud &lt;/a&gt;relating to its operations in China from 2010- 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nasdaq’s Hollow Requirement for PCAOB Oversight of Accounting Firms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NASDAQ requires that all companies trading on its exchange be audited by firms that are registered with the PCAOB. This is meant to assure investors that the companies listed on the Nasdaq are receiving the highest quality audits, because the auditors are subject to oversight from the PCAOB. The PCAOB is a quasi-private organization that was created after the Enron scandal to conduct investigations of audits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin’s auditor, Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP, has been registered &lt;a href=&quot;https://rasr.pcaobus.org/Firms/FirmSummaryPublic.aspx?FirmID=7F42AF1786DA878DD7EAC2AFA2A74C03&quot;&gt;with&lt;/a&gt; the PCAOB since 2004.  EYHM is the Chinese affiliate of Ernst &amp;amp; Young Global Limited, one the big four. Ernst &amp;amp; Young’s Chinese affiliate EYHM, by itself, may be one of the largest accounting firms in the world. If one looks only at EYHM’s Chinese-based clients that are public companies trading on U.S. exchanges, in 2018&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EYHM collected over $57 million in fees, from companies valued at over $213 billion dollars. EYHM also audits the Chinese operations of many multinational companies, like Apple and Walmart, and they undoubtably have many private company clients and clients listed on foreign exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a firm of EYHM’s stature as its external auditor certainly boosted investor confidence in Luckin’s financial statements. The fact that EYHM was registered with the PCAOB probably also contributed to this confidence, which is why Chinese &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3111973&quot;&gt;companies&lt;/a&gt; often pay a premium for auditors that are registered with the PCAOB. However, EYHM has never been subject to an inspection by the PCAOB: indeed no other Chinese audit firm has been inspected either. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/International/Inspections/Pages/IssuerClientsWithoutAccess.aspx&quot;&gt;CCP&lt;/a&gt; simply does not permit the PCAOB to inspect its audit firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the PCAOB is to provide oversight of the accounting profession, so that companies and their investors receive high quality audits. Its role is so important, that the NASDAQ *requires *every company that lists on its exchange to be registered with the PCAOB. The most important tools in the PCAOB’s toolbox are its ability to inspect audit firms and to deregister them if they fail to meet industry standards. But they simply do not have these tools when it comes to Chinese firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why then are Chinese audit firms allowed to register with the PCAOB at all, if they are not subject to inspections? After all, isn’t that the point of the PCAOB? The PCAOB does not deregister them, because that would be enormously disruptive to business: Chinese-based audit firms provide services for Chinese-based companies worth over a trillion dollars, and they provide audit services for China based operations of multinational companies as well. The PCAOB cannot effectively delist hundreds of companies, collectively valued at over a trillion dollars, on its own. The public policy implications are so broad, that only Congress could make a decision like that. Unless Congress takes some action, then, the NASDAQ’s insistence that all firms be registered with the PCAOB will remain a flaccid requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One small step that the SEC and PCAOB have taken is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-kingsoft-cloud-ipo/kingsoft-sets-terms-for-u-s-listing-first-major-ipo-since-coronavirus-crisis-idUSKBN22G2JB&quot;&gt;require &lt;/a&gt;companies in China to disclose, in all relevant financial statements, the fact that their auditors are not subject to inspections by the PCAOB . But is this enough? And why is this allowance given to Chinese-based but not US companies with major operations in China?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have Underwriters Become Careless?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before a company offers its stock to the public in an IPO, it is supposed to undergo an extensive vetting process. Part of this process is called underwriting, and it involves having investment banks act as intermediaries between the company and the public. The investment bankers conduct a substantial factual investigation of the company and its prospectus so that it can accurately price the stock. Sometimes, the underwriters will purchase shares at a wholesale price and then resell them to other investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/business/banking-finance/article/3078667/credit-suisse-out-tencent-backed-wedoctors-hong-kong-ipo&quot;&gt;underwriters&lt;/a&gt; for the Luckin IPO were Credit Suisse, Morgan Stanley, China International Capital corporation and Haitong. This consortium of influential investment banks certainly had the resources to conduct proper due diligence on Luckin, but did they? The IPO was on May 17th, 2019, and Luckin has now stated that its numbers were unreliable for the quarter starting on April 1, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, even if one accepts the story (and we are skeptical) that the fraud at Luckin began in the second quarter of 2019, there is still overlap between the start of the fraud and the timeframe in which the banking consortium should have been conducting its due diligence. There have also been troubling allegations in an anonymous report published by Muddy Waters of related party transactions, and other red flags, which the banking consortium might have discovered in its due diligence process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible that the banking consortium could have discovered the fraud with proper due diligence? The SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-luckin-investigation/u-s-sec-investigates-luckin-coffee-over-accounting-scandal-wsj-idUSKBN22B1D6&quot;&gt;declared&lt;/a&gt; an investigation into Luckin’s fraud, and they will likely take a look at the banking consortium’s due diligence practices. Luckin’s fraud has already resulted in lawsuits. Because Chinese law will probably shelter Luckin’s assets, it is likely that suits will also be filed against the underwriters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Effective Immunity from Private Suit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A suit against the underwriters could be very difficult to win. In 1994 the Supreme Court held that private plaintiffs could not sue a third party for aiding or abetting a fraud, in Central Bank v. First Interstate, 511, U.S. 164 (1994). In 2008, the Supreme Court doubled down in Stoneridge Investment Partners v. Scientific-Atlanta, holding that third parties are not liable for participating in corporate wrongdoing if they did not directly mislead investors. In 2008, the Supreme Court had also denied certiorari in California Regents v. Merrill Lynch, a case in which the 5th Circuit found Merrill Lynch and other investment banks not liable for Enron’s fraud, even though they had aided Enron in cooking their books, on the grounds that they did not have a duty to investors, and they had made no false statements directly to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These decisions in the Supreme Court have been reinforced by decisions in the lower courts, such as SEC v. Tambone, where the 1st Circuit held that the underwriters for an IPO do not make any implied representations in the prospectus, even though they have a duty to investigate a company. But it seems timely to ask: Has this protection from private suit made underwriters careless?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1933 Securities Act does allow underwriters to be sued in a private cause of action when there are false statements in the prospectus for an IPO under sections 11 and 12a-3 (unlike the provision 10b-5 that allows a private cause of action for fraud subject to the Central Bank and Stoneridge decisions discussed above). However, unlike a private suit brought under 10b-5, due diligence is a complete defense to this charge. If the consortium can show they took “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/230.176&quot;&gt;reasonable care&lt;/a&gt;” and conducted a reasonable investigation of Luckin, then they will be immune from suit. It will be interesting to see if substance will triumph over style in the court’s analysis of the consortium’s due diligence. Since most of the events occurred in China, we will also be interested to see if any investigation is even feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SEC as the Last Line of Defense&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note is that the SEC, for its part, &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; bring a 10b-5 case against an entity that aids and abets a fraud, because it is a government entity and not a private entity. The publicity surrounding this case, and the SEC investigation into Luckin, has actually raised the possibility that Credit Suisse and Morgan will be charged with aiding and abetting Luckin’s fraud. But, once again, a lack of information coming out of China may hamper any investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign companies and domestic companies are both trying to gain access to the capital markets in the United States, but they do not have to play by the same rules. Foreign companies have numerous allowances designed to give leeway, and Luckin took advantage of them. Yet consider how enormous Luckin’s fraud was: it fabricated half of its revenue and potentially stole &lt;em&gt;billions&lt;/em&gt; from Western investors. This will happen again, and happen soon, unless policymakers take decisive action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send the author of this piece John Cheffers, our Director of Research and Associate General Counsel, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="Emerging Growth Companies" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="Congress" /><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="Fraud" /><summary type="html">This post is the second part in a three-part series on Luckin Coffee. The post below was completed this on May 6th, 2020, while the story was still developing. Since we wrote this piece, Luckin has changed its story and admitted that its CEO was involved in the massive fraud and delayed releasing its annual report. It has also been delisted from the Nasdaq, spelling death for the company. It has also spurred action in Washington, with the Senate passing a bill that could potentially delist every Chinese company unless the Chinese Communist Party releases its iron grip on information and allows the PCAOB to inspect its audit firms.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/America%20Runs%20From%20Luckin-%20II.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/America%20Runs%20From%20Luckin-%20II.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">America Runs from Luckin: I</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America Runs from Luckin: I" /><published>2020-05-22T12:44:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T12:44:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/">&lt;p&gt;This post is Part I in a three-part series on Luckin Coffee. The post below was completed on April 27th, 2020, as the story was still developing. Since we wrote this piece, Luckin has changed its story and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920059927/a20-19256_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;admitted&lt;/a&gt; that its CEO was involved in the massive fraud and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;delayed&lt;/a&gt; releasing its annual report. It has also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920063497/a20-20057_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt; from the Nasdaq, spelling death for the company. It has also spurred action in Washington, with the Senate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/senate-could-vote-on-bill-that-could-delist-chinese-companies-from-us-stock-exchanges-2020-05-19&quot;&gt;passing&lt;/a&gt; a bill that could potentially delist every Chinese company unless the Chinese Communist Party releases its iron grip on information and allows the PCAOB to inspect its audit firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Senate bill, if signed into law, would be a serious escalation in the ongoing dispute between the U.S. and the Chinese Communist Party. To understand how a fraud at a Chinese coffee company could spark an international conflict, read our original analysis…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part I: The Fraud at Luckin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Executive Summary. If one tallies all the money lost in the West from the Luckin fraud, which went either to Luckin, or directly to its chairman Charles Lu, before the stock was shorted, this amounts to $2.165 billion. If one additionally includes money from short positions, and other potentially undisclosed and improper insider trading, the total could be far higher. Thus, from issues of sheer scale, the fraud requires careful attention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For many years, there have been credible &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2020/02/10/804501991/chinese-hackers-charged-in-alleged-cyber-theft-of-145-million-americans-data&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; that elements of the CCP have sponsored selective looting of intellectual property from Western companies, through cyber hacking and other scams, and that similarly, the CCP has protected the perpetrators from prosecution. Can this alternative be ruled out in the case of Luckin?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ‘downside’, which must be protected against, would be extremely serious. If elements of the CCP have aided and abetted Chinese companies in defrauding Western investors on a grand scale, then there are significant implications for the US legislators, regulators, and gatekeepers for the capital markets and their relationships with the CCP. The implications range all the way from the relatively small-scale, such as whether a US company’s important supply chain should be located solely in China, all the way up to policy questions about the relationship, going forward, between economic engagement and civil liberties in China.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The evidence raises the colorable claim that Luckin’s fraud involved further bad actors, and greater coordination, than a renegade COO—the current official explanation. Watchdog Research believes that the currently available information more than justifies an investigation, by investigative journalists and competent US public authorities, to rule out if possible the worst-case hypothesis, that Luckin was a scam from the beginning, where its public statements, capital raising, revenue projections, expense disclosures, and borrowings came together in an orchestrated, fraudulent scheme to fleece billions of dollars from greedy Western investors hungry for big returns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It must be kept in mind that, according to official communist ideology, the system of free markets is itself corrupt and inherently a system of greed, and the destabilization of such markets can only serve to promote an eventual communist revolution. To exploit the ‘capitalist system’ to the advantage of communism, on this ideology, is regarded as a positive good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 2nd 2020, Luckin Coffee, which had been a darling for American investors since its IPO in 2019, and which had attracted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1061165/000106116520000006/sc13gluckincoffee.htm&quot;&gt;support&lt;/a&gt; from institutional investors like Lone Pine Capital, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that its COO and some employees had fabricated expenses and revenue. TAL Education Group, another company based in China, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1499620/000110465920044459/tm2015354d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales numbers just five days later. These stories quickly gained prominence in the news, in part because of corresponding stories about the CCP’s blatant &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/02/us/politics/cia-coronavirus-china.html&quot;&gt;lies&lt;/a&gt; about the numbers of infections and deaths from the Wuhan flu in China. Indeed, it has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/5-million-left-wuhan-before-coronavirus-quarantine-2020-1&quot;&gt;become clear&lt;/a&gt; that the Chinese government allowed 5 million visitors to leave Wuhan for other parts of the world, after it knew about the virus and had blocked travel from Wuhan to other parts of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The confluence of these stories about the virus and the CCP, and about two prominent Chinese companies, produced a widespread negative reaction, with many investors gaining a newfound &lt;a href=&quot;https://finanz.dk/luckin-debacle-shakes-investor-faith-in-new-yorks-china-listings/page/2/&quot;&gt;skepticism&lt;/a&gt; about reported financial results in China. New stories that the CCP has almost certainly been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/coronavirus-covid-19-origins-investigation-wuhan-lab-accident/&quot;&gt;covering&lt;/a&gt; up the origins of the Wuhan flu serve only to deepen skepticism of the reliability of regulatory and oversight institutions in China, and standards of transparency and fairness. The SEC and DOJ have had no ability to prosecute frauds in China, and the CCP seems intent on covering them up, creating a dangerous dynamic. With no fear of punishment or disgorgement, it is reasonable to suppose that criminals in China have been emboldened to commit fraud on Western investors. As mentioned, on communist ideology, it is not clear, to say the least, that such fraud would even be identified as ‘wrong.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conventional Wisdom on the Fraud&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The massive Luckin fraud was first revealed by the activist short-seller Muddy Waters, which published a report by an anonymous author detailing the fraud. This triggered an investigation by Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP (EYHM). When EYHM learned of the fraud, they reportedly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yicaiglobal.com/news/exclusive-auditor-anti-fraud-team-led-to-luckin-confession-sources-say&quot;&gt;pressured&lt;/a&gt; Luckin to come clean. When Luckin did make its report, there began a massive sell-off, and a halt on trading, for the short-term at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Share price of Luckin Coffee for 2020, which is mapped to Watchdog Flags on the interactive Watchdog website&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;own disclosure&lt;/a&gt; states that the COO was responsible for initiating the fraudulent overreporting of revenue by over $300 million for 2019, which was more than half of the company’s reported revenue that year. This furthers a narrative that the pressure to meet expectations after the company’s IPO in May of last year motivated the COO and his underlings to inflate sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official story is of course not the only reasonable hypothesis. We find this narrative highly unpersuasive on its face. It seems doubtful that the COO could have pulled off fabricating more than half of Luckin’s revenue, and made “substantial” changes to expenditures, without the knowledge of the CFO or CEO. And it is implausible that a fraud so massive began only after the IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close look at the available evidence suggests that, possibly, it was Luckin’s top executives who benefited most from this fraud. Moreover, there are indications that at some point, if not from the beginning, the company’s primary purpose changed from serving coffee to scamming Western investors. Enough evidence already exists, we believe, to justify an investigation to determine the true scope of Luckin’s fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this represent an Enron moment? Are truly large questions necessarily raised by this fraud, about how US securities regulators, auditors, exchanges, underwriters and Congressional representatives should respond?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digging into the Anonymous Report&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carson Block’s Muddy Waters has become renowned for eviscerating Chinese companies, ever since Carson Block kickstarted his career by publishing a damaging &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/id/43765929&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; on Orient Paper. Since then, Muddy Waters has issued numerous reports which resulted in serious losses for Chinese companies and even delisting, making Muddy Waters a wealthy and powerful short seller. However, in the case of Luckin, Muddy Waters claims not to have written the report, but to have received it from an anonymous source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1LKOYMpXVo1ssbWQx8j4G3-strg6mpQ7F/view&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; published by Muddy Waters was not created by amateurs. It included thousands of hours of footage shot by 92 full-time and 1,418 part-time staff in 38 separate cities. The costs for producing this report would have easily run into the millions, which raises the question of who funded this report. Muddy Waters could have funded it and be lying. It could also have been Starbucks that paid for it, looking to kneecap a potential competitor. Perhaps it was a Chinese firm that received an inside scoop and wanted to benefit from the short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core claim of the report is that reported sales numbers simply did not match actual customer volume, such that 70%-90% of sales were inflated. Luckin apparently rigged its ordering system to skip numbers so make it more difficult if not impossible to discover the manipulation. The report appears to have obtained a screenshot of instructions sent to employees telling them to ignore the discrepancies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Text.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Text.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings were confirmed when Luckin admitted through its financial restatement that its COO had started inflating sales in May 2019. The restatement also indicated that some costs and expenses had been substantially inflated. But the report contains other red flags which indicate that it may have been the chairman of Luckin, Charles Zhengyao Lu, and his associates, who were ultimately responsible for the fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indicia of a Larger Fraud in the Anonymous Report&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous report pointed out a red flag, which had been buried in the fine print of the Luckin’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000104746920000079/a2240174zf-1.htm&quot;&gt;prospectus&lt;/a&gt;, filed on January 7th, 2020, which is this: Charles Lu, Luckin’s chairman, Jenny Zhiya Qian, the CEO, and Sunying Wong (who is &lt;a href=&quot;https://luckincoffee.info/2020/04/07/goldman-sachs-usd-520-million-ruixing-stock-pledge-loan-default/&quot;&gt;alleged&lt;/a&gt; to be the sister of Charles Lu, a fact not disclosed in the SEC filing) pledged 49% of their collective shares to underwrite loans. The anonymous report argued that pledging shares for personal loans allowed Charles Lu and his associates effectively to cash out their ownership without panicking other shareholders. This theory appeared to be confirmed, when Goldman Sachs reported that Charles Lu defaulted on his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.morningstar.com/news/dow-jones/202004071246/loan-to-luckin-chairman-could-cost-banks-millions-wsj&quot;&gt;$518 million&lt;/a&gt; loan only a few days after the fraud was revealed, which looks like a smoking gun for his involvement in the fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous report also claimed that Luckin engaged in related party transactions with companies that were controlled by Charles Lu and his associates. Luckin’s SEC filings disclosed it received advertising services from a company that is affiliated with Charles Lu. But the anonymous report claims not only that Charles Lu understated his relationship with advertising companies, but also that he controlled additional companies that provided coffee vending machines and food products to Luckin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a related party transaction, a person in control of two companies can syphon off money for himself, by having the one company overpay for goods or services to the other company, pocketing for himself the difference of overpayment. The report accuses Luckin of inflating its advertising costs by over 150% and of dramatically inflating the cost of its coffee vending machines. One way of hiding such overcharges on related party transactions is to increase revenue falsely, to make it look as though revenue is increasing apace, with all the extra expenditures. Thus, there needs to be an investigation to determine if Luckin’s fraud started with fabricating expenses, instead of fabricating revenue. There should also be an investigation of the cost of building and outfitting new stores, one of Luckin’s largest expenditures, to see if that cost was inflated as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymous report also accuses the founding partner of Centurium Capital of being an old friend of Charles Lu because of its investment in one of Charles Lu’s other companies. Centurium Capital was one of the early investors in Luckin, contributing over $180 million in 2018. On January 8th, 2020, it made over $230 million by selling 20% of its holdings in Luckin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/chinas-centurium-capital-to-reach-first-close-at-%242-bln%3A-sources-2020-03-05&quot;&gt;netting $50&lt;/a&gt; million on its initial investment. One could argue that the sale was not suspicious, after all, because Centurium retained 80% of its holdings. However, if an investing firm believed it was in on the ground floor of the Chinese Starbucks, would it sell 20% of its holdings? Besides, the percentages do not really matter that much: what really matters is how much money they were putting in their pockets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report contains many other claims, but the existence of the report itself indicates that there may be a larger conspiracy here, something we believe is obvious. There are two reasonable inferences that can be drawn from the mere existence of this report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. &lt;em&gt;Someone on the inside of Luckin leaked this information&lt;/em&gt;. There is no chance anyone would have spent several months and millions of dollars to create this report on a hunch. They had to know what they would find before they started looking, and the report was merely to document the fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;Certain members of the CCP were aware of this report before it came out&lt;/em&gt;. China is an authoritarian &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifesitenews.com/news/chinese-govt-uses-smartphones-to-track-citizens-deny-service-to-those-deemed-threat-to-society&quot;&gt;surveillance state&lt;/a&gt;, which uses advanced technology to track and grade all of its citizens movements, all the time. It would be exceedingly difficult for any group to spend millions of dollars, and hire over 1,500 people to conduct surveillance, without the CCP knowing about it. Additionally, the authors of the report must have known that exposing the CCP to potential embarrassment could easily cost them everything. Therefore, it is unlikely that the authors would have hired so many people in this endeavor without sufficient ‘comfort,’ taking the form of knowledge and permission of suitably placed CCP authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the origin of the report itself, and who knew about it, needs to be investigated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Springtime for Luckin; Winter for Western Investors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its peak in January, Luckin had a market cap of over &lt;a href=&quot;https://ycharts.com/companies/LK/market_cap&quot;&gt;$12 billion&lt;/a&gt; (reaching $50.4 per share on January 19, 2020). Now it stands at $1 billion, but only because the halt in trading has kept it from falling still lower. However, it is unlikely that the people responsible will face any punishment because most of that money belonged to Western investors. For over a decade, the CCP has employed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/06/us/politics/china-hacking-cyber.html&quot;&gt;state sponsored hackers&lt;/a&gt;, tasked with stealing information, intellectual property, and technology from Western governments and companies. These groups do not restrict themselves to stealing sensitive information: they also steal plenty of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.knowbe4.com/chinese-state-sponsored-phishing&quot;&gt;money&lt;/a&gt;. Elements of the CCP have long sponsored the looting of Western companies and protected the perpetrators from any consequences, provided they get some of the benefit themselves, and their long-term interests are not threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This broader context is important, because if Charles Lu purchased the patronage of certain elements of the CCP, then one must consider the possibility that the launch of Luckin, from the start, was a scam to defraud Western investors; and, if not from the beginning, then whether it turned into such a scheme, when it became clear to those on the inside, after the IPO in April 2019, that growth at the pace that investors were expecting would be untenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin was founded in 2018, and in June it received $200 million in investments from a private equity firm in Singapore and two Chinese firms, Centurium Capital and Joy Capital. In November, it raised another $200 million from the same investors. Up to this point, Luckin had mostly been in the business of building stores (over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/luckin-coffee-ipo-stock-price-51558054869&quot;&gt;2,370&lt;/a&gt; of them in about a year), and it had little revenue to show for it. By this time, Charles Lu probably had gained the patronage of some important Party officials. Indeed, to have built so many shops, in such a short period of time, in a country so tightly controlled by Party officials, would otherwise have been impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2019, foreign investments started to roll in. Luckin received $150 million from Blackrock in pre-IPO fundraising. Then, in May, Luckin generated over $645 million from its IPO. By November, the company had made two fraudulent quarterly reports, which showed rising revenues and associated expenses, while also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465919065621/a19-23472_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;claiming&lt;/a&gt; the number of its stores had risen to 3,680:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%203d%20quarter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin 3d quarter.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One must consider that Charles Lu, after his lock-up on shares came to an end in November 2019, potentially wished to use these fraudulent results to pledge shares as collateral for a $518 million loan. In January 2020, Luckin raised over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920003929/a20-3405_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;$850 million&lt;/a&gt; more in shares and bond offerings, even though they claimed to retain, still, over $650 million in cash and cash equivalents after the third quarter. As mentioned, Centurium Capital, whose founding partner is allegedly affiliated with Charles Lu, sold over $230 million in holdings, just a few weeks before Muddy Waters published its anonymous report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not know if Centurium was able to extricate any more capital out of Luckin. However, a thorough investigation is necessary, to see which other investors bailed just prior to the publication of the report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin’s share price was initially resilient, but it plummeted when the fraud was confirmed. The short sellers made a killing, estimated at about &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/news/luckin-coffee-short-sellers-1-152036003.html&quot;&gt;$1.1 billion&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, an investigation into the Luckin fraud also needs to discover who benefited from the short besides Muddy Waters, to see if in particular if there are any related parties that benefited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Timeline.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final tally of cash flowing into China is this: $150 million taken from Blackrock; $1.5 billion raised from public offerings; $518 million in a personal loan to Charles Lu; and an unknown amount of proceeds from share and short sales. Moreover, Western investors lost a company that was valued at $12 billion as recently as January 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Was the COO Responsible?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the evidence, it is hard to believe that Charles Lu and the other executives were unaware of the fraud. A look at the company’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465919065621/a19-23472_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;unaudited&lt;/a&gt; third quarter results indicates that they claim that about $300 million was spent on operating costs for that quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total operating expenses&lt;/strong&gt; were RMB2,132.5 million (US$298.3 million), representing an increase of 193.6% from RMB726.4 million in the third quarter of 2018. The increase in operating expenses was the result of business expansion. Meanwhile, operating expenses as a percentage of net revenues decreased to 138.3% in the third quarter of 2019 from 301.7% in the third quarter of 2018, mainly driven by increased economies of scale and the Company’s technology-driven operations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that the revenue number for this company was almost completely fabricated, one has reason to doubt every number in these statements. Luckin reported approximately a billion dollars in total expenses for 2018 and the first three quarters of 2019. Given that this number is likely overstated, perhaps by hundreds of millions of dollars, and that Luckin did make some revenue, the company ought to have been swimming in cash, and anyone with access to company accounts would have noticed something was wrong. Yet we are expected to believe that the COO and a few other employees conducted this fraud without the knowledge of the CFO, the CEO, or Charles Lu. A far more reasonable hypothesis is that much of this money ended up in the pockets of Charles Lu and associates through related party transactions, and significant amounts probably greased the palms of important CCP officials as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the CCP and the Western media have uncritically accepted Luckin’s offering of its COO as a sacrificial scapegoat. It does not appear that the CCP is investigating Charles Lu and his family members—someone might comment mordantly that when the CCP is displeased with a business owner, that person often simply &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/news/china-billionaires-ceo-disappearing-missing-station-sanctioned-abductions-beijing-security-agencies-a7564896.html&quot;&gt;disappears&lt;/a&gt;. Some doctors who blew the whistle on the coronavirus are still &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/china-coronavirus-whistleblowers-speak-out-vanish-2020-2&quot;&gt;missing&lt;/a&gt;. Since Charles Lu is still with us and apparently flourishing, it is probably because officials at the CCP are pleased with his contributions to the Party. For all we know, he is being hailed a hero, and there is some &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WBYeats1865/status/1245730490234982400&quot;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; supporting this idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are these idle speculations, or colorable claims that require investigating, because of the potential downside? But none of the uses of funds, or relationship between expenditures and revenues, makes any sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Revealing the Fraud as an Exit Strategy: Cui bono?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The craziest part of this fraud, if perpetrated as we suspect by Charles Lu and his patrons in the CCP, is that they could have made even more money by revealing it. As we said, it is likely that someone inside of Luckin leaked information to the writers of the anonymous report, and by extension to Muddy Waters. Who had motive? Sure, it might have been some midlevel manager who wanted cash. But if we look at the sequence of events, the possibility that it was actually Charles Lu and his associates becomes a more plausible explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carson Block’s firm Muddy Waters has shown how lucrative it can be to expose fraud. Why wouldn’t fraudsters themselves, then, give it a try? Did any of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/news/luckin-coffee-short-sellers-1-152036003.html&quot;&gt;$1.1 billion&lt;/a&gt; that short-sellers made on Luckin go into the pockets of Charles Lu, or members of the CCP? Moreover, there would be no risk or exposure to them, if the CCP had never had an interest in pursuing the case, because foreign banks and investors would have no recourse and no methods of enforcement. Neither the SEC nor the DOJ can investigate, and Chinese laws prevent foreigners from taking effective measures (such as taking control of the operations of the company, or seizing and selling off property and equipment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCP has played an active role in looting Western governments and companies for years. And their willingness to allow fraud has created an environment where investors are exposed to every type of fraud. We know for certain that Luckin inflated revenues. But Charles Lu also appears to have taken out a $518 million dollar loan without any intention of repaying it. He also may have used related party transactions to syphon money out of the company and encouraged friends to sell in January before the fraud was revealed. But that is just the fraud that is well substantiated by available evidence. Fraud is not carried out in plain sight: it comes to light only when something compels disclosure. The available evidence likely represents only the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can rule out that, after Luckin’s cash disappears (perhaps to buy coffee vending machines from a company allegedly owned by Charles Lu), and the firm declares bankruptcy—what can rule out that, on that day, the people involved in this scam are able to buy up again all the property, inventory, and equipment, for pennies on the dollar, and try something similar once more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Muddy Waters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could some of this conjecture be false? Yes, and Muddy Waters might have some inside information that could reinforce or dispel our thesis. But without cooperation from the CCP, some questions will never be answered. We hope that Muddy Waters would participate in any investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet one is reasonably troubled by the ethics of Muddy Waters’ short selling activism. Indeed, they are incentivized to expose fraud, which is good. But they are also incentivized to let a fraud go on for as long as possible, to allow the stock price to climb as high as possible, before pulling out the rug. Do they have some sort of moral obligation to warn investors at the first sign of trouble? Perhaps they think that any investor foolish enough to invest money in China gets what he or she deserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion of Part I&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is compelling enough evidence that Charles Zhengyao Lu and his associates, not the COO, are principally responsible for fabricating numbers and stealing an enormous amount of money from foreign investors out of Luckin Coffee. And, if that is true, then it is at least a possibility, which needs examination, that the executives were the ones who leaked details of the fraud and had it released, after they had raised additional capital so that they could short the stock. Considering the astonishing, meteoric rise of Luckin, and the amount of money in play (billions), is it possible that Charles Lu and his associates made substantial contributions to certain CCP officials every step of the way, allowing them to get off scot free?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most troubling part about this story is the implications it has for the future of permitting Chinese firms unfettered access to Western capital markets. If Chinese companies are able to loot Western investment houses, and all the people they represent, without fear of reprisal or personal responsibility, because segments of the CCP have given fraudsters free reign to steal as much money as they can get their hands on, then we will see frauds like this happen again and again. Yet institutions in the West seem impotent in the face of the CCP. We believe strongly that this fraud cannot be allowed to go uninvestigated by regulators and financial press alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; do to protect &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; money? Perhaps the next time you think you see a Chinese unicorn—you should run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About our Watchdog Transparency Blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watchdog Research is a new resource covering issues associated with the reliability of financial disclosures now available to all institutional and advisory firms. Three years in the making, it draws proprietary analyst driven data from multiple sources and provides that information in a concise, timely and interactive way In our Blog we utilize highly experienced analysts and forensic accountants to take a critical look at particular public company disclosures and focus on issues surrounding transparency, reliability, and accuracy. It you are looking for cheerleading, you have come to the wrong place. We rely on information from the best sources available to gain insight into companies and make predictions about what will happen in the future. Nothing in business is certain, so sometimes we will be wrong, but we will always be an independent voice telling you the truth as we see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send the author of this piece John Cheffers, our Director of Research and Associate General Counsel, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>John_Cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="CCP" /><category term="Luckin Coffee" /><category term="Fraud" /><summary type="html">This post is Part I in a three-part series on Luckin Coffee. The post below was completed on April 27th, 2020, as the story was still developing. Since we wrote this piece, Luckin has changed its story and admitted that its CEO was involved in the massive fraud and delayed releasing its annual report. It has also been delisted from the Nasdaq, spelling death for the company. It has also spurred action in Washington, with the Senate passing a bill that could potentially delist every Chinese company unless the Chinese Communist Party releases its iron grip on information and allows the PCAOB to inspect its audit firms.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/America%20Runs%20from%20Luckin-%20I.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/America%20Runs%20from%20Luckin-%20I.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers" /><published>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;concerns &lt;/a&gt;about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the coronavirus, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;allowed&lt;/a&gt; public companies to delay releasing their annual or quarterly reports by up to 45 days. This order initially went into effect on March 4th, after large accelerated filers (companies with more than 700 million in public float) had already submitted their annual reports. However, large accelerated filers were due to report their first quarter results on May 11th, giving these big companies a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to see how many large accelerated filers were choosing to file their 10-Qs late. Our analysis showed that as of May 19th, &lt;em&gt;only 27 U.S. based companies&lt;/em&gt; had failed to file their 10-Qs due to disruptions from the coronavirus. We arrived at this number by eliminating foreign filers (who have different reporting obligations and dates) and by eliminating companies that failed to file because they were acquired or stated their failure to file was due to internal control problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is significant that so few companies decided to file late. We decided to look deeper to see what made these companies the exceptions. We were not surprised to see Party City (PRTY) on this list. In addition to having its stores closed, long term social distancing practices could destroy their prospects for recovery; its stock has taken such a beating that it was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1592058/000119312520107068/d901922dex991.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt;. But for other companies it is less clear why they were unable to file. For example, Entercom Communications (ETM), which owns radio stations and other digital content, has only reported a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1067837/000119312520142278/d910419dex991.htm&quot;&gt;4% loss in net revenue&lt;/a&gt; for its first quarter, hardly cataclysmic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20Filers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late Filers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found that about 14 of these companies had offered their first quarter results to their investors in an earnings call and concurrent press release. We are not quite sure what to make of this. On one hand, it seems commendable that they are keeping investors appraised of what is going on, but if they can pull together an accurate earnings call, then why can’t they file their 10-Qs on time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20filers%20press%20release.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late filers press release.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interesting Specific Examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circor International (CIR)&lt;/strong&gt;. This industrial valve manufacturer failed to timely file their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000023/circorformnt10-kv10.htm&quot;&gt;10-k&lt;/a&gt; this year because of internal control issues and a cybersecurity breach.  Now they are claiming that the coronavirus is the reason for their late 10-Q. They also filed two of their quarterly reports late in 2019. This company sells manufactures valves and other products for the industrial, aerospace and defense, and energy sectors. This is probably the clearest cut case of a company making a dubious assertion that its filing delay is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000070/cir8-k42920.htm&quot;&gt;due&lt;/a&gt; to the coronavirus as opposed to preexisting internal issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MFA Financial (MFA)&lt;/strong&gt;. This Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT) provided an interesting reason why they could not &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1055160/000105516020000018/mfa-8k05062020.htm&quot;&gt;timely&lt;/a&gt; file their quarterly report, “&lt;em&gt;Company’s management has had to devote significant time and attention to address [the impact of coronavirus], which have diverted management resources from completing tasks necessary to file the Company’s Quarterly Report…&lt;/em&gt;.” The other two REITs who failed to file in a timely manner cited the need for accounting staff to work at home as a reason for the delay. In contrast, it appears MFA’s management simply did not make time to file their 10-Q because the SEC has allowed them to put it on the backburner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credit Acceptance Corp (CACC).&lt;/strong&gt; MFA was not the only company to say its management was too busy to file a 10-Q. CACC had a near identical &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000042/cacc8k20200420.htm&quot;&gt;disclosure&lt;/a&gt;, claiming management was just too busy assessing the potential impact of the coronavirus. For context, CACC specializes in offering subprime loans on vehicles, which some people find &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2019/12/12/787337997/the-big-business-of-subprime-auto-loans&quot;&gt;unsavory&lt;/a&gt;. Even though almost every other company is trying to increase and preserve liquidity to survive the shutdowns, CACC is in the process of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000036/cacc8k20200305.htm&quot;&gt;repurchasing&lt;/a&gt; up to 3 million shares, reducing their cash position. We also can’t help but point out the irony of CACC filing their 10-Q late on the flimsiest of excuses while also issuing this statement on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creditacceptance.com/coronavirus-response&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; “…Credit Acceptance is unable to support payment deferrals, and your payments will continue to be due on your scheduled monthly due date….” Considering the current predicament of many of the low-income recipients of these predatory loans, we don’t know how CACC shareholders can sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every investor wants to know if management is reliable and is dedicated to transparency. When management is opaque, it makes an investment far riskier. The best way to assess the trustworthiness of a management team is to see what kind of choices they make. The coronavirus has presented management teams with lots of choices, and we should watch them carefully as they make their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Late Filings" /><summary type="html">In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed concerns about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?" /><published>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/">&lt;p&gt;To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections.  An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/indicators/unemployment/&quot;&gt;skyrocketing &lt;/a&gt;unemployment.  To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;permitted &lt;/a&gt;companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some companies this may simply be a welcome respite during a difficult time, but we are concerned that some companies may use this as an opportunity to prevent investors from seeing just how badly things are going until it is too late. However, the SEC has also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-clayton-hinman&quot;&gt;encouraged &lt;/a&gt;companies to reveal how the shutdowns are effecting them and to speculate about how they will bounce back from the disaster. The SEC has assured companies concerned about incurring liability for these speculative statements that they will not be “second guessed by the SEC.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect the SEC has created two divergent paths for companies, some will file on time and may include extensive disclosures, but others may take the opportunity to delay reporting for as long as possible, perhaps in hope that by the time the 45 day period runs out, they will be able to report some good news (if they don’t declare bankruptcy first).  We believe that the strongest indicator for which path companies will take is their financial health before the lockdowns.  This would be consistent with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/coronavirus-uncertainties-contribute-to-going-concern-uncertainties/&quot;&gt;findings&lt;/a&gt; from Audit Analytics that the companies who initially received going concern warnings from auditors, where the coronavirus was named as a substantial factor, had already received going concern warnings before the pandemic even started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already expressed concern that some companies might use the coronavirus as a pretext to write off goodwill that was junk before the lockdowns, but we became concerned that some companies might abuse the delay allowance when we saw that Luckin Coffee was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;delaying &lt;/a&gt;its annual report due to the coronavirus.  The disclosure did not even refer to the massive fraud it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;unveiled &lt;/a&gt;less than a month earlier, or the firing of its CEO that was announced a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. large accelerated filers, companies with a public float of over $700 million, were required to file their annual statements before March 1st, so they were unable to take advantage of the ability to file late.  But smaller companies and foreign issuers with later deadlines were able to take advantage to file late if they wanted and many of them did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LateFilings%20graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;LateFilings graph.png&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/impacts-of-covid-19-on-late-filings/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most large accelerated filers are due to file their quarterly statements this week, which is giving the markets their first real insight as to the effects of the coronavirus on the world’s biggest businesses.  For example, the Kraft Heinz Company, (one of our favorite &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;subjects&lt;/a&gt;) has benefited from the shutdowns with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745920000061/khc-20200328.htm&quot;&gt;boost &lt;/a&gt;in revenue, as we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;predicted&lt;/a&gt;.  They also wrote off $226 million in goodwill, but that was apparently from consolidating their reporting into three segments instead of four and not from the coronavirus (how KHC’s figured that its new international segment is worth $226 million less than the sum of its component parts is anyone’s guess).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, Hertz filed its 10-Q in a timely fashion, but it did not have such good news to report.  The rental car industry, which has high fixed costs and relies primarily on people traveling to earn revenue has been hit hard by the shutdowns.  Hertz issued a going concern warning in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/47129/000165785320000049/hghthcq12020form10-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q&lt;/a&gt; that it cannot continue to make necessary payments without more revenue as it is burning through its cash. Currently, one of its biggest debts is in forbearance but that deal is set to end on May 22nd, and Hertz has been unable to offer any assurances that a deal will be struck.  The debtors could potentially seize their collateral, including vehicles in Hertz’s fleet, hurting the company’s ability to recover when the lockdowns end. It is good that Hertz is sharing this crucial information for investors at such a critical time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, some companies have opted to delay their filings.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920010302/fooh20200510_nt10q.htm&quot;&gt;One &lt;/a&gt;such company is HF Food Group (HFFG) which primarily serves Chinese takeout restaurants.  Although not a large accelerated filer, this company had the dubious distinction of earning a higher Gray Swan Event Factor score than any other publicly traded company as of April 8th.  Their high score was mostly attributable to two recent mergers, including one consummated in November 2019.  The company also disclosed in its 10-K, filed on March 16th, 2020, that it identified a material weakness in its internal controls.  HF was also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/hf-foods/&quot;&gt;targeted&lt;/a&gt; by a short seller and had a securities &lt;a href=&quot;http://securities.stanford.edu/filings-case.html?id=107365&quot;&gt;lawsuit &lt;/a&gt;filed against it in March, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920009194/ex_184193.htm&quot;&gt;replaced &lt;/a&gt;its CFO on May 4th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those curious about our Grey Swan Event Factor analysis, here is the analysis for HFFG:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Latefilings%20GSEF.png&quot; alt=&quot;Latefilings GSEF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is it that HFFG was able to put out a timely annual report but has needed to delay its quarterly report due to the coronavirus?  Is it possible that this delay has more to do with material weaknesses in the internal controls and turmoil at the executive level, rather than the coronavirus? To its credit (and unlike Luckin Coffee), HFFG has released some information indicating that it has been suffering an adverse impact from the shutdowns, with net sales declining from $209 million to $175.8 million year over year.  Still, investors will not really be able to assess the big picture until the quarterly results are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this mess is over, the SEC ought to study the effect of its policy.  Did the delayed filings really help companies who were suffering from the coronavirus? Or were they mostly used by companies who would have filed late anyways?  And was any real benefit to companies worth the loss of crucial information for investors at such a critical time?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC" /><category term="Late Filings" /><category term="GSEF" /><summary type="html">To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections. An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and skyrocketing unemployment. To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has permitted companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports" /><published>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/">&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discovered that China had a better score than the U.S., which was shocking, but we also found out that the SEC and PCAOB had issued an extensive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;warning &lt;/a&gt;to investors in Chinese firms.  This warning told investors that financial reporting in China is not consistent, that there is no effective oversight of firms in China, and that there is no enforcement to catch rule-breakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure all the investors who rely on our reports receive this warning, we have added a new SEC Oversight flag to our report. Here is an example for Luckin Coffee:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SEC%20Oversight%20Flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Oversight Flag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on the flag for Luckin, it will bring you to this warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Warning%20Flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Warning Flag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We aren’t picking on Chinese companies; we also issue a similar warning for countries that are known tax-havens.  If you looked closely at our summary table for country by county comparisons, you would have seen that countries classified as a tax-haven have an even lower Gray Swan Event Factor than China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/country%20comparison.ccp.taxhaven.png&quot; alt=&quot;country comparison.ccp.taxhaven.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our new flag highlights an uncomfortable fact.  Our assumptions about the overall health of an investment depends on accurate and reliable information, which is not always available. Investors need to be cautious about having companies in their portfolios that hail from countries that do not have rigorous standards promoting corporate transparency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="SEC" /><summary type="html">In our last post we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it Safer to Invest in China or the U.S.?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it Safer to Invest in China or the U.S.?" /><published>2020-05-06T16:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T16:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/">&lt;p&gt;The China based coffee company Luckin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt; a massive fraud on April 2nd, and only five days later, another China based company TAL Education, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1499620/000110465920044459/tm2015354d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales.  A decade ago, a wave of Chinese companies were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20&quot;&gt;exposed &lt;/a&gt;as frauds, which damaged China’s reputation.  The confluence of Luckin’s fraud with news that the Chinese lied about coronavirus has damaged China’s reputation once again as many people have come to believe that investing in Chinese companies is too risky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to look at some data and see if there were any major variations between Chinese companies and Western companies.  We specialize in tracking and predicting gray swan events. These are events related to the financial reporting of companies that can seriously injure the value and integrity of a company.  Our Gray Swan Event Factor represents an aggregation of these events and their impact on the value of the stock.  A higher Gray Swan Event Factor indicates more risk of an event that could damage a company’s integrity and stock price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Gray Swan Event Factor is an aggregation of many kinds of events, including mergers, restatements, securities litigation, C-suite turnover etc…, it correlates well with the overall health of a company.  We wanted to know if China (or any other country for that matter) would score any differently than the U.S. or Europe. Our PHDs ran the numbers and here were our results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20country%20comparison.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin country comparison.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can see Chinese companies have a significantly lower Gray Swan Event Factor than the United States, Europe, or Canada.  On its face, this result indicates that Chinese companies are healthier and less risky investments companies in Europe, Canada, or the U.S., which would be a stunning and counter-intuitive result.  But after looking deeper into the matter, we believe that it may mean the precise opposite and that Chinese companies are an even riskier investment than most people believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why Chinese companies have a lower GSEF is because they &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; fewer gray swan events than western countries, but that is probably because Chinese companies are subject to less scrutiny than Western companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the SEC and the PCAOB (a quasi-private entity that provides oversight for auditors) issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;joint statement&lt;/a&gt; on April 21st that specifically warned investors about investing in Chinese companies. They warn that, (1) the quality of financial statements are not consistent, (2) the quality of independent audits is uncertain because the PCAOB is unable to conduct inspections, (3) U.S. authorities cannot really enforce the rules against foreign persons and companies, and (4) there is essentially no legal recourse if you fall prey to fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our comparison of GSEF by country proves that fewer gray swan events are &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; in China than in the U.S., Canada, or the EU.  This paradoxically is strong evidence that we should take the SEC’s warning about Chinese companies seriously because they are not subject to the same level of scrutiny as Western companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="GSEF" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="Comparison by Country" /><summary type="html">The China based coffee company Luckin disclosed a massive fraud on April 2nd, and only five days later, another China based company TAL Education, announced that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales. A decade ago, a wave of Chinese companies were exposed as frauds, which damaged China’s reputation. The confluence of Luckin’s fraud with news that the Chinese lied about coronavirus has damaged China’s reputation once again as many people have come to believe that investing in Chinese companies is too risky.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_it%20it%20safer%20to%20invest%20in%20china%20or%20us.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_it%20it%20safer%20to%20invest%20in%20china%20or%20us.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">BorgWarner Wants to Dump Delphi. Will Delphi’s Resistance be Futile?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BorgWarner Wants to Dump Delphi.  Will Delphi’s Resistance be Futile?" /><published>2020-04-08T09:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-08T09:31:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/">&lt;p&gt;With the coronavirus shutting down entire industries and raising the possibility of an extended recession, pending mergers are in peril, and mergers overall will become disfavored as companies lose their appetite for risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner and Delphi &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/908255/000120677420000239/bwa3712381-ex992.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; an all-stock merger on January 28th, 2020.  The conventional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crainsdetroit.com/automotive/borgwarner-buy-delphi-stave-evs-impact&quot;&gt;wisdom &lt;/a&gt;take on this merger was that it was meant to protect to both engine auto part manufacturers from changes in the industry due to the rise of Tesla and electric vehicles.  It would appear the BorgWarner was looking to absorb Delphi so it could use the increase in volume to protect its position in the market, not because Delphi performance made it particularly desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner placed the value of Delphi at $3.3 billion, quite a premium for a company whose stock price had been on a consistent decline for years, and had a particularly rough year in 2019, with a anemic $141 million in operating income and total equity of only $450 million. Naturally, lawsuits were filed against both companies when the merger was announced, but lawsuits are always filed when a merger like this is announced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner chart.png&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Delphi’s value has been on a steady decline since the summer of 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the Deal Fell Apart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 30th, Delphi announced that it was going to draw down its entire $500 million revolving credit so that it would have the cash on hand to endure the coronavirus and the accompanying government ordered shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, BorgWarner &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.borgwarner.com/newsroom/press-releases/2020/03/31/borgwarner-issues-statement-regarding-delphi-technologies-revolver-draw-down&quot;&gt;announced &lt;/a&gt;that Delphi was in material breach of their agreement and that Delphi had 30 days to cure the breach or the merger would be scrapped.  Delphi countered that BorgWarner had unreasonably withheld consent for the withdrawal.  Both arguments have merit, so the stage is set for a nasty legal fight if the deal is not salvaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner’s ostensible reason for backing out is pretty cut and dry.  BorgWarner was not anticipating taking out new debt with its all stock deal. Delphi’s financial condition was anemic, but it was still in the black, and $500 million in potential new debt would be a hard to swallow (especially since it exceeds Delphi’s equity).  But considering that the coronavirus pandemic will be relatively short-lived—it is expected to peak in mid-April—it seems strange that BorgWarner would insist that Delphi risk running out of cash and going bankrupt to keep the deal alive, when it had access to credit that would probably see it safely through the storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead BorgWarner gave Delphi two bad options, damned if you do, and damned if you don’t.  Which leads us to believe that BorgWarner had soured on the whole idea of merging and used this credit draw down as a pretext to kill the deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mergers Traditionally a Sign of Optimism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers are widely considered a sign of optimism in the market, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/&quot;&gt;numbers &lt;/a&gt;bear that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20m&amp;amp;A%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner m&amp;amp;A chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart from the Institute of Mergers, Acquisitions and Alliances (IMAA) shows that mergers fell after the Dot-com bubble burst in 2001 and the housing bubble burst in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers fell during these prior periods of uncertainty because almost all the benefits from a merger are long term.  Our research shows that mergers generally produce negative returns for at least two years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20table-591d34.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner table-591d34.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What accounts for these terrible numbers?  Oftentimes the acquiring company must provide a large amount of cash to consummate the merger, which can leave the survivor strapped for cash or highly leveraged.  In addition, there are often personnel issues, as established norms at one or both companies are upended, and egos are bruised.  Additionally, the survivor usually inherits hidden accounting problems, and this can lead to write-offs, revisions, disclosure controls, or other gray swan events that damage the value and integrity of the company.  This is why a recent merger will significantly increase a company’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/#products&quot;&gt;gray swan event factor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positive outcomes depend on things like synergy, expanded volume, supply efficiency, and innovative technology or intellectual property (acquisitions to get new drugs in the pipeline is a feature of the pharmaceutical industry).  These benefits are generally medium to long-term benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the chart again you can see large cap companies suffer less than small or medium companies after a merger or acquisition, and that is likely due to the fact that big companies often acquire companies that are so much smaller than themselves, that it is completely irrelevant if the benefits of the merger materialize.  PayPal for example, acquired TIO networks, only to essentially &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;write off&lt;/a&gt; the entire value of the acquisition when they learned all the customer lists were compromised by a data breach, yet their share price did not suffer.  Medium and small firms simply don’t have the luxury of having a merger turn into a complete boondoggle without paying a price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We specialize in analyzing the risk of gray swan events, and the likely impact of those events on the future stock price.  A merger is one of the biggest red flags that the acquiring company can have for gray swan events.  Our research in this area affirms the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/040815/how-does-merger-affect-shareholders.asp&quot;&gt;conventional &lt;/a&gt;wisdom that generally depresses the stock price of an acquiring company because in the short-term, it is not a good bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the current market downturn, companies do not want to double down on potential losses by adding a merger to the mix.  Mergers in general are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/m-a-deals-plunge-amid-the-coronavirus-crisis-51585681640&quot;&gt;down&lt;/a&gt;.  And it appears that companies have already inked mergers are looking through the fine print for a &lt;em&gt;material adverse effect&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/coronavirus-covid-19-and-material-adverse-effect-clause&quot;&gt;clause&lt;/a&gt; to bail them out.  BorgWarner was probably thrilled when Delphi asked permission to draw down on their revolving credit, since it gave them a far more clear-cut excuse to bail on the contract than on an untested legal justification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suitors become Adversaries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delphi’s stock &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/acquisition-in-peril%3A-delphi-technologies-shares-fall-on-borgwarner-notice-2020-03-31&quot;&gt;sank &lt;/a&gt;as a result of this news.  Generally, our gray swan event factor only penalizes the acquiring company once a merger is announced, not the acquiree.  That is because generally the company that survives the deal is taking all the risk.  But in an environment like this one, conventional wisdom has been turned on its head, and companies that have been counting on a merger are the ones in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is important in an economic downturn like this is a company’s fundamentals.  Delphi is a weak company: it had anemic financial statements when the market was strong, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autonews.com/article/20181005/OEM10/181009758/delphi-ceo-steps-down-after-10-months-on-the-job&quot;&gt;problems&lt;/a&gt; at the helm to boot. Now, instead of wooing Delphi with a premium offer, BorgWarner has rejected Delphi in hopes that Delphi stumbles into bankruptcy so that they can get what they want at rock bottom prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to a new market, where fundamental analysis matters and cash is king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="BorgWarner" /><category term="Mergers" /><category term="Acquisitions" /><category term="coronavirus" /><summary type="html">With the coronavirus shutting down entire industries and raising the possibility of an extended recession, pending mergers are in peril, and mergers overall will become disfavored as companies lose their appetite for risk.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/borger.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/borger.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Birds of A Feather: How to Tell a “Gray Swan” from a “Black Swan.”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Birds of A Feather: How to Tell a “Gray Swan” from a “Black Swan.”" /><published>2020-04-01T13:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-01T13:14:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/">&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has shocked and stress tested institutions all over the world.  The emergence of the pandemic, and the global panic it has caused, is a true black swan event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gray swan event, on the other hand, is a failure in accounting or management that damages the integrity of a company and reduces its value.  At their core, these events result from a failure in transparency. These events may be infrequent, but the risk can often be anticipated and even quantified with proper due diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has caused substantial disruption, as cash shortages cause default and bankruptcy, and it is inevitable that many companies will need to file legitimate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfo.com/accounting/2020/02/coronavirus-five-things-finance-needs-to-think-about-before-closing-the-books/&quot;&gt;impairments&lt;/a&gt;.   But we suspect some companies will try to use this crisis and see an opportunity to dump billions in worthless goodwill and other assets without it creating the usual bad press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kraft Heinz’s Swan Song&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like to ascribe their failures to black swan events because it absolves them of responsibility for their failures.  We have seen this before in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;look&lt;/a&gt; at Kraft Heinz (KHC).  They issued a surprise $15 billion &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;impairment&lt;/a&gt;, which shocked the markets and sent the company into a tailspin.  KHC claimed that this impairment was due multiple factors in one bad quarter (as if it were their own personal black swan), but a closer look shows that it was more like they ran out of fingers to stick in a leaky dam. Collapse was inevitable and probably a long time coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The $15 billion that set off KHC’s awful year was not enough, and 2019 saw a steady drip of bad news.  When we wrote our original piece on KHC (linked above), they had already filed over $1.2 billion in new impairments for 2019, and we predicted more.  Indeed, shortly after our prediction, they issued another $676 million impairment for the final quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could KHC be in danger of further impairments, even if the economy had remained strong? Consider that intangible assets and goodwill still forms over $84 billion of the KHC’s $101 billion in assets.  And, the company continues to carry over $28 billion in long-term debt.  Today, the net assets of the company stand at $51 billion, but the market cap is $30 billion, that implies an overvaluation of $20 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if KHC writes off another huge chunk in assets and blame it on the coronavirus, will you believe them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expect many companies will blame the “black swan” for accounting issues this quarter, but how can you be sure it was coronavirus and not due to problems in their accounting?  How do you tell a black swan disclosure from a gray swan one?  Do the hard homework or leave it to the experts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/#products&quot;&gt;like us!&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how we think of sniffing-out a company’s own gray swan event from disclosures amid a black swan event.  We’ll use potential impairments to goodwill and other intangible assets as a case in point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;M&amp;amp;As and Balance Sheets Bloated with Goodwill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/#m-and-a-history&quot;&gt;surge&lt;/a&gt; in M&amp;amp;As over the past decade has resulted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/04/business/shrinking-stock-market.html&quot;&gt;fewer&lt;/a&gt; registered companies and more goodwill on balance sheets. Whenever companies have a merger or acquisition, the tangible and intangible assets are accounted for, and amounts paid over the value of those assets is recorded as “goodwill” on the balance sheet.  We see trouble here.  Mergers have been relatively high, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/goodwill-and-intangible-asset-impairments-in-sp-500/&quot;&gt;fewer&lt;/a&gt; companies have been recording impairments to their goodwill recorded during the merger.  Either everyone is a genius when they close their M&amp;amp;A deal, or they are trying to avoid owning up to overstating assets.   We might see impairments happen aggressively during the coronavirus black swan event, but those simply might mask bad M&amp;amp;A deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, another factor possibly inflating the amount of goodwill is FASB’s new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cpajournal.com/2018/09/26/the-new-guidance-for-goodwill-impairment/&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; for (ASU 17-04) which took effect for every public company this year—although some companies had already implemented it.  This accounting standard is simpler that the previous one, but it also allows companies to keep a balance sheet bloated with unknown liabilities.  Take &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt;, which wrote off virtually all the assets it acquired from its acquisition of TIO Networks because of a data breach that made TIO’s assets worthless.  PayPal suspended operations at TIO and impaired the assets it gained in the acquisition—except for the $170 million in goodwill—that money is still &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/paypal-the-importance-of-intangible-asset-impairments/&quot;&gt;lingering&lt;/a&gt; around on the books.  How is it appropriate to buy a company, find out it’s essentially worthless and write down all its real assets, but then retain the goodwill anyways?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most logical reason that so much goodwill is being held on company books is because the market was on the longest bull run in history.  A healthy market increased the market value of companies, which prevented their book values from looking inflated, even when loaded up with goodwill or other intangible assets.  Now there is a pandemic. The market at one point lost a third of its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FASB &lt;a href=&quot;https://asc.fasb.org/imageRoot/79/49129379.pdf&quot;&gt;accounting standards&lt;/a&gt; require that companies test goodwill annually, but they also require a special test if an event triggers a concern that the market value of the company is lower than the book value.  Well … it seems like &lt;em&gt;every company&lt;/em&gt; is going to need a special test because of the pandemic.  We can expect many companies will write down goodwill and other assets after those tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Newest Data on CAMs Indicate Goodwill Accounting is Particularly Squishy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason we are focusing on goodwill is because management’s accounting for it is inherently squishy.  We know this because that is what the auditors tell us.  Auditors are now required to report on Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), accounting areas that are particularly difficult to verify because they rely on subjective judgement of the management team.  Even though the CAMs research is brand new, it has revealed that &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/an-updated-overview-of-cams/&quot;&gt;accounting &lt;/a&gt;for goodwill (and other intangible assets) raises more consternation than any other area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of our company Watchdog Research reports includes a CAM section, with links from viewing our report on our website to the SEC filing showing that CAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Damage Control is Often a Practice in Deception&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjective nature of evaluating goodwill means that the area is ripe for obfuscation and potential abuse.  Companies in decline may delay writing off goodwill and other intangible assets for as long as possible, to look strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already filled you in on KHC, but a disingenuous impairment by KHC might be easy to spot especially since panicked buying at grocery stores and the closure of dine-in restaurants should boost their sales.  Other companies may try equally disingenuous impairments, but they might not be so easy to spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Under Armour (UA) for example.  They declined to report any impairments to goodwill in their latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm&quot;&gt;annual report&lt;/a&gt;, even though their Latin American segment has been struggling. According to UA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fair value of each reporting unit substantially exceeded its carrying value, with the exception of our Latin America reporting unit. The fair value of the Latin America reporting unit exceeded its carrying value by 19%. Holding all other assumptions used in the fair value measurement of the Latin America reporting unit constant, a reduction in the growth rate of revenue by 2.25 percentage points or a reduction in the growth rate of net income by 3.5 percentage points would eliminate the headroom. No events occurred during the period ended December 31, 2019 that indicated it was more likely than not that goodwill was impaired.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here UA seems like they are trying to impress us with the precision of their measurements and soundness of their methods, but our experience tells us that these numbers are more showmanship than science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t persuaded by our opinion, then perhaps you should look at PWC’s critical audit matters in their independent report on UA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The principal considerations for our determination that performing procedures relating to the goodwill impairment assessment of the Latin America reporting unit is a critical audit matter are there was significant judgment by management when developing the fair value measurement of the reporting unit, &lt;strong&gt;which in turn led to a high degree of auditor judgment, effort, and subjectivity&lt;/strong&gt; in performing procedures and evaluating significant assumptions, including the Company’s long-term rate of growth and profitability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if UA writes down the goodwill associated with its Latin American unit, will it be due to coronavirus or because they should have done it already?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="impairment" /><category term="goodwill" /><category term="Kraft Heinz" /><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="coronavirus" /><category term="transparency" /><category term="black swan event" /><category term="gray swan event" /><summary type="html">The coronavirus has shocked and stress tested institutions all over the world. The emergence of the pandemic, and the global panic it has caused, is a true black swan event.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/black-swan-122983_640.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/black-swan-122983_640.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>