<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-29T13:37:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Impact of Restatements: The Bigger They Are…</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Impact of Restatements: The Bigger They Are…" /><published>2020-10-29T13:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-29T13:18:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot/">&lt;p&gt;There is nothing worse as an investor than when a company experiences a gray swan event like a financial restatement. Investors are rarely prepared for the bad news and have difficulty placing it into context; it is no wonder that for many investors the initial reaction to a financial restatement is a panicked sell-off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information is the antidote to panic, so we have looked at the data for restatements and other gray swan events to arm investors with as much information as possible &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; something bad happens. We produce reports on certain kinds of events, like restatements, that take a survey of the field and measure their impact on share price. Investors can also look at our company specific reports and our Gray Swan Event Factor to get a more granular view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we are analyzing the relative impact of restatements when segmenting the market by size. We have found that the impact of a restatement is proportional to the relative size of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog touches on a few data points from an extensive report produced by two of our researchers, Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD. If you want access to the full report, email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The analysis for this report was primarily derived from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt; restatement database.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our research, we broke the market down into three segments, Large cap, Mid cap, and Small cap. In our analysis, Large companies have more $10 billion in market capitalization, Small cap firms have less than $2 billion, and Mid cap companies fall between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at how many restatements occurred for each segment over the past ten years and calculated the likelihood of incurring a restatement for each segment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table shows the financial restatements by size from 2010-2019. One thing to note is just how exceptionally rare it is for a large cap company to issue a restatement. A Mid cap company is more than twice as likely as Large cap company to issue a restatement. And Small cap companies are almost seven times more likely to issue a restatement than a Large cap company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Size Proportional to Impact&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team also measured the impact of these restatements on share value. Our team calculated the impact by looking at how the stock performed in comparison with the S&amp;amp;P 500 over the next 30 days. Share price data was not available for every company which had a restatement, but we were able to get share prices for an adequately representative sample.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of our analysis shows that the impact of a restatement is proportional to the size of the company. Restatements have a large impact on big companies, but a smaller impact on smaller companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%20abnormal%20returns.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements abnormal returns.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table shows abnormal returns by size from 2008 to 2020 year-to-date. What explains this disparity? One factor may be the relative lack of attention and scrutiny on small cap companies. Restatements for big companies are an unusual event, so when a large cap company has one, the market experiences a strongly negative reaction to the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, large cap companies are also far more likely to be subject to a securities class action suit after a restatement, which can amplify the negative cycle and downward pressure on share value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our research, restatements have fallen steadily over the past decade. Restatements for Large cap companies are exceptionally rare, but when they do occur, they can be extremely harmful. But the same does not hold true for Mid cap and Small cap companies Our research indicates that the impact of a restatement is often proportional to the size of a company, so if a Small cap company issues a restatement, it may end up being small potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Independent Research" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Financial Restatements" /><summary type="html">There is nothing worse as an investor than when a company experiences a gray swan event like a financial restatement. Investors are rarely prepared for the bad news and have difficulty placing it into context; it is no wonder that for many investors the initial reaction to a financial restatement is a panicked sell-off.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size%20pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size%20pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Restatements Are Rare, But Can Pack a Punch</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Restatements Are Rare, But Can Pack a Punch" /><published>2020-10-23T15:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T15:35:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch/">&lt;p&gt;Public companies are required to keep investors and the public well informed concerning their financial condition. People rely on this information and expect it to be accurate. Accordingly, a company must file a restatement if it determines that its previous financial disclosures were inaccurate, and that people should not rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog touches on a few data points from an extensive report produced by two of our researchers, Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD. If you want access to the full report, email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The analysis for this report was primarily derived from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt; restatement database.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note is that restatements have declined significantly over the past ten years, although the rate of decline has slowed significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatement%20Probability.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatement Probability.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows the annual share of companies filing one or more financial restatements from 2010 to 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decline should bring a great deal of comfort to many companies since restatements are one of the most harmful gray swan events that we track. Restatements are often the opening salvo in a torrent of bad press. A restatement often occurs because of a substantial material weakness in the internal controls and often can precipitate turnover in the management team, particularly at the CFO position. Additionally, restatements often trigger class action securities lawsuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis compared the returns over the thirty days following a restatement to the returns from the S&amp;amp;P 500 over the same timeframe.   The data shows that the typical reaction of the market to a restatement is negative (approximately 2/3 of restatements resulted in negative returns). The most common result is negative returns from zero to 10%, but a significant portion (approximately 15%) had a negative return of 20% or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%20Histogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements Histogram.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph groups companies by how their share prices performed in comparison with the S&amp;amp;P 500 in the 30 days after a restatement was reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis indicates that for many companies, issuing a restatement is a trying—but manageable—event. However, in a significant minority of cases, the losses can be catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Notable Cases from 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the percentage of companies impacted by a restatement in 2019 was relatively low, some of the restatements that did occur had a near record-breaking impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pareteum Corp (TEUM)&lt;/strong&gt; had a restatement in October, 2019, and lost 69.6% of its value over the next 30 days ($119 in market cap). TEUM’s decline in value (as a percentage of its pre-restatement value) over the thirty days following its restatement was more than any other company in the last ten years. TEUM was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1084384/000110465920115313/tm2033276d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt; in October 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kraft Heinz (KHC)&lt;/strong&gt; had a restatement in February 2019 that erased $12.7 billion in market cap after its restatement on February 9th, 2019. This loss in vale was the second largest in the last ten years. If you want to know more, you can read some of our analysis on KHC &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baxter International Inc (BAX)&lt;/strong&gt; had a restatement in October 2019 that erased $4.39 billion in market cap over the next thirty days. Even though BAX lost significantly less money than KHC, it was still the third largest loss of value in the last ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restatements today are far less common than they were a decade ago, although the rate of decline has slowed in recent years. Our research also shows that 2/3 of restatements have a negative impact on share price. Although the response to a restatement is generally negative, people may be surprised by the fact that 1/3 of restatements had &lt;em&gt;no negative impact&lt;/em&gt; on the share price after 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though restatements are not as common as they used to be, a restatement can still be a catastrophic gray swan event, as is evident from the negative impact that they had on TEUM, KHC, and BAX in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These restatement numbers are just one facet of our Gray Swan Event Factor. With our GSEF we calculate the risk of gray swan events for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. If you would like a demo, email our President Brian Lawe via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Independent Research" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Financial Restatements" /><summary type="html">Public companies are required to keep investors and the public well informed concerning their financial condition. People rely on this information and expect it to be accurate. Accordingly, a company must file a restatement if it determines that its previous financial disclosures were inaccurate, and that people should not rely on them.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Punch%20Pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Punch%20Pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Marcum in the Middle: China, the U.S., and the PCAOB</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marcum in the Middle: China, the U.S., and the PCAOB" /><published>2020-10-20T16:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-20T16:32:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We reached out to Marcum LLP, Marcum BP, and the PCAOB for comment concerning this article and did not receive any responses.  We will keep you apprised of any responses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/signup/&quot;&gt;Sign up&lt;/a&gt; to get our blogs sent directly to your inbox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 24, 2020, the PCAOB released a settled disciplinary order against Marcum LLP for a matter dating back to November 2016, when Marcum issued a single unqualified opinion for the 2013, 2014, and 2015 financial statements of a company incorporated in Delaware, but headquartered and operating primarily located in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The essence of the story is that Marcum’s engagement team, as the signing firm for an audit where its affiliate, Marcum BP, was performing the work on the ground, inappropriately acquiesced to management and should not have offered an unqualified opinion of their financial statements. The disciplinary &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Enforcement/Decisions/Documents/105-2020-012-MARCUM-LLP.pdf&quot;&gt;order&lt;/a&gt; contains all the interesting details and we encourage you to read it for yourself. But the most interesting thing about this PCAOB report is not what it found, &lt;em&gt;but that it exists at all&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tensions between China and the U.S. over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;accounting profession&lt;/a&gt; have been mounting for a decade. After Enron collapsed in 2001, legislative reform—the Sarbanes-Oxley law passed in 2002—created the PCAOB to provide independent oversight of the auditing firms via routine inspections. The law required every company listed on a U.S. exchange to be audited by an auditing firm that was registered with the PCAOB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According the SEC, the PCAOB, and the Big 4, the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) has simply refused to allow PCAOB inspectors to inspect Chinese audit work papers, declaring them “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-vital-role-audit-quality-and-regulatory-access-audit-and-other&quot;&gt;state secrets&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCP has taken other measures to cement control over its accounting profession. They ordered the Big 4 to hand over control of Chinese affiliates to Chinese nationals. In early 2020, they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/u-s-moves-to-audit-chinese-firms-market-frets-over-what-comes-next-11590485401&quot;&gt;outlawed&lt;/a&gt; cooperation with overseas regulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these restrictions, or perhaps because of them, the share of audit opinions issued out Beijing has doubled in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dispute over the auditing profession belies a fantasy that the differences between China and the U.S. are merely accidental and not substantive— a fantasy held by a class of people hoping to benefit from China’s growth potential and foisted on everyone else through the normal institutional channels. However, the dispute over the PCAOB’s access to Chinese auditors shows that China and the U.S. are in separate worlds, playing by different sets of rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum in the Middle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big 4’s response to the inconsistent directives of the U.S. and the CCP has been to bifurcate their firms and put a ring fence around their affiliates in China. Although the U.S. affiliates and the Chinese affiliates share the same global brands, they do much more than socially distance. Our research indicates that every Chinese client of a Big 4 firm has been audited by a local Chinese affiliate since 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the safe way for auditing firms to do business in China. But the downside is that the CCP’s grip on information and refusal to allow PCAOB inspections makes everything that happens in China opaque. We cannot be sure of the quality of audits, or the integrity of financial reporting, and we have no idea if the CCP has been inappropriately pressuring auditors to give some companies an easy time. That is possible given how many state-owned enterprises there are in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read our previous &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk/&quot;&gt;piece &lt;/a&gt;on Marcum BP [Marcum BP is a separate entity from Marcum LLP, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accountingtoday.com/news/pcaob-sanctions-marcum-from-doing-china-audits?utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_content=socialflow&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=accountingtoday-tw&quot;&gt;formed&lt;/a&gt; by a partnership between Marcum LLP and Bernstein &amp;amp; Pinchuk in 2010 and focuses primarily on serving Chinese clients], then you know that Marcum LLP and Marcum BP do not operate in the same way as the Big 4. Marcum LLP and Marcum BP are U.S. firms that provide audits for Chinese companies. Both Marcum firms, and a few other small firms, attempt to navigate the incoherent landscape created by the contradictory directives of China and the U.S. These firms have broken with conventional wisdom and exist in this strange place between the U.S. and China, and it’s not clear which rules apply in this no man’s land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCAOB settled disciplinary order against Marcum LLP points to its inspection of the audit of a company headquartered and operating primarily in China. That is inexplicable considering how everyone says that its impossible for the PCAOB to do that. According to the SEC and the Big 4, this inspection should not have been possible because the work papers are considered “state secrets” by the CCP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, here is a settled disciplinary order based on an inspection of the work papers of an audit of the Chinese operations of a company. It is not clear how this is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to our confusion, a Chinese newspaper has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2020-08/09/c_139275803.htm&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that China’s regulator claims it “&lt;em&gt;has never prohibited or prevented relevant accounting firms from offering audit work papers to overseas regulators&lt;/em&gt;.” That claim is inconsistent with the new law banning cooperation with foreign regulators and how the Chinese affiliates of the Big 4, the SEC, and the PCAOB have characterized the issue over the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what gives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t know the answer to this question, but we suspect that it may have something to do with the fact that both Marcum LLP and Marcum BP are U.S. firms, and not Chinese. The relatively small footprint of Marcum LLP and Marcum BP in China may also contribute to an inconsistent application of the “state secrets” rule.  The CCP is an authoritarian regime; accordingly, there is no reason to believe that the CCP would feel bound to follow the “rule of law” and enforce rules consistently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum Alone in the Spotlight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is inexplicable how Marcum LLP was subject to inspection by the PCAOB, while none of the Big 4 affiliates in China are subject to the same scrutiny. We hypothesized that the state of incorporation was relevant, since the issuer inspected was incorporated in Delaware, but the data did not bear that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Marcum%20China%20incorporation%20location.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marcum China incorporation location.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pie chart is a representation of where Chinese companies listed on the NYSE and Nasdaq are incorporated. Most Chinese companies on the Nasdaq and NYSE are incorporated in tax havens, connected to their Chinese operations through VIEs. A significant portion of Chinese companies were incorporated in U.S. Only a relatively small portion of Chinese companies are incorporated in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we are not sure how it happened. However, it seems that Marcum LLP is the only firm with Chinese clients that has received scrutiny from the PCAOB. The PCAOB’s report on Marcum is certainly embarrassing and upsetting for a reputable firm with a lot of pride. Marcum has been barred from signing audits for Chinese companies for three years. But, given the context, it really should raise concerns about audit quality across China. The Marcum partners made this error even though they knew their work would be subject to meaningful review by the PCAOB; is there any good reason to believe that the audit partners at the Big 4 affiliates are holding themselves to a higher standard when they know the PCAOB cannot review their work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that makes this story so complex is that, on one hand, we would like to applaud Marcum’s relative transparency in comparison to the opaque Big 4 affiliates. But, on the other hand, they are rightfully taking their lumps over the lack of audit quality in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PCAOB Sanctions Will Not Have Much Impact on Marcum LLP&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most attention-grabbing part of the PCAOB’s settled disciplinary order was the three-year ban on issuing audit reports for clients with substantially all their operations in China. But since Marcum LLP partnered up with Bernstein and Pinchuk in 2010, work in China has not been a significant part of their business in recent years. Our research indicates that Marcum LLP only had 8 clients in China in 2019. (Marcum BP has more, but they were not affected by these sanctions.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Marcum%20clients%20in%20China.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marcum clients in China.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent increase is due to the proliferation of “blank check” companies, aka special purpose acquisition companies (SPACs); Marcum LLP specializes in SPACs. In 2019, four of Marcum LLP’s Chinese clients were blank check acquisition companies. Since SPACs do not really have operations, it is unclear if the PCAOB’s ruling will affect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One critical point is that the PCAOB’s order does not appear to have any impact on Marcum BP, since they were only referred to as a related party and not a respondent in this matter. In contrast, Marcum LLP and Marcum BP were both subject to a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/News/Releases/Pages/PCAOB-Sanctions-Two-Firms-and-One-Individual-for-Auditor-Independence-Violations.aspx&quot;&gt;disciplinary order&lt;/a&gt; from the PCAOB related to auditor independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unclear if this settled disciplinary order has concluded this matter, or if the PCAOB will address Marcum BP separately for its role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum LLP has an infinitesimal portion of the Chinese audit market in comparison to the Big 4, but their approach to navigating the contradictory directives of the U.S. and China provides more transparency and accountability than is available from the Big 4 affiliates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another complicating factor is Marcum LLP and Marcum BP’s willingness to take on risky clients. In this case, Marcum LLP took over for another auditor which had resigned nearly a year earlier because of differences with the management team. Recently, Marcum BP took over the audit for Luckin Coffee from Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP after a massive fraud was exposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That transparency, and willingness to take on messy situations from riskier clients has come at a cost for Marcum LLP, but it has provided an invaluable insight to those interested in audit quality in China. This report demonstrates how valuable PCAOB inspections could be for improving audit quality and accountability for management in China. Hopefully, the CCP and the U.S. will reach an agreement to bring the same level of transparency to all accounting firms in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="China" /><category term="Marcum LLP" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="China" /><summary type="html">We reached out to Marcum LLP, Marcum BP, and the PCAOB for comment concerning this article and did not receive any responses. We will keep you apprised of any responses.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Marcum%20LLP%20China%20Image.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Marcum%20LLP%20China%20Image.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SEC Comment Letters Shed More Light on Reverse Factoring</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-shed-more-light-on-reverse-factoring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEC Comment Letters Shed More Light on Reverse Factoring" /><published>2020-09-24T13:50:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-24T13:50:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-shed-more-light-on-reverse-factoring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-shed-more-light-on-reverse-factoring/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is published with permission of Olga Usvyatsky, a former VP of Research at Audit Analytics. She has a distinguished library of blogs and op-eds on accounting, buy-side research, and data analysis. Ms. Usvyatsky is currently enrolled as a PhD in Accounting student at Boston College, where she earned her MS in Accounting degree.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We welcome guest posts on interesting topics. Please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; if you would like to have us feature your work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in January &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/&quot;&gt;we discussed challenges&lt;/a&gt; involved when the risks of reverse factoring agreements are introduced. In 2020 the SEC issued comment letters to at least four companies, namely Procter &amp;amp; Gamble (PG), Graphic Packaging Holding (GPK), Boeing (BA) and Coca-Cola (CO) asking for more details about their reverse factoring agreements. This was after the SEC sent supply chain financing comment letters to Keurig Dr Pepper (KDP) and Masco (MAS) in 2019. In this blog, we would like to look at supply chain financing disclosures following the SEC reviews and discuss some of the language in the comment letters and disclosures that we find interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s provide a quick recap. Reverse factoring agreements document the terms when a company helps a supplier sell the company’s accounts receivable in exchange for better credit terms. The supplier pays a fee to sell the receivables, and if the fee is small enough, the trade is a winner for all parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/12927/000001292720000065/a202006jun3010-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q filing&lt;/a&gt; for the period June 30, 2020, Boeing’s trade payables included $4.4 billion payable to suppliers that participated in supply chain financing programs (SCF). Proctor &amp;amp; Gamble’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/80424/000008042420000053/pg-20200630.htm&quot;&gt;annual report&lt;/a&gt; disclosed that, as of June 30, 2020, the amounts due to suppliers that participated in SCF programs were about $4 billion. And Coca-Cola noted in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/21344/000002134420000041/ko-20200626.htm&quot;&gt;quarterly report&lt;/a&gt; that, as of June 30, 2020, suppliers elected to sell $714 million of the outstanding payment obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/sec-asks-boeing-coca-cola-to-disclose-more-about-popular-financing-tool-11598526651&quot;&gt;WSJ article&lt;/a&gt; used fees generated by banks that participated in reverse factoring agreements to estimate the size of the supply-chain financing sector. According to the article, the fees in the first half of 2020 were $12.7 billion, up 3.6% from the previous year. To develop a complete estimate of the size of the supply-chain financing receivables sold we would also need to know the average fees charged by the banks (the fee for each company would, of course, be different and depend on the credit risk of the receivables).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens if a major shock changes the credit environment and the sources of short-term liquidity suddenly dry up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major challenges with understanding the risk involved in supply chain financing are lack of disclosure, diversity in practice, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://fasb.org/cs/BlobServer?blobkey=id&amp;amp;blobnocache=true&amp;amp;blobwhere=1175836059659&amp;amp;blobheader=application%2Fpdf&amp;amp;blobheadername2=Content-Length&amp;amp;blobheadername1=Content-Disposition&amp;amp;blobheadervalue2=667317&amp;amp;blobheadervalue1=filename%3DAR-2019.UNS.020.BIG_4_ACCOUNTING_FIRMS.pdf&amp;amp;blobcol=urldata&amp;amp;blobtable=MungoBlobs&quot;&gt;lack of regulatory guidance&lt;/a&gt; (we talked about that in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/&quot;&gt;previous blog&lt;/a&gt;). In June 2020 the SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/corpfin/covid-19-disclosure-considerations&quot;&gt;issued an update&lt;/a&gt; on what companies are expected to disclose to address pandemic-related liquidity concerns. Notably, supply chain financing was explicitly referenced in this update:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Are you relying on supplier finance programs, otherwise referred to as supply chain financing, structured trade payables, reverse factoring, or vendor financing, to manage your cash flow? Have these arrangements had a material impact on your balance sheet, statement of cash flows, or short- and long-term liquidity and if so, how? What are the material terms of the arrangements? Did you or any of your subsidiaries provide guarantees related to these programs? Do you face a material risk if a party to the arrangement terminates it? What amounts payable at the end of the period relate to these arrangements, and what portion of these amounts has an intermediary already settled for you?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the SEC comment letters process is to increase the transparency of financial reporting. For the most part, the SEC’s supply chain financing comments requested that the companies provide additional disclosures about the terms and materiality of the supply chain financing programs and their impact on liquidity and cash from operations. A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://jimhamiltonblog.blogspot.com/2020/09/is-supply-chain-financing-disclosure.html&quot;&gt;Jim Hamilton’s blog&lt;/a&gt; (that we found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecorporatecounsel.net/blog/&quot;&gt;TheCorporateCounsel&lt;/a&gt;) described in great detail the nature of the supply chain comments issued so far, so we will skip the general discussion and look at language that sets the letters apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/21344/000002134420000027/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;opening letter&lt;/a&gt; for Coca Cola is provides an example of interesting language on the subject:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We note from your disclosures that accounts payable increased roughly $1.1 billion in 2019 due to the extension of payment terms with your suppliers. &lt;strong&gt;We further note from external sources that it appears you have in place a supply chain finance program&lt;/strong&gt;.” (emphasis added)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not uncommon for the SEC, as part of the comment letter process to review earnings calls, press releases, or media articles. A search of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/products/sec/comment-letter-threads&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics’&lt;/a&gt; comment letter database identified more than 800 companies which received a comment letter that was at least partially based on information disclosed during an earnings call. Yet, to the best of our knowledge, references to an “external source” are very rare. Disclosures about supply chain financing are limited, so it is not surprising that the SEC had to use a third-party source to confirm the existence of the agreements. It would be interesting to know if these external sources named other companies and whether more comment letters are coming. (We will keep monitoring the comment letter disclosures).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we would like to add a note about Boeing’s supply chain financing letters and relevant disclosures. A common theme among the supply chain financing comment letter responses was the lack of materiality of the supply chain financing on overall liquidity. Boeing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/12927/000001292720000056/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt; in its response that the company does not consider supply chain financing programs to be material to the overall liquidity. The company pointed out that they had decided to provide additional disclosure because of the significant negative liquidity impact that the company has experienced. The disclosure below is from the 10-Q filing for the period June 30, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Payables to suppliers who elected to participate in supply chain financing programs declined by $1.3 billion for the six months ended June 30, 2020 and increased by $1.8 billion for the same period in the prior year. Supply chain financing is not material to our overall liquidity. The decline for the six months ended June 30, 2020 was primarily due to reductions in commercial purchases from suppliers and not due to any changes in the availability of supply chain financing. The increase for the six months ended June 30, 2019 reflects a combination of higher purchases, an extension of payment terms with certain suppliers and increased utilization of our supply chain financing programs.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boeing included additional disclosures in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/12927/000001292720000065/a202006jun3010-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q filing&lt;/a&gt;, noting that while the access to supply chain financing can suffer if the company’s credit rating is downgraded, the company does not expect that the changes in availability of supply chain financing to have a material effect on liquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the disclosure we have seen so far, companies tend to record supply chain financing in current liabilities, so extended payment terms following the supply chain programs may result in higher days payable. (For illustrative purposes, P&amp;amp;G &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/80424/000008042419000060/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt; that the company’s days payable increased 8 days as of the June 30, 2019.) The challenge, of course, is to understand whether the increase in accounts payable was part of the supply chain financing, a general change in the account payable’s terms, or just an attempt to delay payments and preserve liquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, receiving a comment letter does not imply that there is anything wrong with a company’s disclosures. The goal of a comment letter is to provide more information to investors, and we have seen increased disclosures of supply chain financing programs following the comment letter review process. For the companies that do not provide any supply chain financing disclosures (as we discussed above, a company may consider the program to be immaterial), investors can get a small hint by looking at the trends in accounts payable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Watchdog Blog Team contacted Coca-Cola, P&amp;amp;G, and Boeing concerning this article. Boeing and Coca-Cola declined to comment, and P&amp;amp;G did not respond to our request for comment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact  our content manager, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about our company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We offer easy-to-use reports on individual public companies, if you would like to demo our products, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>olga_usvyatsky</name></author><category term="Guest Blog" /><category term="featured" /><category term="reverse factoring" /><category term="Supply Chain Financing" /><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><summary type="html">This post is published with permission of Olga Usvyatsky, a former VP of Research at Audit Analytics. She has a distinguished library of blogs and op-eds on accounting, buy-side research, and data analysis. Ms. Usvyatsky is currently enrolled as a PhD in Accounting student at Boston College, where she earned her MS in Accounting degree.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Paperwork.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Paperwork.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybersecurity Litigation Review</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cybersecurity-litigation-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybersecurity Litigation Review" /><published>2020-09-22T10:37:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T10:37:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cybersecurity-litigation-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cybersecurity-litigation-review/">&lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity has gone from a niche concern to a hot topic in the D&amp;amp;O insurance world. Tomorrow, on September 23rd, we will be attending (remotely of course)  a webinar hosted by PLUS on how companies can strategically handle cybersecurity concerns. We are an independent research provider that uses an extensive database of public information to create easy-to-use reports for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. Since we track cybersecurity incidents and all material litigation for public companies, we thought we could use this as an opportunity to provide a little color to the important discussions concerning cybersecurity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overview&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began by looking at incidents that occurred at companies listed on the NYSE and Nasdaq over the past ten years, and the growth rate of cybersecurity incidents is alarming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Cyber%20Incidents.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cyber Incidents.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*The graphs and tables in this post were created by Joseph Burke, PhD, and derived the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt; database.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, only .1 % of companies reported a cybersecurity incident. In 2019, 2.2% of companies reported a cybersecurity incident. The growth of cybersecurity incidents over the past five years has been incredible and it is not clear when it will slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting facet is that the risk of a cybersecurity incident is much higher at a large company that it would be at a small company. Attacks on large companies are driving much of the growth in these numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Cyber%20Incident%20Table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cyber Incident Table.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cybersecurity Security Class Actions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cyberbreach at a company creates all sorts of problems, including litigation. We identified all the security class action suits that were brought over cybersecurity issues and calculated the likelihood of being named in one of those suits. Unsurprisingly, the last ten years has shown significant growth in the risk of being named in a cybersecurity related lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Cyber-lawsuit%20prob.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cyber-lawsuit prob.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that these percentages are for all companies. Large cap companies have a significantly higher probability than is represented in the graph because they are both more likely to be the victim of a cybersecurity incident and are generally more likely to have a securities class action suit filed against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cybersecurity as a Leading and Covariate Indicator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of our researchers, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;research paper&lt;/a&gt; calculating when particular flags from our reports were associated with an increased risk of securities class action litigation for 2014-2018. Companies with a cybersecurity incident were almost three times as likely to get named in a securities class action lawsuit the year that the incident occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, cybersecurity incidents were one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/&quot;&gt;six leading indicators&lt;/a&gt; of securities class action suits. An event is considered a leading indicator of litigation if the occurrence of that event is associated with an increased risk of litigation for the &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chance of being involved in a cybersecurity securities class action lawsuit is still relatively low, but it is increasing rapidly. Additionally, the risk profile is far higher for large companies, which are more likely to be a victim of a cybersecurity incident and more likely to get named in a securities class action lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If company boards wish to prevent having their company victimized twice (by hackers and by lawyers), then they need to make wise and strategic decisions to confront this growing threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company has access to a proprietary database that includes all material litigation, classified by issue, for public companies. If you are interested in some bespoke research on litigation trends, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Cybersecurity" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Cybersecurity" /><category term="Litigaiton" /><summary type="html">Cybersecurity has gone from a niche concern to a hot topic in the D&amp;amp;O insurance world. Tomorrow, on September 23rd, we will be attending (remotely of course) a webinar hosted by PLUS on how companies can strategically handle cybersecurity concerns. We are an independent research provider that uses an extensive database of public information to create easy-to-use reports for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. Since we track cybersecurity incidents and all material litigation for public companies, we thought we could use this as an opportunity to provide a little color to the important discussions concerning cybersecurity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Cybersecurity.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Cybersecurity.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Impact of Cyan: Comparing the Market Today to the Pharmaceuticals of Yesteryear</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/impact-of-cyan-comparing-the-market-today-to-the-pharmaceuticals-of-yesteryear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impact of Cyan: Comparing the Market Today to the Pharmaceuticals of Yesteryear" /><published>2020-09-10T11:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-10T11:51:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/impact-of-cyan-comparing-the-market-today-to-the-pharmaceuticals-of-yesteryear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/impact-of-cyan-comparing-the-market-today-to-the-pharmaceuticals-of-yesteryear/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/&quot;&gt;Watchdog Research&lt;/a&gt; provides an easy-to-use report for over 4,500 public companies based on 29 different categories of public disclosures. Our extensive database enables us to study larger trends affecting publicly traded companies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court’s decision in &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; in 2018 was a big victory to plaintiff’s law firms because it opened the doors of the state courts to federal claims under the Securities Act of 1933. These state law cases had already been permitted in some jurisdictions, but &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; threw the doors open all over the country, with predictable results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last three years, the percentage of companies named in a securities class action suit have been extremely high, hovering around 8%. This has been a great development for plaintiff’s attorneys, but a major problem for corporations and the insurers who provide D&amp;amp;O Insurance to cover the costs of these suits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how disruptive this change has been, we compared the current level of litigation with the amount of litigation associated with what is considered the riskiest class of companies—pharmaceuticals. Our research indicates that over the last 10 years, that on average 7.45% of pharmaceutical companies have been named as defendants in securities class actions annually. If you were to compare the rates of security class action suits year over year between pharmaceuticals and everyone else, it would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Pharma%20v%20nonPharma.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pharma v nonPharma.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph was created by Joseph Burke, PhD, using data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;. Audit Analytics uses NAICS codes to classify companies by industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research indicates that over the last ten years pharmaceuticals have been the second riskiest industry for securities class action litigation (Education and Healthcare has been the riskiest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph demonstrates that the average company is now much more likely to be named as a defendant in a securities class action lawsuit than a company in a very risky class, such as pharmaceuticals, would have been a mere five years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Will the Pendulum Swing Back?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his blog the D&amp;amp;O Diary, Kevin LaCroix recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2020/09/articles/director-and-officer-liability/what-to-watch-in-the-world-of-do-3/&quot;&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; a few court decisions, both in Delaware and California, which indicate that companies may be able to blunt &lt;em&gt;Cyan’s&lt;/em&gt; impact by adopting charter provisions that designate federal courts as the proper forums for their cases. These charter provisions could potentially protect companies from having to defend themselves in state courts where there are fewer procedural protections. It is too early to tell how of much of an impact these decisions will have on litigation trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company has access to a proprietary database that includes all material litigation, classified by issue, for public companies. If you are interested in some bespoke research on litigation trends, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="Litigation Risk" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Pharmaceuticals" /><category term="D&amp;O Insurance" /><category term="Cyan" /><summary type="html">Watchdog Research provides an easy-to-use report for over 4,500 public companies based on 29 different categories of public disclosures. Our extensive database enables us to study larger trends affecting publicly traded companies.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Supreme%20Court%20pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Supreme%20Court%20pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Five Riskiest Industries for Securities Class Action Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-five-riskiest-industries-for-securities-class-action-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Five Riskiest Industries for Securities Class Action Litigation" /><published>2020-09-01T10:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T10:04:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-five-riskiest-industries-for-securities-class-action-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-five-riskiest-industries-for-securities-class-action-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;Our team analyzes public company disclosures for over 4,500 public companies and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report.Beyond creating company reports, our data can be used to analyze general trends and provide insight into many aspects the public company marketplace. Two members of our team, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD, have analyzed our data to delve deeper into the risk that companies face from securities class action lawsuits and &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; their findings on Google Scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are different facets to their research (last week we posted about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/&quot;&gt;six leading indicators of litigation&lt;/a&gt;), their analysis includes a comparison the relative exposure to security class action suits for public companies by industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we are updating that research to include results from 2019, when 8.2% of companies traded on the Nasdaq or NYSE were defendants in a securities class action suit. Industry classifications are based on NAICS codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Manufacturing Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This segment is composed of companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;Kraft Heinz&lt;/a&gt;, Pfizer and Tesla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies classified as manufacturing companies made up the largest segment of all public companies traded on the Nasdaq and NYSE in 2019 at 38%. Manufacturing companies also had a 9% chance of being named a defendant in a securities class action suit in 2019, &lt;strong&gt;10% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt;. About 40% of the defendants in this category were pharmaceutical or biotechnology companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Construction Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the smaller segments, with only 70 companies in 2019, they comprise about 1% of the market. In 2019, construction companies had a 10% chance of being named a defendant in 2019, about &lt;strong&gt;22% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Information Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Netflix, AT&amp;amp;T, and Slack Technologies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information companies had a 10.3% chance of being the defendant in a securities class action for 2019. That means if you had a client in the information industry, they were &lt;strong&gt;25% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt; to be named as a defendant in a class action securities litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Education and Healthcare Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This relatively small industry only accounts for 2% of all public companies traded on the Nasdaq and NYSE, but 10.9% of them were named as defendants in securities class action lawsuits in 2019. Education and Healthcare companies were &lt;strong&gt;33% more likely to be named as a defendant&lt;/strong&gt; than the average company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Retail Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This category is comprised of companies like Wayfair, Barnes &amp;amp; Noble, and Sotheby’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies classified as retail comprise 4% of the market and are the most likely to be named as a defendant in a securities class action lawsuit at 13.9%. Retail companies are &lt;strong&gt;69% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt; to be subject to a securities class action lawsuit, making retail the riskiest industry for securities class action litigation in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information used to create our reports comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;.  Not only do we sell reports, we also perform custom research; if you are interested in doing business with us, or you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers our Director of Research, at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For press inquiries or general questions about our company, contact our President Brian Lawe, at brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="Industry Trends" /><category term="Industry Trends" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><summary type="html">Our team analyzes public company disclosures for over 4,500 public companies and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report.Beyond creating company reports, our data can be used to analyze general trends and provide insight into many aspects the public company marketplace. Two members of our team, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD, have analyzed our data to delve deeper into the risk that companies face from securities class action lawsuits and published their findings on Google Scholar.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Retail%20Picture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Retail%20Picture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Six Leading Indicators of Securities Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Six Leading Indicators of Securities Litigation" /><published>2020-08-26T10:46:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T10:46:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog Research our team analyzes public company disclosures and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report. Our reports include 29 different categories, and each one is assigned a green, yellow, or red flag. These flags have helped our D&amp;amp;O Subscribers assess and price risks into their premiums in a way that is easy to understand for their clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Categorizing the data allows our team to see patterns in the data from the past that allow us to make reasonable predictions about the future. Two members of our team, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD, analyzed our data to see which data points corresponded with an increased risk of securities litigation and &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; their findings on Google Scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many interesting facets to their paper, but one of the most interesting was identifying six flags that were leading indicators of securities litigation. These flags all corresponded with a statistically significant increased risk of litigation the year after they were assigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Yellow Flag for Non-Audit Fees&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a company reports on its audit fees, they will distinguish between audit fees and non-audit fees. Non-audit fees consist of fees paid for something other than the independent audit. High non-audit fees can potentially compromise the independence of the auditing firm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, a spike in non-audit fees could indicate that the company is experiencing some sort of problem that they are attempting to address internally with the help of their auditor. For example, Under Armour had a dramatic &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;spike&lt;/a&gt; in non-audit fees the year before they revealed they were under investigation by the SEC, resulting in a damaging lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Yellow Flag for Cybersecurity Breach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity is an area of increasing concern to companies. A significant breach can lead to immediate negative effects on stock price, loss of goodwill, customer complaints, and lawsuits. But the problems are not merely immediate, they can create long lasting problems and create an elevated risk of a damaging lawsuit for a least a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Yellow Flag for a Beneish M-Score&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beneish M-Score is a statistical model that uses financial ratios of certain accounting data to determine the probability that a company is manipulating its financial results. The model became known when some students at Cornell used it to assert that Enron was manipulating its results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tools online that will allow anyone to measure a company’s Beneish M-Score for themselves, we also provide one in every Watchdog Report (if there is adequate information for the analysis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Red Flag for CFO Change&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFO changes are common and can be a sign of a healthy corporate culture. But rapid changes are a cause for concern, especially when the reason for the departure is vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again Under Armour is &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/&quot;&gt;emblematic&lt;/a&gt;; within a year of being appointed CFO, the new hire resigned for “personal reasons.” The next year, Under Armour was embroiled in litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Red Flag for Securities Class Action Litigation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once an event happens once, it is more likely to happen again. Our research indicates a securities class action suit more than doubles a company’s chance of having a securities lawsuit the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is no surprise to those familiar with insurance, but what may be surprising is that there is another flag which has a stronger predictive factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Red Flag for Revisions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over twenty percent of companies that filed a revision were subject to a new lawsuit the &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; year. One would expect that a lawsuit would follow quickly on the heels of a restatement, but our research shows that a restatement is often only the beginning of a company’s legal woes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to understand how this research was conducted or dig deeper into the details, we encourage you to look at our research report, available for free on &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;google scholar&lt;/a&gt;. Oftentimes, companies will have multiple flags related to litigation, our Gray Swan Event Factor estimates every company’s probability of incurring a securities class action suit over the next 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Leading Indicators" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Insurance" /><category term="D&amp;O" /><summary type="html">At Watchdog Research our team analyzes public company disclosures and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report. Our reports include 29 different categories, and each one is assigned a green, yellow, or red flag. These flags have helped our D&amp;amp;O Subscribers assess and price risks into their premiums in a way that is easy to understand for their clients.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Six%20leading%20indicators.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Six%20leading%20indicators.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Chinese Companies: Listed vs. Delisted in the Past Decade</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/chinese-companies-listed-vs-delisted-in-the-past-decade/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chinese Companies: Listed vs. Delisted in the Past Decade" /><published>2020-08-25T09:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-25T09:56:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/chinese-companies-listed-vs-delisted-in-the-past-decade</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/chinese-companies-listed-vs-delisted-in-the-past-decade/">&lt;p&gt;Our company specializes in assessing the probability a company will suffer a Gray Swan Event, rare but predictable events that can negatively affect the value of company stock.  Our products help capture and assess risk. The collapse of Luckin Coffee was a powerful reminder of how risky an investment in a Chinese company can be, however, at the time our analysis did &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/&quot;&gt;not capture&lt;/a&gt; the risk posed by Luckin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis was lacking because the data was lacking. Foreign companies don’t have to meet the same rigorous disclosure requirements as U.S. companies, and that problem is exasperated among Chinese companies, at least &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to the SEC and PCAOB. Our reports now include a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/&quot;&gt;flag &lt;/a&gt;that warns investors when a company hails from a jurisdiction without much real regulatory oversight, but we are looking to take that analysis one step further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are attempting to quantify the risk associated with investing in Chinese companies by quantifying the risk represented by the absence of data. It’s tricky stuff, but our PhDs are working on it. This project has generated all sorts of interesting data, and we thought we would share a snippet of that research with you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20listed%20and%20delisted%20graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese listed and delisted graph.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows the total number of Chinese companies listed on the Nasdaq and NYSE exchanges every year, along with the number of Chinese companies that were delisted. On average, &lt;strong&gt;over 10%&lt;/strong&gt; of the exchange traded Chinese companies were delisted in the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20delisted%20percentage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese delisted percentage.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows that delistings have not been steady or consistent. In 2012 the Chinese reverse merger scams were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20#:\~:text=The%20Chinese%20reverse%20merger%20fraud,violations%20of%20U.S.%20securities%20laws.&quot;&gt;exposed&lt;/a&gt;, and Western investors soured on Chinese companies. The bad press corresponded with a temporary wave in delistings, and a concurrent fall in overall listings. That wave of delistings started to recede in 2017. It will be interesting to see if Luckin’s collapse generates a new wave of delistings, or if  investments in China will go on undeterred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally a delisting can benefit investors, if it occurs because a company is purchased or absorbed in a merger, but in most cases a delisting means a near total loss for shareholders. Low selling prices are a common reason for delisting, which signify an almost complete lack of investor demand or interest, even at bargain prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, the hunger for investments in China has apparently become insatiable, at least amongst a certain class. This has fueled many hyped Chinese IPOs, including Luckin’s IPO. It will be interesting to see if the combined effect of Luckin’s fraud, and a political clash between the U.S. and the CCP over the CCP’s longstanding &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;refusal&lt;/a&gt; to allow the PCAOB to conduct inspect Chinese auditors will dampen investor enthusiasm for Chinese companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="featured" /><category term="China" /><category term="Listing" /><category term="Delisting" /><summary type="html">Our company specializes in assessing the probability a company will suffer a Gray Swan Event, rare but predictable events that can negatively affect the value of company stock. Our products help capture and assess risk. The collapse of Luckin Coffee was a powerful reminder of how risky an investment in a Chinese company can be, however, at the time our analysis did not capture the risk posed by Luckin.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/aditya-vyas-mHdATQY9fIU-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/aditya-vyas-mHdATQY9fIU-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">UPDATE: Where in the World is Marcum Bernstein Pinchuk?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UPDATE: Where in the World is Marcum Bernstein Pinchuk?" /><published>2020-08-06T08:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-06T08:51:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum BP is a joint venture between Marcum LLP and Bernstein &amp;amp; Pinchuk LLP specializing mostly in Chinese clients. Their practice of “city-swapping” raises some interesting questions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE: Marcum BP was unable to make any official comment on this story. However, we did learn a great deal more about Marcum BP after publishing our article and we would like to provide that context here. As well as point out a few corrections or clarifications in the body of the article itself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our research is data driven and atypical results and outliers generally raise red flags. This sort of data-based analysis can tell you that you are looking at something different or unique, but it does not provide an explanation for outlying results.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When we wrote this article there was an assumption that comparing Marcum BP to other auditors would provide an apples-to-apples comparison, but the truth is far more complex. In short, it is possible that Marcum BP’s results are unique because the firm is unique.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum BP is a U.S. firm that audits Chinese companies. That means Marcum BP stands behind their audits and are ultimately accountable for them. In contrast, the Big 4 have fenced off their Chinese affiliates. Our research indicates a U.S. branch of the Big 4 has not offered an audit opinion of a Chinese company since 2015, instead their Chinese affiliates handle their Chinese clients, and—unlike Marcum BP—these Chinese affiliates of the Big 4 are not subject to inspection by the PCAOB.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other small U.S. auditing firms that provide audit services for Chinese companies often have a Chinese audit firm participate in the audit opinion to some extent. These Chinese audit firms are not subject to inspection by the PCAOB either. In contrast, Marcum BP does not partner up with Chinese audit firms to do their work in China, they do it themselves. This makes Marcum BP stand out amongst their peers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two final points of context. Firstly, by law Marcum BP is subject to inspection by the PCAOB at least every three years, however, the PCAOB can impose additional inspections at any time. There is no evidence that Marcum BP is attempting to avoid inspections. Marcum BP’s concentration of reports out of its New York office in 2018 may not relate to the PCAOB 2018 inspection. If it did, it would probably indicate that Marcum BP was trying to make itself more available to the PCAOB, not less.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Finally, the U.S. and China impose contradictory demands on audit firms. The Big 4 handle this problem by keeping their U.S. and Chinese operations separate, where as Marcum BP and some other small firms attempt to navigate between Scylla and Charybdis at their own peril.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Multiple solutions have been offered to this problem. The Senate unanimously passed the Holding Foreign Companies Accountable Act (yet to be voted on in the House) which would delist Chinese companies that were not inspected by the PCAOB within three years.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carson Block &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/comments/emerging-markets/cll9-7400188-219069.pdf&quot;&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt; that the Big 4 audit firms should be liable for the actions of their global affiliates because of their use of the brand. A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://home.treasury.gov/system/files/136/PWG-Report-on-Protecting-United-States-Investors-from-Significant-Risks-from-Chinese-Companies.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; issued at the direction of the White House has recommended co-audits, which would also make the Big 4 potentially liable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of course, there are many who benefit from the status quo, so it is possible the Senate bill will be quietly scuttled, and the proposed reforms will be given nothing more than lip-service.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research team has always taken a keen interest in China, and our interest surged again with the news of Luckin Coffee’s collapse. There are several reasons why investing in Chinese companies has always been risky, but one of the most significant and ongoing reasons for being wary of Chinese companies is that Chinese auditors are supposed to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;subject&lt;/a&gt; to inspection by the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board, or PCAOB, but the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) refuses to allow inspectors to do that job. This is because the CCP considers the work papers produced by these auditors for their China clients, often state-owned companies, “state secrets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum BP “City-Swapping”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to know if any China-based companies listed in the U.S. had changed their auditors from U.S. member firms to Chinese member firms, perhaps to avoid auditor inspection by the PCAOB. We found a handful of companies whose audits had moved to China, but strangely enough they had not switched audit firms; instead their auditor, Marcum BP, appeared to switch office locations where the reports were issued between China and the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every firm registered with the PCAOB must complete Form AP when issuing an audit report. The firm must include the location of the office that performed the work and issued the report by providing the city where the office is located. Marcum BP appears to have three main offices—one in New York, and two in China. &lt;em&gt;(Correction: The PCAOB inspection report for &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Inspections/Reports/Documents/104-2020-006-Marcum-Bernstein-Pinchuk-LLP.pdf&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt; indicates there are 7 offices, however New York, Beijing, and Guangzhou are named most often in the Form AP Data&lt;/em&gt;). We were surprised to see that some of Marcum BP’s clients “city-swapping” their opinions, alternating between New York and Beijing in successive years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We dug more deeply into the numbers and found that since 2017 Marcum BP has signed audit reports for 37 individual companies, of whom 27 are Chinese clients. Of those clients, twelve of them had a year where the location of the office issuing the audit report for the company appeared to change countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Marcum%20BP%20AP%20Form%20Graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marcum BP AP Form Graph.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows Marcum BP audit reports issued from China and the US from 2017 to 2020 year-to-date for their Chinese clients. The data indicates that Marcum BP generally issues more audit reports from its China office locations than it does in New York, except for 2018 when almost all their reports were issued out of New York. This data was derived from AP Form Data made available by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/firms/5395&quot;&gt;PCAOB&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did not see any other auditors where audit opinions would switch back and forth from China (including Hong Kong) to the U.S. from 2010 to the present. Ernst and Young had one client switch from Hong Kong to Seoul in 2016, and PWC had on client, Nord Anglia Education, Inc. move from China to the UK. In short, we believe this “city-swapping” phenomenon between the U.S. and China is unique to Marcum BP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does a 2018 PCAOB Inspection Explain Marcum BP’s City-Swapping?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clarification: It is possible that Marcum BP has been inspected by the PCAOB since 2018, and that the PCAOB has not issued an inspection report yet. If that is the case, then it would belie any idea that inspections and “city-swapping” were related.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP is a small boutique firm that has never issued more than 25 reports in a given year. One advantage to being a smaller firm is that you are not subject to annual inspections by the PCAOB. Instead firms with less than 100 opinions for public companies each year are subject to inspection every &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Rules/Pages/Section_4.aspx&quot;&gt;third&lt;/a&gt; year. The PCAOB conducted an inspection of Marcum BP in 2018 and partially released the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Inspections/Reports/Documents/104-2020-006-Marcum-Bernstein-Pinchuk-LLP.pdf&quot;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; of that inspection in January 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is well-established that the CCP has forbidden auditors operating in China to share their work papers with the SEC or PCAOB. That has created some friction between the PCAOB and the Big 4 audit firms. The Chinese member firms of the Big 4 — Deloitte, PwC, Ernst &amp;amp; Young, and KPMG, as well as the former BDO affiliate even faced potential sanctions by the SEC for refusing to cooperate with PCAOB inspections and SEC investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the SEC censured the firms, which eventually began providing some documents related to specific cases. Under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/pressrelease/2015-25.html&quot;&gt;settlement&lt;/a&gt;, the firms each agreed to pay $500,000 and admit that they did not produce documents before the proceedings were instituted against them in 2012. However, they have never allowed the PCAOB to come to China and inspect the firms or perform joint inspections with Chinese authorities. In early 2020, the PCAOB &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/International/Pages/China-Related-Access-Challenges.aspx&quot;&gt;removed&lt;/a&gt; a Memorandum Of Understanding  (MOU) with China regarding how these inspections might begin to take place from its website, saying that the MOU had been ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big 4 firms get around the problem of uninspectable China member firms by assigning the opinion for almost all China-based company audits to Chinese member firms. What happens in China stays in China…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP faces a different dilemma. If workpapers for client work done by its Chinese locations are not provided to the PCAOB, then the firm risks deregistration by the PCAOB, a lethal blow for a smaller firm. However, if their Chinese locations share their Chinese client’s information with the PCAOB, then the firm may invite trouble with the CCP for sharing “state secrets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, having the Marcum BP LLP lead engagement partner for the China-based audits work out of New York when the company’s operations and field auditors are in China is a recipe for poor audit quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “city-swapping” may be a workaround to handle the firm’s dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During 2018, Marcum BP appears to have brought most of their work from China back to New York so they could issue their reports out of that office, subject to inspection by the PCAOB. In other years, most of their reports came out of their office in Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP’s next inspection is due in 2021, and it will be interesting to see if the number of reports coming out the New York office shoots up or continues its current trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Power Concentration in Beijing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP’s trend towards having more opinions issued out of Beijing is consistent with industry wide trends in the past few years. When we look at the city locations of the audits performed by the Chinese affiliates of the Big 4, as well as all audits performed in China, we can see a dramatic turn towards Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In absolute numbers, the number of audit opinions coming out of Beijing has risen dramatically in the last four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Beijing%20Audit%20opinions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Beijing Audit opinions.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only are more audit opinions being issued from Beijing, but Beijing’s share of all audit opinions being issued in China has risen as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Beining%20Audit%20opinions%25.png&quot; alt=&quot;Beining Audit opinions%.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These graphs were created by our data scientist Joseph Burke PhD using the audit opinions data from Audit Analytics.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what is driving this trend is that audits that were traditionally done someplace else, like in Hong Kong, are now being performed in Beijing. This concentration of power in the accounting profession mirrors the political developments in Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another part of what is driving this trend is that newly listed companies are increasingly based out of Beijing. This could indicate that one of the prerequisites for a Chinese company to be successful in accessing the U.S. market is the patronage or blessing of Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concentration of power in Beijing does not bode well. Auditors in Beijing are potentially under significantly more political pressure from the Party than those in Hong Kong. Additionally, the partners located in Beijing are also more likely to be active Party members, creating a potential conflict of loyalty when they are auditing a Party-owned enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audit Quality Suffering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP was subject to inspection in 2015 and the PCAOB did not appear to find any issues that made it into the publicly disclosed report. In short, they got a clean bill of health. Their 2018 inspection report, however, had very different results. The PCAOB found serious problems with Marcum BP’s audit of one issuer (likely a Chinese-based issuer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that report the PCAOB identified seven different areas where the issuer was significantly deficient. The lack of sufficient testing to establish effective internal controls over financial reporting (ICFR) featured prominently in the report. According to the PCAOB, “&lt;em&gt;[I]n this audit, the auditor issued an opinion without satisfying its fundamental obligation to obtain reasonable assurance about whether the financial statements were free of material misstatement and the issuer maintained effective IFCR&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was not the only bad news that Marcum BP received from the PCAOB. In September 2019, the PCAOB &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Enforcement/Decisions/Documents/105-2019-023%20-%20MBP.pdf&quot;&gt;fined the firm&lt;/a&gt; $50,000 to the firm for practices in 2013 and 2014 that had undermined auditor independence. Marcum BP had participated in conferences where they had promoted seven of their audit clients to potential investors, creating conflicts concerning their auditor independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP was not alone; Marcum LLP also was assessed a $450,000 fine relating to the same conferences. The PCAOB singled out Marcum BP and Marcum LLP for this auditor independence issue, even though Francine Mckenna of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; has &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/the-sec-proposes-to-modernize-auditor&quot;&gt;pointed&lt;/a&gt; out that audit firms have held similar conferences in the past that included audit clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be some other explanation for the apparent “city-swapping” that has nothing to do with the PCAOB inspections. The firm may simply be filling out their forms incorrectly. The have yet to respond to our inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCAOB and the CCP’s directives are directly contradictory, which is why our reports assign every Chinese company a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/&quot;&gt;red flag&lt;/a&gt;. It should not be surprising that auditors are contorting themselves into pretzels to stay in the good graces of the PCAOB and the CCP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also are not surprised that Marcum BP inspection report showed a myriad of problems with one of their clients (likely a Chinese company); the obstacles to having an adequate audit of a Chinese company are significant. We would point out that it is possible that the Chinese affiliates of the Big 4 have the same significant defects in their audits as Marcum BP, but we will never know because they are not subject to inspection by the PCAOB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="City-Swapping" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="China" /><category term="Marcum BP" /><category term="City-Swapping" /><summary type="html">Marcum BP is a joint venture between Marcum LLP and Bernstein &amp;amp; Pinchuk LLP specializing mostly in Chinese clients. Their practice of “city-swapping” raises some interesting questions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Commie%20flag.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Commie%20flag.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>