<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-10T13:46:13-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Impact of Cyan: Comparing the Market Today to the Pharmaceuticals of Yesteryear</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/impact-of-cyan-comparing-the-market-today-to-the-pharmaceuticals-of-yesteryear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impact of Cyan: Comparing the Market Today to the Pharmaceuticals of Yesteryear" /><published>2020-09-10T11:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-10T11:51:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/impact-of-cyan-comparing-the-market-today-to-the-pharmaceuticals-of-yesteryear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/impact-of-cyan-comparing-the-market-today-to-the-pharmaceuticals-of-yesteryear/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/&quot;&gt;Watchdog Research&lt;/a&gt; provides an easy-to-use report for over 4,500 public companies based on 29 different categories of public disclosures. Our extensive database enables us to study larger trends affecting publicly traded companies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court’s decision in &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; in 2018 was a big victory to plaintiff’s law firms because it opened the doors of the state courts to federal claims under the Securities Act of 1933. These state law cases had already been permitted in some jurisdictions, but &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; threw the doors open all over the country, with predictable results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last three years, the percentage of companies named in a securities class action suit have been extremely high, hovering around 8%. This has been a great development for plaintiff’s attorneys, but a major problem for corporations and the insurers who provide D&amp;amp;O Insurance to cover the costs of these suits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how disruptive this change has been, we compared the current level of litigation with the amount of litigation associated with what is considered the riskiest class of companies—pharmaceuticals. Our research indicates that over the last 10 years, that on average 7.45% of pharmaceutical companies have been named as defendants in securities class actions annually. If you were to compare the rates of security class action suits year over year between pharmaceuticals and everyone else, it would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Pharma%20v%20nonPharma.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pharma v nonPharma.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph was created by Joseph Burke, PhD, using data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;. Audit Analytics uses NAICS codes to classify companies by industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research indicates that over the last ten years pharmaceuticals have been the second riskiest industry for securities class action litigation (Education and Healthcare has been the riskiest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph demonstrates that the average company is now much more likely to be named as a defendant in a securities class action lawsuit than a company in a very risky class, such as pharmaceuticals, would have been a mere five years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Will the Pendulum Swing Back?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his blog the D&amp;amp;O Diary, Kevin LaCroix recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2020/09/articles/director-and-officer-liability/what-to-watch-in-the-world-of-do-3/&quot;&gt;reviewed&lt;/a&gt; a few court decisions, both in Delaware and California, which indicate that companies may be able to blunt &lt;em&gt;Cyan’s&lt;/em&gt; impact by adopting charter provisions that designate federal courts as the proper forums for their cases. These charter provisions could potentially protect companies from having to defend themselves in state courts where there are fewer procedural protections. It is too early to tell how of much of an impact these decisions will have on litigation trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company has access to a proprietary database that includes all material litigation, classified by issue, for public companies. If you are interested in some bespoke research on litigation trends, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="Litigation Risk" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Pharmaceuticals" /><category term="D&amp;O Insurance" /><category term="Cyan" /><summary type="html">Watchdog Research provides an easy-to-use report for over 4,500 public companies based on 29 different categories of public disclosures. Our extensive database enables us to study larger trends affecting publicly traded companies.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Supreme%20Court%20pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Supreme%20Court%20pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Five Riskiest Industries for Securities Class Action Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-five-riskiest-industries-for-securities-class-action-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Five Riskiest Industries for Securities Class Action Litigation" /><published>2020-09-01T10:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T10:04:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-five-riskiest-industries-for-securities-class-action-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-five-riskiest-industries-for-securities-class-action-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;Our team analyzes public company disclosures for over 4,500 public companies and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report.Beyond creating company reports, our data can be used to analyze general trends and provide insight into many aspects the public company marketplace. Two members of our team, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD, have analyzed our data to delve deeper into the risk that companies face from securities class action lawsuits and &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; their findings on Google Scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are different facets to their research (last week we posted about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/&quot;&gt;six leading indicators of litigation&lt;/a&gt;), their analysis includes a comparison the relative exposure to security class action suits for public companies by industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we are updating that research to include results from 2019, when 8.2% of companies traded on the Nasdaq or NYSE were defendants in a securities class action suit. Industry classifications are based on NAICS codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Manufacturing Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This segment is composed of companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;Kraft Heinz&lt;/a&gt;, Pfizer and Tesla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies classified as manufacturing companies made up the largest segment of all public companies traded on the Nasdaq and NYSE in 2019 at 38%. Manufacturing companies also had a 9% chance of being named a defendant in a securities class action suit in 2019, &lt;strong&gt;10% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt;. About 40% of the defendants in this category were pharmaceutical or biotechnology companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Construction Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the smaller segments, with only 70 companies in 2019, they comprise about 1% of the market. In 2019, construction companies had a 10% chance of being named a defendant in 2019, about &lt;strong&gt;22% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Information Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Netflix, AT&amp;amp;T, and Slack Technologies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information companies had a 10.3% chance of being the defendant in a securities class action for 2019. That means if you had a client in the information industry, they were &lt;strong&gt;25% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt; to be named as a defendant in a class action securities litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Education and Healthcare Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This relatively small industry only accounts for 2% of all public companies traded on the Nasdaq and NYSE, but 10.9% of them were named as defendants in securities class action lawsuits in 2019. Education and Healthcare companies were &lt;strong&gt;33% more likely to be named as a defendant&lt;/strong&gt; than the average company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Retail Companies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This category is comprised of companies like Wayfair, Barnes &amp;amp; Noble, and Sotheby’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies classified as retail comprise 4% of the market and are the most likely to be named as a defendant in a securities class action lawsuit at 13.9%. Retail companies are &lt;strong&gt;69% more likely than the average company&lt;/strong&gt; to be subject to a securities class action lawsuit, making retail the riskiest industry for securities class action litigation in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information used to create our reports comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;.  Not only do we sell reports, we also perform custom research; if you are interested in doing business with us, or you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers our Director of Research, at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For press inquiries or general questions about our company, contact our President Brian Lawe, at brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="Industry Trends" /><category term="Industry Trends" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><summary type="html">Our team analyzes public company disclosures for over 4,500 public companies and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report.Beyond creating company reports, our data can be used to analyze general trends and provide insight into many aspects the public company marketplace. Two members of our team, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD, have analyzed our data to delve deeper into the risk that companies face from securities class action lawsuits and published their findings on Google Scholar.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Retail%20Picture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Retail%20Picture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Six Leading Indicators of Securities Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Six Leading Indicators of Securities Litigation" /><published>2020-08-26T10:46:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T10:46:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog Research our team analyzes public company disclosures and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report. Our reports include 29 different categories, and each one is assigned a green, yellow, or red flag. These flags have helped our D&amp;amp;O Subscribers assess and price risks into their premiums in a way that is easy to understand for their clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Categorizing the data allows our team to see patterns in the data from the past that allow us to make reasonable predictions about the future. Two members of our team, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD, analyzed our data to see which data points corresponded with an increased risk of securities litigation and &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; their findings on Google Scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many interesting facets to their paper, but one of the most interesting was identifying six flags that were leading indicators of securities litigation. These flags all corresponded with a statistically significant increased risk of litigation the year after they were assigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Yellow Flag for Non-Audit Fees&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a company reports on its audit fees, they will distinguish between audit fees and non-audit fees. Non-audit fees consist of fees paid for something other than the independent audit. High non-audit fees can potentially compromise the independence of the auditing firm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, a spike in non-audit fees could indicate that the company is experiencing some sort of problem that they are attempting to address internally with the help of their auditor. For example, Under Armour had a dramatic &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;spike&lt;/a&gt; in non-audit fees the year before they revealed they were under investigation by the SEC, resulting in a damaging lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Yellow Flag for Cybersecurity Breach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity is an area of increasing concern to companies. A significant breach can lead to immediate negative effects on stock price, loss of goodwill, customer complaints, and lawsuits. But the problems are not merely immediate, they can create long lasting problems and create an elevated risk of a damaging lawsuit for a least a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Yellow Flag for a Beneish M-Score&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beneish M-Score is a statistical model that uses financial ratios of certain accounting data to determine the probability that a company is manipulating its financial results. The model became known when some students at Cornell used it to assert that Enron was manipulating its results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tools online that will allow anyone to measure a company’s Beneish M-Score for themselves, we also provide one in every Watchdog Report (if there is adequate information for the analysis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Red Flag for CFO Change&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFO changes are common and can be a sign of a healthy corporate culture. But rapid changes are a cause for concern, especially when the reason for the departure is vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again Under Armour is &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/&quot;&gt;emblematic&lt;/a&gt;; within a year of being appointed CFO, the new hire resigned for “personal reasons.” The next year, Under Armour was embroiled in litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Red Flag for Securities Class Action Litigation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once an event happens once, it is more likely to happen again. Our research indicates a securities class action suit more than doubles a company’s chance of having a securities lawsuit the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is no surprise to those familiar with insurance, but what may be surprising is that there is another flag which has a stronger predictive factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Red Flag for Revisions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over twenty percent of companies that filed a revision were subject to a new lawsuit the &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; year. One would expect that a lawsuit would follow quickly on the heels of a restatement, but our research shows that a restatement is often only the beginning of a company’s legal woes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to understand how this research was conducted or dig deeper into the details, we encourage you to look at our research report, available for free on &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;google scholar&lt;/a&gt;. Oftentimes, companies will have multiple flags related to litigation, our Gray Swan Event Factor estimates every company’s probability of incurring a securities class action suit over the next 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Leading Indicators" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Insurance" /><category term="D&amp;O" /><summary type="html">At Watchdog Research our team analyzes public company disclosures and summarizes that information in an easy-to-use report. Our reports include 29 different categories, and each one is assigned a green, yellow, or red flag. These flags have helped our D&amp;amp;O Subscribers assess and price risks into their premiums in a way that is easy to understand for their clients.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Six%20leading%20indicators.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Six%20leading%20indicators.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Chinese Companies: Listed vs. Delisted in the Past Decade</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/chinese-companies-listed-vs-delisted-in-the-past-decade/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chinese Companies: Listed vs. Delisted in the Past Decade" /><published>2020-08-25T09:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-25T09:56:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/chinese-companies-listed-vs-delisted-in-the-past-decade</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/chinese-companies-listed-vs-delisted-in-the-past-decade/">&lt;p&gt;Our company specializes in assessing the probability a company will suffer a Gray Swan Event, rare but predictable events that can negatively affect the value of company stock.  Our products help capture and assess risk. The collapse of Luckin Coffee was a powerful reminder of how risky an investment in a Chinese company can be, however, at the time our analysis did &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/&quot;&gt;not capture&lt;/a&gt; the risk posed by Luckin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis was lacking because the data was lacking. Foreign companies don’t have to meet the same rigorous disclosure requirements as U.S. companies, and that problem is exasperated among Chinese companies, at least &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to the SEC and PCAOB. Our reports now include a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/&quot;&gt;flag &lt;/a&gt;that warns investors when a company hails from a jurisdiction without much real regulatory oversight, but we are looking to take that analysis one step further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are attempting to quantify the risk associated with investing in Chinese companies by quantifying the risk represented by the absence of data. It’s tricky stuff, but our PhDs are working on it. This project has generated all sorts of interesting data, and we thought we would share a snippet of that research with you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20listed%20and%20delisted%20graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese listed and delisted graph.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows the total number of Chinese companies listed on the Nasdaq and NYSE exchanges every year, along with the number of Chinese companies that were delisted. On average, &lt;strong&gt;over 10%&lt;/strong&gt; of the exchange traded Chinese companies were delisted in the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20delisted%20percentage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese delisted percentage.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows that delistings have not been steady or consistent. In 2012 the Chinese reverse merger scams were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20#:\~:text=The%20Chinese%20reverse%20merger%20fraud,violations%20of%20U.S.%20securities%20laws.&quot;&gt;exposed&lt;/a&gt;, and Western investors soured on Chinese companies. The bad press corresponded with a temporary wave in delistings, and a concurrent fall in overall listings. That wave of delistings started to recede in 2017. It will be interesting to see if Luckin’s collapse generates a new wave of delistings, or if  investments in China will go on undeterred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally a delisting can benefit investors, if it occurs because a company is purchased or absorbed in a merger, but in most cases a delisting means a near total loss for shareholders. Low selling prices are a common reason for delisting, which signify an almost complete lack of investor demand or interest, even at bargain prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, the hunger for investments in China has apparently become insatiable, at least amongst a certain class. This has fueled many hyped Chinese IPOs, including Luckin’s IPO. It will be interesting to see if the combined effect of Luckin’s fraud, and a political clash between the U.S. and the CCP over the CCP’s longstanding &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;refusal&lt;/a&gt; to allow the PCAOB to conduct inspect Chinese auditors will dampen investor enthusiasm for Chinese companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="featured" /><category term="China" /><category term="Listing" /><category term="Delisting" /><summary type="html">Our company specializes in assessing the probability a company will suffer a Gray Swan Event, rare but predictable events that can negatively affect the value of company stock. Our products help capture and assess risk. The collapse of Luckin Coffee was a powerful reminder of how risky an investment in a Chinese company can be, however, at the time our analysis did not capture the risk posed by Luckin.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/aditya-vyas-mHdATQY9fIU-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/aditya-vyas-mHdATQY9fIU-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">UPDATE: Where in the World is Marcum Bernstein Pinchuk?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UPDATE: Where in the World is Marcum Bernstein Pinchuk?" /><published>2020-08-06T08:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-06T08:51:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum BP is a joint venture between Marcum LLP and Bernstein &amp;amp; Pinchuk LLP specializing mostly in Chinese clients. Their practice of “city-swapping” raises some interesting questions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE: Marcum BP was unable to make any official comment on this story. However, we did learn a great deal more about Marcum BP after publishing our article and we would like to provide that context here. As well as point out a few corrections or clarifications in the body of the article itself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our research is data driven and atypical results and outliers generally raise red flags. This sort of data-based analysis can tell you that you are looking at something different or unique, but it does not provide an explanation for outlying results.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When we wrote this article there was an assumption that comparing Marcum BP to other auditors would provide an apples-to-apples comparison, but the truth is far more complex. In short, it is possible that Marcum BP’s results are unique because the firm is unique.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum BP is a U.S. firm that audits Chinese companies. That means Marcum BP stands behind their audits and are ultimately accountable for them. In contrast, the Big 4 have fenced off their Chinese affiliates. Our research indicates a U.S. branch of the Big 4 has not offered an audit opinion of a Chinese company since 2015, instead their Chinese affiliates handle their Chinese clients, and—unlike Marcum BP—these Chinese affiliates of the Big 4 are not subject to inspection by the PCAOB.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other small U.S. auditing firms that provide audit services for Chinese companies often have a Chinese audit firm participate in the audit opinion to some extent. These Chinese audit firms are not subject to inspection by the PCAOB either. In contrast, Marcum BP does not partner up with Chinese audit firms to do their work in China, they do it themselves. This makes Marcum BP stand out amongst their peers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two final points of context. Firstly, by law Marcum BP is subject to inspection by the PCAOB at least every three years, however, the PCAOB can impose additional inspections at any time. There is no evidence that Marcum BP is attempting to avoid inspections. Marcum BP’s concentration of reports out of its New York office in 2018 may not relate to the PCAOB 2018 inspection. If it did, it would probably indicate that Marcum BP was trying to make itself more available to the PCAOB, not less.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Finally, the U.S. and China impose contradictory demands on audit firms. The Big 4 handle this problem by keeping their U.S. and Chinese operations separate, where as Marcum BP and some other small firms attempt to navigate between Scylla and Charybdis at their own peril.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Multiple solutions have been offered to this problem. The Senate unanimously passed the Holding Foreign Companies Accountable Act (yet to be voted on in the House) which would delist Chinese companies that were not inspected by the PCAOB within three years.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carson Block &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/comments/emerging-markets/cll9-7400188-219069.pdf&quot;&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt; that the Big 4 audit firms should be liable for the actions of their global affiliates because of their use of the brand. A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://home.treasury.gov/system/files/136/PWG-Report-on-Protecting-United-States-Investors-from-Significant-Risks-from-Chinese-Companies.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; issued at the direction of the White House has recommended co-audits, which would also make the Big 4 potentially liable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of course, there are many who benefit from the status quo, so it is possible the Senate bill will be quietly scuttled, and the proposed reforms will be given nothing more than lip-service.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research team has always taken a keen interest in China, and our interest surged again with the news of Luckin Coffee’s collapse. There are several reasons why investing in Chinese companies has always been risky, but one of the most significant and ongoing reasons for being wary of Chinese companies is that Chinese auditors are supposed to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;subject&lt;/a&gt; to inspection by the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board, or PCAOB, but the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) refuses to allow inspectors to do that job. This is because the CCP considers the work papers produced by these auditors for their China clients, often state-owned companies, “state secrets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum BP “City-Swapping”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to know if any China-based companies listed in the U.S. had changed their auditors from U.S. member firms to Chinese member firms, perhaps to avoid auditor inspection by the PCAOB. We found a handful of companies whose audits had moved to China, but strangely enough they had not switched audit firms; instead their auditor, Marcum BP, appeared to switch office locations where the reports were issued between China and the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every firm registered with the PCAOB must complete Form AP when issuing an audit report. The firm must include the location of the office that performed the work and issued the report by providing the city where the office is located. Marcum BP appears to have three main offices—one in New York, and two in China. &lt;em&gt;(Correction: The PCAOB inspection report for &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Inspections/Reports/Documents/104-2020-006-Marcum-Bernstein-Pinchuk-LLP.pdf&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt; indicates there are 7 offices, however New York, Beijing, and Guangzhou are named most often in the Form AP Data&lt;/em&gt;). We were surprised to see that some of Marcum BP’s clients “city-swapping” their opinions, alternating between New York and Beijing in successive years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We dug more deeply into the numbers and found that since 2017 Marcum BP has signed audit reports for 37 individual companies, of whom 27 are Chinese clients. Of those clients, twelve of them had a year where the location of the office issuing the audit report for the company appeared to change countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Marcum%20BP%20AP%20Form%20Graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marcum BP AP Form Graph.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows Marcum BP audit reports issued from China and the US from 2017 to 2020 year-to-date for their Chinese clients. The data indicates that Marcum BP generally issues more audit reports from its China office locations than it does in New York, except for 2018 when almost all their reports were issued out of New York. This data was derived from AP Form Data made available by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/firms/5395&quot;&gt;PCAOB&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did not see any other auditors where audit opinions would switch back and forth from China (including Hong Kong) to the U.S. from 2010 to the present. Ernst and Young had one client switch from Hong Kong to Seoul in 2016, and PWC had on client, Nord Anglia Education, Inc. move from China to the UK. In short, we believe this “city-swapping” phenomenon between the U.S. and China is unique to Marcum BP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does a 2018 PCAOB Inspection Explain Marcum BP’s City-Swapping?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clarification: It is possible that Marcum BP has been inspected by the PCAOB since 2018, and that the PCAOB has not issued an inspection report yet. If that is the case, then it would belie any idea that inspections and “city-swapping” were related.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP is a small boutique firm that has never issued more than 25 reports in a given year. One advantage to being a smaller firm is that you are not subject to annual inspections by the PCAOB. Instead firms with less than 100 opinions for public companies each year are subject to inspection every &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Rules/Pages/Section_4.aspx&quot;&gt;third&lt;/a&gt; year. The PCAOB conducted an inspection of Marcum BP in 2018 and partially released the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Inspections/Reports/Documents/104-2020-006-Marcum-Bernstein-Pinchuk-LLP.pdf&quot;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; of that inspection in January 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is well-established that the CCP has forbidden auditors operating in China to share their work papers with the SEC or PCAOB. That has created some friction between the PCAOB and the Big 4 audit firms. The Chinese member firms of the Big 4 — Deloitte, PwC, Ernst &amp;amp; Young, and KPMG, as well as the former BDO affiliate even faced potential sanctions by the SEC for refusing to cooperate with PCAOB inspections and SEC investigations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the SEC censured the firms, which eventually began providing some documents related to specific cases. Under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/pressrelease/2015-25.html&quot;&gt;settlement&lt;/a&gt;, the firms each agreed to pay $500,000 and admit that they did not produce documents before the proceedings were instituted against them in 2012. However, they have never allowed the PCAOB to come to China and inspect the firms or perform joint inspections with Chinese authorities. In early 2020, the PCAOB &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/International/Pages/China-Related-Access-Challenges.aspx&quot;&gt;removed&lt;/a&gt; a Memorandum Of Understanding  (MOU) with China regarding how these inspections might begin to take place from its website, saying that the MOU had been ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big 4 firms get around the problem of uninspectable China member firms by assigning the opinion for almost all China-based company audits to Chinese member firms. What happens in China stays in China…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP faces a different dilemma. If workpapers for client work done by its Chinese locations are not provided to the PCAOB, then the firm risks deregistration by the PCAOB, a lethal blow for a smaller firm. However, if their Chinese locations share their Chinese client’s information with the PCAOB, then the firm may invite trouble with the CCP for sharing “state secrets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, having the Marcum BP LLP lead engagement partner for the China-based audits work out of New York when the company’s operations and field auditors are in China is a recipe for poor audit quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “city-swapping” may be a workaround to handle the firm’s dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During 2018, Marcum BP appears to have brought most of their work from China back to New York so they could issue their reports out of that office, subject to inspection by the PCAOB. In other years, most of their reports came out of their office in Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP’s next inspection is due in 2021, and it will be interesting to see if the number of reports coming out the New York office shoots up or continues its current trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Power Concentration in Beijing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP’s trend towards having more opinions issued out of Beijing is consistent with industry wide trends in the past few years. When we look at the city locations of the audits performed by the Chinese affiliates of the Big 4, as well as all audits performed in China, we can see a dramatic turn towards Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In absolute numbers, the number of audit opinions coming out of Beijing has risen dramatically in the last four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Beijing%20Audit%20opinions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Beijing Audit opinions.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only are more audit opinions being issued from Beijing, but Beijing’s share of all audit opinions being issued in China has risen as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Beining%20Audit%20opinions%25.png&quot; alt=&quot;Beining Audit opinions%.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These graphs were created by our data scientist Joseph Burke PhD using the audit opinions data from Audit Analytics.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what is driving this trend is that audits that were traditionally done someplace else, like in Hong Kong, are now being performed in Beijing. This concentration of power in the accounting profession mirrors the political developments in Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another part of what is driving this trend is that newly listed companies are increasingly based out of Beijing. This could indicate that one of the prerequisites for a Chinese company to be successful in accessing the U.S. market is the patronage or blessing of Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concentration of power in Beijing does not bode well. Auditors in Beijing are potentially under significantly more political pressure from the Party than those in Hong Kong. Additionally, the partners located in Beijing are also more likely to be active Party members, creating a potential conflict of loyalty when they are auditing a Party-owned enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audit Quality Suffering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP was subject to inspection in 2015 and the PCAOB did not appear to find any issues that made it into the publicly disclosed report. In short, they got a clean bill of health. Their 2018 inspection report, however, had very different results. The PCAOB found serious problems with Marcum BP’s audit of one issuer (likely a Chinese-based issuer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that report the PCAOB identified seven different areas where the issuer was significantly deficient. The lack of sufficient testing to establish effective internal controls over financial reporting (ICFR) featured prominently in the report. According to the PCAOB, “&lt;em&gt;[I]n this audit, the auditor issued an opinion without satisfying its fundamental obligation to obtain reasonable assurance about whether the financial statements were free of material misstatement and the issuer maintained effective IFCR&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was not the only bad news that Marcum BP received from the PCAOB. In September 2019, the PCAOB &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Enforcement/Decisions/Documents/105-2019-023%20-%20MBP.pdf&quot;&gt;fined the firm&lt;/a&gt; $50,000 to the firm for practices in 2013 and 2014 that had undermined auditor independence. Marcum BP had participated in conferences where they had promoted seven of their audit clients to potential investors, creating conflicts concerning their auditor independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum BP was not alone; Marcum LLP also was assessed a $450,000 fine relating to the same conferences. The PCAOB singled out Marcum BP and Marcum LLP for this auditor independence issue, even though Francine Mckenna of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; has &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/the-sec-proposes-to-modernize-auditor&quot;&gt;pointed&lt;/a&gt; out that audit firms have held similar conferences in the past that included audit clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be some other explanation for the apparent “city-swapping” that has nothing to do with the PCAOB inspections. The firm may simply be filling out their forms incorrectly. The have yet to respond to our inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCAOB and the CCP’s directives are directly contradictory, which is why our reports assign every Chinese company a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/&quot;&gt;red flag&lt;/a&gt;. It should not be surprising that auditors are contorting themselves into pretzels to stay in the good graces of the PCAOB and the CCP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also are not surprised that Marcum BP inspection report showed a myriad of problems with one of their clients (likely a Chinese company); the obstacles to having an adequate audit of a Chinese company are significant. We would point out that it is possible that the Chinese affiliates of the Big 4 have the same significant defects in their audits as Marcum BP, but we will never know because they are not subject to inspection by the PCAOB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="City-Swapping" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="China" /><category term="Marcum BP" /><category term="City-Swapping" /><summary type="html">Marcum BP is a joint venture between Marcum LLP and Bernstein &amp;amp; Pinchuk LLP specializing mostly in Chinese clients. Their practice of “city-swapping” raises some interesting questions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Commie%20flag.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Commie%20flag.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">WEX Exemplifies Accounting Challenges that Accompany Mergers</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/wex-exemplifies-accounting-challenges-that-accompany-mergers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WEX Exemplifies Accounting Challenges that Accompany Mergers" /><published>2020-08-03T08:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T08:18:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/wex-exemplifies-accounting-challenges-that-accompany-mergers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/wex-exemplifies-accounting-challenges-that-accompany-mergers/">&lt;p&gt;WEX Inc (WEX) is a company, headquartered in Maine, that provides payment solutions. Over the years they have grown and expanded the number of services that they offer by going on a acquisition/merger spree. They have engaged in at least one merger or acquisition every year since 2015, and they accelerated this trend in 2019 with four mergers or acquisitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mergers have expanded the company, but they have also given them chronic internal control issues, leading to extensive irregularities in their accounting. A brief look at WEX’s &lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/WEX%20Inc.%20-%20WEX%20(20200728).pdf&quot;&gt;Watchdog Report&lt;/a&gt; shows that their recent financial reporting has been riddled with red and yellow flags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WEX%20Flags.png&quot; alt=&quot;WEX Flags.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Ups and Downs of Mergers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appeal of a merger is that it is a relatively easy way to gain market share, reduce competition, and gain economies of scale. Additionally, many companies seek to capture synergistic value, where a firm not only gains the value of the two previously existing companies but also a new value that arises out of the combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies usually experience diminishing returns on their organic growth strategies associated with their core business over time, and that puts a great deal of pressure on companies to come up with alternative strategies to stimulate growth. Companies will often acquire businesses in the hopes that it will provide additional growth, but acquisitions pose their own difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers have waxed and waned in popularity over the last thirty-five years. As a &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/&quot;&gt;rule&lt;/a&gt;, companies are more eager to engage in mergers when the economy is strong/bubbling and are less inclined during harder times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Mergers%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mergers Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acquisition Accounting Challenges&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting scandals are often rooted in a merger or acquisition. The accounting challenges go beyond the technical problems posed by reconciling two different sets of books, it has to do with reconciling two different management cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron/&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; on Cronos Group highlighted the problems that arose because of a clash of cultures arising from a big investment by the tobacco giant Altria in the small Canadian pot wholesaler. But combining cultures is not the potential pitfall. Even when one entity completely devours the other and displaces the management team, as occurred in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;Kraft Heinz&lt;/a&gt;, the imposition of a new corporate culture on an existing structure can create serious challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turmoil in management can lead to problems with internal controls, fostering an environment that allows for incompetence or even fraud. Our research has shown that mergers are associated with management turnover, material weaknesses in the internal controls, restatements, and other reporting irregularities that we quantify in our Gray Swan Event Factor. Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has also shown that companies with a higher Gray Swan Event Factor tend to have lower returns on investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;WEX’s Chronic Internal Control Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WEX began its current acquisition spree in 2015. Since then it has acquired or merged with at least one company every year. In 2019, WEX accelerated this trend by acquiring/merging with four companies. Concurrently, WEX has experienced serious internal control problems and material weaknesses in their financial reporting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WEX%20controls%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;WEX controls chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of the beginning of 2020, WEX appears to have remediated its material weaknesses, but more trouble lies ahead. WEX did not include the four companies it acquired in 2019 in its assessment of its internal controls:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Company acquired Noventis, Inc. on January 24, 2019, Pavestone Capital, LLC on February 14, 2019, Discovery Benefits, Inc. on March 5, 2019, and Go Fuel Card on July 1, 2019. Management excluded these four businesses from its assessment of the effectiveness of the Company’s internal control over financial reporting as of December 31, 2019. These exclusions were in accordance with Securities and Exchange Commission guidance that an assessment of a recently acquired business’s internal control over financial reporting may be omitted from management’s report on internal control over financial reporting in the year of acquisition of the business. These four businesses represented, in aggregate, approximately 8.3% of the Company’s total consolidated assets (excluding goodwill and intangibles, which are included within the scope of the assessment) and 8.9% of total consolidated revenues, as of and for the year ended December 31, 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering WEX’s track record, we can expect many more internal control problems stemming from its 2019 acquisitions.  The potential internal control issues stemming from its four mergers last year have greatly increased the company’s&lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/Gray%20Swan%20Event%20Factor%20for%20WEX%20Inc.%20-%20WEX%20(20200728).pdf&quot;&gt; Gray Swan Event Factor&lt;/a&gt;, which is a metric we use to quantify the risk of an accounting-related problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Pandemic Spoils the Appetite for Acquisitions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers often decline when the economy hits a rough patch, but the current pandemic appears to have decimated Corporate America’s appetite for mergers. We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/&quot;&gt;discussed&lt;/a&gt; this phenomenon when BorgWarner looked like it would back out of its deal with Delphi (although they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.borgwarner.com/newsroom/press-releases/2020/05/06/borgwarner-and-delphi-technologies-enter-into-amendment-to-transaction-agreement&quot;&gt;appear&lt;/a&gt; to have patched things up). After the pandemic struck, WEX &lt;a href=&quot;https://seekingalpha.com/news/3571322-enett-optal-fight-wexs-attempt-to-nix-deal&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; also planned on ditching the mergers it had planned for this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the economy is experiencing this downturn, accounting related risks have loomed larger. WEX gorged itself on mergers in 2019, hopefully an economic recovery will buoy the company when it starts to experience the first signs of indigestion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Mergers" /><category term="featured" /><category term="WEX" /><category term="Mergers" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><summary type="html">WEX Inc (WEX) is a company, headquartered in Maine, that provides payment solutions. Over the years they have grown and expanded the number of services that they offer by going on a acquisition/merger spree. They have engaged in at least one merger or acquisition every year since 2015, and they accelerated this trend in 2019 with four mergers or acquisitions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/WEX%20picture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/WEX%20picture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SEC Comment Letters and Accounting Problems Plague Contura Energy, Inc. “CTRA”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-and-accounting-problems-plague-contura-energy-inc-ctra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEC Comment Letters and Accounting Problems Plague Contura Energy, Inc. “CTRA”" /><published>2020-07-24T12:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T12:19:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-and-accounting-problems-plague-contura-energy-inc-ctra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-and-accounting-problems-plague-contura-energy-inc-ctra/">&lt;p&gt;CTRA is a company that mines and processes coal before selling it to powerplants and steel producers. 2020 has brought some unexpected challenges for all energy producing companies, as demand has fallen sharply. According to the U.S. Energy Information Association, demand for coal is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eia.gov/outlooks/steo/report/coal.php#:\~:text=EIA%20forecasts%20that%20U.S.%20coal%20exports%20will%20decrease,by%2032%25%20to%2063%20MMst.&amp;amp;text=Based%20on%20an%20assumed%20increase,for%20U.S.%20coal%20in%20India.&quot;&gt;down 37%&lt;/a&gt; from last year. But CTRA is not merely struggling with the fallout of the pandemic, there recent disclosures have raised a bevy of red flags related to their accounting and internal controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repetitive SEC Comment Letters Raise a Red Flag&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our friend and occasional guest contributor, Olga Usvyatsky CPA , drew our attention to CTRA’s recent SEC Comment Letters. These letters concern Item 101(c)(1)(vii) of Regulation S-K, which requires a company to disclose the names of any customers that account for more than 10% of revenue, &lt;em&gt;if the loss of that customer would have a materially adverse effect on the company.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CTRA does not disclose the list of its customers, even though one of their clients &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000095010319008988/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;accounted&lt;/a&gt; for 16.7% of revenue, and their top ten consumers account for 60%. When the SEC first asked about this issue in June of 2019, CTRA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000095010319008248/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt; that the market for coal was highly liquid, and therefore the loss of any one customer would not be material because they would easily be replaced. Markets tend to be liquid when demand consistently outpaces supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CTRA does not explain in their comment letter why the market for coal is highly liquid, but we will take them at their word that this is usually the case, even with a limited consumer base. Thereafter CTRA included their dependence on a few large customers in their risk factor section, although they continued to omit the names of its customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remarkably, in May 2020 the SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000000000020003775/filename1.pdf&quot;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;the exact same question&lt;/em&gt; they had asked in June of 2019. The most reasonable explanation for this repetition is that the SEC staff members believe the impact of the coronavirus out to have changed CTRA’s response. Yet CTRA gave this response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Given the fluid nature of the commodity market for coal products sold by the Company, we do not think a loss of any such customer &lt;strong&gt;would have a material adverse effect&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;on the&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;long-term financial results&lt;/strong&gt; or prospects of our business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Company respectfully advises the Staff that &lt;strong&gt;in a customary business environment&lt;/strong&gt; the coal market exhibits high levels of liquidity given the nature of the commodity. Our sales force is experienced in moving coal sales volumes from one account to another as required by market conditions, either with established customers or new customers.&lt;/em&gt;(emphasis added)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two parts of this statement are problematic, so we will take each in turn. The first problem is that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/17/229.101&quot;&gt;regulation&lt;/a&gt; asks for the names of customers if their loss would be material. It does not qualify this requirement by stating that the loss must be material in the “long-term.” Here CTRA qualifies their statement by saying the loss of any one customer would not be material “on the long-term financial results.” But what about the impact right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in a relatively illiquid market the loss of an important customer might not have a material effect in the “long-term.” Could CTRA replace a lost customer within a day? A week? A month? A quarter? A year? A decade? In the “long-term” it is possible that coal power plants will be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/fernandezelizabeth/2020/03/26/the-us-comes-one-step-closer-to-producing-commercial-fusion-power/#43744d8a6a35&quot;&gt;replaced&lt;/a&gt; with fusion power plants. Lots of things can happen if you stretch out your time horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that amid this coronavirus we are not in a “customary business environment.” As stated earlier, demand has fallen over 37% from last year. Cratering demand means that the market is losing its liquidity. We know that the price of coal is falling because of excess supply, making it more difficult for CTRA to resell their coal on similar terms if one of their big customers scales back use or ceases operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also know that CTRA expects this collapse in price to continue for some time in the future. In their latest quarterly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000170471520000021/contura0331202010-q.htm&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, CTRA wrote off $33 million dollars in mines which are not viable at the current price point, and their estimates for the future do not show them recovering:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[D]ue to declines in metallurgical and thermal coal pricing which reduced forecasted margins at certain locations to amounts below those required for full recoverability, the Company determined that indicators of impairment were present for four long-lived asset groups…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just when will things go back to a “customary business environment?” Hopefully, it will in the “long-term.” As for the SEC, they seem satisfied with CTRA’s response since they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000000000020005481/filename1.pdf&quot;&gt;completed&lt;/a&gt; their review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;CTRA’s Parts Ways with KPMG over Internal Control Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, CTRA dismissed their auditor KPMG and replaced them with RSM US LLP. KPMG had given the company an adverse opinion in their annual &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1704715/000170471520000010/contura1231201910-k.htm&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; for 2019. KPMG highlighted material weaknesses in the risk assessment process was ineffective and their staff was not properly trained in certain control procedures. As a result, there are substantial questions concerning the company’s valuations of its coal inventory, as well as what it reported about its procurement process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of proper internal controls greatly increases the risk that the financial statements could be restated due to error or fraud. It also opens the company to potential litigation if the financial statements turn out to be false. Perhaps the best protection that CTRA currently has against litigation is the fact that their share price has already hit rock bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CTRA%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;CTRA chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has hit all energy companies hard, and hopefully the impacts of this virus will be relatively short lived. This may be a great time to buy energy companies if you believe demand will recover over time, and the stock prices will follow. However, investors should be aware of potential accounting issues that can hinder a company’s stock price. With its auditor changes and internal control issues, CTRA is facing far more challenges on its road to recovery than just recovering from the impact of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><category term="CTRA" /><category term="Auditor Change" /><category term="Coronavirus" /><summary type="html">CTRA is a company that mines and processes coal before selling it to powerplants and steel producers. 2020 has brought some unexpected challenges for all energy producing companies, as demand has fallen sharply. According to the U.S. Energy Information Association, demand for coal is down 37% from last year. But CTRA is not merely struggling with the fallout of the pandemic, there recent disclosures have raised a bevy of red flags related to their accounting and internal controls.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CTRA%20picture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CTRA%20picture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Party is Over at “CRON”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Party is Over at “CRON”" /><published>2020-07-17T14:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-17T14:56:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/party-over-at-cron/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When CRON &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000030/q3exhibit991fs.htm&quot;&gt;restated&lt;/a&gt; the third quarter results for 2019, it attributed the restatement to “accounting errors.” Accounting errors? No kidding! Over a quarter of the company’s supposed revenue went up in smoke.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cronos Group, Inc “CRON” is headquartered in Canada and sells cannabis and its derivative products wholesale. They sell the “medicinal” kind of cannabis in Canada, Israel, and Colombia, where it is legal. And in the U.S., they sell CBD oil and other cannabis derivatives that contain negligible amounts of THC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON was listed on the Nasdaq in May of 2018 and was initially listed as a foreign entity with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;Emerging Growth Company&lt;/a&gt; (EGC) status. Last March, the tobacco giant Altria &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000117184319001610/exh_991.htm&quot;&gt;invested&lt;/a&gt; $1.8 billion in CRON. Under the terms of the deal Altria received 45% of the stock with a warrant to purchase another 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Altria’s cash and valuable experience, CRON seemed poised to dominate the pot market, but there was a catch. Altria’s investment meant that starting in 2020, CRON’s accounting would be subject to more scrutiny. They would no longer qualify as an EGC, or as foreign filer, meaning their accounting would need to comply with GAAP and their auditor KPMG would be required to test their internal controls throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON’s accounting did not hold up well to the extra scrutiny. In March, CRON restated revenue for 2019 and revealed material weaknesses in their internal controls. As can be seen from our Gray Swan Event Factor table, these revelations indicate that CRON will face significant challenges going forward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CRON%20GSEF.png&quot; alt=&quot;CRON GSEF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Restatement Cancels Revenue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 2nd, CRON filed an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000012/cronos12b-25.htm&quot;&gt;incomplete&lt;/a&gt; annual report, citing an internal effort to properly account for revenue from certain wholesale transactions. On March 17th, CRON &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000017/pressrelease-200317.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that it would need to restate its previously issued financial information by canceling C$7.6 million (approximately $5.6 million U.S.) in recorded sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their unaudited 2019 third quarter results, CRON had claimed to have brought in C$31,111 million in gross revenue (approximately $23 million in U.S. dollars). After revealing that over $5 million in sales &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;never occurred&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, they reported that their annual gross revenues were only $25.6 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When CRON &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000030/q3exhibit991fs.htm&quot;&gt;restated&lt;/a&gt; the third quarter results from 2019, it attributed the problem to “accounting errors… due to three wholesale transactions… that were inappropriately accounted for as revenue.” Accounting errors? No kidding! Over a quarter of the company’s supposed revenue a at that time simply did not exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to believe management’s contention that this overstatement was due to an “accounting error” and not outright manipulation and fraud. After all, it beggars belief that the CFO and CEO would be unaware of the details of these &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; wholesale transactions that accounted &lt;em&gt;for a quarter&lt;/em&gt; of the company’s revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;EGCs Internal Controls and Material Weaknesses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON brought on KPMG in May 2018 after it was listed on the Nasdaq. The management at CRON probably wanted to increase investor confidence by hiring a Big 4 firm with lots of experience. But as an EGC, CRON did not have to comply with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;SOX 404(b)&lt;/a&gt;, so KPMG did not test the company’s internal controls throughout the year or offer an opinion of the effectiveness of those controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all changed in 2020, when CRON lost its EGC status after Altria’s investment. The internal investigation that eventually revealed these “accounting errors” was conducted at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000012/cronos12b-25.htm&quot;&gt;direction&lt;/a&gt; of the Audit Committee, indicating that KPMG may have discovered the suspicious transactions while testing the internal controls and alerted the Audit Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KPMG also filed a Critical Audit Matter (CAM) for the revenue recognition related to the company’s wholesale purchases. Auditors are required to file CAMs in their annual report to disclose when a matter requires particularly challenging, complex, or subjective judgements. Investors should pay attention to CAMs because they indicate which numbers in the annual report may be “subjective,” and therefore easier to manipulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, KPMG identified three material weaknesses in the internal controls for the financial reporting of CRON. The weaknesses related to risk assessment, lack of segregation between purchase and sale responsibilities, and an inability to ensure that “non-routine transactions” that &lt;em&gt;deviated from contract terms&lt;/em&gt; were properly authorized and recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Did CRON Add Over $5 Million with an “Accounting Error”?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its CAM disclosure, KPMG specifically pointed to non-monetary transactions where CRON simultaneously purchased and sold inventory with a vendor. Cron would trade dried cannabis flowers for cannabis resin in a “non-monetary transaction.” The company states that no revenue should be recognized from these transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we read the tea leaves, it appears that someone at CRON engaged in three “non-routine transactions” with their vendor, deviating from the terms of the sales contract and recording large amounts of revenue from the transactions, when they actually were non-monetary “trades” that raised no revenue. Additionally, whomever was responsible for this apparently did not record the transaction properly or notify the CEO or CFO of what they were doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bizarrely, the CFO and CEO didn’t notice or ask any questions, which is weird because these non-monetary transactions would not have brought in any new cash, even though they apparently accounted for $5 million in gross sales. The SEC seems interested in how this could have happened; they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/exclusive-pot-company-cronos-receives-sec-inquiry-2020-03-19?mod=bnbh&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; asked CRON to preserve documents concerning the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corporate Governance Problems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a merger, there can be all sorts of problems that arise when bringing together two different management teams. Altria’s investment created a similar problem at CRON. Altria &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000119312519076836/d690389dex992.htm&quot;&gt;added&lt;/a&gt; four new members to the board and brought in Jeffery Barbato as CFO in April 2019. The first “accounting error” occurred in the second quarter of 2019 so that it was Altria’s Barbato that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000156459019030406/cron-ex994_7.htm&quot;&gt;certified&lt;/a&gt; both of the quarterly statements containing over $5 million in “accounting errors”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also interesting that Bruce Gates, added to the board by Altria and Chairman of the Compensation Committee, resigned the same day that the restatement was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1656472/000165647220000019/form8kb.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt;. If that wasn’t fishy enough, the explanation for his departure was that he was “going to focus on other increased professional responsibilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON may have been happy to take Altria’s money, but Altria is a big tobacco company, not a charity. The team members Altria brought in may have been putting a lot of pressure on CRON to accelerate growth. That pressure, coupled with inadequate internal controls, may have created the perfect environment for “accounting errors.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current situation for the top brass of CRON is untenable, expect major changes this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;KPMG Cleaning up the Accounting…For a Price&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON has given over $2 million to KPMG for its services in 2020. That’s 7% of revenue! In total, they have spent &lt;a href=&quot;https://seekingalpha.com/article/4345058-cronos-group-inc-cron-ceo-mike-gorenstein-on-q1-2020-results-earnings-call-transcript?page=6&quot;&gt;$4.4 million&lt;/a&gt; on the internal review costs related to the restatement. It is likely that they will spend much more as the remediation efforts continue and the litigation costs pile up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One bright spot for CRON is that KPMG appears to have helped reduce the complexity of CRON’s disclosures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CRON%20Complexity%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;CRON Complexity Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial disclosures decrease in complexity when companies use fewer custom XBRL tags. It appears that CRON has made an effort in 2020 to put their disclosures into more standard and accessible language. It is likely that KPMG has been assisting them in this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRON is a posterchild for the why the U.S. should reconsider allowing Emerging Growth Companies to forego the SOX 404(b) auditor attestation requirement. We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;discussed&lt;/a&gt; this problem when looking at Luckin’s fraud. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, when the SEC further scaled back the number of companies required to comply with SOX 404(b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the auditor is not testing the internal controls of a company throughout the year, there is very little incentive for management to develop proper internal controls over financial reporting. This creates the perfect environment for the manipulation of financial results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If investors want to protect themselves from potential machinations by management, they should demand that their companies get an auditor to attest to the internal controls, even when they are exempt from SOX 404(b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Watchdog Spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Emerging Growth Companies" /><category term="CRON" /><category term="Errors" /><summary type="html">When CRON restated the third quarter results for 2019, it attributed the restatement to “accounting errors.” Accounting errors? No kidding! Over a quarter of the company’s supposed revenue went up in smoke.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/next-green-wave-JPI6SKrd-Rw-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/next-green-wave-JPI6SKrd-Rw-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Slacker Standards: SEC Exempts Even More Companies From 404(b)</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slacker Standards: SEC Exempts Even More Companies From 404(b)" /><published>2020-07-14T07:29:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-14T07:29:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is scant evidence that 404(b) is scaring companies away from the public marketplace, but there is evidence that the sort of companies that just got an exception from 404(b) were the ones who needed it most.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC issued a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/rules/final/2020/34-88365.pdf&quot;&gt;rule&lt;/a&gt; that took effect on April 27th, 2020 that exempted even more companies from the auditor attestation requirement of SOX Section 404(b). The SEC accomplished this by adjusting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/rules/final/2020/34-88365.pdf&quot;&gt;definitions&lt;/a&gt; of “accelerated” and “large accelerated” filers. We have &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt; discussed 404(b) when looking at Luckin Coffee, and we decried how the loosening of 404(b) by the JOBS Act allowed Luckin’s fraud to go undetected. But this new regulation merits a deeper discussion of 404(b) and its implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) was legislation passed in the wake of the Enron and WorldCom scandals. Its purpose was to end corporate fraud empowering watchdogs and gatekeepers to restrain the impulse of management to manipulate financial reporting. One of the key measures was 404(b), which required &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; publicly traded company to have an independent auditor attest that the “internal controls” of the company were effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;internal controls&lt;/a&gt;” are the first line of defense against fraud and human error. Management is supposed to install a system that aids employees in routinely recording the economic activity of the company in a way that is both accurate and comprehensible. The controls should also ensure that neither employees nor management misuses company assets or manipulates results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every Watchdog Report flags potential issues raised with regards to the internal controls raised by the independent auditor or management. We have discussed them before in our examinations of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg/&quot;&gt;HFFG&lt;/a&gt;. However, Watchdog Reports do not currently flag companies that are not required to comply with 404(b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 404(b) attestation requires the independent auditor to do some due diligence. The auditors must test the internal controls of the company throughout the year, instead of just reviewing financial statements at the end of the year. This is a time-intensive process and estimates by the SEC put the average cost at over $200,000 a year. This process improves internal controls and creates a powerful deterrent against fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whittling Away at 404(b)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that 404(b) is a significant regulatory burden. When the measures were first passed, Small Reporting Companies, (SRCs) with less than $75 million in public float were not required to implement 404(b) right away but were given an extension. The extension was made permanent by the Dodd Frank Act in 2010 so that SRCs would &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; be required to get a 404(b)auditor attestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, President Obama signed the bipartisan JOBS Act. This bill created a new classification, the Emerging Growth Company (EGC). A company can qualify as an EGC for up to five years after going public if it has less than 1 billion in revenue and less than 700 million in public float. A company that fits the criteria does not have to comply with certain regulations, including 404(b). According to Audit Analytics, 1,394, or around 20% of the 6,644 publicly registered companies qualify for EGC status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GAO put out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gao.gov/assets/660/655710.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; in 2013 using Audit Analytics’ data to conduct a review of 404(b) and found that the auditor attestation improved internal controls and decreased the chances of damaging restatements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LK%20GAO%20EGC%206.16.png&quot; alt=&quot;LK GAO EGC 6.16.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now under President Trump, the SEC has changed the definitions of “accelerated” and “large accelerated” filers to reduce the number of companies that must comply with 404(b). This change is commensurate with a change in the definition of Smaller Reporting Companies that was &lt;a href=&quot;https://corpgov.law.harvard.edu/2018/07/21/amended-definition-of-smaller-reporting-company/&quot;&gt;made&lt;/a&gt; in 2018. The result of all these rule changes is a complex set of classifications, where the status of a company changes based on its revenue and public float. This table from an &lt;a href=&quot;https://corpgov.law.harvard.edu/2020/04/04/secs-carve-out-from-sox-404b-for-low-revenue-companies/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; published by Harvard Law is the best representation we have found of the current state of the classifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SRC%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;SRC Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies that are classified as Accelerated filers or as Large Accelerated filers are required to comply with 404(b). The companies that are most affected by this new rule change are companies with relatively low revenue, who nevertheless carry up to $700 million in public float, because they no longer need to comply with 404(b). The SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://corpgov.law.harvard.edu/2018/07/21/amended-definition-of-smaller-reporting-company/&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; that 966 companies would be affected by the rule change, with 161 of them having revenues under $100 million but public float between $250-700 million. The SEC Chair Jay Clayton (who recently announced his departure), specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/sec-proposes-eliminating-auditor-checks-on-controls-at-low-revenue-biotechs-2019-05-09?mod=hp_econ&quot;&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt; bio-tech and healthcare companies as intended beneficiaries of the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New Rule Defies Good Sense&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new carveouts are designed to encourage more private companies to enter the public market by reducing regulatory burdens that may deter some from entering. However, there is scant evidence that 404(b) is scaring companies away from the public marketplace, but there is evidence that the sort of companies that just got an exception from 404(b) were the ones who needed it most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFOs were asked to name the obstacles that were keeping them from going public; the CFOs &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooleypubco.com/2017/06/26/whats-up-with-the-declining-number-of-ipos/&quot;&gt;provided&lt;/a&gt; all sorts of answers, however, concerns about regulatory compliance were at the &lt;em&gt;bottom&lt;/em&gt; of the list. In contrast, a 2011 survey of CEOs of public companies that found 92% stated that compliance costs were a significant barrier to completing an IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What explains this disparity? Compliance with 404(b) is both expensive and time-consuming, and since these companies were &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; public, the CEOs may just have been griping. This is a bit like asking a graduate if the loans they took out for their degree was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a strong narrative that burdensome regulations have contributed to a decline in IPOs, but there are other &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooleypubco.com/2017/06/26/whats-up-with-the-declining-number-of-ipos/&quot;&gt;probable&lt;/a&gt; explanations. Nor is it reasonable to assume that the high watermark for public companies in 1996 represents a benchmark of a healthy marketplace that we should strive towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francine Mckenna wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/sec-proposes-eliminating-auditor-checks-on-controls-at-low-revenue-biotechs-2019-05-09?mod=hp_econ&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; for MarketWatch in 2019 that highlighted data from Audit Analytics indicating that the 404(b) requirement for these soon-to-be-exempted companies provided a lot of value for investors. Companies with revenues under $100 million received 176 adverse opinions on their internal controls from their independent auditors from 2014-2019, that represented 70% of adverse opinions for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; public companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main beneficiary of this new rule is pharmaceutical companies that do not have much revenue but are attracting lots of public investment. The losers are investors who have now lost an important watchdog in these pharmaceutical start-ups. This will only enable companies to play fast and loose with investors money as they doll themselves up to spur an acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final Note on the SEC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a split on this rule, with Commissioner Lee dissenting. She stated, “Eliminating the auditor attestation removes a critical gatekeeping function that we know works to improve the reliability of financial reporting for investors.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably is not the last time the SEC will choose to reduce the scope of 404(b), since there appears to be broad bipartisan support for rolling back the protections it offers for investors. Commissioner Pierce is in favor of making 404(b) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-peirce-accelerated-filer-2020-03-12&quot;&gt;optional&lt;/a&gt; for all companies. If the SEC continues to strip away the burdens placed on corporations by Sarbanes Oxley, it will strip away the corresponding protections for investors as well. The SEC would do well to remember its job is to &lt;em&gt;enforce&lt;/em&gt; the laws passed by Congress, including Sarbanes Oxley, not to minimize them by changing the definitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="Sarbanes Oxley" /><category term="404(b)" /><summary type="html">There is scant evidence that 404(b) is scaring companies away from the public marketplace, but there is evidence that the sort of companies that just got an exception from 404(b) were the ones who needed it most.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SEC%20404(b).jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SEC%20404(b).jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Watchdog Spotlight on HF Food Group “HFFG”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watchdog Spotlight on HF Food Group “HFFG”" /><published>2020-07-07T10:07:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-07T10:07:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watchdog-spotlight-on-hf-food-group-hffg/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In March HFFG was accused of siphoning off investors money to buy a stable of super-cars, but their problems started well before those allegations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG is a food distributor that primarily serves Asian restaurants in the Southeast, Pacific, and Mountain West regions of the U.S. HFFG currently has the dubious distinction of having our highest Gray Swan Event Factor (GSEF) score by far at 17.43%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with our GSEF score, we calculate it by estimating the likelihood of certain “gray swan” events, and then estimate the potential impact of those events. Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; has demonstrated that this risk has not been properly priced into the marketplace, mostly because no one is doing the due diligence necessary to account for it. In fact, most firms rely on the analysts &lt;em&gt;selling the stock&lt;/em&gt; to conduct this research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/HFFG%20GSEF%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;HFFG GSEF Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cascading Bad News for HFFG&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG seems to be suffering from a series of escalating problems. They reported serious material weaknesses in their financial reporting for FY 2018, just a few months before announcing a merger with B&amp;amp;R Global (B&amp;amp;R), another larger Chinese restaurant food distributor for an ostensible value of $400 million. B&amp;amp;R’s shareholders were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919021487/fooh20191104_8k.htm&quot;&gt;awarded&lt;/a&gt; approximately 60% of the ownership of the surviving company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, the company had to contend with the coronavirus and a scathing &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/hf-foods/&quot;&gt;short-seller report&lt;/a&gt; by Hindenburg Research, as well as a securities lawsuit based on that report. HFFG was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920010302/fooh20200510_nt10q.htm&quot;&gt;late&lt;/a&gt; in releasing its first quarter results, and when those &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920011101/fooh20200331_10q.htm&quot;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; came out, they included a whopping $338 million impairment to goodwill. Before the impairment, the company had a goodwill balance of $406 million, which represented almost the entire &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919014692/fooh20190719_prem14a.htm&quot;&gt;value&lt;/a&gt; of the consideration provided by HFFG in the merger. This impairment wiped out approximately 83% of that value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Restatement Incoming?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our statistical analysis, HFFG has a nearly 60% chance of a filing a restatement in the next 12 months. One of the biggest factors in that calculation is recurring material weaknesses in HFFG’s financial reporting. HFFG reported serious material weaknesses in both their annual reports for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919006198/fooh20181231_10k.htm&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920005276/fooh20191231_10k.htm&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;. In 2018, they disclosed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The material weakness related to the &lt;strong&gt;deficiency in the ability of our in-house accounting professionals to generate financial statements in the form required by applicable SEC requirements&lt;/strong&gt;. Control deficiencies are related to the lack of proper documentation to evidence the review of customer orders and purchase orders, and lack of proper documentation to evidence customers’ acknowledgement of transaction amounts and account balances&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the annual report for 2019, the HFFG admitted that little progress had been made, “&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the Company does not have in-house accounting personnel with sufficient knowledge of US GAAP and SEC reporting experiences&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find this strange.  Why haven’t they hired someone over the past year with the ability to follow GAAP? Is it so difficult to find an experienced and qualified person to lead the in-house accounting staff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also note that because HFFG is classified as an Emerging Growth Company, its auditor does not offer an opinion as to the effectiveness of its internal controls. But considering that HFFG’s auditors do not understand how to apply Generally Accepted Accounting Principles, we can venture a guess as to what their auditor’s opinion would be if they gave one. HFFG’s problems are a great example of how the lack of the SOX 404(b) requirement lowers the quality of internal controls, which we have written about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-fraud-enabled-by-slack-standards/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If HFFG can hire someone who understands GAAP, it is likely that they will need to revise the financial results from prior years. They will also need to simplify the financial reporting. This relatively small food distributor makes unusually complex accounting disclosures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/HFFG%20Complexity%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;HFFG Complexity Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC has made a serious effort to make all company disclosures &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/page/osdhistoryandrulemaking&quot;&gt;accessible&lt;/a&gt; to the public by requiring the use of standardized formats and standardized language. As part of this effort, the SEC also requires companies to submit these filings in an XBRL format, so it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/structureddata/what-is-structured-data&quot;&gt;simpler&lt;/a&gt; for software to provide meaningful analysis without too much manual work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a practical matter, when a company makes a filing, they mark it with a set of standardized XBRL tags. However, sometimes a company needs to use “custom” XBRL tags because their data does not fit into the standard language or format. This graph represents how often a company introduces these “custom” tags in comparison with their industry peers. A relatively high number of custom tags indicate that a company’s disclosures are complex and opaque.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extensive Related Party Transactions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG’s material weaknesses also related to the review of their purchase orders. This potentially raises revenue recognition questions, raising a possibility that someone at the company could be engaging in accounting shenanigans. We have written about this issue before, when discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;Under Armour’s&lt;/a&gt; potential channel stuffing issues. Although not proof of manipulation, it is very concerning that HFFG has a “&lt;em&gt;lack of proper documentation to evidence the review of customer orders and purchase orders&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG also has a high number of related party transactions. HFFG disclosed that it made sales of over $19 million and made purchases of over $40 million in related party transactions in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920005276/fooh20191231_10k.htm&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt; alone. HFFG also recorded many other types of related party transactions, including advances both to related suppliers and from related customers, a $55 million term loan guarantee, and related lease transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the company loaned over $8 million to entities either owned by the Chairman- and co-CEO Zhou Min Ni or his son; Ni initially guaranteed the loans before he “purchased” them with over 632,746 shares. But Ni also had to put an additional 208,806 shares into escrow, and he will lose all or part of those shares if the average closing price of the stock is below $13.30 for the 250 days leading up to September 30th, 2020. Considering that the stock price dropped below $13.30 in March and has stayed consistently below $10.00 since, Ni has a very strong incentive to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that will make the share price recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/HFFG%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;HFFG Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Accusations by Hindenburg Research&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindenburg Research is an activist short-seller in the mode of Muddy Waters founded by &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/about-us/&quot;&gt;Nate Andersen&lt;/a&gt;. In March, this short seller published a report on HFFG which included assertions based on public information as well as non-public information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core claim made by Hindenburg was that the merger between HFFG and B&amp;amp;R was not conducted at “arm’s length” as stated by the relevant &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774919014692/fooh20190719_prem14a.htm&quot;&gt;disclosures&lt;/a&gt;, but that both of these companies were previously part of the same Chinese investment group. Unfortunately, many of underlying documents supporting Hindenburg’s contention are in Chinese and are not easily verified. One interesting fact that seems to support Hindenburg’s assertion is that the two companies were neatly divided into east and west divisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key assertion in Hindenburg’s report is that the chairman and co-CEO Zhou Min Ni has been using the related party transactions to inappropriately siphon money out of the company. Hindenburg asserts that background checks of these related parties reveal that no fewer than 17 super-cars with total value of over $3.5 million were registered to these entities. Hindenburg also provides photos, supposedly from the Instagram account of Ni’s son Raymond, of Raymond showing off this collection of super-cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this report was published, the Rosen Law Firm filed a class action Complaint against HFFG in the Central California District Court. The complaint closely mirrors the report by Hindenburg research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The C-Suite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporate governance problems are often at the root of accounting-related issues. Chaos in the C-suite translates into chaos throughout the organization. HFFG has had an unusual structure post-merger. Zhou Min Ni and Xiao Mou “Peter” Zhang, formerly the heads of HFFG and B&amp;amp;R respectively, are now co-CEOs. Adding to the confusion, three different people have held the office of CFO at HFFG since last March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers often hurt companies in the short run because the difficulty of combining systems and cultures cost more than the “synergies.” Even if both companies were previously affiliated, as Hindenberg Research asserts, the fact that Peter Zhang and Zhou Min Ni are sharing the position of CEO will raise a plethora of issues. Additionally, HFFG’s inability to develop effective internal controls for the past two years does not bode well for achieving “synergies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Goodwill Impairment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;anticipated&lt;/a&gt; that the outbreak of the coronavirus would cause many companies to test their goodwill, and that this would lead to a rash of impairments. We also anticipated that some companies would disingenuously use the pandemic as cover to write off junk goodwill. So, did HFFG write off the goodwill because they needed to, or did they write it off because it was a convenient excuse?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG’s $338 million impairment may not be earth shattering in an absolute sense, but relative to its size it is exceptionally large. When Kraft Heinz wrote off $15 billion in intangible assets and goodwill, that wiped out about 12% of the company’s assets and reduced equity by 23%. By comparison, HFFG’s impairment wiped out 35% of the total assets, and eliminated over half of the equity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this merger was consummated in December 2019. At that time HFFG paid a premium for B&amp;amp;R and recorded over $400 million in goodwill from the deal. However, the assumptions underpinning the purchase price have changed, as 83% of that value has now been erased. But was this justified?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all depends on whether you trust management to perform accurate valuations. Valuations are more of an art than a science because they require a great deal of estimates and assumptions about the future. But how can you properly evaluate the future during a black swan event? When they were conducting their valuations in March and April, they did not know what the effects of the coronavirus would be, nor how long those effects would persist. The effects could end soon, or they may &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the irony, the pandemic is so disruptive that it constitutes a triggering event, causing every company to test their goodwill for impairment, but it is also so disruptive that it makes the future predictions critical for a proper valuations &lt;em&gt;highly subjective&lt;/em&gt;. If Hindenburg’s assertions about self-dealing turn out to be accurate, then it would be reasonable to believe that there was an ulterior motive for this impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did HFFG make reasonable assumptions in their valuation estimates? We cannot be sure, but since their financial reporting is unreliable, given their lack of expertise with GAAP and chronic internal control issues, we find it likely that these valuations are riddled with problematic assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HFFG has had a difficult year so far. The merger certainly has posed a difficult set of challenges, made worse by the management team’s material weaknesses in their financial reporting. They are already enduring one securities lawsuit and have made a massive impairment. But if our research is correct this is only the opening salvo and 2020 probably has a lot more in store for HFFG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog send John Cheffers, our Director of Research, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Watchdog Spotlight" /><category term="featured" /><category term="HFFG" /><category term="Material Weaknesses" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="Impairment" /><summary type="html">In March HFFG was accused of siphoning off investors money to buy a stable of super-cars, but their problems started well before those allegations.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Chinese%20Food.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Chinese%20Food.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>