<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-10T09:33:36-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Cyber Incidents Continue to Rise</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cyber-incidents-continue-to-rise/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyber Incidents Continue to Rise" /><published>2021-08-10T09:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-10T09:17:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cyber-incidents-continue-to-rise</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cyber-incidents-continue-to-rise/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cybersecurity Incident and Litigation Review 2021&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity has gone from a niche concern to a hot topic in the D&amp;amp;O insurance world. A cybersecurity breach can be extremely disruptive to any business, but (adding injury to injury) these breaches can also be the source of damaging class action litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog Research we analyze information disclosed by public companies, including information on cybersecurity incidents, Securities Class Action lawsuits, and disclosure controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research presented here relates to Nasdaq and NYSE listed public companies and is derived from our report “&lt;em&gt;Cybersecurity Incidents and Litigation: 2021&lt;/em&gt;,” by Joseph Burke, PhD, Joseph Yarborough, PhD, and John Cheffers and primarily based on data from Audit Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overview&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began by looking at incidents that occurred at companies listed on the NYSE and Nasdaq over the past ten years, and the growth rate of cybersecurity incidents is alarming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CyberImage_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;CyberImage_1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite concerns that cybersecurity incidents would increase during the pandemic as businesses moved more of their operations online, total reported cybersecurity incidents fell during 2020. However, through July 2021, there have already been 106 reported cybersecurity incidents, putting 2021 on pace for a record breaking year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you segregate the companies by size, you can see that risk is most concentrated for large companies. Large companies, those with a market capitalization of $10 billion or more, are the population most at risk for a cyberattack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CyberImage_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;CyberImage_2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting development this year is that Ransomware attacks and Unauthorized Access attacks have become much more common in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CyberImage_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;CyberImage_3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cybersecurity Securities Class Actions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cyberbreach at a company creates all sorts of problems, including litigation. Even though the number of cyber security incidents have increased dramatically, the number of cyber-related lawsuits has not followed suit. As we can see here, the probability that a public company is named as a defendant in a cybersecurity related suit has remained very low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CyberImage_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;CyberImage_4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our review of these cases indicates that it is often difficult for the plaintiffs in these cases to allege specific damages based on a mere breach of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the fact that a company suffered a cybersecurity breach, even a serious one, will not necessarily prove that the company failed to take reasonable cybersecurity measures (see the dismissal of the suit against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2021/06/articles/securities-litigation/marriott-data-breach-related-securities-and-derivative-suits-both-dismissed/&quot;&gt;Marriott&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclosure Controls Concerning IT Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 302 of the Sarbanes Oxley Act of 2002 (SOX), public companies must assess and report on their disclosure controls on their quarterly and annual reports. As part of their SOX 302 assessments, companies have increasingly included discussions of information technology (IT) and cybersecurity issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CyberImage_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;CyberImage_5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Audit Analytics, which gathers and categorizes this information, an IT issue is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[D]eficient program controls, software programs/implementation, segregation of duties associated with personnel having access to computer accounting or financial reporting records and related problems with oversight/access to electronic data/programs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A disclosure control relating to IT can also be an early warning signal for cybersecurity issues. For example, PayPal has only issued one disclosure control in the last five years, and it was on October 24, 2017 and related to IT issues. On December, 1st, 2017, PayPal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foxbusiness.com/markets/paypal-says-personal-data-may-be-compromised-for-1-6-million-tio-users&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that it had suffered a major cybersecurity breach related to their acquisition of TIO. This led to a securities class action suit that was eventually dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chance of being involved in a cybersecurity securities class action lawsuit is still relatively low, but it is increasing rapidly. Additionally, the risk profile is far higher for large companies, which are more likely to be a victim of a cybersecurity incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies are also apparently increasing their scrutiny of their own systems, as the number of companies that have identified IT issues in their disclosure controls has increased significantly over the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, cybersecurity litigation remains relatively rare, despite the increases in attacks. If company boards wish to mitigate their risk of being victimized twice (by hackers and by lawyers), then they need to learn from their successful peers and make wise and strategic decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about our research or the report this blog is derived from, then please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  The underlying report is currently available for $499. You can pair this report with a snapshot of the Cybersecurity Incident data ($1500)  for $1749.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Cybersecurity" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Cybersecurity" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Disclosure Controls" /><summary type="html">Cybersecurity Incident and Litigation Review 2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CyberImage_2-1f3c38.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CyberImage_2-1f3c38.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Concern is Warranted: Warrants as Liabilities vs. Equities</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/concern-is-warranted-warrants-as-liabilities-vs-equities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Concern is Warranted: Warrants as Liabilities vs. Equities" /><published>2021-08-05T12:42:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-05T12:42:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/concern-is-warranted-warrants-as-liabilities-vs-equities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/concern-is-warranted-warrants-as-liabilities-vs-equities/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The SEC issued accounting guidelines that pumped the breaks on the white-hot SPAC market and caused many SPACs restate their financials.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SPAC, also known as blank-check company, is a stock created by sponsors that raises money in an initial public offering with no underlying business. Investors entrust their money to one of these sponsors, instead of to an operating company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;Typically&lt;/a&gt;, the SPAC must use its cash within two years to buy a private company (in a de-SPAC transaction), or refund the money to investors. Generally, investors don’t know what the acquisition target will be until the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reserve now, buy later&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SPAC IPO is usually structured to offer investors a unit of securities consisting of (1) shares of common stock and (2) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investor.gov/introduction-investing/general-resources/news-alerts/alerts-bulletins/investor-bulletins/what-you&quot;&gt;warrants&lt;/a&gt;. A warrant is a contract that gives the holder the right to purchase in the future a certain number of additional shares of common stock at a certain price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lawcast.com/2021/06/25/a-resolution-for-spac-warrant-accounting/&quot;&gt;terms of warrants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; vary greatly across different SPACs. In general, sponsors receive the more advantageous private placement warrants and outside shareholders receive less-desirable public warrants. A SPAC itself can redeem warrants pursuant to their terms. Warrants are often exercised when the merger target is announced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A liability, not an asset&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, the SEC issued &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/accounting-reporting-warrants-issued-spacs?utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_source=govdelivery#_ftnref6&quot;&gt;accounting guidelines&lt;/a&gt; stating that SPACS must consider warrants, often previously classified as equities of the entity, to be liabilities. This is because an outside third party could make a cash tender offer, and the SPAC would be obliged to give all warrant holders cash for their warrants. The classification of warrants also depends on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pkfod.com/insights/spac-warrant-valuation-insights-and-considerations/&quot;&gt;value&lt;/a&gt; on redemption; the value can vary greatly according to the terms of the SPAC’s IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people consider this an unnecessary burden. “In reality, the company will never pay cash because the warrant holder will exercise [the warrant] and get the equity. That’s more valuable to them.” said Harris &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfodive.com/news/spac-warrants-liability-change-SEC-CFO-accounting-antoniades/598655/&quot;&gt;Antoniades&lt;/a&gt;, managing director of global investment bank and advisory firm Stout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workarounds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfodive.com/news/whats-behind-the-secs-spac-warrant-concerns/601658/&quot;&gt;Smith and Tomov&lt;/a&gt; delineated many of the convoluted provisions necessary to classify warrants as derivatives, a form of equity. “In many of the deals, the warrants don’t meet an exception in FASB’s accounting standards for derivatives. As a result, they’re misclassified as equity”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, legal (&lt;a href=&quot;https://lawcast.com/2021/06/25/a-resolution-for-spac-warrant-accounting/&quot;&gt;Laura Anthony&lt;/a&gt;, Esq. and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitecase.com/publications/alert/clarity-emerges-aftermath-sec-statement-spac-warrant-accounting-roadmap-changes&quot;&gt;Joel Rubenstein et al&lt;/a&gt;. of White and Case, LLC.), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pkfod.com/insights/spac-warrant-valuation-insights-and-considerations/&quot;&gt;financial&lt;/a&gt; (Noam Hirschberger, CFA and Eric Gelb, CPA of PKF O’Connor Davies) groups also addressed the fine points of the SEC statement. They came up with several suggestions on how current SPAC agreements might be amended, or how future SPAC contracts might be worded, so that warrants could indeed be classified as equities of the entity rather than liabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One solution would require the sponsors to give up some of the considerable financial advantages they enjoy in holding private placement warrants. It remains to be seen if the sponsors would be willing to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another approach is to simply &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/business/wall-street-grapples-with-new-spac-equity-contracts-after-regulator-crackdown-2021-06-08/&quot;&gt;not include warrants&lt;/a&gt; in the SPAC’s IPO. That’s how flamboyant SPAC proponent Chamath Palihapitiya handled his latest series of biotech SPAC IPOs in June. Alternatively, new contracts might include rights agreements, commonly used in Europe, rather than warrants, but rights agreements are considered riskier for the investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demanding a recount&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the SEC ruling has caused a flurry of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accountingtoday.com/news/sec-warnings-on-spacs-dampen-deals-and-accounting-services&quot;&gt;new filings&lt;/a&gt;, as almost three-quarters of existing SPACs scrambled to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-wave-of-earnings-restatements-slams-a-hot-market-11625218380&quot;&gt;amend their statements&lt;/a&gt; to conform to the new guidelines. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;new standards&lt;/a&gt; are forcing companies to redo the initial IPO valuation and analyze the value of the warrants each quarter, rather than just at the start of the SPAC. They will also have to use more complex valuation models, said Antoniades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the ruling has caused a huge &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.institutionalinvestor.com/article/b1s46zt9m0tj4c/IPO-Market-Cools-as-SPACs-Face-Downturn&quot;&gt;drop&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-wave-of-earnings-restatements-slams-a-hot-market-11625218380&quot;&gt;number&lt;/a&gt; of SPACs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/business/wall-street-grapples-with-new-spac-equity-contracts-after-regulator-crackdown-2021-06-08/&quot;&gt;created&lt;/a&gt; (from 298 January-March 2021 to just 32 in April and May 2021), and fueled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfodive.com/news/spac-warrants-liability-change-SEC-CFO-accounting-antoniades/598655/&quot;&gt;speculation&lt;/a&gt; both that such was the SEC’s intent, and that the IPO market may shift away from SPACs and back to traditional IPOs. However, after an initial &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-wave-of-earnings-restatements-slams-a-hot-market-11625218380&quot;&gt;tumble&lt;/a&gt;, the market appears to have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitecase.com/publications/alert/clarity-emerges-aftermath-sec-statement-spac-warrant-accounting-roadmap-changes&quot;&gt;shrugged off&lt;/a&gt; the reclassification, and value of existing SPACs has not plunged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC has issued new guidelines requiring SPACs to classify or reclassify warrants as liabilities. This means they have to appear on balance sheets quarterly rather than only once, and to undergo a more complex valuation process. This and other recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/unsafe-to-mislead/&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; from the SEC has put the brakes on a previously red-hot SPAC market.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>elise_rose</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Warrants" /><category term="Restatements" /><summary type="html">The SEC issued accounting guidelines that pumped the breaks on the white-hot SPAC market and caused many SPACs restate their financials.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Punch%20Pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Punch%20Pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Are Companies Using 10-K/As to Disclose Bad News in 2021?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/why-are-companies-using-10-k-slash-as-to-disclose-bad-news-in-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Are Companies Using 10-K/As to Disclose Bad News in 2021?" /><published>2021-08-03T15:06:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-03T15:06:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/why-are-companies-using-10-k-slash-as-to-disclose-bad-news-in-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/why-are-companies-using-10-k-slash-as-to-disclose-bad-news-in-2021/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SPACs have been utilizing amended annual reports, 10-K/As, to break bad news in 2021.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have ever had to tell someone bad news, you know that you can lessen the impact by picking your moment carefully. It is a way of abdicating responsibility, and it is extremely common in corporate America. For example, negative corporate disclosures tend to be released on a Friday evening, preferably before a long weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For public companies, it is not just about &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; the disclosure is made, but &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; it is made. We are seeing a concerning trend in 2021 where companies are waiting to make their initial disclosures of bad news such as going concern opinions, ineffective internal control disclosures, and financial restatements in an &lt;em&gt;amended&lt;/em&gt; annual 10-K filings (10-K/As), instead of 8-Ks and other traditional methods and long after the original “clean” 10-K was filed with the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lordstown Motors is an electric car company that went public via SPAC. On June 8th, Lordstown Motors filed a 10-K/A, more than two months after it released its annual report on March 25th. As reported by Francine McKenna in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/a-rollercoaster-ride-for-lordstown&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Lordstown disclosed a going concern opinion, an ineffective internal control assessment by management, and two subpoenas from the SEC (indicating that the SEC was conducting a formal investigation, not an informal inquiry). Lordstown also disclosed that their restatement announced in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1759546/000110465921064530/tm2110489d2_8k.htm&quot;&gt;May&lt;/a&gt; would include an additional charge of $23.5 million, perhaps what tipped it into the “going concern” warning range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10 Years of Data on 10-K/As&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 2021, it was very unusual to see these sorts of disclosures originate in the 10-K/A. Generally, this sort of negative information that could move the stock price would be released in an 8-K, or in a press release. This graph represents initial disclosures by filing over the last ten years: (All our analysis is for publicly traded companies on the NYSE and Nasdaq.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Initial%20Disclosure%20Methods.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial Disclosure Methods.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, 10-K/As are not even represented on this graph. That’s because they account for less than 1% of initial disclosures and are lumped in with some other filings in the “all other methods” category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point that adds context is that 10-K/As themselves are not rare. They are filed by about 10% of companies a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/10-KAs%20per%20year.png&quot; alt=&quot;10-KAs per year.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though they are used to amend 10-Ks, 10-K/As are not typically used to communicate serious issues at a company for the first time, like an internal control issue, going concern issue, or a restatement. Over the last ten years only &lt;strong&gt;3.6%&lt;/strong&gt; of 10-K/As were used to reveal ineffective internal controls. Going concern opinions were even more uncommon, with only &lt;strong&gt;.06%&lt;/strong&gt; of 10-K/As being used to reveal a going concern opinion. Finally, there were nearly 6,000 10-K/As filed from 2011-2020, but only 3 of them were used to initially disclose a non-reliance restatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 Brings a Big Change&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lordstown’s use of a 10-K/A to disclose its going concern and internal control issues was, therefore, highly unusual. But Lordstown was just the biggest, most closely-watched company of many in 2021 that used this stealth maneuver. In 2021, companies have used 10-K/As to first disclose internal control issues, going concern warnings, and restatements at levels far in excess of the normal incidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our analysis, this change is due almost entirely to companies that went public via a SPAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Initial%20Disclosures%20Table%20final.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial Disclosures Table final.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPACs and companies went public via SPACs have started using the 10-K/A to disclose bad news in a way that is novel and a bit sneaky. This may be due to incompetence, or it may be part of an effort to soften the impact on share price. What the market doesn’t read, the market doesn’t see and react to. (Fortunately, our Watchdog Reports capture all this information regardless of where it is filed!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just another example of how SPACs, and the companies that go public via SPACs, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/matchmaker-matchmaker-sponsor-advantage/&quot;&gt;differ&lt;/a&gt; from companies that go public via a traditional IPO. This may raise questions about the competence of the accounting, finance and legal advisors to these companies and their auditors, who are also supposed to be act as a control on bad financial information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve written previously about how SPACs are in a hurry to make deals and are incentivized to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/money-to-burn/&quot;&gt;overpay&lt;/a&gt; for acquisitions. That’s bad for investors. The penchant for hiding bad news in a 10-K/A is a sign that many SPACs are not prepared to become a successful public company, and that their sponsors may have pushed them through a SPAC merger because the payout was too good to turn down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in more learning more about our research, contact jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was amended on 8/9/2021 to correct the final table. We made an error that inflated the number of going concern opinions and have revised the numbers accordingly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="10-K/A" /><summary type="html">SPACs have been utilizing amended annual reports, 10-K/As, to break bad news in 2021.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Sinking%20Ship.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Sinking%20Ship.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unsafe to Mislead</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/unsafe-to-mislead/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unsafe to Mislead" /><published>2021-07-27T08:43:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-27T08:43:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/unsafe-to-mislead</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/unsafe-to-mislead/">&lt;p&gt;Legal liability for those involved in SPACs &lt;em&gt;may be higher&lt;/em&gt; than in conventional IPOs because of potential conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SPAC, also known as blank-check company, is a stock created by sponsors that raises money in an initial public offering with no underlying business. Investors entrust their money to one of these sponsors, instead of to an operating company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;Typically&lt;/a&gt;, the SPAC must use its cash within two years to buy a private company (in a de-SPAC transaction), or refund the money to investors. Generally, investors don’t know what the acquisition target will be until the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more free passes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 8, 2021, John Coates, Acting Director, Division of Corporation Finance of the US Securities and Exchange Commission, wrote an &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/spacs-ipos-liability-risk-under-securities-laws&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; primarily addressing the legal liability attached to disclosures in the de-SPAC transaction. He stressed that in some cases the risk of liability for those involved in SPACs may be higher, not lower, than in conventional IPOs because of potential conflicts of interest in the SPAC structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unsafe to mislead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coates stressed that both federal and state law prohibit any material misstatement in, or omission from, SPAC registration statements either in the IPO or as part of a de-SPAC merger. In conflict-of-interest settings, Delaware corporate law in particular has stricter requirements on both fiduciary duties and on a duty of candor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some SPAC advocates have argued that “safe harbor” provisions of the Private Securities Litigation Reform Act (PSLRA) of 1995 provide SPACs protections when making projections. The PSLRA was passed to curb frivolous securities lawsuits and its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/15/78u-5&quot;&gt;safe harbor provision&lt;/a&gt; protects stock issuers from legal liability for projections, also known as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;amp;height=800&amp;amp;iframe=true&amp;amp;def_id=15-USC-1658834582-1964343826&amp;amp;term_occur=999&amp;amp;term_src=title:15:chapter:2B:section:78u%E2%80%935&quot;&gt;forward-looking statements&lt;/a&gt;.” However, the safe harbor does not apply to any situation where the issuer knows the statement is untrue, misleading, or omits material facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more relevant, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/15/78u-5&quot;&gt;15 US Code 78u-5b1B&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;specifically excludes&lt;/em&gt; blank check companies from any safe harbor protections. Initial Public Offerings are also excluded from using the safe harbor provisions by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/15/78u-5&quot;&gt;15 US Code 78u-5b1D&lt;/a&gt; because of a danger for abuse. Coates argues that a de-SPAC transaction essentially functions as an IPO because even though the public entity has existed as a legal entity for some time, the actual operations from de-SPAC entity will come from the projections of a private company:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…the public knows nothing about this private company. Appropriate liability should attach to whatever claims it is making, or others are making on its behalf.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/spacs-ipos-liability-risk-under-securities-laws&quot;&gt;Coates&lt;/a&gt; rightly insists that PSLRA does not protect against false or misleading statements when made with actual knowledge that the statement was false or misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also warns against only disclosing favorable projections while omitting mention of equally reliable but unfavorable projections. Statements about current valuation or operations are also outside the safe harbor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The party’s over&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This heightened scrutiny caused alarm in some quarters. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/tech-and-spacs-sec-regulation-could-result-in-fewer-but-better-spacs-64000801&quot;&gt;Michael Fitzgerald&lt;/a&gt;, a managing director at MorganFranklin Consulting LLC, a Vaco company, said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“One of the biggest advantages of SPACs over traditional IPOs is the availability of target projections and information on valuation that are not common in a traditional IPO prospectus. Changes in securities laws or elimination of safe harbor protections could reduce the benefit of SPACs in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Withers partner M. Ridgway &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfodive.com/news/new-spac-scrutiny-CFO-forward-looking-guidance-withers-barker/598728/&quot;&gt;Barker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt; didn’t see the SEC as prohibiting forward-looking disclosures in SPAC deals. They feel the new guidelines are a signal that the Commission would examine what sponsors and target companies say about their merger, looking for the kinds of statements that are banned in traditional IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See you in court&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March the SEC opened an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/business/exclusive-us-regulator-opens-inquiry-into-wall-streets-blank-check-ipo-frenzy-2021-03-25/&quot;&gt;inquiry&lt;/a&gt; into Wall Street banks seeking information on how underwriters are managing the risks involved on their SPACs. Stanford University reported that investors have sued eight target companies acquired by SPACs this year. Some of the lawsuits allege that the SPACs and their sponsors hid weaknesses ahead of the de-SPAC transactions, allowing them to make huge profits when the SPAC combined with its target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lawsuits could go the other way as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://us02web.zoom.us/rec/play/Znwtw0auC_8E3VhUqKMubB36yIYb_68ZmR2uVzdrfnb_s4IPHGdQZljJDaySg3IyrgMLsVa9ZXFqeM0_.2lQLCsjtBGGv6mSr?startTime=1620154753000&amp;amp;_x_zm_rtaid=0JMEqKCfTtalGZBaGkyrXg.1620655622652.f15c27c1bd68e43e3819ebadb837735a&amp;amp;_x_zm_rhtaid=600&quot;&gt;Paul Atkins&lt;/a&gt;, CEO of Patomak Global Partners and former SEC commissioner predicted that if the SEC attempted to limit SPACs, companies and investors would take legal action against the regulatory agency. “At some point there will be people who will push back and this may well be tested in court if the SEC is overly aggressive on this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent SEC publications indicate that those involved in &lt;em&gt;SPACs&lt;/em&gt; may not have safe harbor protection from legal liability under the PSLRA. In fact, the risk of liability for those involved with SPACs &lt;em&gt;may be&lt;/em&gt; higher than in risk of launching a conventional IPO because of structural conflicts of interest in SPACs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>elise_rose</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Safe Harbor" /><summary type="html">Legal liability for those involved in SPACs may be higher than in conventional IPOs because of potential conflicts of interest.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Courtroom.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Courtroom.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Slouching in SPAC-land: Poor Returns</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slouching-in-spac-land-poor-returns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slouching in SPAC-land: Poor Returns" /><published>2021-07-14T09:27:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-14T09:27:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slouching-in-spac-land-poor-returns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slouching-in-spac-land-poor-returns/">&lt;p&gt;The investment returns for most SPACs are not as good as those for traditional IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SPAC, also known as blank-check company, is a stock created by sponsors that raises money in an initial public offering with no underlying business. Investors entrust their money to one of these sponsors, instead of to an operating company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;Typically&lt;/a&gt;, the SPAC must use its cash within two years to buy a private company (in a de-SPAC transaction), or refund the money to investors. Generally, investors don’t know what the acquisition target will be until the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New but not necessarily improved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors always intend to make money. Unfortunately, the track record for profitability among SPACs is not stellar. Most of the larger SPACs formed since 2020 that were still trading as of April 30, 2021, have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/tech-and-spacs-sec-regulation-could-result-in-fewer-but-better-spacs-64000801&quot;&gt;declined in value&lt;/a&gt;. Nearly 200 of these stocks dropped between 0% and 2% compared to their IPO prices; over half of those did worse. Overall, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.renaissancecapital.com/IPO-Center/News/71816/Updated-SPAC-returns-fall-short-of-traditional-IPO-returns-on-average#:\~:text=Of%20the%20313%20SPACs%20IPOs,for%20traditional%20IPOs%20since%202015.&quot;&gt;mean return&lt;/a&gt; of SPACs since 2015 was -9.6%; the median return was -29.1%. Only 31.1% had positive returns. Traditional IPOs had returns of &lt;strong&gt;47%&lt;/strong&gt; over the same period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Riding the roller coaster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors may be fooled by short-term performance of SPACs. In the first phase of their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indexologyblog.com/2021/04/15/special-purpose-acquisition-companies-spacs-part-iv/&quot;&gt;life cycle&lt;/a&gt;, post-IPO, i.e., the initiation of the SPAC, SPACs somewhat underperformed the S&amp;amp;P SmallCap 600 Index. However, on announcement of a target for acquisition, the stocks temporarily soar, and some of the stocks continue to do well for a little while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But only 30 days later, most are back to underperforming the S&amp;amp;P SmallCap 600. After the de-SPAC deal is completed, the stocks tend to decline, and investment returns get worse over time after the merger deal, with mean down 17.6% and median down 28.8% a year later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Down when the market is up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/.SPACCNBC&quot;&gt;CNBC SPAC 50 Index&lt;/a&gt;, which tracks the 50 largest U.S.-based pre-merger blank-check deals by market cap, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/02/a-spac-frenzy-this-year-could-lead-to-riskier-deals-heres-why.html&quot;&gt;slumped&lt;/a&gt; nearly 4% year to date, erasing all 2021 gains, at a time when the Nasdaq has gained 6%. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/.SPACDEAL&quot;&gt;CNBC SPAC Post Deal Index&lt;/a&gt;, which includes the largest SPACs that have come to market and have announced a target, is down about 15% year to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tech SPACs that have closed a deal have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/tech-and-spacs-too-much-of-two-good-things-63177042&quot;&gt;underperformed&lt;/a&gt;. Financial firms and industrials have done better. Automotive companies have done particularly well, though that is possibly due to speculative investment in driverless or “green” technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPACs may seem to be a good alternative to traditional IPOs for small-time retail investors, because of the relatively low cost to own shares. However, over the last 18 months, the average investment returns for SPACs have been far inferior to those for traditional IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>elise_rose</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Returns" /><summary type="html">The investment returns for most SPACs are not as good as those for traditional IPOs.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Burning%20Money.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Burning%20Money.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Matchmaker, Matchmaker–Sponsor Advantage</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/matchmaker-matchmaker-sponsor-advantage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Matchmaker, Matchmaker–Sponsor Advantage" /><published>2021-07-07T15:38:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-07T15:38:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/matchmaker-matchmaker-sponsor-advantage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/matchmaker-matchmaker-sponsor-advantage/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The structure of SPACs leads to an inherent advantage for sponsors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SPAC, also known as blank-check company, is a stock created by sponsors that raises money in an initial public offering with no underlying business. Investors entrust their money to one of these sponsors, instead of to an operating company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;Typically&lt;/a&gt;, the SPAC must use its cash within two years to buy a private company (in a de-SPAC transaction), or refund the money to investors. Generally, investors don’t know what the acquisition target will be until the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beware the unknown “spouse”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could think of the sponsors of a SPAC as matchmakers. The retail investor puts money in based on the reputation of the matchmaker, who may have brought about brilliant financial “marriages” in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the investor has little to go on but trust in the promises of the matchmaker. The matchmaker is obliged to find a “spouse” (merger target), but it could be an indifferent or even a poor match for the investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matchmaker is guaranteed to make money, and in some cases has undisclosed or even blatant conflicts of interests in the proposed match. The retail investor may end up with no money, no dowry, and an unhappy marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nothing down&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPAC sponsors usually buy into a SPAC at more favorable terms than retail investors in the IPO or subsequent investors on the open market. Often a sponsor obtains 20% of the shares in a SPAC for either nothing or a nominal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investor.gov/introduction-investing/general-resources/news-alerts/alerts-bulletins/investor-bulletins/what-you&quot;&gt;investment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chamath Palihapitiya, the “King of SPACs”, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-05-27/spacs-can-take-away-the-insiders-advantage-in-ipos-and-markets&quot;&gt;plea&lt;/a&gt; for regulation of the trendy vehicles, recommends that the government require sponsors to commit personal capital to the SPAC. Palihapitiya notes that only 48 of the 127 SPACs that have announced, but not yet closed on, a deal had some form of sponsor investment, with only 10 making long-term commitments to the companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Celebrities or &lt;a href=&quot;ttps://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2021-05-13/spac-king-chamath-palihapitiya-hopes-his-hype-will-keep-mesmerizing-you&quot;&gt;big-name investors&lt;/a&gt; receive far more value than they pay for. Often the retail investor has little information other than the reputation of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thinkadvisor.tradepub.com/free/w_johc18/&quot;&gt;sponsor&lt;/a&gt;. “You might think of investing in a new SPAC as being more interested in the jockey than the horse.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/authors/AOq-oPqQBBI/chamath-palihapitiya&quot;&gt;Palihapitiya&lt;/a&gt; advises examining the amount the sponsor is investing to assess the legitimacy of a SPAC. Although most of the SPAC’s capital has been provided by IPO investors, the sponsors will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/corpfin/disclosure-special-purpose-acquisition-companies&quot;&gt;benefit&lt;/a&gt; more than other investors from the SPAC’s completion of an initial business combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Chamath &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/authors/AOq-oPqQBBI/chamath-palihapitiya&quot;&gt;Palihapitiya&lt;/a&gt; himself exemplifies sponsor advantage. He received 20,500,000 “founders shares” of the SPAC IPOC, worth $205 million in stock, for an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.socialcapitalhedosophiaholdings.com/&quot;&gt;investment&lt;/a&gt; of $25,000 from his firm Social Capital Hedosophia, and for promoting the SPAC and its target Clover. He also bought $100 million worth of shares at the regular price, so he obtained 30.5 million shares for the price of slightly over 10 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dilution is not the solution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thinkadvisor.tradepub.com/free/w_johc18/&quot;&gt;dilution&lt;/a&gt;. Many investors sell their shares when the merger is announced, which is usually the highest point of value in the SPAC life cycle. This drains the cash that could help the soon-to-be-acquired company. The sponsors, who initially put down almost nothing, are still in the deal. Retail SPAC investors who stay with the deal hold shares backed by substantially less cash than at their initial investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. Senator John Kennedy (R-La.), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kennedy.senate.gov/public/2021/4/kennedy-introduces-spac-act-to-increase-transparency-surrounding-blank-check-companies&quot;&gt;introduced a bill&lt;/a&gt; to ensure investors have adequate transparency into SPAC deals, particularly when it comes to what are called “founder’s shares,” a special class of shares that go to the SPAC sponsors after the merger is completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfodive.com/news/as-sec-ramps-up-spac-rules-lawsuits-could-follow/599906/&quot;&gt;Kennedy said&lt;/a&gt; when introducing the bill, “When SPAC sponsors convert the shares that they receive in the merged company, the public’s shares of that company are diluted and lose value. The valuation of SPAC shares may fall even further if a SPAC sponsor chooses a weak company with which to merge.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Under pressure, overvalued&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the deadline for a merger approaches, sponsors may have an incentive to complete a transaction on terms where they make money but the retail investor does not. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finra.org/rules-guidance/notices/08-54#:\~:text=A%20SPAC%20typically%20must%20complete,of%20the%20assets%20in%20escrow.&quot;&gt;FINRA&lt;/a&gt; warned investors of this as far back as 2008:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPAC managers have a strong incentive to buy a company, even at inflated values, since they will get 20 percent of the company at a nominal price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a deal doesn’t go through, the firms that create SPACs must return the money initial investors paid in. The sponsors definitely want to avoid this scenario. So there’s a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/en/research-insights/articles/special-purpose-acquisition-companies-spacs-part-ii&quot;&gt;pressure&lt;/a&gt; for SPAC sponsors to find a target company for merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company targeted for acquisition must comprise over 80% of the trust account assets. This creates an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/en/research-insights/articles/special-purpose-acquisition-companies-spacs-part-ii&quot;&gt;incentive&lt;/a&gt; for the SPAC’s sponsors to overvalue a target company to get the deal done. If sponsors have relatively little “skin in the game”, they are not harmed, but retail investors don’t get their money’s worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion: Beware the matchmaker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail investors who provide the bulk of the funds for SPACs have to weather the ups and downs of the market. Sponsors are not usually required to put very much, if any, of their own money into their SPACs. Therefore, they are guaranteed to make a profit when the merger happens, regardless of how the SPAC performs. Sponsors also have perverse incentives to target weaker companies for acquisition to avoid refunding money if the de-SPAC transaction doesn’t go through. Investors are cautioned to examine the matchmaker with care, because in most cases, they won’t find a matchless match.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>elise_rose</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Conflict of Interest" /><summary type="html">The structure of SPACs leads to an inherent advantage for sponsors.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Couple.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Couple.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sizzle and PIPE Dreams in SPAC-land</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sizzle-and-pipe-dreams-in-spac-land/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sizzle and PIPE Dreams in SPAC-land" /><published>2021-06-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sizzle-and-pipe-dreams-in-spac-land</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sizzle-and-pipe-dreams-in-spac-land/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SPACs are allowed to make dazzling projections without supporting data and retail investors may not be aware of some conflicts of interest that influence sponsors’ investment behavior.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special purpose acquisition companies (SPACs) have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/05/27/sec-considers-new-investor-protections-for-spacs.html&quot;&gt;exploded&lt;/a&gt; in popularity in the last 18 months, with 90% created in 2020 or 2021. A SPAC, also known as blank-check company, is a stock created by sponsors that raises money in an initial public offering with no underlying business. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;Typically&lt;/a&gt;, the SPAC must use its cash within two years to buy a private company (in a de-SPAC transaction), or refund the money to investors. Generally, investors don’t know what the acquisition target will be until the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SPAC usually uses additional funds from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2021/03/26/spac-investing-101-what-is-a-pipe-and-what-should/&quot;&gt;PIPE&lt;/a&gt; (private investment in public equity) to accomplish the de-SPAC. By starting the company this way, a SPAC purports to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thinkadvisor.tradepub.com/free/w_johc18/&quot;&gt;avoid&lt;/a&gt; the regulatory requirements of a traditional IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of SPACs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/spacs-an-attractive-alternative-to-a-8460350/&quot;&gt;tout&lt;/a&gt; them as good for small-time retail investors, because of the relatively low cost to own shares (usually only $10) and the ability to divest of shares before the merger. However, there are a number of notable risks for investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sizzle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPACs have a looser regulatory environment than traditional IPOs. They can make projections that traditionally are “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/spacs-ipos-liability-risk-under-securities-laws&quot;&gt;not commonly found in conventional IPO prospectuses&lt;/a&gt;.” This allows the sponsors, those who start the SPAC, to “sell the sizzle, not the steak”, because until the merger is announced, there is, in fact, no steak to sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors have little information to go on in assessing the SPAC. In particular, retail investors may not be aware of conflicts of interest that influence sponsors’ investment behavior. The SEC admitted as much when it provided &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/corpfin/disclosure-special-purpose-acquisition-companies&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; for SPAC disclosure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The economic interests of the entity or management team&lt;/em&gt; … &lt;em&gt;often differ from the economic interests of public shareholders which may lead to conflicts of interests&lt;/em&gt; as they evaluate and decide whether to recommend business combination transactions to shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this guidance, SPAC sponsors have &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2021/06/04/um-where-is-the-sec-when-it-comes-to-spacs-and-conflicts-of-interest/&quot;&gt;continued&lt;/a&gt; to target companies where they have apparently have a personal vested interest. SPAC are not prohibited from these self-interested transactions. They only have to tell investors, usually in a lengthy disclosure, that the SPAC capital might be used to buy one of their own companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent story &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2021/06/04/um-where-is-the-sec-when-it-comes-to-spacs-and-conflicts-of-interest/&quot;&gt;featured&lt;/a&gt; in TechCrunch looked at the example of Reid Hoffman, a SPAC sponsor who is close to finalizing a merger deal with autonomous vehicle startup Aurora. But Hoffman’s venture firm, Greylock, began investing in Aurora in 2018, and he is on its board of directors. He could set the price for acquisition of Aurora by his SPAC at a level that would greatly enhance its value and therefore his bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPAC proponent Chamath Palihapitiya, the “King of SPACs”, invested in insurance company Clover through his firm Social Capital &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2021-05-13/spac-king-chamath-palihapitiya-hopes-his-hype-will-keep-mesmerizing-you&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; one of his SPACs merged with Clover &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-clover-health-m-a-social-capital/clover-health-to-go-public-via-3-7-billion-deal-with-social-capital-idUSKBN26R1XB&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/jonathanponciano/2021/06/07/spac-king-regains-billionaire-status-as-trading-frenzy-boosts-clover-health/?sh=3990179f3828&quot;&gt;Since the merger&lt;/a&gt;, Clover has been the subject of an SEC investigation, an undisclosed Justice Department inquiry, and an accusation by short-seller Hindenburg Research of fraud, including kickbacks, misrepresentation and undisclosed third-party deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing stops these ethically questionable investments because the SEC’s guidelines are suggestions, not law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment banks that sponsor SPACs also have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/tech-and-spacs-sec-regulation-could-result-in-fewer-but-better-spacs-64000801&quot;&gt;potential&lt;/a&gt; conflict of interest. Some banking sponsors invest minimal amounts into a SPAC, but then also underwrite the launch of the IPO and serve as advisors for the deal to acquire an operating company. Often those fees are much larger than the bank’s investment as a sponsor, so the bank might have a much greater financial interest in completion of the merger deal than in the success of the SPAC itself. In March the SEC opened an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/business/exclusive-us-regulator-opens-inquiry-into-wall-streets-blank-check-ipo-frenzy-2021-03-25/&quot;&gt;inquiry&lt;/a&gt; into Wall Street banks, seeking information on how underwriters are managing the risks involved in their SPACs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC may be looking into the depth of due diligence SPACs perform before acquiring assets in the de-SPAC transaction, and whether huge payouts are fully disclosed to investors. The regulators may also be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/business/exclusive-us-regulator-opens-inquiry-into-wall-streets-blank-check-ipo-frenzy-2021-03-25/&quot;&gt;concerned&lt;/a&gt; about the heightened risk of insider trading between the initiation of the SPAC and when it announces its acquisition target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail investors should be aware that SPAC sponsors who have a vested interest in the target company may be using the merger to shore up a failing venture, a risky investment strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PIPE Dreams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail investors also fare &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2021/03/26/spac-investing-101-what-is-a-pipe-and-what-should/&quot;&gt;worse&lt;/a&gt; than the PIPE investors, who come in just before or after the merger is announced. The PIPE investors come in after they know the target, but still get to buy shares for $10, though they are often worth $15 or $20 right away. Ordinary investors can’t buy at the lower price this late in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waking From the Dream&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison Herren Lee, the SEC’s current acting chair, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfodive.com/news/ipo-deregulation-Allison-Herren-Lee-Jay-Clayton/586858/&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; last October at the Practicing Law Institute’s SEC Speaks, “In the short term, a SPAC investment acts largely as a blank check, so it is critical that [there’s an understanding of] the material risks involved.” As Paul &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/munter-spac-20200331&quot;&gt;Munter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Acting Chief Accountant of the SEC,&lt;/em&gt; noted,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether a company enters the public markets through a merger with a SPAC, traditional IPO, or other process, the quality and reliability of financial reporting and the quality of audits on the financial statements provided to investors is vital to our efforts to protect investors and to the confidence of investors in our markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past six months the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;signaled&lt;/a&gt; that SPACs will be subject to increased levels of scrutiny. One key area of focus has been on the disclosure of germane conflicts of interest from each SPAC participant: insiders like the sponsors and management team; the IPO’s public shareholders; and third parties like underwriters. These parties will need to avoid conflicts or scrupulously disclose them if they wish to avoid enforcement actions and liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajiv Shukla, chairman and CEO of SPAC Alpha Healthcare Acquisition Corp., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/tech-and-spacs-sec-regulation-could-result-in-fewer-but-better-spacs-64000801&quot;&gt;believes&lt;/a&gt; the SEC will also likely require enhanced disclosures on other financial interests of sponsors over the lifecycle of the SPAC deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail investors who are interested in investing in a SPAC should do as much due diligence on the sponsors of the SPAC as they reasonably can. After all, since there is no underlying company, you really are just investing in the sponsors. If in the past, the sponsors have used SPAC funds to invest in target companies with financial ties to those sponsors, you may want to reconsider giving them your money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up next: SPAC Risks Part 2: Matchmaker, Matchmaker–Sponsor Advantage&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>elise_rose</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Conflict of Interest" /><summary type="html">SPACs are allowed to make dazzling projections without supporting data and retail investors may not be aware of some conflicts of interest that influence sponsors’ investment behavior.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Pipes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Pipes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Securities Class Actions by Size</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/analyzing-securities-class-actions-by-size/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Securities Class Actions by Size" /><published>2021-06-25T06:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-25T06:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/analyzing-securities-class-actions-by-size</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/analyzing-securities-class-actions-by-size/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bigger companies may be more likely to be sued than smaller companies, but they are also more resilient.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our firm, Watchdog Research, uses statistical analysis of past events to evaluate a company’s future. One of the most important events we track is the occurrence of Securities Class Action (SCA) lawsuits. All the data presented in this article is based on our statistical analysis of publicly available data concerning public companies on the NYSE and NASDAQ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our database allows us to track the probability that any given companies will be named in a SCA suit for a given year. Overall, the probability in the last ten years has increased, which has contributed to a hard market for D&amp;amp;O insurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Picture1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Picture1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Segmenting by Size&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our database shows us that this risk is not uniform for companies of all sizes. The larger a company is, the more likely it is to be named in a SCA suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Picture2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Picture2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our research companies with over $10 billion in market capitalization are categorized as Large cap. Companies with less than $1 billion are categorized as Small cap. And all the companies that fall between them are considered Mid cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; brought about a significant shift in the legal landscape for SCAs. So it is possible that higher SCA rates are part of a new paradigm and that there will be no return to mean. If that is the case, then the averages seen between 2017-2020 may become the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Table%20SCA%20by%20Market%20Cap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table SCA by Market Cap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of a company may be one the most important factors to know concerning a company’s likelihood of being named in a SCA. It holds true in every industry, even in pharmaceuticals where small companies are particularly volatile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20by%20Size%20and%20Industry.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA by Size and Industry.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resilience&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large companies are far more likely to be named in a SCA than small companies, but larger companies often have the resources to handle these suits. We looked at the abnormal returns for all companies after they were named in a SCA suit and found that these events had a far greater negative impact on smaller companies than larger companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20impact%20by%20size-278a03.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA impact by size-278a03.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We calculated these abnormal returns by comparing the company’s stock price performance to the S&amp;amp;P 500 over the 30 days following the announcement of a SCA suit. It is clear that after the initial shock of the announcement wears off, large companies tend to recover quickly. Smaller companies tend not to fare as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our data shows that no matter the industry, the larger a company is, the more likely it is to get sued in a SCA. However the risk calculation is not simple. Smaller firms are far less likely to get sued, but far more likely to suffer dramatic losses as a result of that suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These graphs and charts were made by our data scientist Joseph Burke, PhD. Much of this information is derived from “&lt;em&gt;Frequency and Impact of Securities Class Actions: 2021&lt;/em&gt;” a Watchdog Report made by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD. If you are interested in purchasing this report, or a license to the dataset we used to create it, then contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Securities Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Data Analysis" /><summary type="html">Bigger companies may be more likely to be sued than smaller companies, but they are also more resilient.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Picture2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Picture2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mergers Plant the Seeds For Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/mergers-plant-seeds-for-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mergers Plant the Seeds For Litigation" /><published>2021-06-21T09:20:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T09:20:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/mergers-plant-seeds-for-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/mergers-plant-seeds-for-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our research indicates that large mergers are a strong leading indicator for Securities Class Actions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway and the Brazilian firm 3G Capital collaborated to facilitate a merger that formed Kraft Heinz (KHC). In 2019 Kraft Heinz issued one of the largest impairments in history, over $15 billion. This impairment seems to have been a direct consequence of corporate governance &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; arising out of the merger. And it did not end there, Kraft Heinz impaired an additional $5 billion over the next two years and has been engaged in protracted legal battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every merger presents a difficult challenge of reconciling two different systems (each company has its own corporate culture, governance philosophy, financial reporting methods, IT solutions, compensation practices, etc.). When this reconciliation process does not go well, it can create serious problems that can play out over a course of years. This has been the story for Kraft Heinz, but they are not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correlating Mergers and Securities Class Action (SCA) Lawsuits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research into mergers indicates that a company takes a big risk when it merges with another company that is relatively comparable in size. In contrast, a company takes significantly less risk if it gobbles up a relatively small operation. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt; wrote off almost all of the $230 million it spent acquiring TIO in 2017 without batting an eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When cataloging these mergers for our research, relatively large mergers are assigned a red flag and relatively small mergers are assigned a yellow flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research indicates that over the last 20 years companies with a red-flag merger were &lt;strong&gt;2.12&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be named in a SCA lawsuit in the same calendar year (potentially occurring before or after the merger). Companies with a yellow-flag merger were &lt;strong&gt;1.38&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be subject to suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not as dramatic as it sounds. It is likely that in many cases these lawsuits &lt;em&gt;preceded&lt;/em&gt; the merger as merger-objection suits. Merger objection lawsuits typically lack substance and are often dealt with quickly. These ubiquitous lawsuits artificially inflate the number of lawsuits included in the calculation and diminish the importance of the relatively high correlation we found in the same calendar year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we were surprised to see that when we looked at the correlation between red-flag mergers and SCA suits there was a slightly stronger signal in the &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20Merger%20Leading%20Indicator.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA Merger Leading Indicator.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 20 years, any company that had a merger was &lt;strong&gt;1.45&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be subject to a SCA suit as a company that had not engaged in a merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for companies that had red-flag mergers, they were &lt;strong&gt;2.14&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be subject to a SCA the following year. Even without the inflationary effect of the merger objection suits, these red-flag mergers were a very strong leading indicator for SCA suits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This research comes from “Securities Class Actions: Leading Indicators and Covariates” by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD. Available at $399 for an individual license and $699 for firm-wide license. Contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; to purchase. Free for subscribers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most actors in the market think on a quarterly basis, but insurance and investment professionals need to think in longer terms. Mergers are often forgotten by the markets almost as soon as they are consummated, but the problems that they create can linger for months, or even years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We grade past risk factors and predict future risk impacts for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. Contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; to learn how we can help you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Mergers" /><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><summary type="html">Our research indicates that large mergers are a strong leading indicator for Securities Class Actions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Red%20Flag-8cbf8e.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Red%20Flag-8cbf8e.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Watch Out for Audit Fee Jumps</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watch-out-for-audit-fee-jumps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch Out for Audit Fee Jumps" /><published>2021-06-03T13:29:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-03T13:29:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watch-out-for-audit-fee-jumps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watch-out-for-audit-fee-jumps/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audit fees are usually “sticky,” so you should notice when they jump.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By law, every public company must hire an independent auditor to review their financial statements and offer an opinion. Although the public is privy to an auditor’s final opinion, almost all the auditor’s work is shrouded in mystery. However, every company must disclose how much money it spends on audit related services (audit fees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies negotiate with their auditors every year over price, so year-over-year and peer-to-peer comparisons of fees can potentially reveal interesting insights about what is going on behind the scenes at a company. For this reason, there have been a number of academic papers on audit fees and their potential implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time evidence has emerged that audit fees are “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/MAJ-08-2013-0915/full/html&quot;&gt;sticky&lt;/a&gt;” and do not adjust rapidly to changing conditions at a company. This makes sense considering the multifaceted relationship that develops between an auditor and management. Yes, auditors are independent, but they want to serve their clients and maintain a strong relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes an auditor’s fee will buck this trend and jump…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomenon was the subject of a 2016 academic paper titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2826272&quot;&gt;Abnormal Audit Fees and Accounting Quality&lt;/a&gt;.” The authors found evidence that companies whose audit fees jumped up out of their normal range had indicators of lower accounting quality (e.g., a greater risk for restatements, material weaknesses, and fraud). The authors hypothesized that sharp increases in fees were due to efforts by auditors to fix problems, indicating the &lt;em&gt;existence&lt;/em&gt; of problems in financial statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unexplained jump in audit fees is certainly a red flag (we have also discussed that same point with respect to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/do-not-ignore-spikes-in-non-audit-fees/&quot;&gt;non-audit fees&lt;/a&gt;). But insurance and investment professionals should be cautious even when a ready explanation for the increase in fees is at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Complicated Real-World Example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, TCF Financial Corporation’s annual report disclosed a sharp jump in their audit fees. This increase coincided with a reverse merger with Chemical Bank that was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961219000179/a8-kmergerannouncmentc.htm&quot;&gt;consummated&lt;/a&gt; in 2019, but the increase in audit fees may also have represented remediation efforts by the auditor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Audit%20Fees%20TCF.png&quot; alt=&quot;Audit Fees TCF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another possible signal of trouble came from the non-audit fees, which also reported a spike in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2020, Probes Reporter confirmed that TCF Financial was subject to an undisclosed investigation by the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/TCF%20SEC%20Investigation.png&quot; alt=&quot;TCF SEC Investigation.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2020, Craig Dahl left &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961220000190/a8k2020.htm&quot;&gt;abruptly&lt;/a&gt; as CEO after serving in the position of the joint company after a little over a year (he had been &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.tcfbank.com/news/news-details/2020/TCF-Financial-Corp.-CEO-Craig-R.-Dahl-to-Retire/default.aspx&quot;&gt;tenured&lt;/a&gt; at TCF for 21 years and had served as their CEO prior to the merger).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A company spokesperson took issue with an earlier version of this story where we characterized Mr. Dahl’s departure as a removal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear why he was departed from his position early, but his resignation was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961220000190/a8k2020.htm&quot;&gt;effective&lt;/a&gt; the day after the announcement. For some context, the TCF’s CFO’s resignation also became effective in October, but his departure was announced in December 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961220000190/exhibit101dahlseparati.htm&quot;&gt;agreed&lt;/a&gt; to pay the former CEO a significant lump sum, over $11 million, and $1.5 million a month for 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is possible that TCF’s sharp increases in audit fees and non-audit fees had nothing to do with the SEC investigation, or whatever lead to the abrupt departure of the CEO, but the academic literature indicates that jumps in audit fees are a sign of trouble in the financial statements and should not be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academic research of audit fees indicates that they are “sticky,” so sharp increases can be considered an abnormal event.  Insurance and investment professionals should do their best to carefully discern when these abnormal increases are a sign of potential trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every Watchdog Report provides a year-to-year and peer-to-peer comparison for audit fees, non audit fees, and many other potential risk factors. These reports are available for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. If you want one of our team members to give you a tour, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A company spokesperson for TCF Financial said that they would get back to us concerning further comments regarding an earlier version of this piece. We will append any comments they make to this article.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Audit Fees" /><summary type="html">Audit fees are usually “sticky,” so you should notice when they jump.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/goo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/goo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>