<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-30T04:25:15-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Are We Making the Same Mistakes with ETFs that We Made with CDOs?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/are-we-making-the-same-mistakes-with-etfs-that-we-made-with-cdos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are We Making the Same Mistakes with ETFs that We Made with CDOs?" /><published>2021-01-29T10:22:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T10:22:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/are-we-making-the-same-mistakes-with-etfs-that-we-made-with-cdos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/are-we-making-the-same-mistakes-with-etfs-that-we-made-with-cdos/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most ETFs aren’t technically derivatives, but they may pose similar risks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CDOs were at heart of 2008 financial crash&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the housing bubble burst, there was a lot of finger pointing. But one thing everyone agreed on was that collateralized debt obligations (CDOs) were at the heart of the crash because people did not appreciate the real risks associated with these instruments. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/cdo.asp#:\~:text=A%20collateralized%20debt%20obligation%20(CDO)%20is%20a%20complex%20structured%20finance,derived%20from%20another%20underlying%20asset.&quot;&gt;CDOs&lt;/a&gt; are a complex financial product backed by a pool of loans that can be sold to investors. Prior to the crash, it was believed that pooling together risky mortgages with solid mortgages would make the entire product safe, so many CDOs were AAA rated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, this should have worked, but there were some problems. Firstly, &lt;em&gt;no one buying these derivative products was checking the health of the underlying mortgages&lt;/em&gt;, so they did not realize that the CDOs were filled with far more risky mortgages than previously believed. Secondly, there was an assumption that the growth in housing prices would continue forever (seriously, what were people thinking?) and the system was completely unprepared for a decline, or even a slow-down, in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Few People Think About What is In Their ETFs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs) are a tool that allow investors to easily invest in a pool of investments. These can be stocks, bonds, commodities, or some mixture. The value of the ETF is adjusted so that it reflects the value of the underlying basket of investments. Investing in an ETF gives the investor a share in the ETF fund, but not in the underlying assets that they reflect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying an ETF is considered less risky that purchasing an individual stock because there is diversification in the bundle that you are purchasing. For example, some ETFs track the entire market, or the whole S&amp;amp;P 500. The diversification can gives a specific ETF the resiliency of the market (or whatever creates the pool of assets) so that risky companies are offset by more stable companies in the pool. Different ETFs offer differing degrees of diversification as some ETFs track relatively small subsets of the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most ETFs are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/102815/are-etfs-considered-derivatives.asp#:\~:text=The%20short%20answer%20is%20that,not%20considered%20to%20be%20derivatives.&amp;amp;text=Generally%20speaking%2C%20ETFs%20are%20not,leveraged%20ETFs%20and%20inverse%20ETFs.&quot;&gt;not considered&lt;/a&gt; derivatives because they are backed by the actual assets in the pool, not some contractual arrangement based on the assets. However, the value of the ETF is &lt;em&gt;derived&lt;/em&gt; from the value of the underlying basket of stocks, so people can fall into a similar trap. They focus on the performance of the ETF and overlook the health of the underlying assets. This is the same kind of thinking that got so many investors in trouble with the CDOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Funds Are Not Doing Any Due Diligence on Their Investments&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another potential problem with ETFs. One reason they are considered safer is because they are usually passive investments. The managers use some criteria to create a basket of stocks and then generally don’t tinker with it. For example, some ETFs track the S&amp;amp;P 500 or the entire market; and they don’t try to pick winners and losers. Since ETFs don’t do research into the underlying assets, don’t have many employees, and don’t have to pay brokerage fees, it keeps costs low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prospectuses for ETFs routinely warn investors that they do not research the assets that undergird the fund. Here is an example of some boilerplate from a prospectus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“[We] does not invest the assets of the Fund in securities or financial instruments based on [our] view of the investment merit of a particular security, instrument, or company, nor does it conduct conventional investment research or analysis or forecast market movement or trends.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You need to do this research for yourself. We can help.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all ETFs cover broad and diverse markets, instead, some are incredibly specific. For example, there are approximately 50 “all-China” ETFs, each offering a different slice of the Chinese market. This is where the lack of research can really come back to bite investors on passive investments that feel “safe”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ETF providers are not carefully researching the companies in their portfolio, but instead are putting together a set of criteria that they think will sell. &lt;em&gt;If an investor wants to know how risky the underling basket of stocks are, they need to do the due diligence for themselves&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can help with that. We have reports available for hundreds of ETFs that list and assess the underlying assets in the fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big difference between ETFs and CDOs is that the assets backing up most ETFs (stock from public companies) face far more scrutiny than the NINJA loans did prior to 2008. That does provide today’s investors in ETFs with more protection than the investors in CDOs had in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, investors need to be wary of being lulled into a false sense of security surrounding ETFs. They are skyrocketing in popularity, leading to a wide proliferation of different types of ETFs to satisfy every appetite. Investors should not get caught up in the frenzy, but instead make sure that they understand what they are putting their money into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to buy an ETF, especially a specialized one, then do your due diligence on the underlying stocks, because no one else is doing it for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;O insurers spend a lot of time on new bid requests. Our clients use our Watchdog Reports to quickly discover which bids they should pursue. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="ETFs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="ETFs" /><category term="CDOs" /><summary type="html">Most ETFs aren’t technically derivatives, but they may pose similar risks.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CDOs.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CDOs.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Brokers are … Not Brokers?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/online-brokers-are-dot-dot-dot-not-brokers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Brokers are … Not Brokers?" /><published>2021-01-26T13:44:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T13:44:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/online-brokers-are-dot-dot-dot-not-brokers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/online-brokers-are-dot-dot-dot-not-brokers/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently, online brokers are operating in a gray space. They seem to want to replace traditional brokers, as evidenced by their marketing and the services they offer. Yet they do not want to take on the responsibility of making suitable recommendations for investors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you want to know the risks in your equity investments, read our independent research, available for individual companies and ETFs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the stock market crash in 1929, Congress acted to put more effective protections in place for investors. Congress passed the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/reportspubs/investor-publications/divisionsmarketregbdguidehtm.html#:&quot;&gt;required&lt;/a&gt; a broker’s investment recommendations be suitable for each investor. Shortly thereafter, Congress passed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/COMPS-1879/pdf/COMPS-1879.pdf&quot;&gt;Investment Advisers Act&lt;/a&gt; of 1940, which required investment advisors to act as fiduciaries when advising and investing their client’s money. These laws ratcheted up the legal responsibilities of brokers and investment advisors by making them potentially liable for failures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A crucial source for this article was a note in the Columbia Law Review by Alec Smith. You can read his note, “Advisors, Brokers, and Online Platforms: How a Uniform Fiduciary Duty Will Better Serve Investors” &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.library.columbia.edu/index.php/CBLR/article/view/1730/751&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brokers are held to a suitability standard and courts have repeatedly found that a recommendation is suitable if it is consistent with the customer’s best interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to FINRA’s guidance, for a broker to provide &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finra.org/rules-guidance/rulebooks/finra-rules/2111&quot;&gt;suitable&lt;/a&gt; recommendations they must first take reasonable steps to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; the customer. FINRA’s rule states that brokers should pull together an investment profile that includes factors like the customer’s age, financial situation, tax status, investment objectives, and risk tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the broker must make reasonable recommendations that are in line with customer’s objectives. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finra.org/rules-guidance/rulebooks/finra-rules/2111&quot;&gt;FINRA&lt;/a&gt;, a broker is not permitted to “disclaim any responsibilities under the suitability rule.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1940 most people interacted with their brokers in person, or on the phone, but today many people use online brokers like Fidelity or TD Ameritrade. Like traditional brokers, these online platforms ask you questions and construct an investment profile. Many of these platforms also have online tools that will suggest investment strategies that correspond with the information you imputed into your profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The online platforms will also attempt to teach you about investing through materials available on their website and through regular emails. This education should help you to recognize if the suggestions made by the programming is a good fit for your investing needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Online Brokers Argue That They Are Not in a Position of Trust&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike traditional brokers, these online platforms argue that they are not liable if they suggest an unsuitable investment. In essence, they argue that they should not be considered “brokers” as contemplated in the 1934 Securities Exchange Act. They argue that since they do not exercise “&lt;a href=&quot;https://casetext.com/case/williams-v-scottrade&quot;&gt;discretionary authority&lt;/a&gt;” over the client’s account, the client has not entrusted the money to the online broker and therefore no fiduciary responsibilities arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, online brokers require new users to sign an agreement before opening an online &lt;em&gt;brokerage account&lt;/em&gt;. The agreement will typically state that the user does not rely on the platform for any recommendations or advice concerning their investments. This language is designed to reinforce the notion that the online broker and the investor are operating at arm’s length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here a modified example from a top online broker:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have not and will not rely on [Online Broker] or any [Online Broker] representative for advice, information or recommendations regarding Designated Investments, their nature or features, their risk profiles, or their suitability for me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although rarely tested, these agreements have held up so far in court. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://casetext.com/case/williams-v-scottrade&quot;&gt;Williams v. Scottrade&lt;/a&gt;, Inc., No. 06-10677, 2006 WL 2077588, at *9-10 (E.D. Mich. July24, 2006) a judge found that the online platform did not owe a fiduciary duty to its customer, and that &lt;em&gt;even if it did&lt;/em&gt;, the contractual agreement would have modified any duty owed. This case is hardly binding precedent for the whole legal system, but it stands for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Could the Courts Change Their Minds?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Williams v. Scottrade case was decided in 2006. Plenty of things have changed since then. The internet is no longer a sandbox where people keep some of their toys. It is rapidly becoming fully integrated into every aspect of our lives. Our dependence on the internet grows daily as online businesses slowly but surely replace traditional businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.library.columbia.edu/index.php/CBLR/article/view/1730/751&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/a&gt;, Alec Smith argues that the suggestions online brokers offer based on a customer profile, along with the frequent educational material offered, could give a court grounds to find that online brokers exercise some de facto control over their customer’s accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, he argues that online brokers are … brokers. And that investors should have the same protections in their dealings with online brokers as they would have with traditional brokers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Hybrid Solution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a practical problem with requiring online brokers to make suitable recommendations to investors. It would dramatically increase costs as the online brokers would need to communicate with every customer and assess their accounts to ensure that the algorithms had correctly identified suitable investments for the customers. Many of the competitive advantages that online brokers possess (cost savings, lower barrier to entry for investors), would be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A potential hybrid solution would be for the online platforms to provide investors with lots of independent research, enabling investors to make truly independent judgements.  Here at Watchdog Research, we have independent research on almost every public company listed on a U.S. exchange, as well as on hundreds of ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the online brokers are operating in a gray space. They seem to want to replace traditional brokers, as evidenced by their marketing and the services they offer. Yet they do not want to take on the responsibility of making suitable recommendations for investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Online Brokers" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Online Brokers" /><category term="Independent Research" /><summary type="html">Currently, online brokers are operating in a gray space. They seem to want to replace traditional brokers, as evidenced by their marketing and the services they offer. Yet they do not want to take on the responsibility of making suitable recommendations for investors.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Online%20Brokers.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Online%20Brokers.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Who is Auditing SPACs?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/who-is-auditing-spacs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is Auditing SPACs?" /><published>2021-01-19T15:16:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T15:16:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/who-is-auditing-spacs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/who-is-auditing-spacs/">&lt;p&gt;The number of SPACs exploded in 2020, exceeding the number of traditional IPOs for the first time ever. That growth looks like it will continue in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pymnts.com/news/ipo/2021/will-spacs-be-back-with-a-bang-in-2021/&quot;&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt;. SPACs have been around for a long time, however, they have only recently generated significant interest and capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, SPACs were a novelty and treated as such: FINRA warned investors about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/money-to-burn/&quot;&gt;problematic incentives&lt;/a&gt;; D&amp;amp;O insurance coverage was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2021/01/articles/director-and-officer-liability/the-top-ten-do-stories-of-2020/&quot;&gt;expensive&lt;/a&gt; because it was so specialized; and only smaller more specialized accounting firms would provide independent auditing services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last five years, two auditors have dominated the SPAC market, Marcum LLP and WithumSmith+Brown PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Picture3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Picture3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up through the last five years, the Big 4, PwC, Delloite, Ernst &amp;amp; Young, and KPMG have largely steered clear of SPACs. From 2015-2020, PwC only took on one SPAC client. It will be interesting to see if the dramatic increase in the number of SPACs will result in greater interest from the Big 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we know about the two auditing firms that currently enjoy the lion’s share of the SPAC market? Marcum LLP did recently have some &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/&quot;&gt;trouble&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rasr.pcaobus.org/Firms/FirmSummaryPublic.aspx?FirmID=76E6B737AAB06B9D9470E48AE55F30C3&quot;&gt;PCAOB&lt;/a&gt; concerning their business in China; however, that does not tell us much about the SPAC side of their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WithumSmith+Brown has not had any recent disciplinary issues with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rasr.pcaobus.org/Firms/FirmSummaryPublic.aspx?FirmID=7E4B42A51F1A72B7BDFE6C10FF510996&quot;&gt;PCAOB&lt;/a&gt;. According to their last inspection report (which was released in 2016) the firm has 11 offices, all within the U.S. Interestingly, they appear to specialize &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.withum.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/FOREIGN-DOMICILED-SPACs.pdf&quot;&gt;assisting&lt;/a&gt; SPACs which are looking to incorporate in “tax havens.” For the past five years, they have been the clear leader for SPACs looking to incorporate in the Cayman Islands, a tax haven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Cayamn%20SPACs%20by%20auditor.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cayamn SPACs by auditor.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the last twenty years, SPACs occupied an insignificant portion of the market. Only two small auditing firms catered to this portion of the market. However, in the last three years, the number of SPACs has grown significantly, raising the profiles of Marcum LLP and WithumSmith+Brown. Now that SPACs are attracting billions in capital, it will be interesting to see if the Big 4 take any significant steps to encroach on the SPAC market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;O insurers spend a lot of time on new bid requests. Our clients use our Watchdog Reports to quickly discover which bids they should pursue. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Auditors" /><category term="Cayman Islands" /><summary type="html">The number of SPACs exploded in 2020, exceeding the number of traditional IPOs for the first time ever. That growth looks like it will continue in 2021. SPACs have been around for a long time, however, they have only recently generated significant interest and capital.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SPAC%20Picture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SPAC%20Picture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SPACs in the Cayman Islands</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/spacs-in-the-cayman-islands/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SPACs in the Cayman Islands" /><published>2021-01-12T14:25:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-12T14:25:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/spacs-in-the-cayman-islands</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/spacs-in-the-cayman-islands/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our research indicates that only &lt;strong&gt;3.3%&lt;/strong&gt; of all companies are incorporated in the Cayman Islands, and that includes some companies that are actually located there. In contrast, &lt;strong&gt;28%&lt;/strong&gt; of all SPACs are incorporated in the Cayman Islands, despite the fact that &lt;strong&gt;88%&lt;/strong&gt; of them are located in the United States.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 has been called the year of the SPAC, as the number of SPAC IPOs eclipsed the number of traditional IPOs for the first time ever. The dramatic rise of SPACs has raised a lot of questions. In this post we will compare the differences in where SPACs are located with where they are incorporated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is typical for companies to incorporate in Delaware or Nevada, even when they are located another state. However, it is not typical for companies to incorporate in a foreign jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, even though SPACs are overwhelmingly located in the United States, many of them are incorporated in the Cayman Islands. Compare this graph of SPACs by their &lt;em&gt;location&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SPAC%20locations.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPAC locations.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this graph of SPACs by their state of &lt;em&gt;incorporation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SPAC%20incorporation.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPAC incorporation.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research indicates that only &lt;strong&gt;3.3%&lt;/strong&gt; of all companies are incorporated in the Cayman Islands, and that includes some companies that are actually located there. In contrast, &lt;strong&gt;28%&lt;/strong&gt; of all SPACs are incorporated in the Cayman Islands, despite the fact that &lt;strong&gt;88%&lt;/strong&gt; of them are located in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likely that SPACs are incorporated in the Cayman Islands because they are a tax shelter with lax disclosure requirements. The Cayman Islands do not have any reporting requirements to speak of, so a company incorporated there can do the bare minimum necessary to stay on the exchanges. This has given companies incorporated in the Cayman Islands a dubious reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, the Cayman Islands are also heavily used by Chinese companies for their &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/&quot;&gt;state of incorporation&lt;/a&gt;. This similar use of the Cayman Islands as a place of incorporation by SPACs and Chinese companies invites an unflattering comparison for SPACs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of SPACs has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/money-to-burn/&quot;&gt;spectacular&lt;/a&gt; in the last year. That kind of growth can be extremely attractive and create its own sort of momentum. However, it is not yet clear that SPACs are a good alternative to traditional IPOs for investors. Their tendency to incorporate in the Cayman Islands is concerning, especially since incorporating in the Cayman Islands is a common tactic for Chinese companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Cayman Islands" /><summary type="html">Our research indicates that only 3.3% of all companies are incorporated in the Cayman Islands, and that includes some companies that are actually located there. In contrast, 28% of all SPACs are incorporated in the Cayman Islands, despite the fact that 88% of them are located in the United States.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beach.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beach.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Money to Burn?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/money-to-burn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Money to Burn?" /><published>2020-12-30T09:43:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T09:43:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/money-to-burn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/money-to-burn/">&lt;p&gt;Long ago FINRA warned that SPAC managers were incentivized to overpay for companies. This year a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.renaissancecapital.com/IPO-Center/News/71816/Updated-SPAC-returns-fall-short-of-traditional-IPO-returns-on-average#:\~:text=Of%20the%20313%20SPACs%20IPOs,for%20traditional%20IPOs%20since%202015.&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; of SPACs showed that their average return was &lt;strong&gt;-9.6%&lt;/strong&gt;. Of all the SPACs studied, only &lt;strong&gt;31.1%&lt;/strong&gt; had positive returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Show me the incentive and I’ll show you the outcome.”&lt;/em&gt; -Charlie Munger&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 has held a lot of surprises, mostly bad. But one interesting surprise is that our records indicate that &lt;strong&gt;480&lt;/strong&gt; companies went public this year, far more than any other year in the past decade (the next highest was 369 in 2014). This could benefit investors since they should have more options and more competition for their investing dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant reason for the overall increase in public companies is a dramatic increase in the number of companies that are going public through special purpose acquisition companies (SPACs). Look for yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SPAC%20growth.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPAC growth.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPACs have become enormously popular. And they do offer some interesting advantages over traditional IPOs. A SPAC is formed as a blank check shell company and does not have any operations. This lack of prior operations makes performing due diligence less expensive and time consuming. This allows companies to go public much &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.crunchbase.com/news/spac-vs-traditional-ipo-investors-see-benefits-of-blank-check-companies/&quot;&gt;faster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money invested in a SPAC sits in an escrow fund while the manager of the SPAC looks for a suitable private company to invest in. Typically, the SPAC must find a target within 2 years, or the SPAC will be dissolved (and the money refunded).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manager of the SPAC will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-spac-compensation/investors-push-back-on-blank-check-company-insiders-payout-bonanza-idUSKBN28J1I9&quot;&gt;typically&lt;/a&gt; receive 20% of the SPAC at a discount for consummating a merger (although sometimes they get less). This discount allows a manager to make money on an investment in a SPAC, even if the other investors lose money on the deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FINRA provided some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finra.org/rules-guidance/notices/08-54#:\~:text=A%20SPAC%20typically%20must%20complete,of%20the%20assets%20in%20escrow.&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; on SPACs back on October 13th 2008, and at the end of the notice they warn about a potential incentive problem for SPAC managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“SPAC managers have a strong incentive to buy a company, even at inflated values, since they will get 20 percent of the company at a nominal price.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPAC Returns Indicate Prices Are Inflated&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 1st, Renaissance Capital released the results of its own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.renaissancecapital.com/IPO-Center/News/71816/Updated-SPAC-returns-fall-short-of-traditional-IPO-returns-on-average#:\~:text=Of%20the%20313%20SPACs%20IPOs,for%20traditional%20IPOs%20since%202015.&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; of SPACs since 2015 and found that the average return was &lt;strong&gt;-9.6%&lt;/strong&gt;. And the median return was even worse at &lt;strong&gt;-29.1%&lt;/strong&gt;. Of all the SPACs that they studied, only &lt;strong&gt;31.1%&lt;/strong&gt; had positive returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a dismal track record considering that traditional IPOs had returns of &lt;strong&gt;47%&lt;/strong&gt; over the same period. It is likely that the SPAC mangers’ incentive to pay inflated prices for mergers has contributed to the wide disparity in returns for SPACs versus IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really a corporate governance issue. Good corporate governance requires that the managers be properly incentivized to act in the best interests of the investors, since the money belongs to the investors and not to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here SPAC managers get nothing if they cannot find a target but can still win big even if they overpay for an underperforming company. Although not &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1811882/000119312520175042/d930055ds1.htm&quot;&gt;every&lt;/a&gt; SPAC is structured this way, looking carefully at the incentives in a SPAC is something that every investor should do before following the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;O insurers spend a lot of time on new bid requests. Our clients use our Watchdog Reports to quickly discover which bids they should pursue. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="featured" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Incentives" /><category term="Returns" /><summary type="html">Long ago FINRA warned that SPAC managers were incentivized to overpay for companies. This year a study of SPACs showed that their average return was -9.6%. Of all the SPACs studied, only 31.1% had positive returns.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Burning%20Money.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Burning%20Money.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Impact of CEO Changes</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-ceo-changes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Impact of CEO Changes" /><published>2020-12-22T10:18:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-22T10:18:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-ceo-changes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-ceo-changes/">&lt;p&gt;This year we have looked at the impact of several different types of events, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch/&quot;&gt;restatements&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/material-weaknesses-worsen/&quot;&gt;material weaknesses,&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm-part-ii/&quot;&gt;securities class actions&lt;/a&gt; on share values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We measure the impact of these “gray swan” events by comparing the change in a company’s share price in the 30 days after the event with the contemporaneous change in the S&amp;amp;P 500. We do this analysis so that we can more accurately predict both the probability and the likely price decline of future gray swan events for over 4,800 public companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is derived from the report “Frequency and Impact of CEO Changes” by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD. If you would like a copy of the report, please contact jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we will take a brief look at CEO changes and impact they have had on share price. One interesting thing to note is that CEO changes appear to be distributed evenly among companies of all sizes. In the last ten years, bigger companies have only been slightly more likely to retain their CEOs for longer than smaller companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CEO%20Changes%20table%20by%20market%20cap.png&quot; alt=&quot;CEO Changes table by market cap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting because our examination of material weaknesses, restatements, and securities class action suits all uncovered vast disparities between companies based on market cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEO changes tend to have a negative effect on the stock price, although the impact is not typically too substantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CEO%20Impact%20Histogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;CEO Impact Histogram.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a little more detail on the above graph. The average impact of a CEO change is &lt;strong&gt;-2.7%&lt;/strong&gt; over the 30 days following the CEO departure. Although, &lt;strong&gt;15.8%&lt;/strong&gt; of the CEO changes resulted in losses of &lt;strong&gt;20%&lt;/strong&gt; or more during that window. In contrast, however, &lt;strong&gt;40%&lt;/strong&gt; of CEO changes do not result in negative returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data indicates that a CEO change is not necessarily a significant event, but the challenges that come with turnover in management will tend to have slight negative effect on share value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in about &lt;strong&gt;15%&lt;/strong&gt; of cases, the losses associated with the departure of a CEO will be significant. We suspect that in these cases the CEO’s departure is only a part of a “parade of horribles” that the company is experiencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;O insurers spend a lot of time on new bid requests. Our clients use our Watchdog Reports to quickly discover which bids they should pursue. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt;to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. Or you can contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="CEO Turnover" /><category term="featured" /><category term="CEO Changes" /><category term="Impact Analysis" /><summary type="html">This year we have looked at the impact of several different types of events, like restatements, material weaknesses, and securities class actions on share values.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CEO%20Image.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CEO%20Image.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Material Weaknesses Worsen</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/material-weaknesses-worsen/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Material Weaknesses Worsen" /><published>2020-12-17T09:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-17T09:39:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/material-weaknesses-worsen</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/material-weaknesses-worsen/">&lt;p&gt;Accounting related problems at a company generally don’t get much press … until they do. A total accounting failure can result in an SEC investigation, restatements, lawsuits, and a catastrophic and long-lasting decline in stock price. In the last few years, we have seen &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/ge-goosing-accounting-estimates-to-lay-golden-eggs/&quot;&gt;GE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;Kraft Heinz&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;Under Armour&lt;/a&gt; all suffer severe and lasting consequences for accounting related issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were not black swan events, each of them was presaged by warning flags that should have warned investors of what lay ahead. Unfortunately, few people had the time to notice these flags, or had the expertise to factor in the risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you correctly foresaw these gray swan events, but the odds are that you were in the majority of people who missed them and lost money. Our Gray Swan Event Factor can help you stay ahead of the curve and anticipate accounting risks more easily. Request a free &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/request_demo&quot;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Material Weaknesses on the Rise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we calculate our Gray Swan Event Factor, we look at a lot of different variables. One variable is whether a company disclosed a material weakness. A company will disclose a material weakness when one or more of their internal controls (procedures and safeguards against financial reporting irregularities) is ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year we create a report on the frequency and impact of material weaknesses. This article touches on a few key points, but if you would like to see the full report, email us and we will send it to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of companies that reported a material weakness increased sharply in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Material%20Weaknesses%20numbers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Material Weaknesses numbers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This increase in the overall number of material weaknesses reported continues an upward trend that has been consistent over the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of the likelihood that any given company will disclose a material weakness, we took the same information and expressed it in percentages. In 2019, &lt;strong&gt;13.3%&lt;/strong&gt; of companies disclosed a material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Material%20Weaknesses%20percentages.png&quot; alt=&quot;Material Weaknesses percentages.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This increase in material weaknesses should raise concerns amongst investors. When a company has a material weakness it means that there could be undetected problems with their financial reporting. Those undetected problems could be grievous accounting errors requiring a restatement, or worse, fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting that the number of disclosed material weaknesses are on the rise, despite the fact that the SEC continues to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/&quot;&gt;loosen standards&lt;/a&gt; concerning the auditor attestation requirement under Sox 404(b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company Size Predictive of Frequency and Impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all companies are equally likely to experience a material weakness. In fact, our research indicates that a small company is far more likely to have a material weakness than a large company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Material%20Weakness%20table%20by%20market%20cap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Material Weakness table by market cap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason for this disparity is that the auditors of large companies must test their internal controls, this creates a strong incentive to expend the resources necessary to create effective internal controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the disclosure of a material weakness does not tend to have a large impact on the value of a company’s stock price, particularly for larger companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Material%20Weakness%20table%20returns%20by%20market%20cap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Material Weakness table returns by market cap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A company that has material weaknesses in their financial reporting is more likely to experience other events that have a much greater impact on stock price, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch/&quot;&gt;restatements&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm-part-ii/&quot;&gt;securities class action suits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Material weaknesses have increased steadily over the past decade from &lt;strong&gt;7.2%&lt;/strong&gt; in 2010 to &lt;strong&gt;13.3%&lt;/strong&gt; in 2019. Smaller companies that have fewer regulatory requirements and fewer resources were far more likely to disclose a material weakness than larger companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These material weaknesses do not have much of an immediate impact on stock price, but they do increase the risk of problems with the financial reporting. Problems with the financial reporting can lead to restatements, lawsuits, investigations, and a host of other problems that can result in catastrophic losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gray swan event can lead to catastrophic losses unless you are one of the few people who see it coming. Our Gray Swan Reports can help you navigate an uncertain future. Sign up for a free &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/request_demo&quot;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; today and learn how our information can keep you ahead of the curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would to have our blog sent directly to your inbox, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/signup/&quot;&gt;sign up&lt;/a&gt; here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com about this article.  For press inquires, contact our President, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Material Weaknesses" /><category term="Red Flags" /><summary type="html">Accounting related problems at a company generally don’t get much press … until they do. A total accounting failure can result in an SEC investigation, restatements, lawsuits, and a catastrophic and long-lasting decline in stock price. In the last few years, we have seen GE, Kraft Heinz, and Under Armour all suffer severe and lasting consequences for accounting related issues.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Material%20Weakness.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Material%20Weakness.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Red Flag CEO Changes</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/red-flag-ceo-changes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Red Flag CEO Changes" /><published>2020-12-11T15:12:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-11T15:12:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/red-flag-ceo-changes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/red-flag-ceo-changes/">&lt;p&gt;Public companies disclose an enormous amount of information every year, but they don’t tell you what it means. Our Watchdog Reports summarize all the relevant corporate governance and financial reporting issues in a simple report that flags issues and provides peer-to-peer comparisons. Once you know what the information means, you can act with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important issues that we track is turnover in the C-suite. We track CEO and CFO changes for every public company and assign them a red, yellow, or green flag. If an investor should look to one person to best protect the investor’s interest it would be the CEO. If the CEO goes, investors should be very concerned and want to know a clear reason for the departure. In this post we will look specifically at CEO changes and show you the criteria for how we assign a red flag&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Reason Offered for a CEO Departure Can Raise a Red Flag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies must file a disclosure when they make a change at the CEO position, and they oftentimes offer some sort of reason for the departure. For example, we will assign a red flag if the CEO departs to “pursue other interests,” which is always suspicious considering how much CEOs get paid to be interested in working for their employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our system also will assign a red flag to any CEO change due to a disagreement with management, a dismissal for cause, or if wrongdoing was suspected or determined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, McDonald’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/63908/000089882219000080/pressrelease1.htm&quot;&gt;parted ways&lt;/a&gt; with ex-CEO Steve Easterbrook for violating company policy by engaging in an inappropriate relationship with an employee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/$MCD%20CEO%20Change.png&quot; alt=&quot;$MCD CEO Change.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McDonald’s disclosure of wrongdoing was unusual. Our previous &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/why-has-ceo-turnover-remained-high-for-the-last-three-years/&quot;&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; of company disclosures concerning CEO departures from 2020 found that less than 4% of the departures were ascribed to misconduct. However, for almost 70% of CEO departures, the companies either gave no explanation, or an explanation so nondescript that it revealed nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is indisputable that companies replace CEOs for misconduct far more often than they &lt;em&gt;disclose&lt;/em&gt; that they replace a CEO for misconduct. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pwc.com/gx/en/news-room/press-releases/2019/ceo-turnover-record-high.html&quot;&gt;PwC study&lt;/a&gt; suggested that &lt;em&gt;nearly 40%&lt;/em&gt; of CEO departures in 2018 were due to an “ethical lapse.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we cannot rely on the companies to tell us when a CEO departure should raise a red flag, we also look at the surrounding facts and circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Brief Tenure Can Also Raise a Red Flag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common reason we assign a CEO change a red flag is if the departing CEO leaves their position after a relatively brief period. For example, in 2019 we assigned a red flag to Mark Okerstrom’s departure from Expedia because he had only held the position for two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/$EXPE%20CEO%20change.png&quot; alt=&quot;$EXPE CEO change.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expedia also replaced its CFO the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1324424/000119312519305833/d843290dex991.htm&quot;&gt;same day&lt;/a&gt; as a part of a change in direction for the company. This decision appears to have been strategic and not related to any misconduct on the part of Expedia’s executives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect our red flag for Lawrence Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was on point. Molloy resigned for “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691717000008/january312017form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;personal reasons&lt;/a&gt;” in January 2017. His departure appears to have sparked an investigation by the SEC of accounting practices from 2015-2016 that earned Under Armour a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000119312520199113/d43403d8k.htm&quot;&gt;Wells notice&lt;/a&gt; this past July. Interestingly, Molloy’s abrupt departure as CEO appears to have been due to the ethical lapses of *other *executives at Under Armour, not him. But his departure should have raised a big red flag for investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PwC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pwc.com/gx/en/news-room/press-releases/2019/ceo-turnover-record-high.html&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; that we referenced earlier claimed that 40% of CEO departures were due to ethical lapses in 2018, nearly 50% higher than in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our own analysis shows that the number of CEO changes that we have assigned a red flag has steadily increased over the last three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CEO%20RED%20Flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;CEO RED Flag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These numbers give credence to the idea that a far greater portion of CEOs are departing under questionable circumstances than these corporations would like to admit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our System Filters Interim Changes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note on this topic of red flag CEO changes. As a part of the normal CEO turnover process, many companies will select an interim CEO while they search for someone to fill the position in the long-term. Our system does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; assign red flags for these brief interim appointments because they are common practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why we assign green, yellow, and red flags in our reports is because we want to make it easier to spot future gray swan events (public disclosures that often lead to a steep decline in a company’s stock price).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes at the CEO position are always important, but our system can help cut through the noise and draw attention to the CEO departures that are the most likely to have a significant effect on the company’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;O insurers spend a lot of time on new bid requests. Our clients use our Watchdog Reports to quickly discover which bids they should pursue. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="CEO Changes" /><summary type="html">Public companies disclose an enormous amount of information every year, but they don’t tell you what it means. Our Watchdog Reports summarize all the relevant corporate governance and financial reporting issues in a simple report that flags issues and provides peer-to-peer comparisons. Once you know what the information means, you can act with confidence.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Red%20Flag.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Red%20Flag.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Has CEO Turnover Remained High for the Last Three Years?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/why-has-ceo-turnover-remained-high-for-the-last-three-years/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Has CEO Turnover Remained High for the Last Three Years?" /><published>2020-12-04T09:43:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T09:43:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/why-has-ceo-turnover-remained-high-for-the-last-three-years</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/why-has-ceo-turnover-remained-high-for-the-last-three-years/">&lt;p&gt;When assessing a company, it is always a good idea to see if there has been any unusual turnover in the C-suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turmoil in the C-suite often trickles down to other aspects of a company and is often associated with other problems. New CEOs can clash with existing management, and often there is a rocky transition as new systems are imposed on a company. Sometimes a new CEO will uncover problems successfully hidden by the previous CEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, some of our previous &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; showed that companies with a red flag CEO change were more than twice as likely to be named in a Securities Class Action suit in that same year as companies without one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly the rate of CEO departures had remained steady for most of the last decade, at least until 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CEO%20turnover.png&quot; alt=&quot;CEO turnover.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart depicts the CEO turnover for publicly traded companies on the Nasdaq and NYSE for the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis for the year-to-date in 2020 shows that the rate for CEO departures so far this year is &lt;strong&gt;13.5%&lt;/strong&gt;. This number will tick up as more CEOs depart in December. We won’t know the final results for about another month, but it is clear that 2020 has continued in the same vein as 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is this happening?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to establish exactly what is driving this trend, but we can point to two interesting pieces of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pwc.com/gx/en/news-room/press-releases/2019/ceo-turnover-record-high.html&quot;&gt;PwC&lt;/a&gt;, who found that 39% of CEO departures in 2018 were due to “ethical lapses.” This was up 50% from 2017. This number itself is something of a mystery. It would be tempting to ascribe this increase to the #metoo movement that lead to so many accusations of sexual harassment in 2017-2018, but that explanation does not explain why the turnover would remain high the following years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also don’t know how PwC determined that a CEO departure was due to an “ethical lapse.” We looked at the company disclosures concerning the departures most of them don’t give any real information. For the year-to-date in 2020, 38.5% of the explanations were opaque. And another 30.3% actually said nothing at all. Only 2.9% of the company disclosures stated that there was misconduct on the CEO’s part. Since companies are so tight lipped, PwC must be looking at some other sources of information to support their conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second piece of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; is ours and it relates to the increase of litigation after the Supreme Court’s decision in Cyan, Inc. v. Beaver County Employees’ Retirement Fund. &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; helped dramatically increase the rates at which companies were sued in Securities Class Action suits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Probability%20of%20Litigaiton-3491fb.png&quot; alt=&quot;Probability of Litigaiton-3491fb.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows the likelihood for any company on the Nasdaq or NYSE to be named in a Securities Class Action suit in the last decade. The graph shows that litigation increased dramatically in 2017 and has remained at an elevated level ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear if litigation is causing CEO turnover or if CEO turnover is causing litigation, but the phenomena are related. Litigation can put a strain on a company’s resources and put a spotlight on the decisions or conduct of the CEO, causing them to depart prematurely. A sudden CEO departure can also trigger a lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the sustained increases in litigation and CEO departures point to a widespread increase in volatility in public companies. It’s not clear if this volatility is occurring for legal or cultural reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The volatility could be due to decisions from the Supreme Court and the outgoing Trump Administration, or it could be due to the emergence of new cultural values in boardrooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall increase in volatility could also just be a part of a generational shift as baby boomers exit the stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this new volatility a blip, or a paradigm shift? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public companies publish so much information that it is easy to miss critically important information.  Our Watchdog Reports allow our clients to quickly assess any public company. If you never want to  get caught flatfooted, then request a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/request_demo&quot;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; . Special offers available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="CEO Turnover" /><category term="featured" /><category term="CEO" /><summary type="html">When assessing a company, it is always a good idea to see if there has been any unusual turnover in the C-suite.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CEO%20Departure.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CEO%20Departure.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Divided Loyalty: Something is Rotten in Beijing</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Divided Loyalty: Something is Rotten in Beijing" /><published>2020-11-30T08:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-30T08:39:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Xi Jinping’s rebuke of Jack Ma has laid bare a critical problem in Chinese corporate governance. Chinese companies are required to put loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping before all other loyalties. Any perceived lack of loyalty to Xi Jinping is punished.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ANT Group was supposed to IPO on November 5th, it was going to raise $34.4 billion, the biggest capital raising of all time. In a remarkable turn of events reported by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/china-president-xi-jinping-halted-jack-ma-ant-ipo-11605203556&quot;&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;, Xi Jinping, China’s dictator, scuttled the IPO after getting incensed at some comments made by ANT Group’s Chairman Jack Ma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wall Street Journal quoted a senior Chinese official, who stated “&lt;em&gt;Xi doesn’t care about if you made any of those rich lists or not … What he cares about is what you do after you get rich, and whether you’re aligning your interests with the state’s interests&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wall Street Journal’s reporting makes it clear that the sole purpose for scuttling ANT Group’s IPO was to punish a lack of loyalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though investors are aware that Xi Jinping is an authoritarian dictator and that his whim is law, it still came as a shock to see his power exercised in this way. Alibaba, which shares ownership of ANT Group with Jack Ma, lost a significant amount of value after ANT Group’s IPO was scrapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was unsettling to see the raw power and influence of Xi Jinping and his associates on display in this case. But there are broader implications for China and the U.S. that should really be giving investors pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerning the broader implications of the ANT Group story, Kevin Lacroix, author of blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2020/11/articles/securities-litigation/ant-groups-scrubbed-ipo-triggers-u-s-failure-to-launch-claim-against-alibaba/&quot;&gt;The D&amp;amp;O Diary&lt;/a&gt;, wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The one thing this sequence of events does show is that there is a substantial component of political risk involved in doing business in, and investing in companies that do business in, China. The fact that political officials and financial regulators might intervene in markets out of anger against company executives or out of a desire to cut company officials down to size underscores the fact that the political dimension of China’s economy can never be disregarded. These events put a huge asterisk beside the market capitalization and business prospects of any company doing business in China.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every Chinese Company Has a Serious Flaw in its Corporate Governance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For Chinese executives, loyalty to Xi Jinping supersedes all others and leaves shareholders holding the bag.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog, we produce reports for every public company traded on U.S. exchanges. Each one of these reports contains a section on corporate governance issues because understanding what is going on in the C-suite is critical for understanding what is going on at a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pith of the problem in Chinese corporate governance is that executives have obligations to both the state and investors, and those loyalties are in conflict. But to understand that conflict over loyalty and why it is such a significant problem, we need to take a few steps back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporations exist to facilitate the flow of capital from people outside the corporation (investors) to the people inside the corporation (the directors and officers). Investors put their capital at risk to generate productivity, growth, and wealth, and they reap some share of the profits as a reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directors and officers at the company are in a position of trust, and corporate governance rules are designed to ensure that they do not abuse this trust. Courts and legislators have taken steps to protect this trust because it is essential to the efficient flow of capital, indeed to capitalism itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To protect investors, the legislators and courts in this country have found that directors and officers owe a fiduciary duty to the investors and the corporate entity. In his 1928 opinion in Meinhard v. Salmon, Judge Cardozo articulated the essence of this legal duty as a “&lt;em&gt;duty of the finest &lt;strong&gt;loyalty&lt;/strong&gt;… Not honesty alone, but the punctilio of an honor the most sensitive, is then the standard of behavior&lt;/em&gt;.” (emphasis added) This duty has real teeth, since when a director or officer violates their fiduciary duty, shareholders can seek redress in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courts have found that this duty of loyalty requires that the director or officer put the interests of the company and the shareholders before other interests. Directors and officers must act within the confines of the law, but they violate their duty of loyalty if they advance their own interests, or the interests of any other entity, including the State or the broader community, over the interests of the shareholders (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/3528000/dodge-v-ford-motor-co/&quot;&gt;*507&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core corporate governance problem for Chinese companies is that they are required to put loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping before all other loyalties. Any perceived lack of loyalty to Xi Jinping is punished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practice reflects the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npc.gov.cn/zgrdw/englishnpc/Constitution/2007-11/15/content_1372963.htm&quot;&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt; of the People’s Republic of China, which states in Article 1, “&lt;em&gt;The People’s Republic of China is a socialist state under the people’s democratic dictatorship …. Disruption of the socialist system by any organization or individual is prohibited.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, shareholders of Chinese companies have no recourse if the directors engage in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;self-dealing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problems in corporate governance &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;often&lt;/a&gt; lead to problems in financial reporting because proper corporate governance is a key safeguard against fraud and abuse. Our research has shown that Chinese companies delist from U.S. exchanges at a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/only-the-good-die-young-chinese-delistings-part-i/&quot;&gt;higher rate&lt;/a&gt; than any other country, and that almost 60% of those delistings were credibly associated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finding-fraud-chinese-delistings-part-ii/&quot;&gt;fraud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Conflict in Loyalty is Not Just a Corporate Governance Issue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Xi Jinping’s demand for absolute loyalty also warps the roles of lawyers and accountants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conflict over loyalty is not limited to a tiff between China’s dictator and its wealthiest business owner. This problem touches many different aspects in international business in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in a post cautioning business owners from relying on Chinese lawyers, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chinalawblog.com/2020/10/beware-of-china-lawyers.html&quot;&gt;China Law Blog&lt;/a&gt; raises the possibility that “ &lt;em&gt;working&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;em&gt;your interest … might be your lawyer’s patriotic duty in China&lt;/em&gt;.” Since Chinese lawyers take a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rfa.org/english/news/china/china-makes-lawyers-swear-oath-12042018113905.html&quot;&gt;loyalty oath&lt;/a&gt; to the CCP, so “&lt;em&gt;it is simply unrealistic to expect there will be any meaningful pushback against government pressure&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pressure has been brought to bear in the accounting profession as well. We have written several stories about how the CCP refuses to allow auditors to share their work papers with the PCAOB, at least &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/&quot;&gt;most&lt;/a&gt; of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCP &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;requires&lt;/a&gt; Chinese nationals to run the Chinese Big 4 affiliates. This suggests that the CCP is exercising influence on the accounting profession, and we were not surprised to see an increasing share of audit opinions issued out of Beijing as power has concentrated there under Xi Jinping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Beining%20Audit%20opinions%25-d476d5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Beining Audit opinions%-d476d5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ANT Group’s failure to launch is a canary in the coalmine. It is not the first warning that investors &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;received&lt;/a&gt; concerning the dangers of investing in China, but it has struck close to home. Jack Ma’s former company, Alibaba, is the biggest recipient of western investment dollars, and is currently capitalized at $750 billion. The share price of Alibaba dropped significantly after ANT Group’s failure to launch; it will recover, even though Xi Jinping has demonstrated that he could seize Alibaba on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This episode also reveals a fundamental problem effecting every Chinese company. The communist ideology that animates the CCP undermines the fundamental relationships in a corporation. An executive’s primary loyalty is supposed to lie with the shareholders, &lt;em&gt;because the executive has been entrusted with the shareholder’s money&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in China, loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping supersedes all other loyalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communist ideology undermines the fundamental trust in relationships that make capital flow efficiently. Indeed, it undermines capitalism itself. This realization is no surprise to those who are familiar with communism’s history, or the writings of Marx, but it seems to have escaped those holding the levers of power in government and Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="Loyalty" /><category term="China" /><category term="CCP" /><summary type="html">Xi Jinping’s rebuke of Jack Ma has laid bare a critical problem in Chinese corporate governance. Chinese companies are required to put loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping before all other loyalties. Any perceived lack of loyalty to Xi Jinping is punished.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Ruins.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Ruins.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>