<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-30T14:01:15-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Divided Loyalty: Something is Rotten in Beijing</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Divided Loyalty: Something is Rotten in Beijing" /><published>2020-11-30T08:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-30T08:39:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Xi Jinping’s rebuke of Jack Ma has laid bare a critical problem in Chinese corporate governance. Chinese companies are required to put loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping before all other loyalties. Any perceived lack of loyalty to Xi Jinping is punished.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ANT Group was supposed to IPO on November 5th, it was going to raise $34.4 billion, the biggest capital raising of all time. In a remarkable turn of events reported by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/china-president-xi-jinping-halted-jack-ma-ant-ipo-11605203556&quot;&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;, Xi Jinping, China’s dictator, scuttled the IPO after getting incensed at some comments made by ANT Group’s Chairman Jack Ma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wall Street Journal quoted a senior Chinese official, who stated “&lt;em&gt;Xi doesn’t care about if you made any of those rich lists or not … What he cares about is what you do after you get rich, and whether you’re aligning your interests with the state’s interests&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wall Street Journal’s reporting makes it clear that the sole purpose for scuttling ANT Group’s IPO was to punish a lack of loyalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though investors are aware that Xi Jinping is an authoritarian dictator and that his whim is law, it still came as a shock to see his power exercised in this way. Alibaba, which shares ownership of ANT Group with Jack Ma, lost a significant amount of value after ANT Group’s IPO was scrapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was unsettling to see the raw power and influence of Xi Jinping and his associates on display in this case. But there are broader implications for China and the U.S. that should really be giving investors pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerning the broader implications of the ANT Group story, Kevin Lacroix, author of blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2020/11/articles/securities-litigation/ant-groups-scrubbed-ipo-triggers-u-s-failure-to-launch-claim-against-alibaba/&quot;&gt;The D&amp;amp;O Diary&lt;/a&gt;, wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The one thing this sequence of events does show is that there is a substantial component of political risk involved in doing business in, and investing in companies that do business in, China. The fact that political officials and financial regulators might intervene in markets out of anger against company executives or out of a desire to cut company officials down to size underscores the fact that the political dimension of China’s economy can never be disregarded. These events put a huge asterisk beside the market capitalization and business prospects of any company doing business in China.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every Chinese Company Has a Serious Flaw in its Corporate Governance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For Chinese executives, loyalty to Xi Jinping supersedes all others and leaves shareholders holding the bag.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog, we produce reports for every public company traded on U.S. exchanges. Each one of these reports contains a section on corporate governance issues because understanding what is going on in the C-suite is critical for understanding what is going on at a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pith of the problem in Chinese corporate governance is that executives have obligations to both the state and investors, and those loyalties are in conflict. But to understand that conflict over loyalty and why it is such a significant problem, we need to take a few steps back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporations exist to facilitate the flow of capital from people outside the corporation (investors) to the people inside the corporation (the directors and officers). Investors put their capital at risk to generate productivity, growth, and wealth, and they reap some share of the profits as a reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directors and officers at the company are in a position of trust, and corporate governance rules are designed to ensure that they do not abuse this trust. Courts and legislators have taken steps to protect this trust because it is essential to the efficient flow of capital, indeed to capitalism itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To protect investors, the legislators and courts in this country have found that directors and officers owe a fiduciary duty to the investors and the corporate entity. In his 1928 opinion in Meinhard v. Salmon, Judge Cardozo articulated the essence of this legal duty as a “&lt;em&gt;duty of the finest &lt;strong&gt;loyalty&lt;/strong&gt;… Not honesty alone, but the punctilio of an honor the most sensitive, is then the standard of behavior&lt;/em&gt;.” (emphasis added) This duty has real teeth, since when a director or officer violates their fiduciary duty, shareholders can seek redress in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courts have found that this duty of loyalty requires that the director or officer put the interests of the company and the shareholders before other interests. Directors and officers must act within the confines of the law, but they violate their duty of loyalty if they advance their own interests, or the interests of any other entity, including the State or the broader community, over the interests of the shareholders (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/3528000/dodge-v-ford-motor-co/&quot;&gt;*507&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core corporate governance problem for Chinese companies is that they are required to put loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping before all other loyalties. Any perceived lack of loyalty to Xi Jinping is punished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practice reflects the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npc.gov.cn/zgrdw/englishnpc/Constitution/2007-11/15/content_1372963.htm&quot;&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt; of the People’s Republic of China, which states in Article 1, “&lt;em&gt;The People’s Republic of China is a socialist state under the people’s democratic dictatorship …. Disruption of the socialist system by any organization or individual is prohibited.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, shareholders of Chinese companies have no recourse if the directors engage in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;self-dealing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problems in corporate governance &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;often&lt;/a&gt; lead to problems in financial reporting because proper corporate governance is a key safeguard against fraud and abuse. Our research has shown that Chinese companies delist from U.S. exchanges at a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/only-the-good-die-young-chinese-delistings-part-i/&quot;&gt;higher rate&lt;/a&gt; than any other country, and that almost 60% of those delistings were credibly associated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finding-fraud-chinese-delistings-part-ii/&quot;&gt;fraud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Conflict in Loyalty is Not Just a Corporate Governance Issue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Xi Jinping’s demand for absolute loyalty also warps the roles of lawyers and accountants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This conflict over loyalty is not limited to a tiff between China’s dictator and its wealthiest business owner. This problem touches many different aspects in international business in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in a post cautioning business owners from relying on Chinese lawyers, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chinalawblog.com/2020/10/beware-of-china-lawyers.html&quot;&gt;China Law Blog&lt;/a&gt; raises the possibility that “ &lt;em&gt;working&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;em&gt;your interest … might be your lawyer’s patriotic duty in China&lt;/em&gt;.” Since Chinese lawyers take a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rfa.org/english/news/china/china-makes-lawyers-swear-oath-12042018113905.html&quot;&gt;loyalty oath&lt;/a&gt; to the CCP, so “&lt;em&gt;it is simply unrealistic to expect there will be any meaningful pushback against government pressure&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pressure has been brought to bear in the accounting profession as well. We have written several stories about how the CCP refuses to allow auditors to share their work papers with the PCAOB, at least &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/&quot;&gt;most&lt;/a&gt; of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCP &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;requires&lt;/a&gt; Chinese nationals to run the Chinese Big 4 affiliates. This suggests that the CCP is exercising influence on the accounting profession, and we were not surprised to see an increasing share of audit opinions issued out of Beijing as power has concentrated there under Xi Jinping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Beining%20Audit%20opinions%25-d476d5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Beining Audit opinions%-d476d5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ANT Group’s failure to launch is a canary in the coalmine. It is not the first warning that investors &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;received&lt;/a&gt; concerning the dangers of investing in China, but it has struck close to home. Jack Ma’s former company, Alibaba, is the biggest recipient of western investment dollars, and is currently capitalized at $750 billion. The share price of Alibaba dropped significantly after ANT Group’s failure to launch; it will recover, even though Xi Jinping has demonstrated that he could seize Alibaba on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This episode also reveals a fundamental problem effecting every Chinese company. The communist ideology that animates the CCP undermines the fundamental relationships in a corporation. An executive’s primary loyalty is supposed to lie with the shareholders, &lt;em&gt;because the executive has been entrusted with the shareholder’s money&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in China, loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping supersedes all other loyalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communist ideology undermines the fundamental trust in relationships that make capital flow efficiently. Indeed, it undermines capitalism itself. This realization is no surprise to those who are familiar with communism’s history, or the writings of Marx, but it seems to have escaped those holding the levers of power in government and Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="Loyalty" /><category term="China" /><category term="CCP" /><summary type="html">Xi Jinping’s rebuke of Jack Ma has laid bare a critical problem in Chinese corporate governance. Chinese companies are required to put loyalty to the CCP and Xi Jinping before all other loyalties. Any perceived lack of loyalty to Xi Jinping is punished.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Ruins.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Beijing%20Ruins.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Post-Cyan Paradigm: Part II</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm-part-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Post-Cyan Paradigm: Part II" /><published>2020-11-20T12:57:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-20T12:57:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm-part-ii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm-part-ii/">&lt;p&gt;Securities Class Action suits tend to have a negative effect on companies of all sizes. But Small and Mid cap companies tend to suffer more when named as a defendant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our last &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; we measured the impact of the Supreme Court’s decision in Cyan, Inc. v. Beaver County Employee Retirement Fund (&lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt;). It increased the rates of Securities Class Action lawsuits for all companies but had a larger effect on litigation for Small and Mid cap companies than for Large companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is derived from “Frequency and Impact of Securities Class Actions” a research report produced by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD, for Watchdog Research. If you are interested in accessing the entire report, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team measures the impact of Securities Class Actions suits on public companies by looking at returns over the thirty-day period following a lawsuit and comparing those returns to the S&amp;amp;P 500 for the same period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at the abnormal returns of for every company following a Securities Class Action lawsuit for the past ten years and segmented the results by size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Table%20SCA%20Effect%20by%20Size.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table SCA Effect by Size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistically, the negative impact of a Securities Class Action lawsuit was inversely proportional to a company’s size. The impact on Small cap companies was more than five times worse than the impact on Large cap companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These statistics bring the impact of &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; into clearer focus. It appears that by opening state courts to Securities Class Action suits, the Supreme Court’s decision has created a significant burden on Small to Mid cap companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court’s decision has dramatically increased the rate of litigation for Small cap companies, a group which traditionally suffers the most when involved in this sort of litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small cap and Mid cap companies have limited resources, and this post-&lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; paradigm has put an unwelcome strain on these limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even Small cap companies that have not been subject to Securities Class Action suits have suffered, as the D&amp;amp;O insurance market has hardened in response to these trends since getting named in a suit is not a matter of &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher insurance premiums are passed on to investors, employees, and customers, harming everyone. The question is, is the post-&lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; paradigm here to stay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Cyan" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><summary type="html">Securities Class Action suits tend to have a negative effect on companies of all sizes. But Small and Mid cap companies tend to suffer more when named as a defendant.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Supreme%20Court.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Supreme%20Court.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Post-Cyan Paradigm</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Post-Cyan Paradigm" /><published>2020-11-17T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-17T11:30:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm/">&lt;p&gt;In March 2018, the Supreme Court handed down a unanimous decision in Cyan Inc. v. Beaver County Employees Retirement Fund (&lt;em&gt;“Cyan”&lt;/em&gt;). This decision allowed plaintiffs to bring cases in some state courts which previously had only been triable in federal court. &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; made it easier for plaintiffs to bring cases, and the predicable result has been an increase in cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is derived from “Frequency and Impact of Securities Class Actions” a research report produced by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD, for Watchdog Research. If you are interested in accessing the entire report, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; was a boon for plaintiff’s attorneys and for the defense attorneys called up to answer these claims, but it has been a real disaster for everyone else. D&amp;amp;O Insurance premiums have risen dramatically and created a hard market for policies. The increase in the cost of doing business has certainly been felt elsewhere too as costs get passed through to investors, employees, and customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just how much of an impact has &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; had? Our team has published a report that can help quantify its impact. One way to measure the impact of Cyan is to see the dramatic increase in the likelihood that any given company will be named in a Securities Class Action suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Probability%20of%20Litigaiton.png&quot; alt=&quot;Probability of Litigaiton.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, as &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; was working its way toward the Supreme Court, cases shot up dramatically. The number of Securities Class Action suits has remained at an elevated level ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph actually understates the increase in litigation post-&lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; because many companies have more than one suit filed against them in a given year. So, we also measured the rate of Securities Class Actions over the past ten years to better capture the frequency with which these suits are filed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20rates.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA rates.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table reveals a few interesting things about how &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; has changed Securities Class Action litigation. The first thing to note is that the litigation rates have gone up for companies of every size. (Large cap companies have a market capitalization of $10+ billion, Mid cap companies have $1-10 billion, and Small cap companies is everything under $1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing to note is that the increase in the rate of litigation has been relatively higher for Small and Mid cap companies than for Large cap companies. This indicates that &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; has made it easier and more cost effective to bring cases against smaller companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This result was predictable, since the state courts have fewer procedural safeguards, making it easier and less expensive to bring a case. Small defendants with fewer resources and a smaller potential payout appear to have become more appealing targets for litigation. Additionally, fewer procedural safeguards make it easier to justify bringing a weaker case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research corresponds with academic research and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2020/06/articles/securities-litigation/the-post-cyan-section-11-litigation-environment/&quot;&gt;commentary&lt;/a&gt; indicating that suits in state courts are settled at significantly higher rates because it is much easier for plaintiffs to survive a motion to dismiss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Securities Class Action litigation hit record levels in 2017, and thanks to &lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt;, litigation has remained at an elevated level. In this new paradigm, companies of all sizes are at far more risk of being named in one or more suits than in years past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research indicates that the size of a company is one of the most important factors determining the impact of litigation, but we will take a closer look at that data in our next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Litigation Risk" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Litigaiton" /><category term="Cyan" /><summary type="html">In March 2018, the Supreme Court handed down a unanimous decision in Cyan Inc. v. Beaver County Employees Retirement Fund (“Cyan”). This decision allowed plaintiffs to bring cases in some state courts which previously had only been triable in federal court. Cyan made it easier for plaintiffs to bring cases, and the predicable result has been an increase in cases.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Legal.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Legal.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding Fraud: Chinese Delistings Part II</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finding-fraud-chinese-delistings-part-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding Fraud: Chinese Delistings Part II" /><published>2020-11-11T09:55:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-11T09:55:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finding-fraud-chinese-delistings-part-ii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finding-fraud-chinese-delistings-part-ii/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;57% of Chinese delistings are associated with fraud, illegal activity, or highly suspicious circumstances, according to our research&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our previous post, we looked at how Chinese companies are delisted at a higher rate than companies from any other country. In this post, we will look at why Chinese companies are delisted at such high rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collected data on 158 Chinese companies delisted from the NYSE and NASDAQ between 2010 and 2020. We gathered this data by searching through articles and public statements concerning each company, specifically examining the facts and circumstances around the time of delisting. We then categorized our results by keywords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is derived from “Chinese Deslistings: Frequency and Causes” a research report produced by Joseph Burke, PhD, and John Cheffers, for Watchdog Research. If you are interested in accessing the entire report, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were surprised to find that a majority of the delistings were associated with the keyword fraud, or that the facts and circumstances surrounding the delisting provided the indicia of fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20Fraud%20Table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese Fraud Table.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the same information in an eye-catching Pie Chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20Fraud%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese Fraud Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Limitations on our Research&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies rarely admit to committing fraud, so we cannot definitively determine whether fraud occurred in many of these cases. A delisting associated with the keyword “fraud,” means only that we found credible articles connecting the company to fraud in the press, or that circumstances surrounding the delisting were sufficiently suspicious to infer fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mere fact that press articles accused a company of fraud does not mean that a fraud caused the delisting, or even occurred at the same time as the delisting, so we may have put some companies in the fraud category where there was no fraud. By the same token, we may have missed fraud in some cases where the fraud was missed by the press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we know of at least one occasion where we initially missed a company entirely because the company changed its location out of China before getting officially delisted. We knew about this company from other research we were conducting, but we do not know if that sort of transfer is common or exceptionally rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patterns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all fraud takes the same form, but we saw some common patterns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few companies were delisted on suspicion of fraud, but that was rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More often, companies had credible accusations of fraud directed at them by short sellers or in lawsuits &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; a delisting. Others were credibly accused of fraud &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; a merger that seemed to defraud shareholders and enrich insiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we inferred fraud in some circumstances where it multiple auditor changes and chronic late filings make it appear that independent auditors came across serious problems and would no longer sign off on the financial statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research strongly suggests that Chinese companies are delisted at higher rates than companies from other countries because they are far more likely to be unmasked as frauds. It will take some time to gather an equivalent dataset for U.S. and other foreign listings, but we suspect that a much smaller percentage of delistings in the U.S. will be associated with fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese companies are getting listed on U.S. exchanges in record numbers. Investors should exercise extreme caution if they are considering investing in a Chinese company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Fraud" /><category term="Delisting" /><category term="China" /><summary type="html">57% of Chinese delistings are associated with fraud, illegal activity, or highly suspicious circumstances, according to our research.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/57%25%20Pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/57%25%20Pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Only the Good Die Young? Chinese Delistings: Part I</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/only-the-good-die-young-chinese-delistings-part-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only the Good Die Young? Chinese Delistings: Part I" /><published>2020-11-06T15:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T15:01:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/only-the-good-die-young-chinese-delistings-part-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/only-the-good-die-young-chinese-delistings-part-i/">&lt;p&gt;Investors in Chinese companies are at a greater risk of a total loss from delisting than those investing in companies from any other country. This risk is especially high in the first few years after a Chinese company is listed on a U.S. Exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is derived from “Chinese Deslistings: Frequency and Causes” a research report produced by Joseph Burke, PhD, and John Cheffers, for Watchdog Research. If you are interested in accessing the entire report, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IPO activity has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2020/11/articles/ipos/does-increased-ipo-activity-foreshadow-increased-ipo-related-securities-litigation-ahead/&quot;&gt;boomed&lt;/a&gt; in 2020, with October the busiest month in 20 years. For Chinese companies, this recent uptick continues a trend from 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Graph%20Chinese%20listings.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph Chinese listings.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the previous IPO wave that crested in 2011, Chinese companies experienced a subsequent wave of delistings. Over the past ten years an average of 7.63% of Chinese issuers have been delisted every year, although that number has experienced tremendous variation year-to-year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Graph%20Chinese%20Delistings.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph Chinese Delistings.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the Chinese companies that made up the first wave of Chinese listings were small China-based issuers that gained access to the market via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20&quot;&gt;reverse merger&lt;/a&gt;. Small Chinese companies merged with defunct publicly traded companies, thereby getting onto U.S. exchanges through a “backdoor listing.” Many of these companies were later exposed as frauds, and the SEC and the Nasdaq eventually tightened up standards to prevent widespread abuse of these “backdoor listings.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC and Nasdaq tightened their rules in 2011, which resulted in a number of delistings. But interestingly, Chinese delistings remained at elevated levels for several years, and rose again in 2019. For the first and later part of the past decade, Chinese companies have consistently delisted at a higher rate than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Delistings%20by%20country.png&quot; alt=&quot;Delistings by country.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that a good portion of early Chinese delistings were associated with the reverse merger scandal and that the SEC and the exchanges tightened restrictions in the aftermath of the reverse merger wave. But this table demonstrates that delistings for Chinese companies have remained high since 2015, despite the reforms that were made by the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also worth noting that much of the recent IPO surge has been due to the proliferation of SPAC mergers, which are a hybrid of traditional reverse mergers and traditional IPOs. We don’t know how these SPAC companies will fare, but the early results have not been promising, with average returns of negative 9.6% according to a study by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.renaissancecapital.com/IPO-Center/News/71816/Updated-SPAC-returns-fall-short-of-traditional-IPO-returns-on-average#:\~:text=Of%20the%20313%20SPACs%20IPOs,for%20traditional%20IPOs%20since%202015.&quot;&gt;Renaissance Capital&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Age at Delisting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key piece of our report looks at how long these companies stayed on the exchanges before they were delisted. Our research indicates that most Chinse companies were delisted within a few years of getting onto an exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Age%20of%20delistings.png&quot; alt=&quot;Age of delistings.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows that most Chinese delistings occur within a few years of an IPO. That should give investors pause when they consider pouring their money into one of the many Chinese companies have listed in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No company is a sure bet, but some are riskier than others. Investors expect some up and downs in the market, but a delisting can represent a total loss of value in an investment, and the potential risk of a delisting should be a top concern when deciding where to invest. Investors should exercise great caution when investing in Chinese companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a part of our analysis, we also looked at when the circumstances surrounding these delistings raised concerns of fraud. But to see those numbers, you will have to wait for Part II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="China" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Delisting" /><category term="China" /><summary type="html">Investors in Chinese companies are at a greater risk of a total loss from delisting than those investing in companies from any other country. This risk is especially high in the first few years after a Chinese company is listed on a U.S. Exchange.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Good%20die%20young.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Good%20die%20young.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Impact of Restatements: The Bigger They Are…</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Impact of Restatements: The Bigger They Are…" /><published>2020-10-29T13:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-29T13:18:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot/">&lt;p&gt;There is nothing worse as an investor than when a company experiences a gray swan event like a financial restatement. Investors are rarely prepared for the bad news and have difficulty placing it into context; it is no wonder that for many investors the initial reaction to a financial restatement is a panicked sell-off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information is the antidote to panic, so we have looked at the data for restatements and other gray swan events to arm investors with as much information as possible &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; something bad happens. We produce reports on certain kinds of events, like restatements, that take a survey of the field and measure their impact on share price. Investors can also look at our company specific reports and our Gray Swan Event Factor to get a more granular view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we are analyzing the relative impact of restatements when segmenting the market by size. We have found that the impact of a restatement is proportional to the relative size of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog touches on a few data points from an extensive report produced by two of our researchers, Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD. If you want access to the full report, email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The analysis for this report was primarily derived from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt; restatement database.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our research, we broke the market down into three segments, Large cap, Mid cap, and Small cap. In our analysis, Large companies have more $10 billion in market capitalization, Small cap firms have less than $2 billion, and Mid cap companies fall between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at how many restatements occurred for each segment over the past ten years and calculated the likelihood of incurring a restatement for each segment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table shows the financial restatements by size from 2010-2019. One thing to note is just how exceptionally rare it is for a Large cap company to issue a restatement. A Mid cap company is more than twice as likely as Large cap company to issue a restatement. And Small cap companies are almost seven times more likely to issue a restatement than a Large cap company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Size Proportional to Impact&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team also measured the impact of these restatements on share value. Our team calculated the impact by looking at how the stock performed in comparison with the S&amp;amp;P 500 over the next 30 days. Share price data was not available for every company which had a restatement, but we were able to get share prices for an adequately representative sample.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of our analysis shows that the impact of a restatement is proportional to the size of the company. Restatements have a large impact on big companies, but a smaller impact on smaller companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%20abnormal%20returns.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements abnormal returns.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table shows abnormal returns by size from 2008 to 2020 year-to-date. What explains this disparity? One factor may be the relative lack of attention and scrutiny on Small cap companies. Restatements for big companies are an unusual event, so when a Large cap company has one, the market experiences a strongly negative reaction to the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Large cap companies are also far more likely to be subject to a securities class action suit after a restatement, which can amplify the negative cycle and downward pressure on share value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our research, restatements have fallen steadily over the past decade. Restatements for Large cap companies are exceptionally rare, but when they do occur, they can be extremely harmful. But the same does not hold true for Mid cap and Small cap companies Our research indicates that the impact of a restatement is often proportional to the size of a company, so if a Small cap company issues a restatement, it may end up being small potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Independent Research" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Financial Restatements" /><summary type="html">There is nothing worse as an investor than when a company experiences a gray swan event like a financial restatement. Investors are rarely prepared for the bad news and have difficulty placing it into context; it is no wonder that for many investors the initial reaction to a financial restatement is a panicked sell-off.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size%20pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size%20pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Restatements Are Rare, But Can Pack a Punch</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Restatements Are Rare, But Can Pack a Punch" /><published>2020-10-23T15:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T15:35:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch/">&lt;p&gt;Public companies are required to keep investors and the public well informed concerning their financial condition. People rely on this information and expect it to be accurate. Accordingly, a company must file a restatement if it determines that its previous financial disclosures were inaccurate, and that people should not rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog touches on a few data points from an extensive report produced by two of our researchers, Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarbrough, PhD. If you want access to the full report, email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The analysis for this report was primarily derived from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt; restatement database.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note is that restatements have declined significantly over the past ten years, although the rate of decline has slowed significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatement%20Probability.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatement Probability.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph shows the annual share of companies filing one or more financial restatements from 2010 to 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decline should bring a great deal of comfort to many companies since restatements are one of the most harmful gray swan events that we track. Restatements are often the opening salvo in a torrent of bad press. A restatement often occurs because of a substantial material weakness in the internal controls and often can precipitate turnover in the management team, particularly at the CFO position. Additionally, restatements often trigger class action securities lawsuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis compared the returns over the thirty days following a restatement to the returns from the S&amp;amp;P 500 over the same timeframe.   The data shows that the typical reaction of the market to a restatement is negative (approximately 2/3 of restatements resulted in negative returns). The most common result is negative returns from zero to 10%, but a significant portion (approximately 15%) had a negative return of 20% or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%20Histogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements Histogram.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph groups companies by how their share prices performed in comparison with the S&amp;amp;P 500 in the 30 days after a restatement was reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis indicates that for many companies, issuing a restatement is a trying—but manageable—event. However, in a significant minority of cases, the losses can be catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some Notable Cases from 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the percentage of companies impacted by a restatement in 2019 was relatively low, some of the restatements that did occur had a near record-breaking impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pareteum Corp (TEUM)&lt;/strong&gt; had a restatement in October, 2019, and lost 69.6% of its value over the next 30 days ($119 in market cap). TEUM’s decline in value (as a percentage of its pre-restatement value) over the thirty days following its restatement was more than any other company in the last ten years. TEUM was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1084384/000110465920115313/tm2033276d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt; in October 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kraft Heinz (KHC)&lt;/strong&gt; had a restatement in February 2019 that erased $12.7 billion in market cap after its restatement on February 9th, 2019. This loss in vale was the second largest in the last ten years. If you want to know more, you can read some of our analysis on KHC &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baxter International Inc (BAX)&lt;/strong&gt; had a restatement in October 2019 that erased $4.39 billion in market cap over the next thirty days. Even though BAX lost significantly less money than KHC, it was still the third largest loss of value in the last ten years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restatements today are far less common than they were a decade ago, although the rate of decline has slowed in recent years. Our research also shows that 2/3 of restatements have a negative impact on share price. Although the response to a restatement is generally negative, people may be surprised by the fact that 1/3 of restatements had &lt;em&gt;no negative impact&lt;/em&gt; on the share price after 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though restatements are not as common as they used to be, a restatement can still be a catastrophic gray swan event, as is evident from the negative impact that they had on TEUM, KHC, and BAX in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These restatement numbers are just one facet of our Gray Swan Event Factor. With our GSEF we calculate the risk of gray swan events for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. If you would like a demo, email our President Brian Lawe via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Independent Research" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Financial Restatements" /><summary type="html">Public companies are required to keep investors and the public well informed concerning their financial condition. People rely on this information and expect it to be accurate. Accordingly, a company must file a restatement if it determines that its previous financial disclosures were inaccurate, and that people should not rely on them.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Punch%20Pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Punch%20Pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Marcum in the Middle: China, the U.S., and the PCAOB</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marcum in the Middle: China, the U.S., and the PCAOB" /><published>2020-10-20T16:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-20T16:32:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/marcum-in-the-middle-china-the-u-dot-s-and-the-pcaob/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We reached out to Marcum LLP, Marcum BP, and the PCAOB for comment concerning this article and did not receive any responses.  We will keep you apprised of any responses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/signup/&quot;&gt;Sign up&lt;/a&gt; to get our blogs sent directly to your inbox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 24, 2020, the PCAOB released a settled disciplinary order against Marcum LLP for a matter dating back to November 2016, when Marcum issued a single unqualified opinion for the 2013, 2014, and 2015 financial statements of a company incorporated in Delaware, but headquartered and operating primarily located in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The essence of the story is that Marcum’s engagement team, as the signing firm for an audit where its affiliate, Marcum BP, was performing the work on the ground, inappropriately acquiesced to management and should not have offered an unqualified opinion of their financial statements. The disciplinary &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Enforcement/Decisions/Documents/105-2020-012-MARCUM-LLP.pdf&quot;&gt;order&lt;/a&gt; contains all the interesting details and we encourage you to read it for yourself. But the most interesting thing about this PCAOB report is not what it found, &lt;em&gt;but that it exists at all&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tensions between China and the U.S. over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;accounting profession&lt;/a&gt; have been mounting for a decade. After Enron collapsed in 2001, legislative reform—the Sarbanes-Oxley law passed in 2002—created the PCAOB to provide independent oversight of the auditing firms via routine inspections. The law required every company listed on a U.S. exchange to be audited by an auditing firm that was registered with the PCAOB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According the SEC, the PCAOB, and the Big 4, the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) has simply refused to allow PCAOB inspectors to inspect Chinese audit work papers, declaring them “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-vital-role-audit-quality-and-regulatory-access-audit-and-other&quot;&gt;state secrets&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCP has taken other measures to cement control over its accounting profession. They ordered the Big 4 to hand over control of Chinese affiliates to Chinese nationals. In early 2020, they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/u-s-moves-to-audit-chinese-firms-market-frets-over-what-comes-next-11590485401&quot;&gt;outlawed&lt;/a&gt; cooperation with overseas regulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these restrictions, or perhaps because of them, the share of audit opinions issued out Beijing has doubled in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dispute over the auditing profession belies a fantasy that the differences between China and the U.S. are merely accidental and not substantive— a fantasy held by a class of people hoping to benefit from China’s growth potential and foisted on everyone else through the normal institutional channels. However, the dispute over the PCAOB’s access to Chinese auditors shows that China and the U.S. are in separate worlds, playing by different sets of rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum in the Middle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big 4’s response to the inconsistent directives of the U.S. and the CCP has been to bifurcate their firms and put a ring fence around their affiliates in China. Although the U.S. affiliates and the Chinese affiliates share the same global brands, they do much more than socially distance. Our research indicates that every Chinese client of a Big 4 firm has been audited by a local Chinese affiliate since 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the safe way for auditing firms to do business in China. But the downside is that the CCP’s grip on information and refusal to allow PCAOB inspections makes everything that happens in China opaque. We cannot be sure of the quality of audits, or the integrity of financial reporting, and we have no idea if the CCP has been inappropriately pressuring auditors to give some companies an easy time. That is possible given how many state-owned enterprises there are in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read our previous &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/where-in-the-world-is-marcum-bernstein-pinchuk/&quot;&gt;piece &lt;/a&gt;on Marcum BP [Marcum BP is a separate entity from Marcum LLP, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accountingtoday.com/news/pcaob-sanctions-marcum-from-doing-china-audits?utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_content=socialflow&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=accountingtoday-tw&quot;&gt;formed&lt;/a&gt; by a partnership between Marcum LLP and Bernstein &amp;amp; Pinchuk in 2010 and focuses primarily on serving Chinese clients], then you know that Marcum LLP and Marcum BP do not operate in the same way as the Big 4. Marcum LLP and Marcum BP are U.S. firms that provide audits for Chinese companies. Both Marcum firms, and a few other small firms, attempt to navigate the incoherent landscape created by the contradictory directives of China and the U.S. These firms have broken with conventional wisdom and exist in this strange place between the U.S. and China, and it’s not clear which rules apply in this no man’s land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCAOB settled disciplinary order against Marcum LLP points to its inspection of the audit of a company headquartered and operating primarily in China. That is inexplicable considering how everyone says that its impossible for the PCAOB to do that. According to the SEC and the Big 4, this inspection should not have been possible because the work papers are considered “state secrets” by the CCP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, here is a settled disciplinary order based on an inspection of the work papers of an audit of the Chinese operations of a company. It is not clear how this is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to our confusion, a Chinese newspaper has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2020-08/09/c_139275803.htm&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that China’s regulator claims it “&lt;em&gt;has never prohibited or prevented relevant accounting firms from offering audit work papers to overseas regulators&lt;/em&gt;.” That claim is inconsistent with the new law banning cooperation with foreign regulators and how the Chinese affiliates of the Big 4, the SEC, and the PCAOB have characterized the issue over the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what gives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t know the answer to this question, but we suspect that it may have something to do with the fact that both Marcum LLP and Marcum BP are U.S. firms, and not Chinese. The relatively small footprint of Marcum LLP and Marcum BP in China may also contribute to an inconsistent application of the “state secrets” rule.  The CCP is an authoritarian regime; accordingly, there is no reason to believe that the CCP would feel bound to follow the “rule of law” and enforce rules consistently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marcum Alone in the Spotlight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is inexplicable how Marcum LLP was subject to inspection by the PCAOB, while none of the Big 4 affiliates in China are subject to the same scrutiny. We hypothesized that the state of incorporation was relevant, since the issuer inspected was incorporated in Delaware, but the data did not bear that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Marcum%20China%20incorporation%20location.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marcum China incorporation location.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pie chart is a representation of where Chinese companies listed on the NYSE and Nasdaq are incorporated. Most Chinese companies on the Nasdaq and NYSE are incorporated in tax havens, connected to their Chinese operations through VIEs. A significant portion of Chinese companies were incorporated in U.S. Only a relatively small portion of Chinese companies are incorporated in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we are not sure how it happened. However, it seems that Marcum LLP is the only firm with Chinese clients that has received scrutiny from the PCAOB. The PCAOB’s report on Marcum is certainly embarrassing and upsetting for a reputable firm with a lot of pride. Marcum has been barred from signing audits for Chinese companies for three years. But, given the context, it really should raise concerns about audit quality across China. The Marcum partners made this error even though they knew their work would be subject to meaningful review by the PCAOB; is there any good reason to believe that the audit partners at the Big 4 affiliates are holding themselves to a higher standard when they know the PCAOB cannot review their work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that makes this story so complex is that, on one hand, we would like to applaud Marcum’s relative transparency in comparison to the opaque Big 4 affiliates. But, on the other hand, they are rightfully taking their lumps over the lack of audit quality in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PCAOB Sanctions Will Not Have Much Impact on Marcum LLP&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most attention-grabbing part of the PCAOB’s settled disciplinary order was the three-year ban on issuing audit reports for clients with substantially all their operations in China. But since Marcum LLP partnered up with Bernstein and Pinchuk in 2010, work in China has not been a significant part of their business in recent years. Our research indicates that Marcum LLP only had 8 clients in China in 2019. (Marcum BP has more, but they were not affected by these sanctions.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Marcum%20clients%20in%20China.png&quot; alt=&quot;Marcum clients in China.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent increase is due to the proliferation of “blank check” companies, aka special purpose acquisition companies (SPACs); Marcum LLP specializes in SPACs. In 2019, four of Marcum LLP’s Chinese clients were blank check acquisition companies. Since SPACs do not really have operations, it is unclear if the PCAOB’s ruling will affect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One critical point is that the PCAOB’s order does not appear to have any impact on Marcum BP, since they were only referred to as a related party and not a respondent in this matter. In contrast, Marcum LLP and Marcum BP were both subject to a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/News/Releases/Pages/PCAOB-Sanctions-Two-Firms-and-One-Individual-for-Auditor-Independence-Violations.aspx&quot;&gt;disciplinary order&lt;/a&gt; from the PCAOB related to auditor independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unclear if this settled disciplinary order has concluded this matter, or if the PCAOB will address Marcum BP separately for its role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marcum LLP has an infinitesimal portion of the Chinese audit market in comparison to the Big 4, but their approach to navigating the contradictory directives of the U.S. and China provides more transparency and accountability than is available from the Big 4 affiliates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another complicating factor is Marcum LLP and Marcum BP’s willingness to take on risky clients. In this case, Marcum LLP took over for another auditor which had resigned nearly a year earlier because of differences with the management team. Recently, Marcum BP took over the audit for Luckin Coffee from Ernst &amp;amp; Young Hua Ming LLP after a massive fraud was exposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That transparency, and willingness to take on messy situations from riskier clients has come at a cost for Marcum LLP, but it has provided an invaluable insight to those interested in audit quality in China. This report demonstrates how valuable PCAOB inspections could be for improving audit quality and accountability for management in China. Hopefully, the CCP and the U.S. will reach an agreement to bring the same level of transparency to all accounting firms in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="China" /><category term="Marcum LLP" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="China" /><summary type="html">We reached out to Marcum LLP, Marcum BP, and the PCAOB for comment concerning this article and did not receive any responses. We will keep you apprised of any responses.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Marcum%20LLP%20China%20Image.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Marcum%20LLP%20China%20Image.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SEC Comment Letters Shed More Light on Reverse Factoring</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-shed-more-light-on-reverse-factoring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SEC Comment Letters Shed More Light on Reverse Factoring" /><published>2020-09-24T13:50:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-24T13:50:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-shed-more-light-on-reverse-factoring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sec-comment-letters-shed-more-light-on-reverse-factoring/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is published with permission of Olga Usvyatsky, a former VP of Research at Audit Analytics. She has a distinguished library of blogs and op-eds on accounting, buy-side research, and data analysis. Ms. Usvyatsky is currently enrolled as a PhD in Accounting student at Boston College, where she earned her MS in Accounting degree.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We welcome guest posts on interesting topics. Please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; if you would like to have us feature your work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in January &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/&quot;&gt;we discussed challenges&lt;/a&gt; involved when the risks of reverse factoring agreements are introduced. In 2020 the SEC issued comment letters to at least four companies, namely Procter &amp;amp; Gamble (PG), Graphic Packaging Holding (GPK), Boeing (BA) and Coca-Cola (CO) asking for more details about their reverse factoring agreements. This was after the SEC sent supply chain financing comment letters to Keurig Dr Pepper (KDP) and Masco (MAS) in 2019. In this blog, we would like to look at supply chain financing disclosures following the SEC reviews and discuss some of the language in the comment letters and disclosures that we find interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s provide a quick recap. Reverse factoring agreements document the terms when a company helps a supplier sell the company’s accounts receivable in exchange for better credit terms. The supplier pays a fee to sell the receivables, and if the fee is small enough, the trade is a winner for all parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/12927/000001292720000065/a202006jun3010-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q filing&lt;/a&gt; for the period June 30, 2020, Boeing’s trade payables included $4.4 billion payable to suppliers that participated in supply chain financing programs (SCF). Proctor &amp;amp; Gamble’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/80424/000008042420000053/pg-20200630.htm&quot;&gt;annual report&lt;/a&gt; disclosed that, as of June 30, 2020, the amounts due to suppliers that participated in SCF programs were about $4 billion. And Coca-Cola noted in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/21344/000002134420000041/ko-20200626.htm&quot;&gt;quarterly report&lt;/a&gt; that, as of June 30, 2020, suppliers elected to sell $714 million of the outstanding payment obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/sec-asks-boeing-coca-cola-to-disclose-more-about-popular-financing-tool-11598526651&quot;&gt;WSJ article&lt;/a&gt; used fees generated by banks that participated in reverse factoring agreements to estimate the size of the supply-chain financing sector. According to the article, the fees in the first half of 2020 were $12.7 billion, up 3.6% from the previous year. To develop a complete estimate of the size of the supply-chain financing receivables sold we would also need to know the average fees charged by the banks (the fee for each company would, of course, be different and depend on the credit risk of the receivables).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens if a major shock changes the credit environment and the sources of short-term liquidity suddenly dry up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major challenges with understanding the risk involved in supply chain financing are lack of disclosure, diversity in practice, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://fasb.org/cs/BlobServer?blobkey=id&amp;amp;blobnocache=true&amp;amp;blobwhere=1175836059659&amp;amp;blobheader=application%2Fpdf&amp;amp;blobheadername2=Content-Length&amp;amp;blobheadername1=Content-Disposition&amp;amp;blobheadervalue2=667317&amp;amp;blobheadervalue1=filename%3DAR-2019.UNS.020.BIG_4_ACCOUNTING_FIRMS.pdf&amp;amp;blobcol=urldata&amp;amp;blobtable=MungoBlobs&quot;&gt;lack of regulatory guidance&lt;/a&gt; (we talked about that in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-practice-of-reverse-factoring-raises-transparency-concerns/&quot;&gt;previous blog&lt;/a&gt;). In June 2020 the SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/corpfin/covid-19-disclosure-considerations&quot;&gt;issued an update&lt;/a&gt; on what companies are expected to disclose to address pandemic-related liquidity concerns. Notably, supply chain financing was explicitly referenced in this update:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Are you relying on supplier finance programs, otherwise referred to as supply chain financing, structured trade payables, reverse factoring, or vendor financing, to manage your cash flow? Have these arrangements had a material impact on your balance sheet, statement of cash flows, or short- and long-term liquidity and if so, how? What are the material terms of the arrangements? Did you or any of your subsidiaries provide guarantees related to these programs? Do you face a material risk if a party to the arrangement terminates it? What amounts payable at the end of the period relate to these arrangements, and what portion of these amounts has an intermediary already settled for you?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the SEC comment letters process is to increase the transparency of financial reporting. For the most part, the SEC’s supply chain financing comments requested that the companies provide additional disclosures about the terms and materiality of the supply chain financing programs and their impact on liquidity and cash from operations. A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://jimhamiltonblog.blogspot.com/2020/09/is-supply-chain-financing-disclosure.html&quot;&gt;Jim Hamilton’s blog&lt;/a&gt; (that we found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecorporatecounsel.net/blog/&quot;&gt;TheCorporateCounsel&lt;/a&gt;) described in great detail the nature of the supply chain comments issued so far, so we will skip the general discussion and look at language that sets the letters apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/21344/000002134420000027/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;opening letter&lt;/a&gt; for Coca Cola is provides an example of interesting language on the subject:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We note from your disclosures that accounts payable increased roughly $1.1 billion in 2019 due to the extension of payment terms with your suppliers. &lt;strong&gt;We further note from external sources that it appears you have in place a supply chain finance program&lt;/strong&gt;.” (emphasis added)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not uncommon for the SEC, as part of the comment letter process to review earnings calls, press releases, or media articles. A search of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/products/sec/comment-letter-threads&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics’&lt;/a&gt; comment letter database identified more than 800 companies which received a comment letter that was at least partially based on information disclosed during an earnings call. Yet, to the best of our knowledge, references to an “external source” are very rare. Disclosures about supply chain financing are limited, so it is not surprising that the SEC had to use a third-party source to confirm the existence of the agreements. It would be interesting to know if these external sources named other companies and whether more comment letters are coming. (We will keep monitoring the comment letter disclosures).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we would like to add a note about Boeing’s supply chain financing letters and relevant disclosures. A common theme among the supply chain financing comment letter responses was the lack of materiality of the supply chain financing on overall liquidity. Boeing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/12927/000001292720000056/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt; in its response that the company does not consider supply chain financing programs to be material to the overall liquidity. The company pointed out that they had decided to provide additional disclosure because of the significant negative liquidity impact that the company has experienced. The disclosure below is from the 10-Q filing for the period June 30, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Payables to suppliers who elected to participate in supply chain financing programs declined by $1.3 billion for the six months ended June 30, 2020 and increased by $1.8 billion for the same period in the prior year. Supply chain financing is not material to our overall liquidity. The decline for the six months ended June 30, 2020 was primarily due to reductions in commercial purchases from suppliers and not due to any changes in the availability of supply chain financing. The increase for the six months ended June 30, 2019 reflects a combination of higher purchases, an extension of payment terms with certain suppliers and increased utilization of our supply chain financing programs.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boeing included additional disclosures in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/12927/000001292720000065/a202006jun3010-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q filing&lt;/a&gt;, noting that while the access to supply chain financing can suffer if the company’s credit rating is downgraded, the company does not expect that the changes in availability of supply chain financing to have a material effect on liquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the disclosure we have seen so far, companies tend to record supply chain financing in current liabilities, so extended payment terms following the supply chain programs may result in higher days payable. (For illustrative purposes, P&amp;amp;G &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/80424/000008042419000060/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt; that the company’s days payable increased 8 days as of the June 30, 2019.) The challenge, of course, is to understand whether the increase in accounts payable was part of the supply chain financing, a general change in the account payable’s terms, or just an attempt to delay payments and preserve liquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, receiving a comment letter does not imply that there is anything wrong with a company’s disclosures. The goal of a comment letter is to provide more information to investors, and we have seen increased disclosures of supply chain financing programs following the comment letter review process. For the companies that do not provide any supply chain financing disclosures (as we discussed above, a company may consider the program to be immaterial), investors can get a small hint by looking at the trends in accounts payable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Watchdog Blog Team contacted Coca-Cola, P&amp;amp;G, and Boeing concerning this article. Boeing and Coca-Cola declined to comment, and P&amp;amp;G did not respond to our request for comment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact  our content manager, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about our company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We offer easy-to-use reports on individual public companies, if you would like to demo our products, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>olga_usvyatsky</name></author><category term="Guest Blog" /><category term="featured" /><category term="reverse factoring" /><category term="Supply Chain Financing" /><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><summary type="html">This post is published with permission of Olga Usvyatsky, a former VP of Research at Audit Analytics. She has a distinguished library of blogs and op-eds on accounting, buy-side research, and data analysis. Ms. Usvyatsky is currently enrolled as a PhD in Accounting student at Boston College, where she earned her MS in Accounting degree.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Paperwork.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Paperwork.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybersecurity Litigation Review</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cybersecurity-litigation-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybersecurity Litigation Review" /><published>2020-09-22T10:37:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T10:37:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cybersecurity-litigation-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cybersecurity-litigation-review/">&lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity has gone from a niche concern to a hot topic in the D&amp;amp;O insurance world. Tomorrow, on September 23rd, we will be attending (remotely of course)  a webinar hosted by PLUS on how companies can strategically handle cybersecurity concerns. We are an independent research provider that uses an extensive database of public information to create easy-to-use reports for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. Since we track cybersecurity incidents and all material litigation for public companies, we thought we could use this as an opportunity to provide a little color to the important discussions concerning cybersecurity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overview&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began by looking at incidents that occurred at companies listed on the NYSE and Nasdaq over the past ten years, and the growth rate of cybersecurity incidents is alarming:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Cyber%20Incidents.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cyber Incidents.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*The graphs and tables in this post were created by Joseph Burke, PhD, and derived the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt; database.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, only .1 % of companies reported a cybersecurity incident. In 2019, 2.2% of companies reported a cybersecurity incident. The growth of cybersecurity incidents over the past five years has been incredible and it is not clear when it will slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting facet is that the risk of a cybersecurity incident is much higher at a large company that it would be at a small company. Attacks on large companies are driving much of the growth in these numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Cyber%20Incident%20Table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cyber Incident Table.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cybersecurity Security Class Actions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cyberbreach at a company creates all sorts of problems, including litigation. We identified all the security class action suits that were brought over cybersecurity issues and calculated the likelihood of being named in one of those suits. Unsurprisingly, the last ten years has shown significant growth in the risk of being named in a cybersecurity related lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Cyber-lawsuit%20prob.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cyber-lawsuit prob.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that these percentages are for all companies. Large cap companies have a significantly higher probability than is represented in the graph because they are both more likely to be the victim of a cybersecurity incident and are generally more likely to have a securities class action suit filed against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cybersecurity as a Leading and Covariate Indicator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of our researchers, Joseph Burke PhD and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3562785&quot;&gt;research paper&lt;/a&gt; calculating when particular flags from our reports were associated with an increased risk of securities class action litigation for 2014-2018. Companies with a cybersecurity incident were almost three times as likely to get named in a securities class action lawsuit the year that the incident occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, cybersecurity incidents were one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/&quot;&gt;six leading indicators&lt;/a&gt; of securities class action suits. An event is considered a leading indicator of litigation if the occurrence of that event is associated with an increased risk of litigation for the &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chance of being involved in a cybersecurity securities class action lawsuit is still relatively low, but it is increasing rapidly. Additionally, the risk profile is far higher for large companies, which are more likely to be a victim of a cybersecurity incident and more likely to get named in a securities class action lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If company boards wish to prevent having their company victimized twice (by hackers and by lawyers), then they need to make wise and strategic decisions to confront this growing threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this article, please contact the author, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have questions about the company generally, or for press inquires, please contact our president Brian Lawe, brianlawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company has access to a proprietary database that includes all material litigation, classified by issue, for public companies. If you are interested in some bespoke research on litigation trends, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Cybersecurity" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Cybersecurity" /><category term="Litigaiton" /><summary type="html">Cybersecurity has gone from a niche concern to a hot topic in the D&amp;amp;O insurance world. Tomorrow, on September 23rd, we will be attending (remotely of course) a webinar hosted by PLUS on how companies can strategically handle cybersecurity concerns. We are an independent research provider that uses an extensive database of public information to create easy-to-use reports for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. Since we track cybersecurity incidents and all material litigation for public companies, we thought we could use this as an opportunity to provide a little color to the important discussions concerning cybersecurity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Cybersecurity.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Cybersecurity.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>