<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Watchdog Transparency Blog - Most recent 5 featured articles</title>
        <description>Most recent 5 articles categorized as 'Featured'</description>
        <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com</link>
        <atom:link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.featured.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 13:55:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>


        
        <item>
            <title>Kraft Heinz: Complaint Alleges Fundamental Corporate Governance Problems, Accounting Shenanigans, and Insider Trading</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>Litigation</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;Kraft Heinz (KHC) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000020/february2019form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a massive $15.4 billion impairment in February, 2019 to its goodwill and intangible assets.  This impairment was essentially an admission by management major components of the combined company were worth billions less than recorded on the balance sheet.  It was also an admission that 3G Capital (3G) and Warren Buffett’s much touted merger of Kraft and Heinz was a failure.   In the aftermath, Warren Buffett &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/buffett-criticizes-others-for-using-non-standard-accounting-metricsbut-he-does-too-2019-02-26&quot;&gt;admitted &lt;/a&gt;that he had overpaid for his 27% of combined company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHC’s impairment crushed share prices and has led to lawsuits, rapid executive bloodletting, an SEC investigation, and other deleterious events.  We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about the KHC bus-crash last September and argued that KHC’s core problem was a loss of investor trust and a poor management ethos.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-29T13:55:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/conclusion-of-the-contract-3100578_640.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>New Research: Gray Swan Event Factor is Predictive of Stock Return</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>Gray Swan Event Factor</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joseph Burke PhD. and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, have produced two white papers for Watchdog Research that show that companies with higher Gray Swan Event Factors have a lower return on investment. This is because accounting-related risks are not properly priced into the market, potentially giving investors who use this valuable tool an edge over the broader market.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-22T15:33:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/New%20Research.png" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>Coronavirus</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;concerns &lt;/a&gt;about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>featured</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections.  An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/indicators/unemployment/&quot;&gt;skyrocketing &lt;/a&gt;unemployment.  To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;permitted &lt;/a&gt;companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports</title><author>John Cheffers</author>
            
            <category>Red Flags</category>
            

            <description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/</link><enclosure url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" length="100000" type="image/jpeg"/><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/</guid>
        </item>
        

    </channel>
</rss>

