<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-29T06:17:56-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Sizzle and PIPE Dreams in SPAC-land</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sizzle-and-pipe-dreams-in-spac-land/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sizzle and PIPE Dreams in SPAC-land" /><published>2021-06-28T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T10:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sizzle-and-pipe-dreams-in-spac-land</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/sizzle-and-pipe-dreams-in-spac-land/">&lt;p&gt;SPACs are allowed to make dazzling projections without supporting data and retail investors may not be aware of some conflicts of interest that influence sponsors’ investment behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special purpose acquisition companies (SPACs) have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/05/27/sec-considers-new-investor-protections-for-spacs.html&quot;&gt;exploded&lt;/a&gt; in popularity in the last 18 months, with 90% created in 2020 or 2021. A SPAC, also known as blank-check company, is a stock created by sponsors that raises money in an initial public offering with no underlying business. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;Typically&lt;/a&gt;, the SPAC must use its cash within two years to buy a private company (in a de-SPAC transaction), or refund the money to investors. Generally, investors don’t know what the acquisition target will be until the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SPAC usually uses additional funds from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2021/03/26/spac-investing-101-what-is-a-pipe-and-what-should/&quot;&gt;PIPE&lt;/a&gt; (private investment in public equity) to accomplish the de-SPAC. By starting the company this way, a SPAC purports to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thinkadvisor.tradepub.com/free/w_johc18/&quot;&gt;avoid&lt;/a&gt; the regulatory requirements of a traditional IPO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of SPACs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/spacs-an-attractive-alternative-to-a-8460350/&quot;&gt;tout&lt;/a&gt; them as good for small-time retail investors, because of the relatively low cost to own shares (usually only $10) and the ability to divest of shares before the merger. However, there are a number of notable risks for investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sizzle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPACs have a looser regulatory environment than traditional IPOs. They can make projections that traditionally are “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/spacs-ipos-liability-risk-under-securities-laws&quot;&gt;not commonly found in conventional IPO prospectuses&lt;/a&gt;.” This allows the sponsors, those who start the SPAC, to “sell the sizzle, not the steak”, because until the merger is announced, there is, in fact, no steak to sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors have little information to go on in assessing the SPAC. In particular, retail investors may not be aware of conflicts of interest that influence sponsors’ investment behavior. The SEC admitted as much when it provided &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/corpfin/disclosure-special-purpose-acquisition-companies&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; for SPAC disclosure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The economic interests of the entity or management team&lt;/em&gt; … &lt;em&gt;often differ from the economic interests of public shareholders which may lead to conflicts of interests&lt;/em&gt; as they evaluate and decide whether to recommend business combination transactions to shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this guidance, SPAC sponsors have &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2021/06/04/um-where-is-the-sec-when-it-comes-to-spacs-and-conflicts-of-interest/&quot;&gt;continued&lt;/a&gt; to target companies where they have apparently have a personal vested interest. SPAC are not prohibited from these self-interested transactions. They only have to tell investors, usually in a lengthy disclosure, that the SPAC capital might be used to buy one of their own companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent story &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2021/06/04/um-where-is-the-sec-when-it-comes-to-spacs-and-conflicts-of-interest/&quot;&gt;featured&lt;/a&gt; in TechCrunch looked at the example of Reid Hoffman, a SPAC sponsor who is close to finalizing a merger deal with autonomous vehicle startup Aurora. But Hoffman’s venture firm, Greylock, began investing in Aurora in 2018, and he is on its board of directors. He could set the price for acquisition of Aurora by his SPAC at a level that would greatly enhance its value and therefore his bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SPAC proponent Chamath Palihapitiya, the “King of SPACs”, invested in insurance company Clover through his firm Social Capital &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2021-05-13/spac-king-chamath-palihapitiya-hopes-his-hype-will-keep-mesmerizing-you&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; one of his SPACs merged with Clover &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-clover-health-m-a-social-capital/clover-health-to-go-public-via-3-7-billion-deal-with-social-capital-idUSKBN26R1XB&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/jonathanponciano/2021/06/07/spac-king-regains-billionaire-status-as-trading-frenzy-boosts-clover-health/?sh=3990179f3828&quot;&gt;Since the merger&lt;/a&gt;, Clover has been the subject of an SEC investigation, an undisclosed Justice Department inquiry, and an accusation by short-seller Hindenburg Research of fraud, including kickbacks, misrepresentation and undisclosed third-party deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing stops these ethically questionable investments because the SEC’s guidelines are suggestions, not law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment banks that sponsor SPACs also have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/tech-and-spacs-sec-regulation-could-result-in-fewer-but-better-spacs-64000801&quot;&gt;potential&lt;/a&gt; conflict of interest. Some banking sponsors invest minimal amounts into a SPAC, but then also underwrite the launch of the IPO and serve as advisors for the deal to acquire an operating company. Often those fees are much larger than the bank’s investment as a sponsor, so the bank might have a much greater financial interest in completion of the merger deal than in the success of the SPAC itself. In March the SEC opened an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/business/exclusive-us-regulator-opens-inquiry-into-wall-streets-blank-check-ipo-frenzy-2021-03-25/&quot;&gt;inquiry&lt;/a&gt; into Wall Street banks, seeking information on how underwriters are managing the risks involved in their SPACs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC may be looking into the depth of due diligence SPACs perform before acquiring assets in the de-SPAC transaction, and whether huge payouts are fully disclosed to investors. The regulators may also be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/business/exclusive-us-regulator-opens-inquiry-into-wall-streets-blank-check-ipo-frenzy-2021-03-25/&quot;&gt;concerned&lt;/a&gt; about the heightened risk of insider trading between the initiation of the SPAC and when it announces its acquisition target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail investors should be aware that SPAC sponsors who have a vested interest in the target company may be using the merger to shore up a failing venture, a risky investment strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PIPE Dreams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail investors also fare &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/investing/2021/03/26/spac-investing-101-what-is-a-pipe-and-what-should/&quot;&gt;worse&lt;/a&gt; than the PIPE investors, who come in just before or after the merger is announced. The PIPE investors come in after they know the target, but still get to buy shares for $10, though they are often worth $15 or $20 right away. Ordinary investors can’t buy at the lower price this late in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waking From the Dream&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison Herren Lee, the SEC’s current acting chair, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfodive.com/news/ipo-deregulation-Allison-Herren-Lee-Jay-Clayton/586858/&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; last October at the Practicing Law Institute’s SEC Speaks, “In the short term, a SPAC investment acts largely as a blank check, so it is critical that [there’s an understanding of] the material risks involved.” As Paul &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/munter-spac-20200331&quot;&gt;Munter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Acting Chief Accountant of the SEC,&lt;/em&gt; noted,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether a company enters the public markets through a merger with a SPAC, traditional IPO, or other process, the quality and reliability of financial reporting and the quality of audits on the financial statements provided to investors is vital to our efforts to protect investors and to the confidence of investors in our markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past six months the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/five-key-takeaways-from-the-sec-s-3931115/&quot;&gt;signaled&lt;/a&gt; that SPACs will be subject to increased levels of scrutiny. One key area of focus has been on the disclosure of germane conflicts of interest from each SPAC participant: insiders like the sponsors and management team; the IPO’s public shareholders; and third parties like underwriters. These parties will need to avoid conflicts or scrupulously disclose them if they wish to avoid enforcement actions and liability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajiv Shukla, chairman and CEO of SPAC Alpha Healthcare Acquisition Corp., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/tech-and-spacs-sec-regulation-could-result-in-fewer-but-better-spacs-64000801&quot;&gt;believes&lt;/a&gt; the SEC will also likely require enhanced disclosures on other financial interests of sponsors over the lifecycle of the SPAC deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail investors who are interested in investing in a SPAC should do as much due diligence on the sponsors of the SPAC as they reasonably can. After all, since there is no underlying company, you really are just investing in the sponsors. If in the past, the sponsors have used SPAC funds to invest in target companies with financial ties to those sponsors, you may want to reconsider giving them your money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up next: SPAC Risks Part 2: Matchmaker, Matchmaker–Sponsor Advantage&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>elise_rose</name></author><category term="SPACs" /><category term="SPACs" /><category term="Conflict of Interest" /><summary type="html">SPACs are allowed to make dazzling projections without supporting data and retail investors may not be aware of some conflicts of interest that influence sponsors’ investment behavior.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Pipes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Pipes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Securities Class Actions by Size</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/analyzing-securities-class-actions-by-size/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Securities Class Actions by Size" /><published>2021-06-25T06:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-25T06:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/analyzing-securities-class-actions-by-size</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/analyzing-securities-class-actions-by-size/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bigger companies may be more likely to be sued than smaller companies, but they are also more resilient.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our firm, Watchdog Research, uses statistical analysis of past events to evaluate a company’s future. One of the most important events we track is the occurrence of Securities Class Action (SCA) lawsuits. All the data presented in this article is based on our statistical analysis of publicly available data concerning public companies on the NYSE and NASDAQ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our database allows us to track the probability that any given companies will be named in a SCA suit for a given year. Overall, the probability in the last ten years has increased, which has contributed to a hard market for D&amp;amp;O insurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Picture1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Picture1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Segmenting by Size&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our database shows us that this risk is not uniform for companies of all sizes. The larger a company is, the more likely it is to be named in a SCA suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Picture2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Picture2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our research companies with over $10 billion in market capitalization are categorized as Large cap. Companies with less than $1 billion are categorized as Small cap. And all the companies that fall between them are considered Mid cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cyan&lt;/em&gt; brought about a significant shift in the legal landscape for SCAs. So it is possible that higher SCA rates are part of a new paradigm and that there will be no return to mean. If that is the case, then the averages seen between 2017-2020 may become the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Table%20SCA%20by%20Market%20Cap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table SCA by Market Cap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of a company may be one the most important factors to know concerning a company’s likelihood of being named in a SCA. It holds true in every industry, even in pharmaceuticals where small companies are particularly volatile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20by%20Size%20and%20Industry.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA by Size and Industry.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resilience&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large companies are far more likely to be named in a SCA than small companies, but larger companies often have the resources to handle these suits. We looked at the abnormal returns for all companies after they were named in a SCA suit and found that these events had a far greater negative impact on smaller companies than larger companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20impact%20by%20size-278a03.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA impact by size-278a03.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We calculated these abnormal returns by comparing the company’s stock price performance to the S&amp;amp;P 500 over the 30 days following the announcement of a SCA suit. It is clear that after the initial shock of the announcement wears off, large companies tend to recover quickly. Smaller companies tend not to fare as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our data shows that no matter the industry, the larger a company is, the more likely it is to get sued in a SCA. However the risk calculation is not simple. Smaller firms are far less likely to get sued, but far more likely to suffer dramatic losses as a result of that suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These graphs and charts were made by our data scientist Joseph Burke, PhD. Much of this information is derived from “&lt;em&gt;Frequency and Impact of Securities Class Actions: 2021&lt;/em&gt;” a Watchdog Report made by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD. If you are interested in purchasing this report, or a license to the dataset we used to create it, then contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Securities Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Data Analysis" /><summary type="html">Bigger companies may be more likely to be sued than smaller companies, but they are also more resilient.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Picture2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Picture2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mergers Plant the Seeds For Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/mergers-plant-seeds-for-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mergers Plant the Seeds For Litigation" /><published>2021-06-21T09:20:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T09:20:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/mergers-plant-seeds-for-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/mergers-plant-seeds-for-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our research indicates that large mergers are a strong leading indicator for Securities Class Actions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway and the Brazilian firm 3G Capital collaborated to facilitate a merger that formed Kraft Heinz (KHC). In 2019 Kraft Heinz issued one of the largest impairments in history, over $15 billion. This impairment seems to have been a direct consequence of corporate governance &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; arising out of the merger. And it did not end there, Kraft Heinz impaired an additional $5 billion over the next two years and has been engaged in protracted legal battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every merger presents a difficult challenge of reconciling two different systems (each company has its own corporate culture, governance philosophy, financial reporting methods, IT solutions, compensation practices, etc.). When this reconciliation process does not go well, it can create serious problems that can play out over a course of years. This has been the story for Kraft Heinz, but they are not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correlating Mergers and Securities Class Action (SCA) Lawsuits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research into mergers indicates that a company takes a big risk when it merges with another company that is relatively comparable in size. In contrast, a company takes significantly less risk if it gobbles up a relatively small operation. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt; wrote off almost all of the $230 million it spent acquiring TIO in 2017 without batting an eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When cataloging these mergers for our research, relatively large mergers are assigned a red flag and relatively small mergers are assigned a yellow flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research indicates that over the last 20 years companies with a red-flag merger were &lt;strong&gt;2.12&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be named in a SCA lawsuit in the same calendar year (potentially occurring before or after the merger). Companies with a yellow-flag merger were &lt;strong&gt;1.38&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be subject to suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not as dramatic as it sounds. It is likely that in many cases these lawsuits &lt;em&gt;preceded&lt;/em&gt; the merger as merger-objection suits. Merger objection lawsuits typically lack substance and are often dealt with quickly. These ubiquitous lawsuits artificially inflate the number of lawsuits included in the calculation and diminish the importance of the relatively high correlation we found in the same calendar year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we were surprised to see that when we looked at the correlation between red-flag mergers and SCA suits there was a slightly stronger signal in the &lt;em&gt;following&lt;/em&gt; year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20Merger%20Leading%20Indicator.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA Merger Leading Indicator.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 20 years, any company that had a merger was &lt;strong&gt;1.45&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be subject to a SCA suit as a company that had not engaged in a merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for companies that had red-flag mergers, they were &lt;strong&gt;2.14&lt;/strong&gt; times as likely to be subject to a SCA the following year. Even without the inflationary effect of the merger objection suits, these red-flag mergers were a very strong leading indicator for SCA suits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This research comes from “Securities Class Actions: Leading Indicators and Covariates” by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD. Available at $399 for an individual license and $699 for firm-wide license. Contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; to purchase. Free for subscribers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most actors in the market think on a quarterly basis, but insurance and investment professionals need to think in longer terms. Mergers are often forgotten by the markets almost as soon as they are consummated, but the problems that they create can linger for months, or even years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We grade past risk factors and predict future risk impacts for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. Contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; to learn how we can help you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Mergers" /><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><summary type="html">Our research indicates that large mergers are a strong leading indicator for Securities Class Actions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Red%20Flag-8cbf8e.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Red%20Flag-8cbf8e.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Watch Out for Audit Fee Jumps</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watch-out-for-audit-fee-jumps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch Out for Audit Fee Jumps" /><published>2021-06-03T13:29:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-03T13:29:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watch-out-for-audit-fee-jumps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/watch-out-for-audit-fee-jumps/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Audit fees are usually “sticky,” so you should notice when they jump.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By law, every public company must hire an independent auditor to review their financial statements and offer an opinion. Although the public is privy to an auditor’s final opinion, almost all the auditor’s work is shrouded in mystery. However, every company must disclose how much money it spends on audit related services (audit fees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies negotiate with their auditors every year over price, so year-over-year and peer-to-peer comparisons of fees can potentially reveal interesting insights about what is going on behind the scenes at a company. For this reason, there have been a number of academic papers on audit fees and their potential implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time evidence has emerged that audit fees are “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/MAJ-08-2013-0915/full/html&quot;&gt;sticky&lt;/a&gt;” and do not adjust rapidly to changing conditions at a company. This makes sense considering the multifaceted relationship that develops between an auditor and management. Yes, auditors are independent, but they want to serve their clients and maintain a strong relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes an auditor’s fee will buck this trend and jump…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomenon was the subject of a 2016 academic paper titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2826272&quot;&gt;Abnormal Audit Fees and Accounting Quality&lt;/a&gt;.” The authors found evidence that companies whose audit fees jumped up out of their normal range had indicators of lower accounting quality (e.g., a greater risk for restatements, material weaknesses, and fraud). The authors hypothesized that sharp increases in fees were due to efforts by auditors to fix problems, indicating the &lt;em&gt;existence&lt;/em&gt; of problems in financial statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unexplained jump in audit fees is certainly a red flag (we have also discussed that same point with respect to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/do-not-ignore-spikes-in-non-audit-fees/&quot;&gt;non-audit fees&lt;/a&gt;). But insurance and investment professionals should be cautious even when a ready explanation for the increase in fees is at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Complicated Real-World Example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, TCF Financial Corporation’s annual report disclosed a sharp jump in their audit fees. This increase coincided with a reverse merger with Chemical Bank that was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961219000179/a8-kmergerannouncmentc.htm&quot;&gt;consummated&lt;/a&gt; in 2019, but the increase in audit fees may also have represented remediation efforts by the auditor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Audit%20Fees%20TCF.png&quot; alt=&quot;Audit Fees TCF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another possible signal of trouble came from the non-audit fees, which also reported a spike in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2020, Probes Reporter confirmed that TCF Financial was subject to an undisclosed investigation by the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/TCF%20SEC%20Investigation.png&quot; alt=&quot;TCF SEC Investigation.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2020, Craig Dahl left &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961220000190/a8k2020.htm&quot;&gt;abruptly&lt;/a&gt; as CEO after serving in the position of the joint company after a little over a year (he had been &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.tcfbank.com/news/news-details/2020/TCF-Financial-Corp.-CEO-Craig-R.-Dahl-to-Retire/default.aspx&quot;&gt;tenured&lt;/a&gt; at TCF for 21 years and had served as their CEO prior to the merger).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A company spokesperson took issue with an earlier version of this story where we characterized Mr. Dahl’s departure as a removal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear why he was departed from his position early, but his resignation was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961220000190/a8k2020.htm&quot;&gt;effective&lt;/a&gt; the day after the announcement. For some context, the TCF’s CFO’s resignation also became effective in October, but his departure was announced in December 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/19612/000001961220000190/exhibit101dahlseparati.htm&quot;&gt;agreed&lt;/a&gt; to pay the former CEO a significant lump sum, over $11 million, and $1.5 million a month for 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is possible that TCF’s sharp increases in audit fees and non-audit fees had nothing to do with the SEC investigation, or whatever lead to the abrupt departure of the CEO, but the academic literature indicates that jumps in audit fees are a sign of trouble in the financial statements and should not be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academic research of audit fees indicates that they are “sticky,” so sharp increases can be considered an abnormal event.  Insurance and investment professionals should do their best to carefully discern when these abnormal increases are a sign of potential trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every Watchdog Report provides a year-to-year and peer-to-peer comparison for audit fees, non audit fees, and many other potential risk factors. These reports are available for over 4,500 publicly traded companies. If you want one of our team members to give you a tour, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A company spokesperson for TCF Financial said that they would get back to us concerning further comments regarding an earlier version of this piece. We will append any comments they make to this article.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Audit Fees" /><summary type="html">Audit fees are usually “sticky,” so you should notice when they jump.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/goo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/goo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Not Ignore Spikes in Non-Audit Fees</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/do-not-ignore-spikes-in-non-audit-fees/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Not Ignore Spikes in Non-Audit Fees" /><published>2021-05-12T14:41:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-12T14:41:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/do-not-ignore-spikes-in-non-audit-fees</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/do-not-ignore-spikes-in-non-audit-fees/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A dramatic increase in non-audit fees means something is happening, and you should know what it is.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every publicly traded company must disclose how much money they pay their independent auditor, and thanks to Sarbanes Oxley, they must disclose how much money was for audit services (audit fees) and how much was for services unrelated to the audit (non-audit fees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent audit firms have expertise in a wide range of services, so it is not unusual for a company to hire their auditor for services unrelated to their audit. In fact, despite the independence concern it can create, our research shows that companies with higher non-audit fees are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/auditors-can-help-prevent-costly-litigation/&quot;&gt;less likely&lt;/a&gt; to be subject to securities class action litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a spike in non-audit fees can be a cause for concern. A dramatic increase in non-audit fees does not necessarily indicate a negative event, but it does indicate that something &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; is occurring and that it requires the expertise of an accounting firm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spikes in Non-Audit Fees Can Foreshadow Negative Events&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019 Under Armour reported a dramatic spike in non-audit fees. In November 2019, the Wall Street Journal broke a story that Under Armour was subject to an SEC investigation concerning their accounting practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is likely that Under Armour’s increase in non-audit fees were related to navigating the investigation and remediating the problems that led to the SEC investigation. The SEC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2021-78&quot;&gt;settled&lt;/a&gt; the case for $9 million less than two weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spikes in Non-Audit Fees Can Merely Accompany Complicated Financial Transactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spike in non-audit fees signals a new event, but not necessarily one that is negative. For example, in 2016 Hilton Hotels paid non-audit fees of over $13 million, a &lt;strong&gt;181%&lt;/strong&gt; increase over the prior year. This increase was primarily due the complicated tax implications for Hilton’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/hilton-completes-split-into-three-independent-companies/2017/01/06/04414772-d287-11e6-a783-cd3fa950f2fd_story.html&quot;&gt;spinoff&lt;/a&gt; into three distinct entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Example of Motorola&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motorola is a casualty of the iPhone. From dominance to relative obscurity, the company has all but faded from memory (although it remains a relatively large company with $33 billion in market capitalization).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020 Motorola had the largest percentage increase in non-audit fees of any company over the last five years, rising &lt;strong&gt;2,200%&lt;/strong&gt; from $100,000 to $2.3 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Motorola%20non-audit%20fees.png&quot; alt=&quot;Motorola non-audit fees.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This increase was probably due in part to Motorola’s auditor change, from KPMG (which had served as their auditor for over 50 years) to PricewaterhouseCoopers. It is also interesting that Motorola’s CFO departed in June, 2020, for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/68505/000119312520184064/d939178d8k.htm&quot;&gt;personal reasons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are &lt;em&gt;not claiming&lt;/em&gt; that Motorola has done something wrong. But unexplained change carries risk, and our job at Watchdog is to help investment and insurance professionals spot risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We contacted Motorola for comment and they simply replied that non-audit fees for 2021 were disclosed on page 76 of their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/68505/000119312521103275/d25774ddef14a.htm&quot;&gt;annual report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disclosure of audit and non-audit fees gives some limited insight into a company. If the fees are changing, it must be because something at the company is changing. Although oftentimes the explanation is readily available to investors, sometimes it isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is important to know what you do not know. For D&amp;amp;O insurance professionals, it is important to spot these potential risks and get explanations from the company when underwriting a policy or renewing a contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports help insurance and investment professionals spot risk, and they are available for over 4,500 public companies. Email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com to find out if our reports can help you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Non-Audit Fees" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Non-Audit Fees" /><category term="Red Flags" /><summary type="html">A dramatic increase in non-audit fees means something is happening, and you should know what it is.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Motorola%20non-audit%20fees.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Motorola%20non-audit%20fees.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Auditors Can Help Prevent Costly Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/auditors-can-help-prevent-costly-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Auditors Can Help Prevent Costly Litigation" /><published>2021-05-06T08:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-06T08:30:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/auditors-can-help-prevent-costly-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/auditors-can-help-prevent-costly-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Independence issues aside, hiring your auditor as a consultant can help avoid lawsuits.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Audit Fees and Independence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arthur Anderson was famously paid more by Enron for consultancy work than for audit work. Arthur Anderson’s loss of independence, along with allegations that they had participated in Enron’s fraud, destroyed the largest accounting firm in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legislation currently requires that every public company disclose how much money it pays its auditor. Companies must also distinguish between money paid for the legally required audit (audit fees), and money paid for other services (non-audit fees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulators like the SEC and the FRC are concerned with the effect that non-audit work can have on &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/changes-to-auditor-independence-regulations-us-vs-uk/&quot;&gt;auditor independence&lt;/a&gt;. Different regulators have different &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ifac.org/system/files/meetings/files/2901.pdf&quot;&gt;thresholds&lt;/a&gt; for deciding when non-audit work potentially raises a red flag for independence issues, ranging from 10-30% of the total fee. Despite the widespread agreement by regulators that non-audit fees create independence issues, the academic literature is mixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog Research we follow the lead of major regulators and assign a yellow flag whenever non-audit fees exceed 30% of the total fee paid to the independent auditor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Audit Fees are Negatively Correlated with Securities Class Action Litigation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used the Audit Analytics database, which has over 20 years of data, to examine the relationship between non-audit fees and securities class action litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found that the presence of a yellow flag for non-audit fees in a given year is &lt;em&gt;negatively&lt;/em&gt; correlated with securities class action lawsuits for that year. Companies with a yellow flag for non-audit fees were &lt;strong&gt;12% less likely&lt;/strong&gt; to be named as a defendant in a securities class action lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more surprising, this negative correlation persists for the &lt;em&gt;following year&lt;/em&gt;. Companies assigned a yellow flag for non-audit fees in a given year were &lt;strong&gt;7% less likely&lt;/strong&gt; to be named a defendant in a securities class action in the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost every public company has complex tax and accounting issues, but companies vary widely in how many resources they allocate to address these issues. It is possible that non-audit fees are negatively associated with litigation because these companies are dedicating more resources to resolving complex accounting and tax issues instead of letting them fester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment and insurance professionals should carefully consider the overall resources the company allocates to addressing complex accounting and tax issues, including non-audit fees. Too little investment increases the risk of costly mistakes, which can lead to costly litigation. For D&amp;amp;O underwriters, the level of non-audit fees could be a helpful factor to consider when setting a price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Watchdog Reports can help investment and insurance professionals by putting lots of critical information, including audit and non-audit fees, in one place. Email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; for a demo today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="Non-Audit Fees" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><summary type="html">Independence issues aside, hiring your auditor as a consultant can help avoid lawsuits.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Green%20field.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Green%20field.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The 5 Worst Industries for CFO Turnover</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-5-worst-industries-for-cfo-turnover/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 5 Worst Industries for CFO Turnover" /><published>2021-04-23T10:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-23T10:47:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-5-worst-industries-for-cfo-turnover</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-5-worst-industries-for-cfo-turnover/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All public company CFOs have a tough job, but keeping that job is particularly tough in these industries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFOs play a crucial role at every public company. They are the ones primarily responsible for ensuring that the financial reporting is accurate and complete. It is important for the CFO to be diligent, highly competent, and confident enough to fix problems when other members of management would rather have them swept under the rug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research consistently identifies red-flag CFO changes as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/&quot;&gt;leading indicator&lt;/a&gt; of securities class action suits. This would indicate that an unusual CFO departure has a ripple effect that can create short-term and long-term problems at a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is derived from our 2021: Frequency and Impact of CFO Changes report authored by Joseph Burke and Joseph Yarborough. If you would like to read the report, please email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past 10 years &lt;strong&gt;13.9%&lt;/strong&gt; of companies replaced their CFO in any given year. However, some industries had significantly higher turnover rates. Here are the five industries (classified by NAICS code) that had the worst turnover rates for the CFO position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Pharmaceuticals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceuticals are well known for their volatility and are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/impact-of-cyan-comparing-the-market-today-to-the-pharmaceuticals-of-yesteryear/&quot;&gt;frequently&lt;/a&gt; named in securities class action suits. Pharmaceuticals had an annual turnover rate of &lt;strong&gt;15.1%&lt;/strong&gt;. The only surprising thing about their appearance on this list is that they aren’t higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Wholesale Trade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are companies that sell merchandise, energy, or even food to wholesalers. Their CFOs had an annual turnover rate of &lt;strong&gt;15.2%&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the biggest companies in that industry Sysco (SYY), a food distributor, had red-flag departures for both their CEO and CFO in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Professional, Scientific, and Technical Services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes companies like Facebook, S&amp;amp;P Global, and Accenture. The CFOs in this industry had a turnover rate of &lt;strong&gt;16.5%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Entertainment, Recreation, and Other Services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes companies like Disney, DraftKings, and Planet Fitness. The CFOs in this industry had a turnover rate of &lt;strong&gt;17.1%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Retail&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst industry for CFO turnover is retail, where the turnover rate over the last ten years has been &lt;strong&gt;18.3%&lt;/strong&gt;. Interestingly enough, companies in the retail industry also get sued in securities class action suits &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-five-riskiest-industries-for-securities-class-action-litigation/&quot;&gt;more often&lt;/a&gt; than any other industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies in the retail industry can have all sorts of difficulty accounting related challenges for the CFOs to handle. For a cautionary tale, read our post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;Under Armour&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn how Watchdog helps D&amp;amp;O insurance professionals identify red-flag CFO changes and other risks by emailing &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; for a demo and pricing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="CFO Change" /><category term="featured" /><category term="CFO Change" /><category term="Red Flags" /><summary type="html">All public company CFOs have a tough job, but keeping that job is particularly tough in these industries.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Empty%20Chair.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Empty%20Chair.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CFO Turnover Falls (a little) in 2020</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cfo-turnover-falls-a-little-in-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CFO Turnover Falls (a little) in 2020" /><published>2021-04-20T12:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-20T12:35:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cfo-turnover-falls-a-little-in-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/cfo-turnover-falls-a-little-in-2020/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In 2020 CFO turnover fell from historic levels, yet CFO turnover maintains its long-term upward trend.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CFO position may be one of the most important positions at any public company. Financial problems at a public company tend to fall in the lap of the CFO first. If the CFO departs under troubling circumstances, that can be a signal of trouble down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Lawrence Molloy &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/&quot;&gt;left Under Armour&lt;/a&gt; in 2017 for “personal reasons” it was a serious red-flag. Under Armour soon disclosed significant accounting-related problems, problems that have resulted in an SEC investigation and a Wells Notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not surprising that our research consistently identifies &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/six-leading-indicators-of-securities-litigation/&quot;&gt;red-flag CFO changes&lt;/a&gt; as leading indicators for securities class action litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is derived from our 2021: Frequency and Impact of CFO Changes report authored by Joseph Burke and Joseph Yarborough. If you would like to read the report, please email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFO changes have been rising steadily over the last ten years. In 2011, only &lt;strong&gt;10.8%&lt;/strong&gt; of companies reported a CFO change, whereas in 2020, &lt;strong&gt;15.1%&lt;/strong&gt; of companies reported a CFO change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/CFO%20turnover%202020.png&quot; alt=&quot;CFO turnover 2020.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFO changes reached historic highs in 2018 and 2019. The turnover in 2020 represents a slight decline from those historic highs, although it remains the third-highest year on record. The overall trend continues to bend upwards, signaling continued volatility in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red-flag CFO changes tend to follow the overall CFO turnover trends. Red-flag changes have also increased over the last 10 years, rising from &lt;strong&gt;3.1%&lt;/strong&gt; in 2011 to &lt;strong&gt;4.8%&lt;/strong&gt; of companies in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Watchdog Reports can help you keep an eye on over 30 crucial flags, like CFO turnover. Retail investors can see our reports for free. Investment and Insurance Professionals should contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; for special offers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="CFO Change" /><category term="featured" /><category term="CFO Change" /><category term="Red Flag" /><summary type="html">In 2020 CFO turnover fell from historic levels, yet CFO turnover maintains its long-term upward trend.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CFO%20turnover%202020.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/CFO%20turnover%202020.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">On Trial: Personal Experience versus Hard Data</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/on-trial-personal-experience-versus-hard-data/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Trial: Personal Experience versus Hard Data" /><published>2021-04-12T09:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T09:26:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/on-trial-personal-experience-versus-hard-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/on-trial-personal-experience-versus-hard-data/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a big difference between knowing that similar circumstances have rarely occurred and believing similar circumstances have never occurred.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks, a federal lawsuit has offered a rare glimpse inside the world of the Big 4 accounting firms. In Botta v. PricewaterhouseCoopers, LLP, Mauro Botta, a former senior audit manager at PwC, is suing the firm for wrongful termination and retaliation as a whistleblower. He alleges he was fired because he submitted a whistleblower complaint to the SEC. Botta has argued that PwC unlawfully retaliated against him for submitting a “reasonable” complaint. PwC has argued that Botta’s complaint to the SEC was the actual retaliation, and that he was properly fired for misconduct unrelated to his whistleblower complaint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a complex case and has lots of interesting facets. If you want to really want to get a feel for the personal drama, the office politics, and the thorny issues at play, then we highly recommend you read Francine Mckenna’s reporting on the trial at &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Her writing is well worth the price of admission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This case, however, is about more than personal drama. The case raises questions about auditor independence, a core safeguard of our capital markets. In live testimony via Zoom we heard about how PwC and its employees navigated the tension that exists between serving the client and protecting auditor independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francine suggested we do some research on a specific accounting issue that came up during some expert testimony offered by PwC. PwC’s expert testimony concerned the reasonableness of the complaint that Botta filed with the SEC, a key issue in the case. But before we go any further, some context is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botta was a senior manager at PwC (the position right below a partner), working on an audit of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/edgar/browse/?CIK=1175609&amp;amp;owner=exclude&quot;&gt;Cavium&lt;/a&gt;, a publicly traded company which had approximately $400 million in assets. Botta filed a memo with PwC in 2014 arguing that Cavium ought to declare a material weakness in its internal controls because it purportedly had 2 significant control deficiencies and 11 lesser control deficiencies. (fn.1) (1336) None of these issues by themselves would constitute a material weakness, but Botta argued that in their totality, these deficiencies demonstrated a lack of competency by the financial department that ought to constitute a material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A material weakness is a deficiency, or combination of deficiencies, in the internal controls of a company that creates a reasonable possibility that a material misstatement of the financial statements will not be prevented or detected. A material weakness can exist even when the financial statements are not misstated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When deciding whether to issue a material weakness, audit firms consider the guidelines set forth in the PCAOB’s Auditing Standard No. 5. Those guidelines specify that some of the more prominent indicators of a material weakness include (fn.2):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fraud on the part of senior management, regardless of the severity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restatements to correct material misstatements.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A material misstatement from the current period identified by the auditor that would not have otherwise been identified by management.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ineffective oversight by the Audit Committee&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an exhaustive list. The PCAOB’s guidelines also include a catchall provision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly, this catchall provision specifies that any deficiency, or combination of deficiencies, that would cause prudent officials to conclude that they do not have a reasonable assurance that the company’s financial transactions are recorded properly may be classified as a material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botta’s memo to PwC proposed that a material weakness for Cavium be filed based on a lack of competency by the financial department concerning income taxes, treasury, and technical accounting. (1358-1359). Since Cavium did not have any fraud, material misstatements, or lack of oversight by the Audit Committee, this material weakness would have fallen under the catchall provision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botta’s memo was taken seriously by PwC and an assessment was performed by its National Office. The National Office disagreed with Botta’s assessment, and neither Cavium nor PwC issued a material weakness in 2014. Botta then filed a whistleblower report with the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Assessment by PwC’s Expert&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, PwC hired an expert witness to assess Botta’s report, and the report by PwC. PwC’s expert witness spent twelve years in the SEC’s Enforcement Division and held the position of deputy chief accountant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to PwC’s expert witness, it is occasionally appropriate to issue a material weakness for a lack of competency, but that lack of competency is usually accompanied by red flags. (1360-61). The expert witness specified that these red flags were restatements, out of period adjustments, prior material weaknesses, previously identified deficiencies that remain unfixed, and a lack of experience in GAAP by the financial department. (1360-1361).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This expert witness also stated PwC’s assessment of Cavium demonstrated that the company’s financials did not exhibit any of the red flags which he had previously mentioned. Cavium did not have a restatement or out-of-period adjustment. (1362) Nor did it have a prior material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to PwC’s assessment, even though PwC had identified many control deficiencies in 2012 and 2013, Cavium was apparently able to remediate these deficiencies by the end of the year, so that all the control deficiencies Botta identified in 2014 were new deficiencies. (1368)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expert witness also reviewed PwC’s assessment of the expertise of Cavium’s financial department. This assessment focused on the prior experience of the staff and their tenure. According to the PwC expert’s testimony, Cavium’s accounting staff was comprised of numerous Big 4 alumni with significant experience in the industry. When PwC’s expert witness was asked if he had ever seen a material weakness issued based on incompetence when a staff had similar experience, his response was a simple “no.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PwC’s expert witness concluded that the National Office at PwC came to a reasonable conclusion in deciding not to issue a material weakness for Cavium. Finally, the expert was asked the following question (and it is important because it speaks to the reasonableness of Botta’s whistleblower complaint to the SEC):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Q. &lt;em&gt;Sir, in your entire career, including your 12 years at the SEC, have you ever seen a material weakness due to incompetency exist in these circumstances?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A. &lt;em&gt;Not in these circumstances.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PwC’s expert has excellent credentials and a wealth of valuable and relevant experience. Yet even his experience is necessarily limited by the cases that crossed his desk, the clients he served, and the topics discussed by his friends and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were curious, and so was Francine, whether we could find a material weakness filed under comparable circumstances by a careful analysis of the publicly available data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walking Through Our Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We performed our analysis using the Audit Analytics database, which includes every material weakness since 2004. The Audit Analytics database assigns each material weakness tags categorizing the potential issues at play in the material weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audit Analytics is used by over 300 universities, many different regulators, and prominent accounting firms. It’s the gold standard for accounting related data on public companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audit Analytics tags disclosures about issues that relate to competency for material weaknesses in two ways. One tag is used for a lack of competency by the accounting department, and another for a lack of competency by senior management. These two tags nearly always coincide because hiring an incompetent accounting department is a red flag that the senior management team is incompetent too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2004 to 2020, publicly traded companies listed on the U.S. exchanges disclosed ineffective internal controls over financial reporting 4,444 times. Of those, 2,443 were tagged for incompetency in the accounting department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Material%20Weakness%20Competency%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Material Weakness Competency Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, small cap companies are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency/&quot;&gt;more than 5X&lt;/a&gt; as likely as large cap companies to declare a material weakness. Since Cavium was a large company, any analysis that includes small cap companies would be potentially misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a more comparable set of companies, we narrowed our search to competence issues at large cap companies. Additionally, we only looked at companies which had hired a Big 4 audit firm. We thought that these large companies, with plenty of resources and the expertise of a Big 4 firm at their disposal, ought to have accounting staff with comparable experience and expertise to Cavium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of this search were far narrower, with only 98 material weaknesses that fit these criteria. These material weaknesses were filed by 69 unique companies, as some companies filed more than one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PwC’s expert described a number of red flags that were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; in Cavium’s case. These included fraud, material misstatements or restatements, out of period adjustments, and prior material weaknesses. We combed through the 69 different companies and eliminated the cases where these red flags identified by PwC’s expert were present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This analysis has allowed us to conclude that from 2004 to 2020, 22 companies filed a material weakness under comparable circumstances to Cavium.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/MW%20over%20time%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;MW over time chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One factor that PwC’s expert discussed that we could not examine was unfixed deficiencies. That is part of an internal assessment done by a company’s auditing firm that never becomes public. So, it is possible that some of the 22 comparable material weaknesses that we identified were due to unfixed control deficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how rare these events are, we are not surprised that PwC’s expert was not personally familiar with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would also note that declaring a material weakness is a big step for an independent auditor. There is no public information that allows us to measure the severity of the control deficiencies that lead to these 22 material weaknesses. They may have been comparable to Cavium’s deficiencies, or they may have been for more severe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of his testimony when PwC’s expert witness was asked if it is ever appropriate to file a material weakness for incompetence, he stated “It’s possible but only in very extreme circumstances.” (1360) Our analysis tends to confirm that assessment (so long as you exclude cases where the red flags for incompetency are also present).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our analysis shows that material weaknesses &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; filed in similar circumstances to Cavium, but it is rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, one of PwC’s clients, Allergan plc, who had assets of almost $150 billion, disclosed a material weakness in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1578845/000156459017002433/0001564590-17-002433-index.htm&quot;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt; due to a lack of competency concerning the tax implications of certain transactions between their subsidiaries. This material weakness did not result in any misstatements, but the lack of competency concerning tax issues created a substantial risk of misstatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Deeper into The Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting fact was that out of these 22 companies, only 8 were headquartered in US. This result stands in contrast with the fact that historically fewer than 20% of U.S. listed companies are located outside of the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Results%20by%20country.png&quot; alt=&quot;Results by country.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disparity is possibly due to differences in culture between foreign affiliates of the Big 4 and the U.S. firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also categorized the result by global audit firm. Here we lumped the US and foreign affiliates of each firm together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Results%20by%20auditor.png&quot; alt=&quot;Results by auditor.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also looked at the &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; issue raised in the material weakness disclosure (oftentimes the material weaknesses touched on more than one issue). The two primary issues that companies had struggles with were 1) the interplay of IT systems and the financial controls, and 2) complex tax issues that their accounting staff struggled to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Primary%20Issue.png&quot; alt=&quot;Primary Issue.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal experience, even the personal experience of a well-qualified expert, has its limitations. A careful analysis of hard data will usually be more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that our analysis does not comment on whether Botta’s whistleblower claim was reasonable, from a legal perspective, in this case. However, there is a big difference between knowing that companies in similar circumstances to Cavium &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;rarely&lt;/em&gt; issued material weaknesses as opposed to believing that companies in similar circumstances &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; issued a material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1) Francine provided us with a transcript of PwC’s expert witness’s testimony on 3/30/2021. All quotes and inferences concerning the trial are taken from the transcript.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2) These indicators are derived from the PCAOB’s page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/oversight/standards/archived-standards/pre-reorganized-auditing-standards-interpretations/details/Auditing_Standard_5&quot;&gt;Accounting Standard No. 5&lt;/a&gt;. They are edited for brevity and clarity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Independent Research" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="Litigation" /><category term="Data Analysis" /><category term="Independent Research" /><summary type="html">There is a big difference between knowing that similar circumstances have rarely occurred and believing similar circumstances have never occurred.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Courtroom.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Courtroom.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Small Companies 5X More Likely Than Large Companies to Report a Control Deficiency</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Small Companies 5X More Likely Than Large Companies to Report a Control Deficiency" /><published>2021-03-29T10:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-03-29T10:17:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency/">&lt;p&gt;After the Enron scandal, Congress passed Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) to improve the quality of financial reporting and deter fraud. One core reform was to require every company’s management team to annually assess and report on the effectiveness of the company’s disclosure controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is derived from a report generated by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD, titled “Frequency and Impact of Control Deficiencies: 2020.” The full report is currently available at no cost, just email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com and ask for the report.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclosure controls are the policies and procedures that ensure a company can provide timely, accurate, and reliable financial information to the SEC and the market. When a company has disclosure control problems, it does not &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; mean that their financial information is not reliable, but it does mean that the company &lt;em&gt;cannot be sure&lt;/em&gt; that the information is reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, the law also required the independent auditor to independently assess and attest to the quality of the internal controls. However, this attestation requirement, known as SOX 404(b), has been narrowed in scope &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/&quot;&gt;repeatedly&lt;/a&gt; over the last two decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, the SOX 404(a) requirement for management to annually report on the effectiveness of internal controls has remained intact. Additionally, the SOX 302 requirement for management to report quarterly on any disclosure control issues has also remained in effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management always has a strong interest in minimizing negative events, and we will touch on how that effects how they report on control issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control Deficiencies Continue Long-Term Trend&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control deficiencies have been increasing at a steady rate over the last ten years. In 2019 a record number of control deficiencies were disclosed, but in 2020 there was a return to the mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Control%20Deficiencies.png&quot; alt=&quot;Control Deficiencies.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control Deficiencies Are Primarily Reported by Small Companies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are over 5,000 companies listed on U.S. exchanges. Although larger companies receive the majority of investor and media attention, there are far more small companies than large companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often important to segment the market by size because companies of different sizes have different regulatory and reporting requirements, so they are often operating in different environments. For example, smaller reporting companies with less than $75 million in public float don’t have to comply with 404(b), neither to Emerging Growth Companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These small companies still need to assess their internal controls, but that assessment is not independently verified by their auditor. This lack of verification can result in companies “phoning-in” their assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to “phone-in” the assessment is to provide an adverse opinion. This is safer than claiming that internal controls are good, and risk being humiliated if they are eventually forced to file a restatement. And since so many other small companies are filing adverse opinions, the announcement of an adverse opinion on a small company has relatively little impact. After all, many people expect small companies to lack the resources necessary to implement rigorous controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adverse opinions by management are far more meaningful for large companies. Since the independent auditors at large companies provide their own independent assessment of internal controls, management is strongly incentivized to implement and maintain rigorous controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The different incentives at play create a remarkably different results when we segment the company population by size. Small companies were over 5 times more likely to report a control deficiency than large companies. This is consistent with our research demonstrating that small companies are far more likely to report a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot/&quot;&gt;restatement &lt;/a&gt;than large companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Deficiencies%20by%20Market%20Cap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Deficiencies by Market Cap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller companies are more likely to report control deficiencies than larger companies. This is probably due to the differences in stakes. With considerably less attention and lower expectations, it is easy for management at smaller companies to save time and money by truncating their assessment of internal controls by giving themselves a failing grade. And since so many of their peers give themselves this same failing grade, there is little pressure to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always expect companies to take the easiest road. Since SOX has created a two-tier system, with one set of rules for small companies and another set of rules for large companies, we are not surprised to see wildly disparate results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><summary type="html">After the Enron scandal, Congress passed Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) to improve the quality of financial reporting and deter fraud. One core reform was to require every company’s management team to annually assess and report on the effectiveness of the company’s disclosure controls.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Green%20Fields.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Green%20Fields.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>