<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-19T14:06:25-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers" /><published>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;concerns &lt;/a&gt;about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the coronavirus, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;allowed&lt;/a&gt; public companies to delay releasing their annual or quarterly reports by up to 45 days. This order initially went into effect on March 4th, after large accelerated filers (companies with more than 700 million in public float) had already submitted their annual reports. However, large accelerated filers were due to report their first quarter results on May 11th, giving these big companies a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to see how many large accelerated filers were choosing to file their 10-Qs late. Our analysis showed that as of May 19th, &lt;em&gt;only 27 U.S. based companies&lt;/em&gt; had failed to file their 10-Qs due to disruptions from the coronavirus. We arrived at this number by eliminating foreign filers (who have different reporting obligations and dates) and by eliminating companies that failed to file because they were acquired or stated their failure to file was due to internal control problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is significant that so few companies decided to file late. We decided to look deeper to see what made these companies the exceptions. We were not surprised to see Party City (PRTY) on this list. In addition to having its stores closed, long term social distancing practices could destroy their prospects for recovery; its stock has taken such a beating that it was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1592058/000119312520107068/d901922dex991.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt;. But for other companies it is less clear why they were unable to file. For example, Entercom Communications (ETM), which owns radio stations and other digital content, has only reported a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1067837/000119312520142278/d910419dex991.htm&quot;&gt;4% loss in net revenue&lt;/a&gt; for its first quarter, hardly cataclysmic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20Filers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late Filers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found that about 14 of these companies had offered their first quarter results to their investors in an earnings call and concurrent press release. We are not quite sure what to make of this. On one hand, it seems commendable that they are keeping investors appraised of what is going on, but if they can pull together an accurate earnings call, then why can’t they file their 10-Qs on time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20filers%20press%20release.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late filers press release.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interesting Specific Examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circor International (CIR)&lt;/strong&gt;. This industrial valve manufacturer failed to timely file their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000023/circorformnt10-kv10.htm&quot;&gt;10-k&lt;/a&gt; this year because of internal control issues and a cybersecurity breach.  Now they are claiming that the coronavirus is the reason for their late 10-Q. They also filed two of their quarterly reports late in 2019. This company sells manufactures valves and other products for the industrial, aerospace and defense, and energy sectors. This is probably the clearest cut case of a company making a dubious assertion that its filing delay is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000070/cir8-k42920.htm&quot;&gt;due&lt;/a&gt; to the coronavirus as opposed to preexisting internal issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MFA Financial (MFA)&lt;/strong&gt;. This Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT) provided an interesting reason why they could not &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1055160/000105516020000018/mfa-8k05062020.htm&quot;&gt;timely&lt;/a&gt; file their quarterly report, “&lt;em&gt;Company’s management has had to devote significant time and attention to address [the impact of coronavirus], which have diverted management resources from completing tasks necessary to file the Company’s Quarterly Report…&lt;/em&gt;.” The other two REITs who failed to file in a timely manner cited the need for accounting staff to work at home as a reason for the delay. In contrast, it appears MFA’s management simply did not make time to file their 10-Q because the SEC has allowed them to put it on the backburner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credit Acceptance Corp (CACC).&lt;/strong&gt; MFA was not the only company to say its management was too busy to file a 10-Q. CACC had a near identical &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000042/cacc8k20200420.htm&quot;&gt;disclosure&lt;/a&gt;, claiming management was just too busy assessing the potential impact of the coronavirus. For context, CACC specializes in offering subprime loans on vehicles, which some people find &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2019/12/12/787337997/the-big-business-of-subprime-auto-loans&quot;&gt;unsavory&lt;/a&gt;. Even though almost every other company is trying to increase and preserve liquidity to survive the shutdowns, CACC is in the process of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000036/cacc8k20200305.htm&quot;&gt;repurchasing&lt;/a&gt; up to 3 million shares, reducing their cash position. We also can’t help but point out the irony of CACC filing their 10-Q late on the flimsiest of excuses while also issuing this statement on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creditacceptance.com/coronavirus-response&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; “…Credit Acceptance is unable to support payment deferrals, and your payments will continue to be due on your scheduled monthly due date….” Considering the current predicament of many of the low-income recipients of these predatory loans, we don’t know how CACC shareholders can sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every investor wants to know if management is reliable and is dedicated to transparency. When management is opaque, it makes an investment far riskier. The best way to assess the trustworthiness of a management team is to see what kind of choices they make. The coronavirus has presented management teams with lots of choices, and we should watch them carefully as they make their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Late Filings" /><summary type="html">In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed concerns about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?" /><published>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/">&lt;p&gt;To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections.  An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/indicators/unemployment/&quot;&gt;skyrocketing &lt;/a&gt;unemployment.  To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;permitted &lt;/a&gt;companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some companies this may simply be a welcome respite during a difficult time, but we are concerned that some companies may use this as an opportunity to prevent investors from seeing just how badly things are going until it is too late. However, the SEC has also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-clayton-hinman&quot;&gt;encouraged &lt;/a&gt;companies to reveal how the shutdowns are effecting them and to speculate about how they will bounce back from the disaster. The SEC has assured companies concerned about incurring liability for these speculative statements that they will not be “second guessed by the SEC.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect the SEC has created two divergent paths for companies, some will file on time and may include extensive disclosures, but others may take the opportunity to delay reporting for as long as possible, perhaps in hope that by the time the 45 day period runs out, they will be able to report some good news (if they don’t declare bankruptcy first).  We believe that the strongest indicator for which path companies will take is their financial health before the lockdowns.  This would be consistent with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/coronavirus-uncertainties-contribute-to-going-concern-uncertainties/&quot;&gt;findings&lt;/a&gt; from Audit Analytics that the companies who initially received going concern warnings from auditors, where the coronavirus was named as a substantial factor, had already received going concern warnings before the pandemic even started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already expressed concern that some companies might use the coronavirus as a pretext to write off goodwill that was junk before the lockdowns, but we became concerned that some companies might abuse the delay allowance when we saw that Luckin Coffee was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;delaying &lt;/a&gt;its annual report due to the coronavirus.  The disclosure did not even refer to the massive fraud it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;unveiled &lt;/a&gt;less than a month earlier, or the firing of its CEO that was announced a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. large accelerated filers, companies with a public float of over $700 million, were required to file their annual statements before March 1st, so they were unable to take advantage of the ability to file late.  But smaller companies and foreign issuers with later deadlines were able to take advantage to file late if they wanted and many of them did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LateFilings%20graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;LateFilings graph.png&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/impacts-of-covid-19-on-late-filings/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most large accelerated filers are due to file their quarterly statements this week, which is giving the markets their first real insight as to the effects of the coronavirus on the world’s biggest businesses.  For example, the Kraft Heinz Company, (one of our favorite &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;subjects&lt;/a&gt;) has benefited from the shutdowns with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745920000061/khc-20200328.htm&quot;&gt;boost &lt;/a&gt;in revenue, as we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;predicted&lt;/a&gt;.  They also wrote off $226 million in goodwill, but that was apparently from consolidating their reporting into three segments instead of four and not from the coronavirus (how KHC’s figured that its new international segment is worth $226 million less than the sum of its component parts is anyone’s guess).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, Hertz filed its 10-Q in a timely fashion, but it did not have such good news to report.  The rental car industry, which has high fixed costs and relies primarily on people traveling to earn revenue has been hit hard by the shutdowns.  Hertz issued a going concern warning in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/47129/000165785320000049/hghthcq12020form10-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q&lt;/a&gt; that it cannot continue to make necessary payments without more revenue as it is burning through its cash. Currently, one of its biggest debts is in forbearance but that deal is set to end on May 22nd, and Hertz has been unable to offer any assurances that a deal will be struck.  The debtors could potentially seize their collateral, including vehicles in Hertz’s fleet, hurting the company’s ability to recover when the lockdowns end. It is good that Hertz is sharing this crucial information for investors at such a critical time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, some companies have opted to delay their filings.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920010302/fooh20200510_nt10q.htm&quot;&gt;One &lt;/a&gt;such company is HF Food Group (HFFG) which primarily serves Chinese takeout restaurants.  Although not a large accelerated filer, this company had the dubious distinction of earning a higher Gray Swan Event Factor score than any other publicly traded company as of April 8th.  Their high score was mostly attributable to two recent mergers, including one consummated in November 2019.  The company also disclosed in its 10-K, filed on March 16th, 2020, that it identified a material weakness in its internal controls.  HF was also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/hf-foods/&quot;&gt;targeted&lt;/a&gt; by a short seller and had a securities &lt;a href=&quot;http://securities.stanford.edu/filings-case.html?id=107365&quot;&gt;lawsuit &lt;/a&gt;filed against it in March, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920009194/ex_184193.htm&quot;&gt;replaced &lt;/a&gt;its CFO on May 4th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those curious about our Grey Swan Event Factor analysis, here is the analysis for HFFG:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Latefilings%20GSEF.png&quot; alt=&quot;Latefilings GSEF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is it that HFFG was able to put out a timely annual report but has needed to delay its quarterly report due to the coronavirus?  Is it possible that this delay has more to do with material weaknesses in the internal controls and turmoil at the executive level, rather than the coronavirus? To its credit (and unlike Luckin Coffee), HFFG has released some information indicating that it has been suffering an adverse impact from the shutdowns, with net sales declining from $209 million to $175.8 million year over year.  Still, investors will not really be able to assess the big picture until the quarterly results are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this mess is over, the SEC ought to study the effect of its policy.  Did the delayed filings really help companies who were suffering from the coronavirus? Or were they mostly used by companies who would have filed late anyways?  And was any real benefit to companies worth the loss of crucial information for investors at such a critical time?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC" /><category term="Late Filings" /><category term="GSEF" /><summary type="html">To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections. An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and skyrocketing unemployment. To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has permitted companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports" /><published>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/">&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discovered that China had a better score than the U.S., which was shocking, but we also found out that the SEC and PCAOB had issued an extensive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;warning &lt;/a&gt;to investors in Chinese firms.  This warning told investors that financial reporting in China is not consistent, that there is no effective oversight of firms in China, and that there is no enforcement to catch rule-breakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure all the investors who rely on our reports receive this warning, we have added a new SEC Oversight flag to our report. Here is an example for Luckin Coffee:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SEC%20Oversight%20Flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Oversight Flag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on the flag for Luckin, it will bring you to this warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Warning%20Flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Warning Flag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We aren’t picking on Chinese companies; we also issue a similar warning for countries that are known tax-havens.  If you looked closely at our summary table for country by county comparisons, you would have seen that countries classified as a tax-haven have an even lower Gray Swan Event Factor than China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/country%20comparison.ccp.taxhaven.png&quot; alt=&quot;country comparison.ccp.taxhaven.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our new flag highlights an uncomfortable fact.  Our assumptions about the overall health of an investment depends on accurate and reliable information, which is not always available. Investors need to be cautious about having companies in their portfolios that hail from countries that do not have rigorous standards promoting corporate transparency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="SEC" /><summary type="html">In our last post we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it Safer to Invest in China or the U.S.?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it Safer to Invest in China or the U.S.?" /><published>2020-05-06T16:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T16:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/">&lt;p&gt;The China based coffee company Luckin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt; a massive fraud on April 2nd, and only five days later, another China based company TAL Education, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1499620/000110465920044459/tm2015354d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales.  A decade ago, a wave of Chinese companies were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20&quot;&gt;exposed &lt;/a&gt;as frauds, which damaged China’s reputation.  The confluence of Luckin’s fraud with news that the Chinese lied about coronavirus has damaged China’s reputation once again as many people have come to believe that investing in Chinese companies is too risky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to look at some data and see if there were any major variations between Chinese companies and Western companies.  We specialize in tracking and predicting gray swan events. These are events related to the financial reporting of companies that can seriously injure the value and integrity of a company.  Our Gray Swan Event Factor represents an aggregation of these events and their impact on the value of the stock.  A higher Gray Swan Event Factor indicates more risk of an event that could damage a company’s integrity and stock price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Gray Swan Event Factor is an aggregation of many kinds of events, including mergers, restatements, securities litigation, C-suite turnover etc…, it correlates well with the overall health of a company.  We wanted to know if China (or any other country for that matter) would score any differently than the U.S. or Europe. Our PHDs ran the numbers and here were our results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20country%20comparison.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin country comparison.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can see Chinese companies have a significantly lower Gray Swan Event Factor than the United States, Europe, or Canada.  On its face, this result indicates that Chinese companies are healthier and less risky investments companies in Europe, Canada, or the U.S., which would be a stunning and counter-intuitive result.  But after looking deeper into the matter, we believe that it may mean the precise opposite and that Chinese companies are an even riskier investment than most people believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why Chinese companies have a lower GSEF is because they &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; fewer gray swan events than western countries, but that is probably because Chinese companies are subject to less scrutiny than Western companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the SEC and the PCAOB (a quasi-private entity that provides oversight for auditors) issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;joint statement&lt;/a&gt; on April 21st that specifically warned investors about investing in Chinese companies. They warn that, (1) the quality of financial statements are not consistent, (2) the quality of independent audits is uncertain because the PCAOB is unable to conduct inspections, (3) U.S. authorities cannot really enforce the rules against foreign persons and companies, and (4) there is essentially no legal recourse if you fall prey to fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our comparison of GSEF by country proves that fewer gray swan events are &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; in China than in the U.S., Canada, or the EU.  This paradoxically is strong evidence that we should take the SEC’s warning about Chinese companies seriously because they are not subject to the same level of scrutiny as Western companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="GSEF" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="Comparison by Country" /><summary type="html">The China based coffee company Luckin disclosed a massive fraud on April 2nd, and only five days later, another China based company TAL Education, announced that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales. A decade ago, a wave of Chinese companies were exposed as frauds, which damaged China’s reputation. The confluence of Luckin’s fraud with news that the Chinese lied about coronavirus has damaged China’s reputation once again as many people have come to believe that investing in Chinese companies is too risky.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_it%20it%20safer%20to%20invest%20in%20china%20or%20us.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_it%20it%20safer%20to%20invest%20in%20china%20or%20us.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">BorgWarner Wants to Dump Delphi. Will Delphi’s Resistance be Futile?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BorgWarner Wants to Dump Delphi.  Will Delphi’s Resistance be Futile?" /><published>2020-04-08T09:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-08T09:31:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/">&lt;p&gt;With the coronavirus shutting down entire industries and raising the possibility of an extended recession, pending mergers are in peril, and mergers overall will become disfavored as companies lose their appetite for risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner and Delphi &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/908255/000120677420000239/bwa3712381-ex992.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; an all-stock merger on January 28th, 2020.  The conventional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crainsdetroit.com/automotive/borgwarner-buy-delphi-stave-evs-impact&quot;&gt;wisdom &lt;/a&gt;take on this merger was that it was meant to protect to both engine auto part manufacturers from changes in the industry due to the rise of Tesla and electric vehicles.  It would appear the BorgWarner was looking to absorb Delphi so it could use the increase in volume to protect its position in the market, not because Delphi performance made it particularly desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner placed the value of Delphi at $3.3 billion, quite a premium for a company whose stock price had been on a consistent decline for years, and had a particularly rough year in 2019, with a anemic $141 million in operating income and total equity of only $450 million. Naturally, lawsuits were filed against both companies when the merger was announced, but lawsuits are always filed when a merger like this is announced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner chart.png&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Delphi’s value has been on a steady decline since the summer of 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the Deal Fell Apart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 30th, Delphi announced that it was going to draw down its entire $500 million revolving credit so that it would have the cash on hand to endure the coronavirus and the accompanying government ordered shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, BorgWarner &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.borgwarner.com/newsroom/press-releases/2020/03/31/borgwarner-issues-statement-regarding-delphi-technologies-revolver-draw-down&quot;&gt;announced &lt;/a&gt;that Delphi was in material breach of their agreement and that Delphi had 30 days to cure the breach or the merger would be scrapped.  Delphi countered that BorgWarner had unreasonably withheld consent for the withdrawal.  Both arguments have merit, so the stage is set for a nasty legal fight if the deal is not salvaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner’s ostensible reason for backing out is pretty cut and dry.  BorgWarner was not anticipating taking out new debt with its all stock deal. Delphi’s financial condition was anemic, but it was still in the black, and $500 million in potential new debt would be a hard to swallow (especially since it exceeds Delphi’s equity).  But considering that the coronavirus pandemic will be relatively short-lived—it is expected to peak in mid-April—it seems strange that BorgWarner would insist that Delphi risk running out of cash and going bankrupt to keep the deal alive, when it had access to credit that would probably see it safely through the storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead BorgWarner gave Delphi two bad options, damned if you do, and damned if you don’t.  Which leads us to believe that BorgWarner had soured on the whole idea of merging and used this credit draw down as a pretext to kill the deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mergers Traditionally a Sign of Optimism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers are widely considered a sign of optimism in the market, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/&quot;&gt;numbers &lt;/a&gt;bear that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20m&amp;amp;A%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner m&amp;amp;A chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart from the Institute of Mergers, Acquisitions and Alliances (IMAA) shows that mergers fell after the Dot-com bubble burst in 2001 and the housing bubble burst in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers fell during these prior periods of uncertainty because almost all the benefits from a merger are long term.  Our research shows that mergers generally produce negative returns for at least two years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20table-591d34.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner table-591d34.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What accounts for these terrible numbers?  Oftentimes the acquiring company must provide a large amount of cash to consummate the merger, which can leave the survivor strapped for cash or highly leveraged.  In addition, there are often personnel issues, as established norms at one or both companies are upended, and egos are bruised.  Additionally, the survivor usually inherits hidden accounting problems, and this can lead to write-offs, revisions, disclosure controls, or other gray swan events that damage the value and integrity of the company.  This is why a recent merger will significantly increase a company’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/#products&quot;&gt;gray swan event factor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positive outcomes depend on things like synergy, expanded volume, supply efficiency, and innovative technology or intellectual property (acquisitions to get new drugs in the pipeline is a feature of the pharmaceutical industry).  These benefits are generally medium to long-term benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the chart again you can see large cap companies suffer less than small or medium companies after a merger or acquisition, and that is likely due to the fact that big companies often acquire companies that are so much smaller than themselves, that it is completely irrelevant if the benefits of the merger materialize.  PayPal for example, acquired TIO networks, only to essentially &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;write off&lt;/a&gt; the entire value of the acquisition when they learned all the customer lists were compromised by a data breach, yet their share price did not suffer.  Medium and small firms simply don’t have the luxury of having a merger turn into a complete boondoggle without paying a price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We specialize in analyzing the risk of gray swan events, and the likely impact of those events on the future stock price.  A merger is one of the biggest red flags that the acquiring company can have for gray swan events.  Our research in this area affirms the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/040815/how-does-merger-affect-shareholders.asp&quot;&gt;conventional &lt;/a&gt;wisdom that generally depresses the stock price of an acquiring company because in the short-term, it is not a good bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the current market downturn, companies do not want to double down on potential losses by adding a merger to the mix.  Mergers in general are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/m-a-deals-plunge-amid-the-coronavirus-crisis-51585681640&quot;&gt;down&lt;/a&gt;.  And it appears that companies have already inked mergers are looking through the fine print for a &lt;em&gt;material adverse effect&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/coronavirus-covid-19-and-material-adverse-effect-clause&quot;&gt;clause&lt;/a&gt; to bail them out.  BorgWarner was probably thrilled when Delphi asked permission to draw down on their revolving credit, since it gave them a far more clear-cut excuse to bail on the contract than on an untested legal justification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suitors become Adversaries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delphi’s stock &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/acquisition-in-peril%3A-delphi-technologies-shares-fall-on-borgwarner-notice-2020-03-31&quot;&gt;sank &lt;/a&gt;as a result of this news.  Generally, our gray swan event factor only penalizes the acquiring company once a merger is announced, not the acquiree.  That is because generally the company that survives the deal is taking all the risk.  But in an environment like this one, conventional wisdom has been turned on its head, and companies that have been counting on a merger are the ones in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is important in an economic downturn like this is a company’s fundamentals.  Delphi is a weak company: it had anemic financial statements when the market was strong, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autonews.com/article/20181005/OEM10/181009758/delphi-ceo-steps-down-after-10-months-on-the-job&quot;&gt;problems&lt;/a&gt; at the helm to boot. Now, instead of wooing Delphi with a premium offer, BorgWarner has rejected Delphi in hopes that Delphi stumbles into bankruptcy so that they can get what they want at rock bottom prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to a new market, where fundamental analysis matters and cash is king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="BorgWarner" /><category term="Mergers" /><category term="Acquisitions" /><category term="coronavirus" /><summary type="html">With the coronavirus shutting down entire industries and raising the possibility of an extended recession, pending mergers are in peril, and mergers overall will become disfavored as companies lose their appetite for risk.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/borger.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/borger.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Birds of A Feather: How to Tell a “Gray Swan” from a “Black Swan.”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Birds of A Feather: How to Tell a “Gray Swan” from a “Black Swan.”" /><published>2020-04-01T13:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-01T13:14:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/">&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has shocked and stress tested institutions all over the world.  The emergence of the pandemic, and the global panic it has caused, is a true black swan event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gray swan event, on the other hand, is a failure in accounting or management that damages the integrity of a company and reduces its value.  At their core, these events result from a failure in transparency. These events may be infrequent, but the risk can often be anticipated and even quantified with proper due diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has caused substantial disruption, as cash shortages cause default and bankruptcy, and it is inevitable that many companies will need to file legitimate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfo.com/accounting/2020/02/coronavirus-five-things-finance-needs-to-think-about-before-closing-the-books/&quot;&gt;impairments&lt;/a&gt;.   But we suspect some companies will try to use this crisis and see an opportunity to dump billions in worthless goodwill and other assets without it creating the usual bad press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kraft Heinz’s Swan Song&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like to ascribe their failures to black swan events because it absolves them of responsibility for their failures.  We have seen this before in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;look&lt;/a&gt; at Kraft Heinz (KHC).  They issued a surprise $15 billion &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;impairment&lt;/a&gt;, which shocked the markets and sent the company into a tailspin.  KHC claimed that this impairment was due multiple factors in one bad quarter (as if it were their own personal black swan), but a closer look shows that it was more like they ran out of fingers to stick in a leaky dam. Collapse was inevitable and probably a long time coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The $15 billion that set off KHC’s awful year was not enough, and 2019 saw a steady drip of bad news.  When we wrote our original piece on KHC (linked above), they had already filed over $1.2 billion in new impairments for 2019, and we predicted more.  Indeed, shortly after our prediction, they issued another $676 million impairment for the final quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could KHC be in danger of further impairments, even if the economy had remained strong? Consider that intangible assets and goodwill still forms over $84 billion of the KHC’s $101 billion in assets.  And, the company continues to carry over $28 billion in long-term debt.  Today, the net assets of the company stand at $51 billion, but the market cap is $30 billion, that implies an overvaluation of $20 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if KHC writes off another huge chunk in assets and blame it on the coronavirus, will you believe them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expect many companies will blame the “black swan” for accounting issues this quarter, but how can you be sure it was coronavirus and not due to problems in their accounting?  How do you tell a black swan disclosure from a gray swan one?  Do the hard homework or leave it to the experts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/#products&quot;&gt;like us!&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how we think of sniffing-out a company’s own gray swan event from disclosures amid a black swan event.  We’ll use potential impairments to goodwill and other intangible assets as a case in point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;M&amp;amp;As and Balance Sheets Bloated with Goodwill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/#m-and-a-history&quot;&gt;surge&lt;/a&gt; in M&amp;amp;As over the past decade has resulted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/04/business/shrinking-stock-market.html&quot;&gt;fewer&lt;/a&gt; registered companies and more goodwill on balance sheets. Whenever companies have a merger or acquisition, the tangible and intangible assets are accounted for, and amounts paid over the value of those assets is recorded as “goodwill” on the balance sheet.  We see trouble here.  Mergers have been relatively high, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/goodwill-and-intangible-asset-impairments-in-sp-500/&quot;&gt;fewer&lt;/a&gt; companies have been recording impairments to their goodwill recorded during the merger.  Either everyone is a genius when they close their M&amp;amp;A deal, or they are trying to avoid owning up to overstating assets.   We might see impairments happen aggressively during the coronavirus black swan event, but those simply might mask bad M&amp;amp;A deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, another factor possibly inflating the amount of goodwill is FASB’s new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cpajournal.com/2018/09/26/the-new-guidance-for-goodwill-impairment/&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; for (ASU 17-04) which took effect for every public company this year—although some companies had already implemented it.  This accounting standard is simpler that the previous one, but it also allows companies to keep a balance sheet bloated with unknown liabilities.  Take &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt;, which wrote off virtually all the assets it acquired from its acquisition of TIO Networks because of a data breach that made TIO’s assets worthless.  PayPal suspended operations at TIO and impaired the assets it gained in the acquisition—except for the $170 million in goodwill—that money is still &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/paypal-the-importance-of-intangible-asset-impairments/&quot;&gt;lingering&lt;/a&gt; around on the books.  How is it appropriate to buy a company, find out it’s essentially worthless and write down all its real assets, but then retain the goodwill anyways?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most logical reason that so much goodwill is being held on company books is because the market was on the longest bull run in history.  A healthy market increased the market value of companies, which prevented their book values from looking inflated, even when loaded up with goodwill or other intangible assets.  Now there is a pandemic. The market at one point lost a third of its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FASB &lt;a href=&quot;https://asc.fasb.org/imageRoot/79/49129379.pdf&quot;&gt;accounting standards&lt;/a&gt; require that companies test goodwill annually, but they also require a special test if an event triggers a concern that the market value of the company is lower than the book value.  Well … it seems like &lt;em&gt;every company&lt;/em&gt; is going to need a special test because of the pandemic.  We can expect many companies will write down goodwill and other assets after those tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Newest Data on CAMs Indicate Goodwill Accounting is Particularly Squishy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason we are focusing on goodwill is because management’s accounting for it is inherently squishy.  We know this because that is what the auditors tell us.  Auditors are now required to report on Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), accounting areas that are particularly difficult to verify because they rely on subjective judgement of the management team.  Even though the CAMs research is brand new, it has revealed that &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/an-updated-overview-of-cams/&quot;&gt;accounting &lt;/a&gt;for goodwill (and other intangible assets) raises more consternation than any other area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of our company Watchdog Research reports includes a CAM section, with links from viewing our report on our website to the SEC filing showing that CAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Damage Control is Often a Practice in Deception&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjective nature of evaluating goodwill means that the area is ripe for obfuscation and potential abuse.  Companies in decline may delay writing off goodwill and other intangible assets for as long as possible, to look strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already filled you in on KHC, but a disingenuous impairment by KHC might be easy to spot especially since panicked buying at grocery stores and the closure of dine-in restaurants should boost their sales.  Other companies may try equally disingenuous impairments, but they might not be so easy to spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Under Armour (UA) for example.  They declined to report any impairments to goodwill in their latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm&quot;&gt;annual report&lt;/a&gt;, even though their Latin American segment has been struggling. According to UA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fair value of each reporting unit substantially exceeded its carrying value, with the exception of our Latin America reporting unit. The fair value of the Latin America reporting unit exceeded its carrying value by 19%. Holding all other assumptions used in the fair value measurement of the Latin America reporting unit constant, a reduction in the growth rate of revenue by 2.25 percentage points or a reduction in the growth rate of net income by 3.5 percentage points would eliminate the headroom. No events occurred during the period ended December 31, 2019 that indicated it was more likely than not that goodwill was impaired.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here UA seems like they are trying to impress us with the precision of their measurements and soundness of their methods, but our experience tells us that these numbers are more showmanship than science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t persuaded by our opinion, then perhaps you should look at PWC’s critical audit matters in their independent report on UA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The principal considerations for our determination that performing procedures relating to the goodwill impairment assessment of the Latin America reporting unit is a critical audit matter are there was significant judgment by management when developing the fair value measurement of the reporting unit, &lt;strong&gt;which in turn led to a high degree of auditor judgment, effort, and subjectivity&lt;/strong&gt; in performing procedures and evaluating significant assumptions, including the Company’s long-term rate of growth and profitability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if UA writes down the goodwill associated with its Latin American unit, will it be due to coronavirus or because they should have done it already?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="impairment" /><category term="goodwill" /><category term="Kraft Heinz" /><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="coronavirus" /><category term="transparency" /><category term="black swan event" /><category term="gray swan event" /><summary type="html">The coronavirus has shocked and stress tested institutions all over the world. The emergence of the pandemic, and the global panic it has caused, is a true black swan event.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/black-swan-122983_640.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/black-swan-122983_640.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armour III: Major CFO Change Was a Warning Sign of Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour III: Major CFO Change Was a Warning Sign of Litigation" /><published>2020-03-25T09:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T09:26:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;CFOs play an outsized role in the financial health of a company.  When a CFO leaves abruptly or under bad circumstances, that event can have far reaching implications.  Lawrence “Chip” Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was as damaging as it was sudden and mysterious.  Within a year after being brought in from as an outsider, he had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691717000008/january312017form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;resigned&lt;/a&gt; for “personal reasons.”  In his wake there was litigation, an SEC investigation only recently brought to light, and—of course—more litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already taken a closer look at some of the finer details on this story; we looked at how UA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;spike &lt;/a&gt;in non-audit fees was a leading indicator of financial distress and litigation, and we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;looked&lt;/a&gt; at how UA’s comment letters and recent CAM disclosure lend credence to a theory, supported by Francine Mckenna’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/what-might-be-driving-the-criminal&quot;&gt;reporting&lt;/a&gt;, that UA may be under investigation for “channel stuffing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears in UA’s case that the rounds of litigation and the SEC investigation were a direct result of Molloy’s departure.  Molloy’s departure in 2017, understood in its proper context, was a leading indicator of the financial troubles and litigation that UA would suffer in 2019—&lt;em&gt;over two years later&lt;/em&gt;.  Molloy’s story is interesting, but we wanted to look further into the numbers and see if this was a unique circumstance, or if it was emblematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with at every CFO change that was marked as a red flag in our reports from 2014-2018.  Then we looked at the likelihood that that CFO change would coincide with a Securities Class Action (SCA) lawsuit in the same year.  Here were our results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20Same%20Year.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO Same Year.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This result is not that surprising, since oftentimes the same issues that cause a CFO to resign abruptly are the same issues that provide fodder for a lawsuit. In a previous post we had analyzed ten years of data (which explains the small variation in the numbers) to determine the likelihood of a SCA lawsuit arising in the same year as a red-flag CFO change, and this is what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20same%20year%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO same year by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This result is also interesting, although not surprising.  The bigger companies have more public scrutiny, so if their CFO unexpectedly departs, a SCA is far more likely to occur; or if a SCA is filed upon learning of some problem, the CFO is more likely to be fired.  In the case of UA, litigation followed closely behind both the resignation of Molloy in 2017 and the departure of the founder Kevin Plank as CEO in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CFO Change as a Leading Indicator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear from the numbers that a red-flag CFO change in any given year corresponds with an increased risk of a SCA lawsuit during that year, especially for big companies.  But that warning is often too late, since litigation can come hot on the heels of an early CFO resignation.  We ran the same analysis to see if red-flag CFO changes have been a leading indicator of a more litigation in the following year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20followingyr.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO followingyr.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have a statistically significant correlation, demonstrating that a red-flag CFO change is a leading indicator of SCA litigation in the following year.  Moreover, the risk is greater for large cap companies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20followingyr%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO followingyr by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more interesting point is that the results of a similar study on red-flag CEOs did not yield the same results.  CEO departures did correlate with an increased risk of SCA litigation for the same year, &lt;em&gt;but not for the following year&lt;/em&gt;.  This makes sense, since an abrupt CFO change probably relates to the financial health of a company, but a CEO can be removed abruptly for all sorts of other reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UA’s Issues Emblematic of Other Red-Flag CFO Departures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers we have presented indicate that UA’s problems with SCA litigation following the resignation of Molloy is emblematic, and not a fluke or exception.  The UA example is helpful because it gives a window as to what is going on behind these numbers.  When something dramatic like a unexpected CFO departure occurs and the company offers little or no explanation as to what is going on, it is more likely that there is a major problem going on that will trap the company in expensive litigation.  The best course of action for these companies is to be fully transparent and address their issues head-on so that their problems do not linger for years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="CFO Change" /><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Leading Indicators" /><summary type="html">CFOs play an outsized role in the financial health of a company. When a CFO leaves abruptly or under bad circumstances, that event can have far reaching implications. Lawrence “Chip” Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was as damaging as it was sudden and mysterious. Within a year after being brought in from as an outsider, he had resigned for “personal reasons.” In his wake there was litigation, an SEC investigation only recently brought to light, and—of course—more litigation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/litigation_ua-3.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/litigation_ua-3.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armour II: CAM Raises the Specter of “Channel Stuffing”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour II: CAM Raises the Specter of “Channel Stuffing”" /><published>2020-03-17T14:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-17T14:48:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/">&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; piece on Under Armour (UA) we looked at how a dramatic increase in non-audit fees by PriceWaterhouseCoopers (PWC) was a sign of financial problems and a leading indicator of litigation. We also briefly examined UA’s SEC investigation, which was first reported on by the Wall Street Journal.  This investigation has remained somewhat mysterious and UA has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/under-armour-says-its-accounting-practices-have-been-entirely-appropriate-after-wsj-story-2019-11-15&quot;&gt;denied&lt;/a&gt; any wrongdoing.  Thanks to the newly required disclosures of Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), we are getting some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to news reports, the SEC began its investigation into UA in July of 2017.  The report indicated that there was shuffling sales from quarter to quarter to make the company look healthier.  An extensive report by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/retheauditors&quot;&gt;Francine Mckenna&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/about?utm_source=menu-dropdown&quot;&gt;“The Dig”&lt;/a&gt; raised the possibility that UA may have been “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/channelstuffing.asp&quot;&gt;channel stuffing&lt;/a&gt;” by sending retailers more product than they can sell (a practice more likely when a transaction is not truly at arms-length).  The speculation is that UA would push its inventory on retailers during a traditionally slower time of year, thereby boosting sales, and then record the loss of the returned merchandise in a more profitable time of year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear from the investigation whether or not there has been any “channel stuffing,” but there are a few pieces of evidence that suggest UA has not been completely transparent in their accounting and may have to pay a price at the end of this investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lawrence Molloy Left in January 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molloy, an outsider, was appointed the CFO in January 2016.  In January 2017, he announced his resignation for “personal reasons.”  The short tenure, the non-explanation, and the fact that the outsider Molloy was replaced with a long-time loyalist in David E. Bergman (joined in 2004) suggests that Molloy had a serious disagreement in how the company’s finances should be managed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Correspondence with the SEC in May 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting detail from the Wall Street Journal story is that this investigation by the SEC has been ongoing since July of 2017.  Right around that time, our report flagged the release of an SEC comment letter correspondence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we looked at the letter itself, we found that the SEC first &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/app/view-comment-letter.php?cl_fkey=edgar/data/1336917/0000000000-17-015141.txt&quot;&gt;contacted&lt;/a&gt; UA on May 1st, 2017 with questions about the factors that had led to material increases in revenue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;we note you do not quantify the impacts of these factors or fully describe the specific new products lines or offerings that have caused the increase. Please expand your discussion to fully describe the specific reasons and factors contributing to the material changes in revenue…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC wanted to know how much revenue growth was due to new product lines. UA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000119312517187248/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; on May 30th, amongst other things was that “… &lt;em&gt;the Company is not readily able to quantify the impact of unit sales growth of existing versus new product offerings.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It strikes us as odd that UA would not know how much revenue they were receiving from new product offerings.  The SEC might have found it strange as well.  This exchange shows that the SEC was taking a critical view of UA’s revenue recognition methods, and the SEC may not have been satisfied with UA’s explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plank, Founder and CEO, Stepped Aside in October 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not unusual for a founder of a company to step aside from the day-to-day operations of a company, but the timing here is suspicious.  Plank’s departure came a few weeks before the Wall Street Journal broke its story about the SEC investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PWC’s Critical Audit Matter Disclosure Highlights Issues with Sales Returns and Allowances&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting firms are now required to disclose CAMs as a part of their report on a company.  These disclosures require the firm to highlight areas in the accounting that required particularly challenging, complex, or subjective judgements by the auditor.  Our report indicates that UA already has a red flag CAM concerning its Reserve for Customer Returns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Under%20Armour%20CAM%20redflag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Under Armour CAM redflag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we looked at the filing, PWC explained that the company had recorded $219 million in this reserve for returns and markdowns.  And they offered this by way of explanation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal considerations for our determination that performing procedures relating to the reserve for customer returns is a critical audit matter are there was significant judgment by management in estimating the customer returns reserve, which in turn led to a high degree of auditor judgment, effort, and subjectivity in performing procedures and evaluating the significant assumptions used in developing the estimate, including the amount of outstanding returns that have not yet been received by the Company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC has reportedly been investigating since July of 2017 and yet the increased scrutiny has not spurred UA to solve the issue, as PWC issued this CAM for 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that this “reserve” represents the value of merchandise that the company estimates will be returned to the company, effectively adjusting the final sales numbers.  To understand the magnitude of the issue we took a closer look at some of these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm#ia59c9d23542e4b489dc58de46d9acdd9_25&quot;&gt;numbers&lt;/a&gt; (edited for formatting):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20sales%20returns%20numbers.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA sales returns numbers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sales returns and allowances and allowance for doubtful accounts amounts are significantly less this year than in years past.  This could indicate that UA has been changing how it interacts with its retailers, pushing product less aggressively so that the retailers are less likely to overbuy and then return product.  Additionally, the number has fluctuated greatly over the past three years, from which we can infer that PWC would probably have flagged the sales returns consistently if it had been required to relay CAMs in years past.  Regardless, the fact that PWC highlighted these numbers as being particularly subjective is not comforting for investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Typical was UA’s CAM?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close examination of UA’s financial statements reveals how invaluable new CAMs disclosures are in understanding the story behind the numbers, but the CAMs have more to offer.  They can also help us draw comparisons with other companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/an-updated-overview-of-cams/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; shows that CAMs relating to revenue (including sales returns and allowances) account for about 15% of all CAMS issued so far.  Our analysts wanted to see how typical it is for a company to have a CAM that falls under the category of Sales Returns and Allowances.  Currently, more than 1900 companies have filed CAMs.  We narrowed by only looking at CAMs related to Sales Returns and Allowances.  This narrowed our pool to only 74 companies.  Here are the results broken down by industry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CAMS%20by%20industry.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CAMS by industry.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No other apparel companies have had CAMs concerning the sales and returns allowances.  However we discovered several limitations in this sort of analysis due to the CAMs disclosure requirement &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Standards/Auditing/Pages/AS3101.aspx&quot;&gt;incremental&lt;/a&gt; roll-out.  Currently, only large accelerated filers are required to file CAMs for 2019, and not every company has filed yet.  There are 11 apparel manufacturers who will be required to file CAMs this year, but so far only 3 have done so.  It is too early to draw any real conclusions, but we are excited about how this new disclosure will open the door to new and better insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Last Word on “Channel Stuffing”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Channel Stuffing” is considered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fbi.gov/news/stories/executives-sentenced-in-750-million-fraud-scheme&quot;&gt;serious crime&lt;/a&gt;, and executives have received lengthy prison sentences for wire or mail fraud because of it.  But to convict, the DOJ would need to prove the requisite intent (i.e. a purpose to defraud), and the fact that the investigation has been going on for almost three years indicates that the DOJ does not have a smoking gun.  UA may be entirely innocent of “channel stuffing.”   We won’t really know until the DOJ or UA brings all the details to light.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Channel Stuffing" /><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><category term="Critical Audit Matters" /><summary type="html">In our first piece on Under Armour (UA) we looked at how a dramatic increase in non-audit fees by PriceWaterhouseCoopers (PWC) was a sign of financial problems and a leading indicator of litigation. We also briefly examined UA’s SEC investigation, which was first reported on by the Wall Street Journal. This investigation has remained somewhat mysterious and UA has denied any wrongdoing. Thanks to the newly required disclosures of Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), we are getting some clarity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/clothes_stack.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/clothes_stack.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armour I: Troubling Spike in Non-Audit Fees Went Ignored</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour I: Troubling Spike in Non-Audit Fees Went Ignored" /><published>2020-03-13T11:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-13T11:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/">&lt;p&gt;Under Armour still has not recovered from a serious blow it suffered in early November 2019 when the Wall Street Journal reported that the company had been under investigation by the SEC for its accounting practices.  One element of the story that rattled investors was that the investigation had been going on since July &lt;em&gt;of 2017&lt;/em&gt;, yet it had not been addressed in a transparent way by management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was reported that Under Armour has allegedly been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/03/business/under-armour-sec-justice-dept.html&quot;&gt;shifting&lt;/a&gt; its sales in between quarters to appear healthier.  Companies with seasonal sales often try unconventional and even counter-productive methods to boost traditionally slow quarters and smooth out their numbers, but the ongoing SEC investigation indicates that something more sinister is at play here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For it’s part, Under Armour has said it did nothing wrong.  However, a court found these troubling allegations substantial enough to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm&quot;&gt;revive &lt;/a&gt;a securities lawsuit that it previously had dismissed with prejudice because of the new evidence presented.  Now Under Armour is facing three suits over the matter, and the one certainty of this litigation is that it will be expensive for Under Armour (and their D+O underwriter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Non-Audit Fees Increased Dramatically at Under Armour&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever a story like this gets broken, people always want to look back and see if there were any leading indicators or warning signs. In our opinion a lack of transparency is the most important sign that a company could be in trouble. When a company like Under Armour is going through a lot of turmoil and they attempt to paper over and obscure the problem instead of hitting it straight on, then we get concerned that there are deeper problems festering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors did have some indications that something was wrong at Under Armour. The company went through a tremendous amount of turmoil in their management team in 2016-2017.  Lawrence Molloy replaced a long-time CFO in January 2016, then &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691717000008/january312017form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; his resignation for “personal reasons” about a year later.  If Molloy was experiencing health issues, they didn’t stop him from finding work shortly thereafter, or from serving on the board of &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.sprouts.com/leadership-bios/lawrence-p-molloy/&quot;&gt;Sprouts&lt;/a&gt; during that time.  When highly paid executives start leaving for “personal reasons,” that raises a red flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volatility at the executive level does not necessarily indicate something is wrong; it can be a sign of health if a company has become moribund.  However, those rapid changes at the executive level in 2017 were followed a dramatic 267% increase in Non-Audit fees paid to PWC for 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Under%20Armour%20Non-Audit%20Fees.png&quot; alt=&quot;Under Armour Non-Audit Fees.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that Under Armour’s accounting disclosures are not particularly complex, and that their traditional audit fees had been hovering around the 25th quartile for several years and had actually decreased significantly in 2018, this dramatic increase in non-audit fees signaled that Under Armour was wrestling with significant issues. 
Our Analysts looked back at the period from 2014-2018 and found that a high non-audit fee that raises a yellow flag in our reports corresponded with a statistically significant increase in the risk of securities litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Under%20Armour%20Non-audit%20Fee%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Under Armour Non-audit Fee Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If high non-audit fees are generally a leading indicator of securities litigation, a dramatic one-year increase in non-audit fees would be an even more compelling sign of financial distress.  Here Under Armour’s 268% increase in non-audit fees, paired with unexplained turmoil on the executive level, provided ample notice that trouble was on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Fraud" /><category term="Non-Audit Fees" /><category term="SEC" /><category term="Leading Indicators" /><category term="Red Flag" /><summary type="html">Under Armour still has not recovered from a serious blow it suffered in early November 2019 when the Wall Street Journal reported that the company had been under investigation by the SEC for its accounting practices. One element of the story that rattled investors was that the investigation had been going on since July of 2017, yet it had not been addressed in a transparent way by management.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/under_armour_non_audit_fees.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/under_armour_non_audit_fees.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">UPDATE Nine Critical Days in Hunter Biden’s Time on the Burisma Board</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UPDATE Nine Critical Days in Hunter Biden’s Time on the Burisma Board" /><published>2020-01-17T06:18:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-17T06:18:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/">&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: AG Bondi’s Presentation Adds More Facts and Raises More Questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the Trump administration and the US Department of Justice wants to conduct a meaningful inquiry into the circumstances surrounding Burisma, Joe and Hunter Biden and the loss of billions of dollars associated with the failure of Privat Bank and aid to Ukraine, it must subpoena the records of Boise Schiller concerning Hunter Biden, Zlochevsky, and Burisma, and it must subpoena the IMF records concerning Burisma, PrivatBank and Kolomoisky. If the Senate ends up being dragged into this investigation, it will have to do the same as the only real question that exists that matters is whether Trump was correct to be concerned about corruption in Joe and Hunter Biden’s dealings with Burisma and Ukraine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This an update to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/&quot;&gt;lengthy piece&lt;/a&gt; from last week on Hunter Biden’s potential conflicts of interest and ethical/moral issues he faced during his board tenure. In this fast-paced story, more evidence has come to light about the connection between Bursima to Ihor Kolomoisky and his theft of 5.5 billion from PrivatBank, and a conflict of interest for Hunter concerning his employment at Boise Schiller. Let’s jump in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump’s defense lawyer and former Florida Attorney General Pam Bondi made a presentation during the Senate trial where she made the case showing it was reasonable for the President to raise the issue of investigating Hunter Biden’s role at Burisma with the Ukrainian President Zelensky. Ms. Bondi did not address everything our original blog below addressed, but we are adding her new information to our blog to paint a more damning position for Hunter’s role as a board member at Burisma. We have no personal animosity toward Hunter. Our company acts as a watchdog (WatchdogResearch.com) on proper board governance, transparency, risks and disclosures. Our focus remains on Hunter’s failures in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already argued that Hunter’s role was not really to serve as an independent director. It is far more likely that Zlochevsky brought him on so the Biden name would provide a firewall, preventing the Ukranian government from seizing the energy company either as a wartime measure, or as a way of rewarding those loyal to the new regime. There remains a great deal of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/ukraine-gas-company-burisma-holdings-joe-bidens-son-hunter-explained-2019-9&quot;&gt;confusion&lt;/a&gt; as to what role he actually played at the company. Burisma &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/5980032-Burisma-Announces-Hunter-Biden-s-Appointment-to.html&quot;&gt;initially&lt;/a&gt; reported on May 12, 2014, that he would be in charge of the legal unit. But as Ms. Bondi’s presentation showed, Hunter told the NY Times that he never served in that capacity and Hunter’s lawyer issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; denying it. Hunter undoubtedly denied this claim because serving as an executive head of the “legal unit” would be antithetical to his supposed position as an independent board member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Senate Ought to Subpoena Records From the IMF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our last piece we pointed out that Hunter Biden was on the Board when Ihor Kolomoisky, one of Ukraine’s most powerful Oligarchs, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kyivpost.com/article/content/reform-watch/prosecutors-put-zlochevsky-multimillionaire-ex-ecology-minister-on-wanted-list-377719.html&quot;&gt;purchased 45%&lt;/a&gt; of a company believed to be Burisma’s subsidiary. Kolomoisky was the owner of PrivatBank, the largest private banks in Ukraine at the time. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/&quot;&gt;OCCRP&lt;/a&gt;, Kolomoisky also stole &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/investigations/oligarchs-weaponized-cyprus-eranch-of-ukraines-largest-bank-to-send-5-billion-abroad&quot;&gt;$5.5 billion&lt;/a&gt; (5% of the Ukraine’s GDP) out of PrivatBank in 2016, which lead to the IMF to bail the bank out, and creating an urgent need for loan guarantees from the U.S.  Make no mistake, U.S. taxpayers paid for this bailout. Kolomoisky allegedly stashed and laundered this money through other entities that he owned at the time. It is possible that some of this money went through his newly owned interest in Burisma or its subsidiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PrivatBank was implicated in a money laundering scheme in 2014 where it allegedly laundered over $2 billion from Russia and brought it into Europe. PrivatBank’s reported purchase of a subsidiary of Burisma has all the hallmarks of a money laundering scheme, especially considering Zlochevsky had just had $23 million &lt;a href=&quot;https://johnsolomonreports.com/the-ukraine-scandal-timeline-democrats-and-their-media-allies-dont-want-america-to-see/&quot;&gt;frozen&lt;/a&gt; by the British fraud office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have previously discussed how Hunter was paid 12X the typical salary for an independent board member at a small private company.  But Ms. Bondi helped us see which bank was handling Burisma’s payments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/update_9_days_burisma.png&quot; alt=&quot;update_9_days_burisma.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that Burisma held its accounts at PrivatBank, showing another link between the two companies and the two Oligarchs, Zlochevsky and Kolomoisky. Why is this connection relevant to impeachment? It has been widely reported Joe Biden insistence that Shokin be fired had nothing to do with Burisma and that he was fired because of his failure to investigate the massive theft of IMF money by Kolomoisky. That version of the story doesn’t hold much water when Kolomoisky is potentially closely affiliated with Burisma and may have used it as a vehicle to launder money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more point about Kolomoisky. He is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/13/world/europe/ukraine-ihor-kolomoisky-russia.html&quot;&gt;closely&lt;/a&gt; tied to President Zelensky. Although Kolomoisky seems more like his patron, Zelensky said in an interview “He is my business partner, not my boss.”  Zelensky’s statement is not very reassuring.  Is it so surprising that Trump was hesitant to send more money to the Ukraine? In that interview, Zelensky was all but admitting that he was receiving money from Kolomoisky, and if you read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/investigations/oligarchs-weaponized-cyprus-eranch-of-ukraines-largest-bank-to-send-5-billion-abroad&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; it is clear that he received significant assistance in the form of free advertising and promotion from Kolomoisky’s television station.  Wasn’t it reasonable for Trump to be hesitant about sending US aid to an administration potentially beholden to an Oligarch accused by the IMF of massive fraud, one who already have been implicated in laundering Russian money through its Lativian subsidiary of PrivatBank?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case for impeachment relies on the idea that no reasonable person could have believed that there was corruption going on with Burisma and the Bidens. The Democrats have called the notion “absurd.” In reality, the case that there was corruption at Burisma is unassailable, and it is also indisputable that Hunter Biden’s position on the board may implicate him in attempts to hide potential corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money is fungible, and it is difficult to know exactly where all the money flowed.  But it is certainly worth investigating, and if the Senate wants to quickly get to the bottom of it, it needs to subpoena every IMF record on Kolomoisky, Zlochevsky, PrivatBank, and Burisma and its subsidiaries. Those records will show whether there was a legitimate reason to investigate Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Senate Ought to Subpoena Records from Boise Schiller&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bosie Schiller has been associated with the Biden family for at least a decade, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsfllp.com/news-events/bsf-achieves-dismissal-of-claims-against-family-members-of-vice.html&quot;&gt;represented&lt;/a&gt; them before Hunter worked for Boise.  In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/conflicted-unethical-and-corrupt-nine-critical-days-of-hunter-bidens-burisma-tenure/&quot;&gt;last piece&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed the potential for a conflict of interest between Hunter Biden active role on the board of Burisma and his continued role at Boise. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://johnsolomonreports.com/the-ukraine-scandal-timeline-democrats-and-their-media-allies-dont-want-america-to-see/&quot;&gt;reporting&lt;/a&gt; of John Solomon has demonstrated that this conflict was not simply potential, but that it happened. Hunter was announced as a board member in May of 2014 after being asked to join in April. Prior to that, Hunter had been working for Burisma on behalf of his firm Boise Schiller Flexner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Hunter’s attorney, “Burisma agreed to pay the legal expenses of Boies Schiller to support Hunter in developing corporate reform initiatives.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribd.com/document/436048670/Burisma-Holdings-Accounting-Ledger&quot;&gt;Records&lt;/a&gt; show that Boise billed Burisma $250,000 for a retainer in May 2014, and then an additional $33,000 in September when that presumably did not cover all of Hunter’s expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not the big legal fees that raise eyebrows, even though it seems Hunter &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;subbed out&lt;/a&gt; most of the work to Nardello &amp;amp; Co. which was paid about $55,000 for its work. It is the fact that Burisma started paying Hunter’s investment firm in April, around the time that it asked Hunter to join the board as an independent director. Burisma then paid Hunter $83,000 a month ($1 million/year) to serve as an independent board member starting in May, the same month it gave Boise a $250,000 retainer for the work being done by Hunter Biden on behalf of Boise. If these records are accurate then Hunter was double dipping, at least initially, as both a consultant and as an “independent” board director which is a glaring conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boise Schiller is at risk here too; they allowed this unethical behavior by one of their attorneys. There is a cauldron of conflicts here for Boise Schiller as they had to consider the implications for Burisma, Zlochevsky, Hunter Biden, the Biden family, and any duties of loyalty that may have come with government contracts or legal obligations to report ongoing crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boise is one of the world’s most powerful firms, with some of the brightest and most astute lawyers. There is certainly an extensive file on Burisma, Hunter Biden, and Zlochevsky, including the reports that they put together. There may even be internal memos about the risks posed to the firm for this conflict. There were certainly internal discussions after it was widely reported. The Senate must subpoena all of the documents related to Zlochevsky, Burisma, Hunter Biden, and any other related documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is of course more to this story. Like the fact that Devon Archer failed to serve his full five year term and quietly left the board after he became implicated in an unrelated but massive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/litigation/litreleases/2016/lr23535.htm&quot;&gt;Ponzi&lt;/a&gt; scheme. Or the fact that the other well-connected Board member, the former president of Poland, Aleksander Kwasniewski, was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/24/world/europe/manafort-gusenbauer-hapsburg-ukraine-indictment.html&quot;&gt;connected&lt;/a&gt; with the ousted Pro-Russian Regime and Paul Manafort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be understandable for the Senators to dismiss the impeachment against President Trump without going any further, but if they want to get to the truth, then any roadmap should start with subpoenaing Boise and the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our original post is below…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;But Burisma’s owner, Mykola Zlochevsky, has been under investigation in Britain and in Ukraine. It should be plain to Hunter Biden that any connection with a Ukrainian oligarch damages his father’s efforts to help Ukraine. This is not a board he should be sitting on.&lt;/em&gt;“ &lt;strong&gt;New York Times Op Ed, December 12, 2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;… if President Trump honestly believed that there was a corrupt arrangement with Hunter Biden that was not fully investigated by the Obama Administration, the request for an investigation is not corrupt, notwithstanding its inappropriateness. The Hunter Biden contract has been widely criticized as raw influence peddling. I have joined in that criticism. For many years, I have written about the common practice of companies and lobbyists attempting to curry favor with executive branch officials and members of Congress by giving windfall contracts or jobs to their children. This is a classic example of that corrupt practice.&lt;/em&gt;“ &lt;strong&gt;Jonathan Turley, Esq. Testimony before House Judiciary Committee December 5, 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Watchdog Research, we publish reports and blogs focused on publicly traded company transparency, honest and full public disclosures and gray swan events. Professional investors and D&amp;amp;O insurance industry executives pay to subscribe to our reports because we expose the hidden risks and troubling issues that often cause a stock to lose value. As a public service, we do offer our reports to individual investors for free from our website. Our reports cover 6,500+ public companies, mostly in the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, such as with this blog, we have the opportunity to apply our insights and skills to other situations that need a healthy dose of transparency and our rock-solid analysis. We have been watching the developments in the impeachment of Donald Trump with great interest. The articles of impeachment have been delivered to the Senate and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/trump-impeachment-trial-in-senate-likely-to-start-tuesday-january-21-and-last-3-to-5-weeks-sources-say/&quot;&gt;full trial&lt;/a&gt; in the Senate is imminent. There has been talk that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/01/06/us/politics/bolton-testify-impeachment-trial.html&quot;&gt;John Bolton&lt;/a&gt;, or even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/biden-lays-out-his-objections-to-impeachment-subpoena-demand-11577558319&quot;&gt;Joe Biden&lt;/a&gt; may participate as witnesses, but the most consequential witness that we have not heard from is Hunter Biden. President Trump’s discussion with the President of Ukraine regarding Hunter Biden’s role as an independent board member of Burisma is the key issue to the impeachment case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already written a report on Hunter Biden’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;unusually high&lt;/a&gt; compensation for his position at Burisma, which is a topic he would probably rather avoid.  Our team has investigated Hunter Biden’s tenure at Burisma and found nine specific days in Hunter’s tenure at Burisma that might either prove he was an active, appropriate board member or he was instead a passive board member paid a whopping sum because he had a unique last name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason why it is crucial that the Senate get comprehensive answers from Hunter about Burisma and these nine days is because the Russians just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/01/13/us/politics/russian-hackers-burisma-ukraine.html&quot;&gt;hacked&lt;/a&gt; Burisma. The most effective way to prevent the Russians from interfering with the election by spreading potentially false damaging information about Hunter’s time at Burisma, is for Hunter to immediately disclose all his relevant documents from Burisma and provide complete and comprehensive testimony. For instance, how did Hunter act during the nine days we discuss below?  Did he fulfill his professional board-level responsibilities or did he simply rubber-stamp everything and allow Burisma to operate with little input or oversight? The answer will prove whether Donald Trump’s instincts were right or wrong to raise the issue of Hunter Biden with the president of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why we have taken such a keen interest in Hunter’s time at Burisma is because it gives us the chance to apply principles of good governance to a real-life example (actually Hunter’s story is less real life and more HBO movie). There is much that can be learned from Hunter Biden’s misfortune. And if you serve on a foreign board and your days start looking as bad as Hunter Biden’s, we would strongly recommend taking your career in another direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day One - The Day the NY Times Demanded Hunter Biden’s Resignation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffet famously admonishes his operating executives to apply “the newspaper test” to their actions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I ask the managers to judge every action they take — not just by legal standards, though obviously that’s the first test — but also by what I call the ‘newspaper test.’ If a manager expresses uncertainty, I ask them how they would feel about any given action if they know it was to be written up the next day in their local newspaper by a smart but pretty unfriendly reporter.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good test and one Hunter could apply on December 12, 2015, when the NY Times ran an editorial entitled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/12/opinion/joe-biden-lectures-ukraine.html&quot;&gt;Joe Biden Lectures Ukraine.&lt;/a&gt;”. It is worth quoting the relevant portion on Hunter Biden here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sadly, the credibility of Mr. Biden’s message may be undermined by the association of his son with a Ukrainian natural-gas company, Burisma Holdings, which is owned by a former government official suspected of corrupt practices. A spokesman for the son, Hunter Biden, argues that he joined the board of Burisma to strengthen its corporate governance. That may be so. But Burisma’s owner, Mykola Zlochevsky, has been under investigation in Britain and in Ukraine. It should be plain to Hunter Biden that any connection with a Ukrainian oligarch damages his father’s efforts to help Ukraine. This is not a board he should be sitting on.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you hail from a staunchly democrat-party family, and your father serves as VP of the United States and the NY Times (one of your biggest press advocates dares to call for your resignation, you should probably listen.  Imagine the discussions taking place on that day in the Biden, Obama and Kerry households, not to mention just about all of Ukraine, Russia, China, US intelligence agencies, State department, Attorney General’s office, Congress, and a host of other political, personal and readers of the NY Times.  How could any son of a VP be so belligerent, obtuse or desperate as to not resign immediately?  Was receiving more than a million dollars a year for virtually no-show job, being paid by a pro-Russian, on-the-lam Ukrainian Oligarch worth it?  In our opinion, this had to be the worst of nine days in the life of Hunter Biden and Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Two -The Day Hunter Discovered of a UK Investigation into Burisma’s owner Mykola Zlochevsky:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 28, 2014, most likely right after Hunter joined the board, the UK’s Serious Fraud Office &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfo.gov.uk/2014/04/28/money-laundering-investigation-opened/http://&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; it was launching a criminal investigation into possible money laundering undertaken by Burisma’s owner Mykola Zlochevsky. The UK Guardian wrote an in-depth review of the case &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/apr/12/the-money-machine-how-a-high-profile-corruption-investigation-fell-apart&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Ultimately the case fell apart because of corruption in the Ukranian prosecutor’s office (someone there wrote to the UK court saying that Zlovchevsky was not under investigation, a bald lie which was probably the result of a bribe).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the launching of the investigation, mere days after he joined the board should have been a red flag for Hunter Biden that should have led to his initiating an internal board investigation into potential claims of misuse of funds by Zlochevsky or any of his staff who reported to him.  At a minimum Hunter should have demanded Burisma hire an independent, well-regarded law firm to do a review of the case to advise the board on actions it should take.  Hunter should also have insisted Zlochevsky cooperate fully with the UK in their efforts.  Any resistance by Zlochevsky in this regard should have led to Hunter to ‘resign loudly.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Three - The Day Hunter Learned Burisma’s Owner Was a Fugitive of the Ukrainian Government:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime after October of 2014, Hunter Biden learned that Zlochevsky, Burisma’s owner, was a fugitive wanted by the Ukrainian government. Although it was not until January 16, 2015, approximately nine months after Hunter Biden joined the Burisma board, that the government of Ukraine publicly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kyivpost.com/article/content/reform-watch/prosecutors-put-zlochevsky-multimillionaire-ex-ecology-minister-on-wanted-list-377719.html&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; Zlochevsky’s fugitive status. Zlovchevsky was under investigation for (amongst other things) of using his previous position as Ecology Minister to grant Burisma and its subsidiaries valuable licenses to extract oil and gas that were not granted to competitors. He also had been considered a lackey for Yanukovitch, Putin’s puppet and the former president of Ukraine whose ouster had started the ongoing war with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A point for context. Hunter Biden’s role as an independent board member required him to act as a fiduciary for Burisma. This means he owed the company a duty to act diligently, loyally, and in good faith to advance the interests of the company. What is in the best interest of the owner is not always what is in the best interests of the company, and we can find no clearer example of that than here in the case of Burisma. With Zlovchevsky on the lam, it was the responsibility of the Board to come clean with the government of Ukraine and restore Burisma. However, Hunter was not truly able to do any of this, especially since Zlovchevsky remained the sole owner and his people remained in charge. Since Hunter could not have discharged his duties as an independent board member, he should have resigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team struggled to justify Hunter’s decision to stay on the board. At best, we concluded that Hunter Biden might have stayed IF he had taken steps to approach the Ukrainian government (and given notice to his father and appropriate US security interests) to place Burisma into receivership or something like it. Receivership is an equitable remedy where a court appoints an independent guardian or trustee to oversee the company’s operations. Having a court or government take over a company in such turmoil is not unusual. It happens fairly often in the US through banking and insurance company regulators. Mostly these government takeovers occur to protect creditors in bankruptcy, but it can be used in other extraordinary circumstances, such as during war-time, which we would argue apply here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Hunter or other board members had taken such steps to put Burisma into receivership or remove themselves from the board or had engaged an outside regulator or appointed receiver, these high-paid board members would almost certainly have lost their lucrative board seats and ongoing cash payments. As farfetched as it may sound, given the wild-west nature of Ukraine at the time, they may even have faced threats of bodily harm. Is it reasonable to believe that after joining the board of Burisma that Hunter stayed on because he felt like he had no choice? It’s doubtful, since Hunter never visited Ukraine, and may even have been entitled to Sercret Service proteciton.  We must also not forget that during his board years he was facing extraordinary expenses in the US from a divorce, drug addiction issues, and other expensive personal challenges. It seems likely that Hunter’s primary reason for remaining on the board was for the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Four - The Day Burisma made an Large Sale of Operating Subsidiary Assets to Another Corrupt Ukrainian Oligarch Kolomoisky:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kyiv Post &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kyivpost.com/article/content/reform-watch/prosecutors-put-zlochevsky-multimillionaire-ex-ecology-minister-on-wanted-list-377719.html&quot;&gt;ran a story&lt;/a&gt;, noting that in July 2014 Burisma’s owner, Zlochevsky, sold up to a 45% equity share in at least one of Burisma’s subsidiaries (not Burisma itself) to the Ukrainian oligarch Ihor Kolomoisky, a reputed billionaire whom at that time owned the largest bank in Ukraine (PrivatBank). It is not known how much the sale generated for Burisma (vs. directly for Zlochevsky). It is also not known whether the funds to purchase the 45% interest came from Kolomosky himself or from PrivatBank. However, we do know both Kolomoisky and Zlochevsky would later flee the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, Kolomoisky controlled the Ukrainian bank PrivatBank.  PrivatBank, later nationalized by Ukraine, was the vehicle through which as much as $&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en/investigations/oligarchs-weaponized-cyprus-eranch-of-ukraines-largest-bank-to-send-5-billion-abroad&quot;&gt;5.5 billion&lt;/a&gt; of IMF money was stolen. As reported by the OCCRP, “The central mechanism in the scheme was a series of insider loans to companies Kolomoisky and [his partner] controlled.”  Considering that Kolominisky held a considerable stake in Burisma’s subsidiaries, Hunter and the board would have needed to investigate to ensure that none of the stolen money was being hidden in Burisma through its subsidiaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the money is often quoted in any fraud case. Given that the US is the primary provider of capital to the IMF, it would be wise for Joe Biden use his influence to force the IMF to follow the money from the IMF to Kolomoisky.  From there it could have gone to Burisma through its subsidiaries, and then to Zlovchevsky. If it had gone to Zlovchevsky and Burisma, then by association some could have benefited Hunter Biden, Devon Archer and the former President of Poland Aleksander Kwasniewski who were paid excessively high as board members. At the time, Hunter Biden should have forced Burisma to trace funds going in and out of Burisma, and those going in and out of the hands of Zlovchevsky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the Burisma equity sale to Kolomoisky: this sale reportedly occurred in the summer of 2014, after Hunter had joined the board. The board of directors would have needed to be intimately involved in a decision of this import, and Hunter should have received documentation and an opportunity to vote on it. At a minimum, Hunter Biden should have insisted on proper valuation of the subsidiary interests and demanded a thorough legal review of the transaction. This legal review should have investigated the buyer, and if it was Ihor Kolomoisky, or any of the Ukrainian oligarchs who had by then been named in corrupt practices cases, Hunter should have interceded to stop any further sale discussions and told other board members it would be appropriate to invite US or IMF regulators to weigh-in on their concerns about Kolomoisky. He definitely should have discussed this with his father, and Secretary of State Kerry.  This sale has all the hallmarks of a seriously corrupt transaction.  And as Hunter stated in his recent television interview, he understood that he had been asked to sit on the board because his name was Biden. This should have translated into a two-way street, as Burisma should have expected Hunter to be regularly discussing key Burisma and US and Ukrainian national security issues with his father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Five - The Day Ukraine’s Top Prosecutor was Fired&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PrivatBank was also a banking vehicle that indirectly processed US aid and/or loan guarantees to Ukraine. The IMF loss of billions (in part guaranteed by the US) was central to the IMF loudly demanding Ukraine fire its lead investigator Shokin, presumably for not investigating Kolomoisky and PrivatBank. Shokin has denied the IMF allegations and countered that the primary reason for his firing was his investigation into Burisma and by extension Hunter Biden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least in part because of IMF demands, as is well known, in March 2016 VP Joe Biden subsequently made $1 billion in US funding support for Ukraine contingent on Ukraine firing Shokin. Shokin was then fired and the US funds/guarantees were released. Thus, two years after Hunter joined the board we see evidence of a link between Joe Biden, his son Hunter, Burisma, missing funds, PrivatBank, Kolomoisky, the firing of Shokin and US national security interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of why Shokin was fired, the effect was to chill any ongoing investigations of Burisma and by extension, Zlovchevsky.  The subsequent prosecutor dropped the case, even though it was widely known that there was corruption at Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Six - The Day Hunter Learned his Business Partner Devon Archer Was Banned By SEC from Board Memberships:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunter’s fiduciary duties to the company should not only have created independence from the oligarch Zlovchevsky and his management team, but from the other directors as well. Part of the responsibilities of a board member is to assure the independence of the other directors. Now there was already a potential conflict. As discussed in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;previous report&lt;/a&gt;, both Hunter Biden and Devon Archer were overpaid compared to their peers. But the former President of Poland Aleksander Kwasniewski also was making &lt;a href=&quot;https://polandin.com/44767911/former-polish-president-and-the-ukrainian-investigation-into-biden&quot;&gt;a million euro a year&lt;/a&gt;. Unsurprisingly, these overpaid members would cause more problems during their tenure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 11, 2016, approximately two years after Hunter joined Burisma’s board with Devon Archer, the SEC filed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/litigation/litreleases/2016/lr23535.htm&quot;&gt;litigation release&lt;/a&gt; stating that it was seeking to bar Devon Archer from serving on any SEC regulated company boards and announcing the Southern District of New York was pursuing criminal charges against Devon Archer. Based upon our experience analyzing SEC cases, it is very likely that word of this investigation into Archer and his cohorts would have first become known to Archer and his business partners Christopher Heinz and Hunter Biden, in at least mid-2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no need to mince words here: Devon Archer, a long-time associate and friend of Hunter Biden was accused by the SEC of running a $43 million Ponzi scheme. In the history of US fraud cases, Ponzi schemes are considered among the worst financial swindles. And here it happened to Hunter Biden’s a friend, business associate, and fellow board member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, Hunter Biden should have demanded Devon Archer’s immediate resignation from the Burisma board and requested a full outside counsel review of Devon Archer’s SEC complaint to learn of what, if any risk Burisma was exposed to while Devon Archer served on its board. We note that back in the States, Hunter and Devon’s other politically connected partner, Chris Heinz, the step-son of ex-US Secretary of State John Kerry, seemed to make the appropriate actions to disassociate himself with Devon Archer (and Hunter Biden) when this news broke. By mid-2015, through his step-son, then Secretary John Kerry and most likely VP Joe Biden would have also become aware of the reputational risks facing Heinz and Hunter Biden through their close relationship with Archer. So in short, Christopher Heinz considered this news to be so disconcerting that he disassociated himself from all business matters, likely taking a significant financial loss in the action. Hunter continued his financial and reputational relationship with Archer, a move that is consistent with his refusing to give up his million dollar board-ship at Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Seven -The Day Hunter Learned One of His Other “Independent” Fellow Board Member Was Connected to Paul Manafort and Manafort’s alleged Payoffs and Diversions of Funds Schemes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 24, 2018, another New York Times story &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/24/world/europe/manafort-gusenbauer-hapsburg-ukraine-indictment.html&quot;&gt;ran&lt;/a&gt; linking then President Donald Trump’s ex-campaign manager Paul Manafort to illegal lobbying work tied to Hunter Biden’s Burisma co-board member named Aleksander Kwasniewski. Manafort illegal lobbying had been done on behalf of Putin’s puppet Yanukovych, whose removal had sparked the war in Ukraine. Kwasniewski was well known to Hunter Biden. Kwasniewski was the ex-President of Poland and allegedly &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;played an instrumental role&lt;/a&gt; in recruiting Hunter to the Burisma board in 2014. We say allegedly because Hunter had already been providing expert advice to Burisma and Zlochevsky through his employment with the Boies law firm. Manafort was subsequently found guilty of the violations for his work with Kwasniewski. Manafort was sentenced to 7.9 years in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When exactly Hunter knew of the connection between Kwasniewski and Manafort is unclear. But he certainly knew after the NY Times article hit. And when that happened, Hunter would immediately understand the intersection of the Trump campaign, his role on Burisma’s board, his close links with the Polish ex-president, Manafort and the potential impact his role might have on his father’s potential participation in the 2020 campaign. Joe Biden announced his candidacy a year later, April 25, 2019. Here again, our team could find no reasonable alternative for Hunter Biden other than his immediate resignation from Burisma’s board. Yet, he did not resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Eight - The Day Hunter Agreed to Serve in April 2014 – Overlooking a Cauldron of Conflicts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Hunter Biden agreed to serve on the board of Burisma, he was counsel at Boies, Schiller Flexner, LLP, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@george.mesires/a-statement-on-behalf-of-hunter-biden-dated-october-13-2019-d80bc11087ab&quot;&gt;advising Burisma on board practices&lt;/a&gt;. This paid professional role demonstrates Hunter Biden presented himself as an expert in proper independent board member actions. As such, Hunter Biden should have been expected to do the following before joining the Burisma board:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review financial documents&lt;/strong&gt;, including: Audited financial statements for Burisma; Previous board minutes for the last two years; Reviewing Burisma’s equity holders (cap table); Reviewing Burisma’s corporate charter, tax practices, subsidiaries and partnerships, along with all legal documents related to those. If any of these documents were withheld from Hunter that would have been a major red-flag leading to his refusal to serve on the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask for other board member bios and conflicts&lt;/strong&gt;, including: The names, roles, compensation, external conflicts and all written or oral agreements between Burisma and any existing board members regarding any possible conflicts of interest. Any questionable board members should have been interviewed and their backgrounds reviewed thoroughly for conflicts. Hunter should have insisted on an understanding that he, and all board members, should recuse themselves from any conflicted votes they might take while serving on the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company Legal Review&lt;/strong&gt;: Hunter should have asked for, and received, a review of legal issues from Burisma’s outside counsel before joining the board. This review should have included a three-year review of any Ukrainian regulatory requests made to Burisma and any violations or accusations made against the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conduct a war footing review&lt;/strong&gt;:  Before agreeing to serve, Hunter should have also met with US government entities, including his own father, to discuss the importance of the role of Burisma to Ukraine’s war activities with Russia (Recall Russia invaded Ukraine in February 2014) and to uncover any known or suspected corruption at the company.   Reuters reported that the owner of Burisma, Zlochevsky, worked as a deputy secretary of Ukraine’s National Security and Defense Council from 2012-2014.  Russia invaded in February of 2014 and the pro-Russian Ukrainian political leadership, including then Ukraine President Yanukovich, were all deposed after street uprisings in 2014.  We note this because it raises serious questions about Zlochevsky’s alignment or opposition to US national security interests at the time Hunter joined the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear it was certainly an odd choice to ask Hunter Biden to join the Burisma board. He had no oil or gas expertise and no expertise in Ukraine. War had just broken out between Russia and Ukraine and his father was just appointed as the top US diplomat covering Ukraine. There were strong reasons NOT to join. Yet, his joining may not sound as crazy as it first seems. To explain why, we need to briefly discuss the relevancy of Hunter Biden serving on the Amtrak board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senator Joe Biden was known as “Senator Amtrak.” He rode Amtrak trains to and from work in DC and often shepherded Amtrak spending legislation through Congress. Amtrak was Hunter Biden’s only other for-profit board member role. Amtrak board members require approval by Congress and Hunter Biden &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/CHRG-109shrg65181/html/CHRG-109shrg65181.htm&quot;&gt;got that approval&lt;/a&gt; in 2006. In other words, it took an act of Congress to approve Hunter working on a board heavily tied to his father’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to be clear here: We do believe Hunter properly acted as an independent board member for Amtrak. We could find no financial or personal relationship conflicts for him on that board. As such, we believe he acted ethically and appropriately, other than possibly being incompetent in his management and oversight of Amtrak. His compensation at Amtrak was minimal. His relationship with his father, who was NOT on the Amtrak board, actually lent credence to the idea that Hunter would act as an independent watchdog over Amtrak because Hunter could go to his father to leverage benefits solely for Amtrak. Benefits to Amtrak are exactly what an independent board member would seek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to paraphrase Sen. Lloyd Benson’s quip: Burisma is no Amtrak.  None of the favorable Amtrak-board elements existed for Hunter when he served on the Burisma board. Hunter Biden was paid &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;excessively for his Burisma board role&lt;/a&gt;. He also seemed to be paid for consulting work which breaks a cardinal rule for independence. There was also the danger that any steps his father took which may have been admirable, but nonetheless aided Burisma directly or indirectly (e.g. the firing of Investigator Shokin discussed later), would be perceived as mostly working to benefit Burisma’s owner. The optics of benefiting Zlovchevsky would be damning. He was a known Ukrainian oligarch who had served in the pro-Russian regime that had just been overthrown in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these elements are negative, we do not automatically subscribe to the belief that Hunter’s relationship to his father necessarily precluded his seat on Burisma’s board. If Hunter was open and honest with his father, the US State Department and Burisma’s owner and other board members regarding his allegiances to US national security interests we can see potential benefits in his placement – but never at one million a year. Any potential benefits we might identify, however, seem to be precluded by Joe Biden’s insistence that he and his son never spoke about Hunter’s activities and relationship with Burisma and its pro-Russian owner and sympathetic board members. But there could have been benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a long-standing business practice to encourage executives to accept cross-board membership as a way to help one company learn from another company. For instance, Disney’s CEO Robert Iger sat on the board of Apple for seven years until it became clear that Apple would enter Disney’s space. With that as context and the Amtrak precedent, one can understand why the Obama administration may have viewed the Hunter Biden-Burisma board role as a positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular supplies of natural gas would be a requirement for fighting the war with Russia. The US would obviously like to have a “connected” insider at Burisma rather than be blind to Burisma’s operations. From this viewpoint, it makes logical sense that Hunter may have been a benefit to US interests at Burisma. Except, again, his compensation at Burisma was exceedingly high and his Burisma role was far different than Amtrak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, Boies Schiller Conflicts&lt;/strong&gt;: Before joining the board, Hunter should have also requested a review about accepting a board role at Burisma, by Boies Schiller’s internal compliance officer to identify any and all conflicts of interest that could arise from Hunter’s joining the Burisma board while serving as of counsel at Boies. This review may well have required Boies to sever its relationship with either or both Hunter Biden and Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe the potential conflicts and implications from Hunter Biden’s role at Burisma and Boies arising are so significant that Boies may have exposed itself to liability from claims arising from an independently operated Burisma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day Nine - The Day Hunter Actually Became a Board Member and Receiving His First Monthly $83,000 Check:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Solomon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://https://johnsolomonreports.com/the-ukraine-scandal-timeline-democrats-and-their-media-allies-dont-want-america-to-see/&quot;&gt;timeline&lt;/a&gt; shows that Boise was receiving payments for services while Hunter was on the Board, and that Hunter was receiving consulting fees from Burisma while still working for Boise before being announced as a board member.  This is a big no-no.  Hunter ought to have undertaken efforts to end any conflicted relationship with Boies, Schiller &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; taking the position. It was a violation of his sole duty of allegiance to Burisma for him to accept payments from, Boies, Schiller during his time on the Burisma board. Likewise, Hunter should have suggested a review of Burisma’s outside auditor, specifically requesting the company seek new auditor bids from well-established, international auditing firms like Deloite, Price-Waterhouse, EY or KPMG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We note that The New Yorker &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2019/07/08/will-hunter-biden-jeopardize-his-fathers-campaign&quot;&gt;ran a piece&lt;/a&gt; claiming Boies, Schiller produced a report within three months of Hunter joining the board of Burisma. The report claimed Boies was “unable to identify any information to date regarding any current government investigation into Zlochevsky or Burisma,” and that Burisma was “vulnerable to investigation for financial crimes” or “perceived abuse of power.” It would be crucial to understand when Hunter received this report, and what, if anything he did with it or what his part was in preparing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summing It All Up:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burisma is like a Charles Dickens story, written to expose the worst kinds of crony capitalism, government cronyism, war, corruption, adverse national security interests, political shenanigans and old fashioned human greed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to put into words how stunning it has been to review all of the adverse situations that Hunter Biden encountered as a member of the board at Burisma. Undoubtably his tenure will provide the Senate with many avenues for questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Russians have hacked Burisma’s records it is crucial that Hunter’s copies of the records are subpoenaed and any problematic transactions are dragged out into the light of day before they are leaked online in a misinformation campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps the most pressing question is why did Hunter choose to join and then remain on the Burisma board for so long? What obstacles did his exorbitant salary place in the way of advancing both Ukrainian and US national security interests?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It certainly is true, as we originally pointed out in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/hunter-biden-was-he-paid-appropriately-as-an-independent-director/&quot;&gt;first blog&lt;/a&gt;, that Hunter Biden was being paid a large amount of money for sitting on the Burisma board. But it seems implausible that the son of one of our current political luminaries, a past VP of the United States and the current top nominee for his party’s presidential candidacy, would participate in the sordid world of Burisma solely for financial gain. Unfortunately, we draw a blank on any other way to reasonably justify Hunter’s decision.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>brian_lawe</name></author><category term="Hunter Biden" /><category term="Corruption" /><summary type="html">UPDATE: AG Bondi’s Presentation Adds More Facts and Raises More Questions</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/oligarch.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/oligarch.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>