<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-01T17:04:11-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Kraft Heinz: Complaint Alleges Fundamental Corporate Governance Problems, Accounting Shenanigans, and Insider Trading</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kraft Heinz: Complaint Alleges Fundamental Corporate Governance Problems, Accounting Shenanigans, and Insider Trading" /><published>2020-05-29T13:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-29T13:55:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/">&lt;p&gt;Kraft Heinz (KHC) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000020/february2019form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a massive $15.4 billion impairment in February, 2019 to its goodwill and intangible assets.  This impairment was essentially an admission by management major components of the combined company were worth billions less than recorded on the balance sheet.  It was also an admission that 3G Capital (3G) and Warren Buffett’s much touted merger of Kraft and Heinz was a failure.   In the aftermath, Warren Buffett &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/buffett-criticizes-others-for-using-non-standard-accounting-metricsbut-he-does-too-2019-02-26&quot;&gt;admitted &lt;/a&gt;that he had overpaid for his 27% of combined company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHC’s impairment crushed share prices and has led to lawsuits, rapid executive bloodletting, an SEC investigation, and other deleterious events.  We &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about the KHC bus-crash last September and argued that KHC’s core problem was a loss of investor trust and a poor management ethos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a carefully researched complaint has brought new revelations that support our initial thesis.  The Complaint is built on the public record, as well as information the plaintiffs have been able to request as shareholders (like board and committee minutes, and some other non-public financial information). Initially filed on March 25th, much of the complaint had been redacted because of KHC’s request for confidentiality.  However, thanks to a challenge to the confidentiality filed by Francine Mckenna of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, KHC has narrowed their scope of requested redactions considerably.  The amended plaintiff’s derivative claim accusing 3G Capital of insider trading revolves around accusations of poor corporate governance and manipulation of accounting concerning goodwill testing and impairment for the benefit of 3G and its executives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KHC was formed in 2015 in a merger arranged by 3G and Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway.  3G is a Brazilian firm that became one of the largest and most successful private equity firms in the world after it used a series of acquisitions to create AB InBev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the acquisition of Tim Horton’s in 2014, 3G has partnered with Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway on a number of acquisitions.  In these joint ventures, Berkshire Hathaway has bankrolled much of the operation, while 3G has seized control and implemented its management philosophy of zero-based budgeting to cut costs and boost profit margins.  This partnership was generally considered successful, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/antoinegara/2015/07/06/kraft-heinz-will-prove-the-power-of-warren-buffetts-dealmaking-partnership-with-3g-capital/#4bc95ed11a4c&quot;&gt;reportedly &lt;/a&gt;making 3G Warren Buffett’s partner of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate Governance Disaster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mutual Pledges of Loyalty&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a company has serious accounting-related problems, usually it also has serious problems in its corporate governance structure.  After the merger that created Kraft Heinz, the company had 11 board members, 5 were appointed by the former board of Kraft, and the other six were evenly divided between representatives of 3G and Berkshire Hathaway.  This gave 3G and Berkshire Hathaway a controlling interest in Kraft Heinz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint draws attention to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000095015716001605/sc13g.htm&quot;&gt;13G&lt;/a&gt; disclosure made by 3G Capital and Berkshire Hathaway where they acknowledged a shareholder agreement to support each other’s nominees to the board and not take any actions to remove the other’s board members.  This effectively created a mutual pledge of loyalty between 3G Capital and Berkshire Hathaway as shareholders.  Even though this agreement does not violate the law, it created a conflict of interest that deprived the board of effective independent members and compromised the loyalty of these directors to the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agreements between shareholders are common, and the law permits them because shareholders do not (usually) owe any duty to each other, or the company, or the board.  However, in this case, the main shareholders (3G and Berkshire Hathaway) were entities whose partners also comprised more than half of the board of directors.  Additionally, and this is key, 3G’s partners were in control of the operations of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go over the basics of corporate governance. Every corporation has a board of directors that oversees the management of the company.  Each member of the board owes the corporate entity a fiduciary duty to the corporate entity to make decisions for the benefit of the shareholders, not for the benefit of management.  A fiduciary duty is a legal term of art defined as an affirmative duty to act on behalf of a person or corporation in good faith, with reasonable care and undivided loyalty.  The duty of loyalty requires board members put the interests of the corporation before all other interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mutual pledge of loyalty by Berkshire Hathaway and 3G undermines the loyalty that the partners are supposed to have toward KHC. It is hard to believe the partners at 3G and Berkshire Hathaway would effectively pledge mutual loyalty to each other as shareholders of KHC in one room, and then walk into another room and act as independent watchdogs monitoring 3G’s management of KHC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint also highlights issues with board independence and asserts that seven of the members had disabling connections to 3G Capital.  The Nasdaq stock exchange requires that the majority of directors on the board be independent so that it is not beholden to management and can act as effective watchdog.  Even if all these directors technically qualified as independent, their connections to 3G, which was in control of management, violated the spirit of Nasdaq rules concerning independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Core Accusation of Manipulation and Insider Trading in the Complaint&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core this case is about whether 3G Capital and its partners manipulated the accounting related to the company’s goodwill in a way that delayed disclosing bad news, and used that delay to sell their holdings at a price they knew was overvalued. This case revolves around the interpretation of ASC 350, an accounting rule that tells companies when and how to test their intangible assets like goodwill for impairment.  The FASB issued ASU 2017-04 simplifying the test for goodwill impairment and allowed companies to adopt it early.  KHC &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;adopted &lt;/a&gt;the revised rule on April 1, 2018, so we will focus on the new test for impairment, not the previous version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have criticized this rule &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.  Whenever companies have a merger or acquisition, the tangible and intangible assets are accounted for, and where the market price of the company exceeds the book value of the company’s assets the excess is recorded as “goodwill” on the balance sheet. To ensure that the amount recorded as goodwill really represents something substantive and defensible, companies are required to test their goodwill value every year as well on the occurrence of a triggering event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they evaluate the fair market value of their companies (often granularly reporting unit by reporting if there is more than one), and secondly, they compare this to the book value.  If the book value exceeds the fair value, then the company writes down, or impairs, the goodwill.  If there is not that much “cushion” between the fair value and the carrying value and the goodwill is at substantial risk for an impairment, then the company is required to disclose that risk to investors.  There is no bright line for the amount of “cushion” but in 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745918000015/form10-k2017.htm&quot;&gt;KHC &lt;/a&gt;used 10% as its threshold.  This threshold was not unusual at the time, as some of KHC’s peers, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1103982/000119312518037332/d466496d10k.htm&quot;&gt;Mondelez &lt;/a&gt;used the same standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASC 350 testing for an impairment to goodwill and other intangible assets is at the center of this case.  The question is when should it have occurred, and what should the results have been?  When KHC disclosed the massive impairment they made a case that the impairment was properly recorded in the 4th Quarter, since that is when it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000020/february2019form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;claims &lt;/a&gt;the circumstances arose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the fourth quarter of 2018, in connection with the preparation of our year-end financial statements, we assessed the changes in circumstances that occurred during the quarter to determine if it was more likely than not that the fair values of any reporting units or indefinite-lived intangible assets were below their carrying amounts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While there was no single determinative event, the consideration in totality of several factors that developed during the fourth quarter of 2018 led us to conclude that it was more likely than not that the fair values of certain reporting units and indefinite-lived intangible assets were below their carrying amounts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint argues that the 3G Capital partners managing KHC knew that the company was in trouble well before the 4th quarter.   We made this point ourselves in our original post, although we pointed to sales that were virtually flat in 2017 and 2018, (2017’s poor results were obscured by a $7 billion benefit from the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act signed by Trump). 
The Complaint looks at KHC’s repeated downward adjustments to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/ebitda.asp&quot;&gt;EBITDA &lt;/a&gt;projections to argue that KHC was aware of serious problems by the end of the second quarter.  EBITDA is a financial metric that measures earnings before taxes, interest expense, depreciation, or amortization costs are realized.  The Plaintiff put together a table of KHC’s revisions to EBITDA in 2018:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/KHC%20EBITDA.png&quot; alt=&quot;KHC EBITDA.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: City of Hollywood v. Kraft Heinz, Motion for Confidential Treatment, Exhibit A (18)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular attention is also given to the Audit Committee and Board meetings at the end of the second quarter.  In those meetings management revised EBITDA projections down by $248 million from earlier revisions for a total decline from the beginning of the year of $727 million.  They also disclosed that the SEC made a request that KHC not destroy accounting-related documents due to a pending investigation.  The management at KHC also told the Audit Committee that it had tested some of its international segments, and that two of them required an impairment because their book value exceeded the carrying value by $265 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, KHC’s management’s valuations of the U.S. reporting units (the same ones subject to a $15.4 billion impairment six months later) did not indicate that those units either required an impairment or that they were at significant risk of an impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Complaint alleges that KHC manipulated the valuations of these segments by using outdated and rosy estimates of future earnings, as well as discount rates on future cash flows that were not high enough.  The Complaint also states that KPMG, which assisted in the required annual testing of goodwill, was also using stale projections from earlier in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plaintiff asserts that an increase in the discount rates by a mere .5% would have resulted in KHC being required to issue a warning to investors that certain segments were at risk for impairment. As they stood, these segments were measured at just over the threshold for 10% that would have required a warning. This accusation of manipulation lies at the heart of their case, and if it were to go to trial both sides would provide experts to argue the reasonableness of their position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Valuations Often Speculative and Subjective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not have access to the underlying financial information that went into this valuation so we cannot make any determination if the allegations of manipulation in the Complaint are true.  But it is worth noting that these valuations are often subjective, unreliable, and easily manipulated.
In their 2018 2nd quarterly report KHC discussed how these valuations were subject to lots of estimates and guesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some of the more significant assumptions inherent&lt;/strong&gt; in estimating the fair values include the estimated future annual net cash flows for each reporting unit (including net sales, cost of products sold, SG&amp;amp;A, working capital, and capital expenditures), income tax rates, and a discount rate that appropriately reflects the risk inherent in each future cash flow stream … &lt;strong&gt;Estimating the fair value of individual reporting units requires us to make assumptions and estimates regarding our future plans&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as industry and economic conditions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the minutes of the Audit Committee Meeting on July 31st, 2018, Kraft Heinz auditor PwC (which had audited both Kraft and Heinz before the merger) warned that management had made some “close call judgements” about the valuations of certain reporting units.  Those warnings appear to be consistent with the PwC’s Critical Audit Matters (CAMs) disclosures made this year.  Auditors are required to disclose any portion of management’s financial reporting that the auditors found particularly challenging, subjective, or complex, and therefore potentially less reliable, as CAMs.  PwC highlighted KHC’s goodwill and intangible asset impairment testing as CAMs for FY 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the potential valuations KHC could have selected given the “play in the numbers,”  it is clear that KHC selected a valuation that allowed them to avoid making an impairment or even warning of a substantial risk of one occurring. &lt;strong&gt;There is no bright-line rule for telling investors when there is a substantial risk of impairment, but KHC changed its threshold after it recorded the massive impairment.  Prior to it, it would disclose only if the “cushion” was below 10%, but afterwards they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;doubled &lt;/a&gt;the “cushion” to 20%.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3G Capital Trims Stake in KHC Before Second Quarter Results Released&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board met on August 2nd.  The CEO, Hees, shared with the board the poor results up to that point, and lowered projections for the end of the year.  Just four days later, on August 6th, 3G trimmed its holdings from 29% to 22% of KHC’s ownership, selling $1.2 billion worth of stock.  Selling at $59.80 a share, 3G netted at least $653 million more than they would have if they sold after the impairment was announced in February 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/KHC%20Chart%20Complaint.png&quot; alt=&quot;KHC Chart Complaint.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3G’s sale was suspicious under the best of circumstances.&lt;/strong&gt;  The firm had orchestrated the merger creating KHC, it was in control of the operations of KHC, and it had three members sitting on the board (plus four other board members with substantial connections).  If 3G smelled something rotten in KHC, then something must have been rotten. Was this decision to sell based on insider information, or was it done properly based on the information disclosed in the 10-Q on August 3rd?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Kraft Heinz" /><category term="Goodwill" /><category term="Corporate Governance" /><category term="Litigaiton" /><summary type="html">Kraft Heinz (KHC) announced a massive $15.4 billion impairment in February, 2019 to its goodwill and intangible assets. This impairment was essentially an admission by management major components of the combined company were worth billions less than recorded on the balance sheet. It was also an admission that 3G Capital (3G) and Warren Buffett’s much touted merger of Kraft and Heinz was a failure. In the aftermath, Warren Buffett admitted that he had overpaid for his 27% of combined company. KHC’s impairment crushed share prices and has led to lawsuits, rapid executive bloodletting, an SEC investigation, and other deleterious events. We wrote about the KHC bus-crash last September and argued that KHC’s core problem was a loss of investor trust and a poor management ethos.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/conclusion-of-the-contract-3100578_640.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/conclusion-of-the-contract-3100578_640.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Research: Gray Swan Event Factor is Predictive of Stock Return</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Research: Gray Swan Event Factor is Predictive of Stock Return" /><published>2020-05-22T15:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T15:33:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/new-research-gray-swan-event-factor-is-predictive-of-stock-return/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joseph Burke PhD. and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, have produced two white papers for Watchdog Research that show that companies with higher Gray Swan Event Factors have a lower return on investment. This is because accounting-related risks are not properly priced into the market, potentially giving investors who use this valuable tool an edge over the broader market.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, we wrote a series of blog posts on Tesla. These posts highlighted some potential red flags, like turmoil at the CFO and director positions. They also criticized opaque disclosures and the SolarCity debacle. Naively, we believed this would likely hamper Tesla’s appeal to investors, but we were wrong. Really, really, wrong!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla growth from 11/6/19 to 5/20/20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the chart makes obvious, if you had sold your shares when our last blog was posted on November 6th, 2019, then you really missed out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a fact, buyers and sellers determine stock prices. A company’s stock price will not necessarily go down just because their business practices raise numerous red flags, or it suffers a gray swan event (like a financial restatement, securities suit, C-suite change, or material weakness disclosure).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, this begs the question, does doing due diligence on management, accounting issues, litigation and other similar red flags have any value for investors? Many investment firms don’t think so, they don’t spend any time tracking or weighing the effects of gray swan events because it’s too much work. How do we know this? We spent months calling and asking them. Instead most firms get their due diligence research from the investment brokers &lt;em&gt;selling the stocks&lt;/em&gt; and assume that the impact of these events is priced into the stock already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But our new white papers show that these events are not priced in, and that companies that are more likely to experience a gray swan event perform worse than their peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key Results from Gray Swan Event Factor Research Papers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Burke and Dr. Yarbrough produced two research reports to examine the predictive power of our Gray Swan Event Factor. In one report, they created a portfolio of the 42 companies that had a Gray Swan Event Factor exceeding 10% on January 1st, 2019 and compared the performance of that portfolio to the performance of the S&amp;amp;P 500 with a hypothetical $1,000 investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20%20image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20 image2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of 2019, the portfolio of companies with a large Gray Swan Event Factor lagged further and further behind the market as investors eventually priced in these adverse events. In fact, these companies suffered a loss while the S&amp;amp;P 500 gained well over $200 on its hypothetical investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note is that no large cap companies had a Gray Swan Event Factor over 10%. In their second white paper, Dr. Burke and Dr. Yarbrough made a far more detailed analysis. They put companies into three categories, small cap, mid cap, and large cap. They then divided companies into four tranches according to their Grey Swan Event Factor score: low risk as 0-2%, medium risk as 2-5%, and high risk as 5-10%, and extremely high risk as &amp;gt;10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping in mind that no large cap companies earned a score of over 10%, lets look at the results of a hypothetical $1,000 investment made in January 2019 by GSEF for large cap companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/WP%205.22.20%20image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;WP 5.22.20 image3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As can be seen here, the high-risk companies did significantly worse than their peers by the end of 2019, returning a loss during a year when the S&amp;amp;P 500 would have returned nearly $300 dollars on the investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research demonstrates that there is significant value in properly assessing and weighing accounting-related risks. Investors could potentially short high-risk stocks, or they could filter high-risk stocks out of their portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is of course a great deal more information in these white papers, if you would like to read them for yourself, then send us an email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retail Investors get free access to our Watchdog Reports. Institutional Investors and those interested in our Gray Swan Event Factor can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/pricing&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;, or call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send the author of this piece John Cheffers, our Director of Research and Associate General Counsel, an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;. For press inquiries or general questions about Watchdog Research, Inc., please contact our President, Brian Lawe at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:blawe@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;blawe@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Gray Swan Event Factor" /><category term="White Paper" /><summary type="html">Joseph Burke PhD. and Joseph Yarbrough PhD, have produced two white papers for Watchdog Research that show that companies with higher Gray Swan Event Factors have a lower return on investment. This is because accounting-related risks are not properly priced into the market, potentially giving investors who use this valuable tool an edge over the broader market.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/New%20Research.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/New%20Research.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Few, We Happy Few, We Late Filers" /><published>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-19T13:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/we-few-we-happy-few-late-filers/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;concerns &lt;/a&gt;about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the coronavirus, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;allowed&lt;/a&gt; public companies to delay releasing their annual or quarterly reports by up to 45 days. This order initially went into effect on March 4th, after large accelerated filers (companies with more than 700 million in public float) had already submitted their annual reports. However, large accelerated filers were due to report their first quarter results on May 11th, giving these big companies a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to see how many large accelerated filers were choosing to file their 10-Qs late. Our analysis showed that as of May 19th, &lt;em&gt;only 27 U.S. based companies&lt;/em&gt; had failed to file their 10-Qs due to disruptions from the coronavirus. We arrived at this number by eliminating foreign filers (who have different reporting obligations and dates) and by eliminating companies that failed to file because they were acquired or stated their failure to file was due to internal control problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is significant that so few companies decided to file late. We decided to look deeper to see what made these companies the exceptions. We were not surprised to see Party City (PRTY) on this list. In addition to having its stores closed, long term social distancing practices could destroy their prospects for recovery; its stock has taken such a beating that it was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1592058/000119312520107068/d901922dex991.htm&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt;. But for other companies it is less clear why they were unable to file. For example, Entercom Communications (ETM), which owns radio stations and other digital content, has only reported a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1067837/000119312520142278/d910419dex991.htm&quot;&gt;4% loss in net revenue&lt;/a&gt; for its first quarter, hardly cataclysmic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20Filers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late Filers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found that about 14 of these companies had offered their first quarter results to their investors in an earnings call and concurrent press release. We are not quite sure what to make of this. On one hand, it seems commendable that they are keeping investors appraised of what is going on, but if they can pull together an accurate earnings call, then why can’t they file their 10-Qs on time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Late%20filers%20press%20release.png&quot; alt=&quot;Late filers press release.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interesting Specific Examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circor International (CIR)&lt;/strong&gt;. This industrial valve manufacturer failed to timely file their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000023/circorformnt10-kv10.htm&quot;&gt;10-k&lt;/a&gt; this year because of internal control issues and a cybersecurity breach.  Now they are claiming that the coronavirus is the reason for their late 10-Q. They also filed two of their quarterly reports late in 2019. This company sells manufactures valves and other products for the industrial, aerospace and defense, and energy sectors. This is probably the clearest cut case of a company making a dubious assertion that its filing delay is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1091883/000109188320000070/cir8-k42920.htm&quot;&gt;due&lt;/a&gt; to the coronavirus as opposed to preexisting internal issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MFA Financial (MFA)&lt;/strong&gt;. This Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT) provided an interesting reason why they could not &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1055160/000105516020000018/mfa-8k05062020.htm&quot;&gt;timely&lt;/a&gt; file their quarterly report, “&lt;em&gt;Company’s management has had to devote significant time and attention to address [the impact of coronavirus], which have diverted management resources from completing tasks necessary to file the Company’s Quarterly Report…&lt;/em&gt;.” The other two REITs who failed to file in a timely manner cited the need for accounting staff to work at home as a reason for the delay. In contrast, it appears MFA’s management simply did not make time to file their 10-Q because the SEC has allowed them to put it on the backburner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credit Acceptance Corp (CACC).&lt;/strong&gt; MFA was not the only company to say its management was too busy to file a 10-Q. CACC had a near identical &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000042/cacc8k20200420.htm&quot;&gt;disclosure&lt;/a&gt;, claiming management was just too busy assessing the potential impact of the coronavirus. For context, CACC specializes in offering subprime loans on vehicles, which some people find &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2019/12/12/787337997/the-big-business-of-subprime-auto-loans&quot;&gt;unsavory&lt;/a&gt;. Even though almost every other company is trying to increase and preserve liquidity to survive the shutdowns, CACC is in the process of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/885550/000088555020000036/cacc8k20200305.htm&quot;&gt;repurchasing&lt;/a&gt; up to 3 million shares, reducing their cash position. We also can’t help but point out the irony of CACC filing their 10-Q late on the flimsiest of excuses while also issuing this statement on their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creditacceptance.com/coronavirus-response&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; “…Credit Acceptance is unable to support payment deferrals, and your payments will continue to be due on your scheduled monthly due date….” Considering the current predicament of many of the low-income recipients of these predatory loans, we don’t know how CACC shareholders can sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every investor wants to know if management is reliable and is dedicated to transparency. When management is opaque, it makes an investment far riskier. The best way to assess the trustworthiness of a management team is to see what kind of choices they make. The coronavirus has presented management teams with lots of choices, and we should watch them carefully as they make their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Late Filings" /><summary type="html">In this post we look at the large accelerated filers who have not filed their 10-Qs yet due to the coronavirus. These companies are outliers, with only 27 active filers delaying quarterly reports out of a population of nearly 600. We have already expressed concerns about the SEC allowing companies to be less transparent during such a critical time, and these concerns were not allayed by our research for this post. We will look at some broader trends and highlight a few egregious examples.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/We%20Few.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Can We Learn From Late Quarterly Filings During the Coronavirus?" /><published>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T09:25:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/what-can-we-learn-from-late-quarterly-filings-during-the-coronavirus/">&lt;p&gt;To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections.  An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epi.org/indicators/unemployment/&quot;&gt;skyrocketing &lt;/a&gt;unemployment.  To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2020-73&quot;&gt;permitted &lt;/a&gt;companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some companies this may simply be a welcome respite during a difficult time, but we are concerned that some companies may use this as an opportunity to prevent investors from seeing just how badly things are going until it is too late. However, the SEC has also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/statement-clayton-hinman&quot;&gt;encouraged &lt;/a&gt;companies to reveal how the shutdowns are effecting them and to speculate about how they will bounce back from the disaster. The SEC has assured companies concerned about incurring liability for these speculative statements that they will not be “second guessed by the SEC.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect the SEC has created two divergent paths for companies, some will file on time and may include extensive disclosures, but others may take the opportunity to delay reporting for as long as possible, perhaps in hope that by the time the 45 day period runs out, they will be able to report some good news (if they don’t declare bankruptcy first).  We believe that the strongest indicator for which path companies will take is their financial health before the lockdowns.  This would be consistent with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/coronavirus-uncertainties-contribute-to-going-concern-uncertainties/&quot;&gt;findings&lt;/a&gt; from Audit Analytics that the companies who initially received going concern warnings from auditors, where the coronavirus was named as a substantial factor, had already received going concern warnings before the pandemic even started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already expressed concern that some companies might use the coronavirus as a pretext to write off goodwill that was junk before the lockdowns, but we became concerned that some companies might abuse the delay allowance when we saw that Luckin Coffee was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920052907/a20-18059_16k.htm&quot;&gt;delaying &lt;/a&gt;its annual report due to the coronavirus.  The disclosure did not even refer to the massive fraud it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;unveiled &lt;/a&gt;less than a month earlier, or the firing of its CEO that was announced a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. large accelerated filers, companies with a public float of over $700 million, were required to file their annual statements before March 1st, so they were unable to take advantage of the ability to file late.  But smaller companies and foreign issuers with later deadlines were able to take advantage to file late if they wanted and many of them did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/LateFilings%20graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;LateFilings graph.png&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/impacts-of-covid-19-on-late-filings/&quot;&gt;Audit Analytics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most large accelerated filers are due to file their quarterly statements this week, which is giving the markets their first real insight as to the effects of the coronavirus on the world’s biggest businesses.  For example, the Kraft Heinz Company, (one of our favorite &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;subjects&lt;/a&gt;) has benefited from the shutdowns with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745920000061/khc-20200328.htm&quot;&gt;boost &lt;/a&gt;in revenue, as we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/&quot;&gt;predicted&lt;/a&gt;.  They also wrote off $226 million in goodwill, but that was apparently from consolidating their reporting into three segments instead of four and not from the coronavirus (how KHC’s figured that its new international segment is worth $226 million less than the sum of its component parts is anyone’s guess).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, Hertz filed its 10-Q in a timely fashion, but it did not have such good news to report.  The rental car industry, which has high fixed costs and relies primarily on people traveling to earn revenue has been hit hard by the shutdowns.  Hertz issued a going concern warning in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/47129/000165785320000049/hghthcq12020form10-q.htm&quot;&gt;10-Q&lt;/a&gt; that it cannot continue to make necessary payments without more revenue as it is burning through its cash. Currently, one of its biggest debts is in forbearance but that deal is set to end on May 22nd, and Hertz has been unable to offer any assurances that a deal will be struck.  The debtors could potentially seize their collateral, including vehicles in Hertz’s fleet, hurting the company’s ability to recover when the lockdowns end. It is good that Hertz is sharing this crucial information for investors at such a critical time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, some companies have opted to delay their filings.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920010302/fooh20200510_nt10q.htm&quot;&gt;One &lt;/a&gt;such company is HF Food Group (HFFG) which primarily serves Chinese takeout restaurants.  Although not a large accelerated filer, this company had the dubious distinction of earning a higher Gray Swan Event Factor score than any other publicly traded company as of April 8th.  Their high score was mostly attributable to two recent mergers, including one consummated in November 2019.  The company also disclosed in its 10-K, filed on March 16th, 2020, that it identified a material weakness in its internal controls.  HF was also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://hindenburgresearch.com/hf-foods/&quot;&gt;targeted&lt;/a&gt; by a short seller and had a securities &lt;a href=&quot;http://securities.stanford.edu/filings-case.html?id=107365&quot;&gt;lawsuit &lt;/a&gt;filed against it in March, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1680873/000143774920009194/ex_184193.htm&quot;&gt;replaced &lt;/a&gt;its CFO on May 4th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those curious about our Grey Swan Event Factor analysis, here is the analysis for HFFG:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Latefilings%20GSEF.png&quot; alt=&quot;Latefilings GSEF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is it that HFFG was able to put out a timely annual report but has needed to delay its quarterly report due to the coronavirus?  Is it possible that this delay has more to do with material weaknesses in the internal controls and turmoil at the executive level, rather than the coronavirus? To its credit (and unlike Luckin Coffee), HFFG has released some information indicating that it has been suffering an adverse impact from the shutdowns, with net sales declining from $209 million to $175.8 million year over year.  Still, investors will not really be able to assess the big picture until the quarterly results are published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this mess is over, the SEC ought to study the effect of its policy.  Did the delayed filings really help companies who were suffering from the coronavirus? Or were they mostly used by companies who would have filed late anyways?  And was any real benefit to companies worth the loss of crucial information for investors at such a critical time?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="SEC" /><category term="Late Filings" /><category term="GSEF" /><summary type="html">To protect the elderly and immunocompromised, federal and state officials have locked down society to flatten the rate of infections. An unfortunate byproduct of these shut-downs has been the destruction of large swaths of the economy and skyrocketing unemployment. To relieve some of the financial pressure these lockdowns have put on businesses, federal and state officials have tried different measures intended to aid businesses. For its part, the SEC has permitted companies affected by the coronavirus to delay their annual and quarterly statements that would normally be due from March 31st-July 1st.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/watchdog%20transparency_late%20filing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Featuring a New “SEC Oversight” Flag in our Watchdog Reports" /><published>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T16:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/featuring-a-new-sec-oversight-flag-in-our-watchdog-reports/">&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discovered that China had a better score than the U.S., which was shocking, but we also found out that the SEC and PCAOB had issued an extensive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;warning &lt;/a&gt;to investors in Chinese firms.  This warning told investors that financial reporting in China is not consistent, that there is no effective oversight of firms in China, and that there is no enforcement to catch rule-breakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure all the investors who rely on our reports receive this warning, we have added a new SEC Oversight flag to our report. Here is an example for Luckin Coffee:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SEC%20Oversight%20Flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;SEC Oversight Flag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on the flag for Luckin, it will bring you to this warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20Warning%20Flag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin Warning Flag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We aren’t picking on Chinese companies; we also issue a similar warning for countries that are known tax-havens.  If you looked closely at our summary table for country by county comparisons, you would have seen that countries classified as a tax-haven have an even lower Gray Swan Event Factor than China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/country%20comparison.ccp.taxhaven.png&quot; alt=&quot;country comparison.ccp.taxhaven.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our new flag highlights an uncomfortable fact.  Our assumptions about the overall health of an investment depends on accurate and reliable information, which is not always available. Investors need to be cautious about having companies in their portfolios that hail from countries that do not have rigorous standards promoting corporate transparency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="SEC" /><summary type="html">In our last post we compared the relative risks of investing in China and many other countries, including the U.S. We used our Gray Swan Event Factor, which weighs the impact of a host of different kinds of adverse events like restatements, disclosures of material weaknesses, turmoil at the C-suite level, mergers, etc.… We also track these events and flag them in our Watchdog Research reports (which are free to retail investors, reporters, and curious souls).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/sec%20oversight.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it Safer to Invest in China or the U.S.?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it Safer to Invest in China or the U.S.?" /><published>2020-05-06T16:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T16:01:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/is-it-safer-to-invest-in-china-or-the-u-dot-s/">&lt;p&gt;The China based coffee company Luckin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1767582/000110465920042189/a20-14831_1ex99d1.htm&quot;&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt; a massive fraud on April 2nd, and only five days later, another China based company TAL Education, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1499620/000110465920044459/tm2015354d1_ex99-1.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales.  A decade ago, a wave of Chinese companies were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/after-china-fraud-boom-nasdaq-steps-up-scrutiny-of-shady-listings-2016-06-20&quot;&gt;exposed &lt;/a&gt;as frauds, which damaged China’s reputation.  The confluence of Luckin’s fraud with news that the Chinese lied about coronavirus has damaged China’s reputation once again as many people have come to believe that investing in Chinese companies is too risky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to look at some data and see if there were any major variations between Chinese companies and Western companies.  We specialize in tracking and predicting gray swan events. These are events related to the financial reporting of companies that can seriously injure the value and integrity of a company.  Our Gray Swan Event Factor represents an aggregation of these events and their impact on the value of the stock.  A higher Gray Swan Event Factor indicates more risk of an event that could damage a company’s integrity and stock price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Gray Swan Event Factor is an aggregation of many kinds of events, including mergers, restatements, securities litigation, C-suite turnover etc…, it correlates well with the overall health of a company.  We wanted to know if China (or any other country for that matter) would score any differently than the U.S. or Europe. Our PHDs ran the numbers and here were our results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Luckin%20country%20comparison.png&quot; alt=&quot;Luckin country comparison.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can see Chinese companies have a significantly lower Gray Swan Event Factor than the United States, Europe, or Canada.  On its face, this result indicates that Chinese companies are healthier and less risky investments companies in Europe, Canada, or the U.S., which would be a stunning and counter-intuitive result.  But after looking deeper into the matter, we believe that it may mean the precise opposite and that Chinese companies are an even riskier investment than most people believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why Chinese companies have a lower GSEF is because they &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; fewer gray swan events than western countries, but that is probably because Chinese companies are subject to less scrutiny than Western companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the SEC and the PCAOB (a quasi-private entity that provides oversight for auditors) issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/news/public-statement/emerging-market-investments-disclosure-reporting&quot;&gt;joint statement&lt;/a&gt; on April 21st that specifically warned investors about investing in Chinese companies. They warn that, (1) the quality of financial statements are not consistent, (2) the quality of independent audits is uncertain because the PCAOB is unable to conduct inspections, (3) U.S. authorities cannot really enforce the rules against foreign persons and companies, and (4) there is essentially no legal recourse if you fall prey to fraud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our comparison of GSEF by country proves that fewer gray swan events are &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; in China than in the U.S., Canada, or the EU.  This paradoxically is strong evidence that we should take the SEC’s warning about Chinese companies seriously because they are not subject to the same level of scrutiny as Western companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Watchdog Reports are Free for Retail Investors&lt;/em&gt;, if you are a professional investor you can sign up or call our subscription manager about a group rate, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="GSEF" /><category term="PCAOB" /><category term="Comparison by Country" /><summary type="html">The China based coffee company Luckin disclosed a massive fraud on April 2nd, and only five days later, another China based company TAL Education, announced that one its employees had been arrested for fabricating sales. A decade ago, a wave of Chinese companies were exposed as frauds, which damaged China’s reputation. The confluence of Luckin’s fraud with news that the Chinese lied about coronavirus has damaged China’s reputation once again as many people have come to believe that investing in Chinese companies is too risky.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_it%20it%20safer%20to%20invest%20in%20china%20or%20us.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Watchdog_it%20it%20safer%20to%20invest%20in%20china%20or%20us.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">BorgWarner Wants to Dump Delphi. Will Delphi’s Resistance be Futile?</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BorgWarner Wants to Dump Delphi.  Will Delphi’s Resistance be Futile?" /><published>2020-04-08T09:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-08T09:31:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/">&lt;p&gt;With the coronavirus shutting down entire industries and raising the possibility of an extended recession, pending mergers are in peril, and mergers overall will become disfavored as companies lose their appetite for risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner and Delphi &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/908255/000120677420000239/bwa3712381-ex992.htm&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; an all-stock merger on January 28th, 2020.  The conventional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crainsdetroit.com/automotive/borgwarner-buy-delphi-stave-evs-impact&quot;&gt;wisdom &lt;/a&gt;take on this merger was that it was meant to protect to both engine auto part manufacturers from changes in the industry due to the rise of Tesla and electric vehicles.  It would appear the BorgWarner was looking to absorb Delphi so it could use the increase in volume to protect its position in the market, not because Delphi performance made it particularly desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner placed the value of Delphi at $3.3 billion, quite a premium for a company whose stock price had been on a consistent decline for years, and had a particularly rough year in 2019, with a anemic $141 million in operating income and total equity of only $450 million. Naturally, lawsuits were filed against both companies when the merger was announced, but lawsuits are always filed when a merger like this is announced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner chart.png&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Delphi’s value has been on a steady decline since the summer of 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why the Deal Fell Apart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 30th, Delphi announced that it was going to draw down its entire $500 million revolving credit so that it would have the cash on hand to endure the coronavirus and the accompanying government ordered shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, BorgWarner &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.borgwarner.com/newsroom/press-releases/2020/03/31/borgwarner-issues-statement-regarding-delphi-technologies-revolver-draw-down&quot;&gt;announced &lt;/a&gt;that Delphi was in material breach of their agreement and that Delphi had 30 days to cure the breach or the merger would be scrapped.  Delphi countered that BorgWarner had unreasonably withheld consent for the withdrawal.  Both arguments have merit, so the stage is set for a nasty legal fight if the deal is not salvaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BorgWarner’s ostensible reason for backing out is pretty cut and dry.  BorgWarner was not anticipating taking out new debt with its all stock deal. Delphi’s financial condition was anemic, but it was still in the black, and $500 million in potential new debt would be a hard to swallow (especially since it exceeds Delphi’s equity).  But considering that the coronavirus pandemic will be relatively short-lived—it is expected to peak in mid-April—it seems strange that BorgWarner would insist that Delphi risk running out of cash and going bankrupt to keep the deal alive, when it had access to credit that would probably see it safely through the storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead BorgWarner gave Delphi two bad options, damned if you do, and damned if you don’t.  Which leads us to believe that BorgWarner had soured on the whole idea of merging and used this credit draw down as a pretext to kill the deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mergers Traditionally a Sign of Optimism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers are widely considered a sign of optimism in the market, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/&quot;&gt;numbers &lt;/a&gt;bear that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20m&amp;amp;A%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner m&amp;amp;A chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart from the Institute of Mergers, Acquisitions and Alliances (IMAA) shows that mergers fell after the Dot-com bubble burst in 2001 and the housing bubble burst in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mergers fell during these prior periods of uncertainty because almost all the benefits from a merger are long term.  Our research shows that mergers generally produce negative returns for at least two years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/BorgWarner%20table-591d34.png&quot; alt=&quot;BorgWarner table-591d34.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What accounts for these terrible numbers?  Oftentimes the acquiring company must provide a large amount of cash to consummate the merger, which can leave the survivor strapped for cash or highly leveraged.  In addition, there are often personnel issues, as established norms at one or both companies are upended, and egos are bruised.  Additionally, the survivor usually inherits hidden accounting problems, and this can lead to write-offs, revisions, disclosure controls, or other gray swan events that damage the value and integrity of the company.  This is why a recent merger will significantly increase a company’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/#products&quot;&gt;gray swan event factor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positive outcomes depend on things like synergy, expanded volume, supply efficiency, and innovative technology or intellectual property (acquisitions to get new drugs in the pipeline is a feature of the pharmaceutical industry).  These benefits are generally medium to long-term benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the chart again you can see large cap companies suffer less than small or medium companies after a merger or acquisition, and that is likely due to the fact that big companies often acquire companies that are so much smaller than themselves, that it is completely irrelevant if the benefits of the merger materialize.  PayPal for example, acquired TIO networks, only to essentially &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;write off&lt;/a&gt; the entire value of the acquisition when they learned all the customer lists were compromised by a data breach, yet their share price did not suffer.  Medium and small firms simply don’t have the luxury of having a merger turn into a complete boondoggle without paying a price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We specialize in analyzing the risk of gray swan events, and the likely impact of those events on the future stock price.  A merger is one of the biggest red flags that the acquiring company can have for gray swan events.  Our research in this area affirms the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/040815/how-does-merger-affect-shareholders.asp&quot;&gt;conventional &lt;/a&gt;wisdom that generally depresses the stock price of an acquiring company because in the short-term, it is not a good bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the current market downturn, companies do not want to double down on potential losses by adding a merger to the mix.  Mergers in general are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/articles/m-a-deals-plunge-amid-the-coronavirus-crisis-51585681640&quot;&gt;down&lt;/a&gt;.  And it appears that companies have already inked mergers are looking through the fine print for a &lt;em&gt;material adverse effect&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/coronavirus-covid-19-and-material-adverse-effect-clause&quot;&gt;clause&lt;/a&gt; to bail them out.  BorgWarner was probably thrilled when Delphi asked permission to draw down on their revolving credit, since it gave them a far more clear-cut excuse to bail on the contract than on an untested legal justification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suitors become Adversaries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delphi’s stock &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/acquisition-in-peril%3A-delphi-technologies-shares-fall-on-borgwarner-notice-2020-03-31&quot;&gt;sank &lt;/a&gt;as a result of this news.  Generally, our gray swan event factor only penalizes the acquiring company once a merger is announced, not the acquiree.  That is because generally the company that survives the deal is taking all the risk.  But in an environment like this one, conventional wisdom has been turned on its head, and companies that have been counting on a merger are the ones in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is important in an economic downturn like this is a company’s fundamentals.  Delphi is a weak company: it had anemic financial statements when the market was strong, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autonews.com/article/20181005/OEM10/181009758/delphi-ceo-steps-down-after-10-months-on-the-job&quot;&gt;problems&lt;/a&gt; at the helm to boot. Now, instead of wooing Delphi with a premium offer, BorgWarner has rejected Delphi in hopes that Delphi stumbles into bankruptcy so that they can get what they want at rock bottom prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to a new market, where fundamental analysis matters and cash is king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact us:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="BorgWarner" /><category term="Mergers" /><category term="Acquisitions" /><category term="coronavirus" /><summary type="html">With the coronavirus shutting down entire industries and raising the possibility of an extended recession, pending mergers are in peril, and mergers overall will become disfavored as companies lose their appetite for risk.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/borger.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/borger.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Birds of A Feather: How to Tell a “Gray Swan” from a “Black Swan.”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Birds of A Feather: How to Tell a “Gray Swan” from a “Black Swan.”" /><published>2020-04-01T13:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-01T13:14:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/birds-of-a-feather-how-to-tell-a-gray-swan-from-a-black-swan-dot/">&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has shocked and stress tested institutions all over the world.  The emergence of the pandemic, and the global panic it has caused, is a true black swan event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gray swan event, on the other hand, is a failure in accounting or management that damages the integrity of a company and reduces its value.  At their core, these events result from a failure in transparency. These events may be infrequent, but the risk can often be anticipated and even quantified with proper due diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus has caused substantial disruption, as cash shortages cause default and bankruptcy, and it is inevitable that many companies will need to file legitimate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfo.com/accounting/2020/02/coronavirus-five-things-finance-needs-to-think-about-before-closing-the-books/&quot;&gt;impairments&lt;/a&gt;.   But we suspect some companies will try to use this crisis and see an opportunity to dump billions in worthless goodwill and other assets without it creating the usual bad press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kraft Heinz’s Swan Song&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like to ascribe their failures to black swan events because it absolves them of responsibility for their failures.  We have seen this before in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;look&lt;/a&gt; at Kraft Heinz (KHC).  They issued a surprise $15 billion &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745919000049/form10-k2018.htm&quot;&gt;impairment&lt;/a&gt;, which shocked the markets and sent the company into a tailspin.  KHC claimed that this impairment was due multiple factors in one bad quarter (as if it were their own personal black swan), but a closer look shows that it was more like they ran out of fingers to stick in a leaky dam. Collapse was inevitable and probably a long time coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The $15 billion that set off KHC’s awful year was not enough, and 2019 saw a steady drip of bad news.  When we wrote our original piece on KHC (linked above), they had already filed over $1.2 billion in new impairments for 2019, and we predicted more.  Indeed, shortly after our prediction, they issued another $676 million impairment for the final quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could KHC be in danger of further impairments, even if the economy had remained strong? Consider that intangible assets and goodwill still forms over $84 billion of the KHC’s $101 billion in assets.  And, the company continues to carry over $28 billion in long-term debt.  Today, the net assets of the company stand at $51 billion, but the market cap is $30 billion, that implies an overvaluation of $20 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if KHC writes off another huge chunk in assets and blame it on the coronavirus, will you believe them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We expect many companies will blame the “black swan” for accounting issues this quarter, but how can you be sure it was coronavirus and not due to problems in their accounting?  How do you tell a black swan disclosure from a gray swan one?  Do the hard homework or leave it to the experts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watchdogresearch.com/#products&quot;&gt;like us!&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how we think of sniffing-out a company’s own gray swan event from disclosures amid a black swan event.  We’ll use potential impairments to goodwill and other intangible assets as a case in point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;M&amp;amp;As and Balance Sheets Bloated with Goodwill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://imaa-institute.org/m-and-a-us-united-states/#m-and-a-history&quot;&gt;surge&lt;/a&gt; in M&amp;amp;As over the past decade has resulted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/04/business/shrinking-stock-market.html&quot;&gt;fewer&lt;/a&gt; registered companies and more goodwill on balance sheets. Whenever companies have a merger or acquisition, the tangible and intangible assets are accounted for, and amounts paid over the value of those assets is recorded as “goodwill” on the balance sheet.  We see trouble here.  Mergers have been relatively high, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/goodwill-and-intangible-asset-impairments-in-sp-500/&quot;&gt;fewer&lt;/a&gt; companies have been recording impairments to their goodwill recorded during the merger.  Either everyone is a genius when they close their M&amp;amp;A deal, or they are trying to avoid owning up to overstating assets.   We might see impairments happen aggressively during the coronavirus black swan event, but those simply might mask bad M&amp;amp;A deals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, another factor possibly inflating the amount of goodwill is FASB’s new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cpajournal.com/2018/09/26/the-new-guidance-for-goodwill-impairment/&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; for (ASU 17-04) which took effect for every public company this year—although some companies had already implemented it.  This accounting standard is simpler that the previous one, but it also allows companies to keep a balance sheet bloated with unknown liabilities.  Take &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/paypal-obscuring-problems-from-new-acquisitions/&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt;, which wrote off virtually all the assets it acquired from its acquisition of TIO Networks because of a data breach that made TIO’s assets worthless.  PayPal suspended operations at TIO and impaired the assets it gained in the acquisition—except for the $170 million in goodwill—that money is still &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/paypal-the-importance-of-intangible-asset-impairments/&quot;&gt;lingering&lt;/a&gt; around on the books.  How is it appropriate to buy a company, find out it’s essentially worthless and write down all its real assets, but then retain the goodwill anyways?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most logical reason that so much goodwill is being held on company books is because the market was on the longest bull run in history.  A healthy market increased the market value of companies, which prevented their book values from looking inflated, even when loaded up with goodwill or other intangible assets.  Now there is a pandemic. The market at one point lost a third of its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FASB &lt;a href=&quot;https://asc.fasb.org/imageRoot/79/49129379.pdf&quot;&gt;accounting standards&lt;/a&gt; require that companies test goodwill annually, but they also require a special test if an event triggers a concern that the market value of the company is lower than the book value.  Well … it seems like &lt;em&gt;every company&lt;/em&gt; is going to need a special test because of the pandemic.  We can expect many companies will write down goodwill and other assets after those tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Newest Data on CAMs Indicate Goodwill Accounting is Particularly Squishy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason we are focusing on goodwill is because management’s accounting for it is inherently squishy.  We know this because that is what the auditors tell us.  Auditors are now required to report on Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), accounting areas that are particularly difficult to verify because they rely on subjective judgement of the management team.  Even though the CAMs research is brand new, it has revealed that &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/an-updated-overview-of-cams/&quot;&gt;accounting &lt;/a&gt;for goodwill (and other intangible assets) raises more consternation than any other area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of our company Watchdog Research reports includes a CAM section, with links from viewing our report on our website to the SEC filing showing that CAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Damage Control is Often a Practice in Deception&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjective nature of evaluating goodwill means that the area is ripe for obfuscation and potential abuse.  Companies in decline may delay writing off goodwill and other intangible assets for as long as possible, to look strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already filled you in on KHC, but a disingenuous impairment by KHC might be easy to spot especially since panicked buying at grocery stores and the closure of dine-in restaurants should boost their sales.  Other companies may try equally disingenuous impairments, but they might not be so easy to spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Under Armour (UA) for example.  They declined to report any impairments to goodwill in their latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm&quot;&gt;annual report&lt;/a&gt;, even though their Latin American segment has been struggling. According to UA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fair value of each reporting unit substantially exceeded its carrying value, with the exception of our Latin America reporting unit. The fair value of the Latin America reporting unit exceeded its carrying value by 19%. Holding all other assumptions used in the fair value measurement of the Latin America reporting unit constant, a reduction in the growth rate of revenue by 2.25 percentage points or a reduction in the growth rate of net income by 3.5 percentage points would eliminate the headroom. No events occurred during the period ended December 31, 2019 that indicated it was more likely than not that goodwill was impaired.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here UA seems like they are trying to impress us with the precision of their measurements and soundness of their methods, but our experience tells us that these numbers are more showmanship than science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t persuaded by our opinion, then perhaps you should look at PWC’s critical audit matters in their independent report on UA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The principal considerations for our determination that performing procedures relating to the goodwill impairment assessment of the Latin America reporting unit is a critical audit matter are there was significant judgment by management when developing the fair value measurement of the reporting unit, &lt;strong&gt;which in turn led to a high degree of auditor judgment, effort, and subjectivity&lt;/strong&gt; in performing procedures and evaluating significant assumptions, including the Company’s long-term rate of growth and profitability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if UA writes down the goodwill associated with its Latin American unit, will it be due to coronavirus or because they should have done it already?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to subscribe to Watchdog Reports, call our subscription manager, at 239-240-9284.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, send our content manager John Cheffers an email at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="impairment" /><category term="goodwill" /><category term="Kraft Heinz" /><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="coronavirus" /><category term="transparency" /><category term="black swan event" /><category term="gray swan event" /><summary type="html">The coronavirus has shocked and stress tested institutions all over the world. The emergence of the pandemic, and the global panic it has caused, is a true black swan event.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/black-swan-122983_640.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/black-swan-122983_640.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armour III: Major CFO Change Was a Warning Sign of Litigation</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour III: Major CFO Change Was a Warning Sign of Litigation" /><published>2020-03-25T09:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T09:26:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-iii-major-cfo-change-a-warning-sign-of-litigation/">&lt;p&gt;CFOs play an outsized role in the financial health of a company.  When a CFO leaves abruptly or under bad circumstances, that event can have far reaching implications.  Lawrence “Chip” Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was as damaging as it was sudden and mysterious.  Within a year after being brought in from as an outsider, he had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691717000008/january312017form8-k.htm&quot;&gt;resigned&lt;/a&gt; for “personal reasons.”  In his wake there was litigation, an SEC investigation only recently brought to light, and—of course—more litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already taken a closer look at some of the finer details on this story; we looked at how UA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;spike &lt;/a&gt;in non-audit fees was a leading indicator of financial distress and litigation, and we &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/&quot;&gt;looked&lt;/a&gt; at how UA’s comment letters and recent CAM disclosure lend credence to a theory, supported by Francine Mckenna’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/what-might-be-driving-the-criminal&quot;&gt;reporting&lt;/a&gt;, that UA may be under investigation for “channel stuffing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears in UA’s case that the rounds of litigation and the SEC investigation were a direct result of Molloy’s departure.  Molloy’s departure in 2017, understood in its proper context, was a leading indicator of the financial troubles and litigation that UA would suffer in 2019—&lt;em&gt;over two years later&lt;/em&gt;.  Molloy’s story is interesting, but we wanted to look further into the numbers and see if this was a unique circumstance, or if it was emblematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with at every CFO change that was marked as a red flag in our reports from 2014-2018.  Then we looked at the likelihood that that CFO change would coincide with a Securities Class Action (SCA) lawsuit in the same year.  Here were our results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20Same%20Year.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO Same Year.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This result is not that surprising, since oftentimes the same issues that cause a CFO to resign abruptly are the same issues that provide fodder for a lawsuit. In a previous post we had analyzed ten years of data (which explains the small variation in the numbers) to determine the likelihood of a SCA lawsuit arising in the same year as a red-flag CFO change, and this is what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20same%20year%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO same year by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This result is also interesting, although not surprising.  The bigger companies have more public scrutiny, so if their CFO unexpectedly departs, a SCA is far more likely to occur; or if a SCA is filed upon learning of some problem, the CFO is more likely to be fired.  In the case of UA, litigation followed closely behind both the resignation of Molloy in 2017 and the departure of the founder Kevin Plank as CEO in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CFO Change as a Leading Indicator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear from the numbers that a red-flag CFO change in any given year corresponds with an increased risk of a SCA lawsuit during that year, especially for big companies.  But that warning is often too late, since litigation can come hot on the heels of an early CFO resignation.  We ran the same analysis to see if red-flag CFO changes have been a leading indicator of a more litigation in the following year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20followingyr.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO followingyr.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have a statistically significant correlation, demonstrating that a red-flag CFO change is a leading indicator of SCA litigation in the following year.  Moreover, the risk is greater for large cap companies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CFO%20followingyr%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CFO followingyr by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more interesting point is that the results of a similar study on red-flag CEOs did not yield the same results.  CEO departures did correlate with an increased risk of SCA litigation for the same year, &lt;em&gt;but not for the following year&lt;/em&gt;.  This makes sense, since an abrupt CFO change probably relates to the financial health of a company, but a CEO can be removed abruptly for all sorts of other reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UA’s Issues Emblematic of Other Red-Flag CFO Departures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers we have presented indicate that UA’s problems with SCA litigation following the resignation of Molloy is emblematic, and not a fluke or exception.  The UA example is helpful because it gives a window as to what is going on behind these numbers.  When something dramatic like a unexpected CFO departure occurs and the company offers little or no explanation as to what is going on, it is more likely that there is a major problem going on that will trap the company in expensive litigation.  The best course of action for these companies is to be fully transparent and address their issues head-on so that their problems do not linger for years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="CFO Change" /><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Leading Indicators" /><summary type="html">CFOs play an outsized role in the financial health of a company. When a CFO leaves abruptly or under bad circumstances, that event can have far reaching implications. Lawrence “Chip” Molloy’s departure from Under Armour was as damaging as it was sudden and mysterious. Within a year after being brought in from as an outsider, he had resigned for “personal reasons.” In his wake there was litigation, an SEC investigation only recently brought to light, and—of course—more litigation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/litigation_ua-3.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/litigation_ua-3.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Under Armour II: CAM Raises the Specter of “Channel Stuffing”</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Under Armour II: CAM Raises the Specter of “Channel Stuffing”" /><published>2020-03-17T14:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-17T14:48:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-part-ii-cam-raises-the-specter-of-channel-stuffing/">&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/under-armour-i-troubling-spike-in-non-audit-fees-went-ignored/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; piece on Under Armour (UA) we looked at how a dramatic increase in non-audit fees by PriceWaterhouseCoopers (PWC) was a sign of financial problems and a leading indicator of litigation. We also briefly examined UA’s SEC investigation, which was first reported on by the Wall Street Journal.  This investigation has remained somewhat mysterious and UA has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/under-armour-says-its-accounting-practices-have-been-entirely-appropriate-after-wsj-story-2019-11-15&quot;&gt;denied&lt;/a&gt; any wrongdoing.  Thanks to the newly required disclosures of Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), we are getting some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to news reports, the SEC began its investigation into UA in July of 2017.  The report indicated that there was shuffling sales from quarter to quarter to make the company look healthier.  An extensive report by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/retheauditors&quot;&gt;Francine Mckenna&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/about?utm_source=menu-dropdown&quot;&gt;“The Dig”&lt;/a&gt; raised the possibility that UA may have been “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/channelstuffing.asp&quot;&gt;channel stuffing&lt;/a&gt;” by sending retailers more product than they can sell (a practice more likely when a transaction is not truly at arms-length).  The speculation is that UA would push its inventory on retailers during a traditionally slower time of year, thereby boosting sales, and then record the loss of the returned merchandise in a more profitable time of year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear from the investigation whether or not there has been any “channel stuffing,” but there are a few pieces of evidence that suggest UA has not been completely transparent in their accounting and may have to pay a price at the end of this investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lawrence Molloy Left in January 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molloy, an outsider, was appointed the CFO in January 2016.  In January 2017, he announced his resignation for “personal reasons.”  The short tenure, the non-explanation, and the fact that the outsider Molloy was replaced with a long-time loyalist in David E. Bergman (joined in 2004) suggests that Molloy had a serious disagreement in how the company’s finances should be managed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Correspondence with the SEC in May 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting detail from the Wall Street Journal story is that this investigation by the SEC has been ongoing since July of 2017.  Right around that time, our report flagged the release of an SEC comment letter correspondence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we looked at the letter itself, we found that the SEC first &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.auditanalytics.com/app/view-comment-letter.php?cl_fkey=edgar/data/1336917/0000000000-17-015141.txt&quot;&gt;contacted&lt;/a&gt; UA on May 1st, 2017 with questions about the factors that had led to material increases in revenue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;we note you do not quantify the impacts of these factors or fully describe the specific new products lines or offerings that have caused the increase. Please expand your discussion to fully describe the specific reasons and factors contributing to the material changes in revenue…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC wanted to know how much revenue growth was due to new product lines. UA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000119312517187248/filename1.htm&quot;&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; on May 30th, amongst other things was that “… &lt;em&gt;the Company is not readily able to quantify the impact of unit sales growth of existing versus new product offerings.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It strikes us as odd that UA would not know how much revenue they were receiving from new product offerings.  The SEC might have found it strange as well.  This exchange shows that the SEC was taking a critical view of UA’s revenue recognition methods, and the SEC may not have been satisfied with UA’s explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plank, Founder and CEO, Stepped Aside in October 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not unusual for a founder of a company to step aside from the day-to-day operations of a company, but the timing here is suspicious.  Plank’s departure came a few weeks before the Wall Street Journal broke its story about the SEC investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PWC’s Critical Audit Matter Disclosure Highlights Issues with Sales Returns and Allowances&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting firms are now required to disclose CAMs as a part of their report on a company.  These disclosures require the firm to highlight areas in the accounting that required particularly challenging, complex, or subjective judgements by the auditor.  Our report indicates that UA already has a red flag CAM concerning its Reserve for Customer Returns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Under%20Armour%20CAM%20redflag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Under Armour CAM redflag.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we looked at the filing, PWC explained that the company had recorded $219 million in this reserve for returns and markdowns.  And they offered this by way of explanation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal considerations for our determination that performing procedures relating to the reserve for customer returns is a critical audit matter are there was significant judgment by management in estimating the customer returns reserve, which in turn led to a high degree of auditor judgment, effort, and subjectivity in performing procedures and evaluating the significant assumptions used in developing the estimate, including the amount of outstanding returns that have not yet been received by the Company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SEC has reportedly been investigating since July of 2017 and yet the increased scrutiny has not spurred UA to solve the issue, as PWC issued this CAM for 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that this “reserve” represents the value of merchandise that the company estimates will be returned to the company, effectively adjusting the final sales numbers.  To understand the magnitude of the issue we took a closer look at some of these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1336917/000133691720000010/ua-20191231.htm#ia59c9d23542e4b489dc58de46d9acdd9_25&quot;&gt;numbers&lt;/a&gt; (edited for formatting):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20sales%20returns%20numbers.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA sales returns numbers.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sales returns and allowances and allowance for doubtful accounts amounts are significantly less this year than in years past.  This could indicate that UA has been changing how it interacts with its retailers, pushing product less aggressively so that the retailers are less likely to overbuy and then return product.  Additionally, the number has fluctuated greatly over the past three years, from which we can infer that PWC would probably have flagged the sales returns consistently if it had been required to relay CAMs in years past.  Regardless, the fact that PWC highlighted these numbers as being particularly subjective is not comforting for investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Typical was UA’s CAM?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close examination of UA’s financial statements reveals how invaluable new CAMs disclosures are in understanding the story behind the numbers, but the CAMs have more to offer.  They can also help us draw comparisons with other companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.auditanalytics.com/an-updated-overview-of-cams/&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; shows that CAMs relating to revenue (including sales returns and allowances) account for about 15% of all CAMS issued so far.  Our analysts wanted to see how typical it is for a company to have a CAM that falls under the category of Sales Returns and Allowances.  Currently, more than 1900 companies have filed CAMs.  We narrowed by only looking at CAMs related to Sales Returns and Allowances.  This narrowed our pool to only 74 companies.  Here are the results broken down by industry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/UA%20CAMS%20by%20industry.png&quot; alt=&quot;UA CAMS by industry.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No other apparel companies have had CAMs concerning the sales and returns allowances.  However we discovered several limitations in this sort of analysis due to the CAMs disclosure requirement &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/Standards/Auditing/Pages/AS3101.aspx&quot;&gt;incremental&lt;/a&gt; roll-out.  Currently, only large accelerated filers are required to file CAMs for 2019, and not every company has filed yet.  There are 11 apparel manufacturers who will be required to file CAMs this year, but so far only 3 have done so.  It is too early to draw any real conclusions, but we are excited about how this new disclosure will open the door to new and better insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Last Word on “Channel Stuffing”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Channel Stuffing” is considered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fbi.gov/news/stories/executives-sentenced-in-750-million-fraud-scheme&quot;&gt;serious crime&lt;/a&gt;, and executives have received lengthy prison sentences for wire or mail fraud because of it.  But to convict, the DOJ would need to prove the requisite intent (i.e. a purpose to defraud), and the fact that the investigation has been going on for almost three years indicates that the DOJ does not have a smoking gun.  UA may be entirely innocent of “channel stuffing.”   We won’t really know until the DOJ or UA brings all the details to light.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Under Armour" /><category term="Channel Stuffing" /><category term="Red Flag" /><category term="SEC Comment Letters" /><category term="Critical Audit Matters" /><summary type="html">In our first piece on Under Armour (UA) we looked at how a dramatic increase in non-audit fees by PriceWaterhouseCoopers (PWC) was a sign of financial problems and a leading indicator of litigation. We also briefly examined UA’s SEC investigation, which was first reported on by the Wall Street Journal. This investigation has remained somewhat mysterious and UA has denied any wrongdoing. Thanks to the newly required disclosures of Critical Audit Matters (CAMs), we are getting some clarity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/clothes_stack.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/clothes_stack.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>