<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-12T10:03:29-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Watchdog Transparency Blog</title><subtitle>Watchdog Transparency is a publication based on reports created by Watchdog Research, Inc.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Trial: Personal Experience versus Hard Data</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/on-trial-personal-experience-versus-hard-data/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Trial: Personal Experience versus Hard Data" /><published>2021-04-12T09:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T09:26:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/on-trial-personal-experience-versus-hard-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/on-trial-personal-experience-versus-hard-data/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a big difference between knowing that similar circumstances have rarely occurred and believing similar circumstances have never occurred.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks, a federal lawsuit has offered a rare glimpse inside the world of the Big 4 accounting firms. In Botta v. PricewaterhouseCoopers, LLP, Mauro Botta, a former senior audit manager at PwC, is suing the firm for wrongful termination and retaliation as a whistleblower. He alleges he was fired because he submitted a whistleblower complaint to the SEC. Botta has argued that PwC unlawfully retaliated against him for submitting a “reasonable” complaint. PwC has argued that Botta’s complaint to the SEC was the actual retaliation, and that he was properly fired for misconduct unrelated to his whistleblower complaint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a complex case and has lots of interesting facets. If you want to really want to get a feel for the personal drama, the office politics, and the thorny issues at play, then we highly recommend you read Francine Mckenna’s reporting on the trial at &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/&quot;&gt;The Dig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Her writing is well worth the price of admission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This case, however, is about more than personal drama. The case raises questions about auditor independence, a core safeguard of our capital markets. In live testimony via Zoom we heard about how PwC and its employees navigated the tension that exists between serving the client and protecting auditor independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francine suggested we do some research on a specific accounting issue that came up during some expert testimony offered by PwC. PwC’s expert testimony concerned the reasonableness of the complaint that Botta filed with the SEC, a key issue in the case. But before we go any further, some context is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botta was a senior manager at PwC (the position right below a partner), working on an audit of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/edgar/browse/?CIK=1175609&amp;amp;owner=exclude&quot;&gt;Cavium&lt;/a&gt;, a publicly traded company which had approximately $400 million in assets. Botta filed a memo with PwC in 2014 arguing that Cavium ought to declare a material weakness in its internal controls because it purportedly had 2 significant control deficiencies and 11 lesser control deficiencies. (fn.1) (1336) None of these issues by themselves would constitute a material weakness, but Botta argued that in their totality, these deficiencies demonstrated a lack of competency by the financial department that ought to constitute a material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A material weakness is a deficiency, or combination of deficiencies, in the internal controls of a company that creates a reasonable possibility that a material misstatement of the financial statements will not be prevented or detected. A material weakness can exist even when the financial statements are not misstated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When deciding whether to issue a material weakness, audit firms consider the guidelines set forth in the PCAOB’s Auditing Standard No. 5. Those guidelines specify that some of the more prominent indicators of a material weakness include (fn.2):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fraud on the part of senior management, regardless of the severity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Restatements to correct material misstatements.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A material misstatement from the current period identified by the auditor that would not have otherwise been identified by management.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ineffective oversight by the Audit Committee&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an exhaustive list. The PCAOB’s guidelines also include a catchall provision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly, this catchall provision specifies that any deficiency, or combination of deficiencies, that would cause prudent officials to conclude that they do not have a reasonable assurance that the company’s financial transactions are recorded properly may be classified as a material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botta’s memo to PwC proposed that a material weakness for Cavium be filed based on a lack of competency by the financial department concerning income taxes, treasury, and technical accounting. (1358-1359). Since Cavium did not have any fraud, material misstatements, or lack of oversight by the Audit Committee, this material weakness would have fallen under the catchall provision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botta’s memo was taken seriously by PwC and an assessment was performed by its National Office. The National Office disagreed with Botta’s assessment, and neither Cavium nor PwC issued a material weakness in 2014. Botta then filed a whistleblower report with the SEC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Assessment by PwC’s Expert&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, PwC hired an expert witness to assess Botta’s report, and the report by PwC. PwC’s expert witness spent twelve years in the SEC’s Enforcement Division and held the position of deputy chief accountant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to PwC’s expert witness, it is occasionally appropriate to issue a material weakness for a lack of competency, but that lack of competency is usually accompanied by red flags. (1360-61). The expert witness specified that these red flags were restatements, out of period adjustments, prior material weaknesses, previously identified deficiencies that remain unfixed, and a lack of experience in GAAP by the financial department. (1360-1361).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This expert witness also stated PwC’s assessment of Cavium demonstrated that the company’s financials did not exhibit any of the red flags which he had previously mentioned. Cavium did not have a restatement or out-of-period adjustment. (1362) Nor did it have a prior material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to PwC’s assessment, even though PwC had identified many control deficiencies in 2012 and 2013, Cavium was apparently able to remediate these deficiencies by the end of the year, so that all the control deficiencies Botta identified in 2014 were new deficiencies. (1368)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expert witness also reviewed PwC’s assessment of the expertise of Cavium’s financial department. This assessment focused on the prior experience of the staff and their tenure. According to the PwC expert’s testimony, Cavium’s accounting staff was comprised of numerous Big 4 alumni with significant experience in the industry. When PwC’s expert witness was asked if he had ever seen a material weakness issued based on incompetence when a staff had similar experience, his response was a simple “no.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PwC’s expert witness concluded that the National Office at PwC came to a reasonable conclusion in deciding not to issue a material weakness for Cavium. Finally, the expert was asked the following question (and it is important because it speaks to the reasonableness of Botta’s whistleblower complaint to the SEC):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Q. &lt;em&gt;Sir, in your entire career, including your 12 years at the SEC, have you ever seen a material weakness due to incompetency exist in these circumstances?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A. &lt;em&gt;Not in these circumstances.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PwC’s expert has excellent credentials and a wealth of valuable and relevant experience. Yet even his experience is necessarily limited by the cases that crossed his desk, the clients he served, and the topics discussed by his friends and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were curious, and so was Francine, whether we could find a material weakness filed under comparable circumstances by a careful analysis of the publicly available data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walking Through Our Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We performed our analysis using the Audit Analytics database, which includes every material weakness since 2004. The Audit Analytics database assigns each material weakness tags categorizing the potential issues at play in the material weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audit Analytics is used by over 300 universities, many different regulators, and prominent accounting firms. It’s the gold standard for accounting related data on public companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audit Analytics tags disclosures about issues that relate to competency for material weaknesses in two ways. One tag is used for a lack of competency by the accounting department, and another for a lack of competency by senior management. These two tags nearly always coincide because hiring an incompetent accounting department is a red flag that the senior management team is incompetent too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2004 to 2020, publicly traded companies listed on the U.S. exchanges disclosed ineffective internal controls over financial reporting 4,444 times. Of those, 2,443 were tagged for incompetency in the accounting department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Material%20Weakness%20Competency%20Chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Material Weakness Competency Chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, small cap companies are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency/&quot;&gt;more than 5X&lt;/a&gt; as likely as large cap companies to declare a material weakness. Since Cavium was a large company, any analysis that includes small cap companies would be potentially misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a more comparable set of companies, we narrowed our search to competence issues at large cap companies. Additionally, we only looked at companies which had hired a Big 4 audit firm. We thought that these large companies, with plenty of resources and the expertise of a Big 4 firm at their disposal, ought to have accounting staff with comparable experience and expertise to Cavium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of this search were far narrower, with only 98 material weaknesses that fit these criteria. These material weaknesses were filed by 69 unique companies, as some companies filed more than one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PwC’s expert described a number of red flags that were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; in Cavium’s case. These included fraud, material misstatements or restatements, out of period adjustments, and prior material weaknesses. We combed through the 69 different companies and eliminated the cases where these red flags identified by PwC’s expert were present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This analysis has allowed us to conclude that from 2004 to 2020, 22 companies filed a material weakness under comparable circumstances to Cavium.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/MW%20over%20time%20chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;MW over time chart.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One factor that PwC’s expert discussed that we could not examine was unfixed deficiencies. That is part of an internal assessment done by a company’s auditing firm that never becomes public. So, it is possible that some of the 22 comparable material weaknesses that we identified were due to unfixed control deficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how rare these events are, we are not surprised that PwC’s expert was not personally familiar with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would also note that declaring a material weakness is a big step for an independent auditor. There is no public information that allows us to measure the severity of the control deficiencies that lead to these 22 material weaknesses. They may have been comparable to Cavium’s deficiencies, or they may have been for more severe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of his testimony when PwC’s expert witness was asked if it is ever appropriate to file a material weakness for incompetence, he stated “It’s possible but only in very extreme circumstances.” (1360) Our analysis tends to confirm that assessment (so long as you exclude cases where the red flags for incompetency are also present).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our analysis shows that material weaknesses &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; filed in similar circumstances to Cavium, but it is rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, one of PwC’s clients, Allergan plc, who had assets of almost $150 billion, disclosed a material weakness in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1578845/000156459017002433/0001564590-17-002433-index.htm&quot;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt; due to a lack of competency concerning the tax implications of certain transactions between their subsidiaries. This material weakness did not result in any misstatements, but the lack of competency concerning tax issues created a substantial risk of misstatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Deeper into The Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting fact was that out of these 22 companies, only 8 were headquartered in US. This result stands in contrast with the fact that historically fewer than 20% of U.S. listed companies are located outside of the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Results%20by%20country.png&quot; alt=&quot;Results by country.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disparity is possibly due to differences in culture between foreign affiliates of the Big 4 and the U.S. firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also categorized the result by global audit firm. Here we lumped the US and foreign affiliates of each firm together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Results%20by%20auditor.png&quot; alt=&quot;Results by auditor.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also looked at the &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; issue raised in the material weakness disclosure (oftentimes the material weaknesses touched on more than one issue). The two primary issues that companies had struggles with were 1) the interplay of IT systems and the financial controls, and 2) complex tax issues that their accounting staff struggled to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Primary%20Issue.png&quot; alt=&quot;Primary Issue.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal experience, even the personal experience of a well-qualified expert, has its limitations. A careful analysis of hard data will usually be more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that our analysis does not comment on whether Botta’s whistleblower claim was reasonable, from a legal perspective, in this case. However, there is a big difference between knowing that companies in similar circumstances to Cavium &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;rarely&lt;/em&gt; issued material weaknesses as opposed to believing that companies in similar circumstances &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; issued a material weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1) Francine provided us with a transcript of PwC’s expert witness’s testimony on 3/30/2021. All quotes and inferences concerning the trial are taken from the transcript.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2) These indicators are derived from the PCAOB’s page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcaobus.org/oversight/standards/archived-standards/pre-reorganized-auditing-standards-interpretations/details/Auditing_Standard_5&quot;&gt;Accounting Standard No. 5&lt;/a&gt;. They are edited for brevity and clarity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Independent Research" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="Litigation" /><category term="Data Analysis" /><category term="Independent Research" /><summary type="html">There is a big difference between knowing that similar circumstances have rarely occurred and believing similar circumstances have never occurred.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Courtroom.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Courtroom.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Small Companies 5X More Likely Than Large Companies to Report a Control Deficiency</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Small Companies 5X More Likely Than Large Companies to Report a Control Deficiency" /><published>2021-03-29T10:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-03-29T10:17:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/small-companies-5x-more-likely-than-large-companies-to-report-control-deficiency/">&lt;p&gt;After the Enron scandal, Congress passed Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) to improve the quality of financial reporting and deter fraud. One core reform was to require every company’s management team to annually assess and report on the effectiveness of the company’s disclosure controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is derived from a report generated by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD, titled “Frequency and Impact of Control Deficiencies: 2020.” The full report is currently available at no cost, just email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com and ask for the report.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclosure controls are the policies and procedures that ensure a company can provide timely, accurate, and reliable financial information to the SEC and the market. When a company has disclosure control problems, it does not &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; mean that their financial information is not reliable, but it does mean that the company &lt;em&gt;cannot be sure&lt;/em&gt; that the information is reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, the law also required the independent auditor to independently assess and attest to the quality of the internal controls. However, this attestation requirement, known as SOX 404(b), has been narrowed in scope &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/slacker-standards-sec-exempts-even-more-companies-from-404-b/&quot;&gt;repeatedly&lt;/a&gt; over the last two decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, the SOX 404(a) requirement for management to annually report on the effectiveness of internal controls has remained intact. Additionally, the SOX 302 requirement for management to report quarterly on any disclosure control issues has also remained in effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management always has a strong interest in minimizing negative events, and we will touch on how that effects how they report on control issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control Deficiencies Continue Long-Term Trend&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control deficiencies have been increasing at a steady rate over the last ten years. In 2019 a record number of control deficiencies were disclosed, but in 2020 there was a return to the mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Control%20Deficiencies.png&quot; alt=&quot;Control Deficiencies.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control Deficiencies Are Primarily Reported by Small Companies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are over 5,000 companies listed on U.S. exchanges. Although larger companies receive the majority of investor and media attention, there are far more small companies than large companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often important to segment the market by size because companies of different sizes have different regulatory and reporting requirements, so they are often operating in different environments. For example, smaller reporting companies with less than $75 million in public float don’t have to comply with 404(b), neither to Emerging Growth Companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These small companies still need to assess their internal controls, but that assessment is not independently verified by their auditor. This lack of verification can result in companies “phoning-in” their assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to “phone-in” the assessment is to provide an adverse opinion. This is safer than claiming that internal controls are good, and risk being humiliated if they are eventually forced to file a restatement. And since so many other small companies are filing adverse opinions, the announcement of an adverse opinion on a small company has relatively little impact. After all, many people expect small companies to lack the resources necessary to implement rigorous controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adverse opinions by management are far more meaningful for large companies. Since the independent auditors at large companies provide their own independent assessment of internal controls, management is strongly incentivized to implement and maintain rigorous controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The different incentives at play create a remarkably different results when we segment the company population by size. Small companies were over 5 times more likely to report a control deficiency than large companies. This is consistent with our research demonstrating that small companies are far more likely to report a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-restatements-the-bigger-they-are-dot-dot-dot/&quot;&gt;restatement &lt;/a&gt;than large companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Deficiencies%20by%20Market%20Cap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Deficiencies by Market Cap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller companies are more likely to report control deficiencies than larger companies. This is probably due to the differences in stakes. With considerably less attention and lower expectations, it is easy for management at smaller companies to save time and money by truncating their assessment of internal controls by giving themselves a failing grade. And since so many of their peers give themselves this same failing grade, there is little pressure to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always expect companies to take the easiest road. Since SOX has created a two-tier system, with one set of rules for small companies and another set of rules for large companies, we are not surprised to see wildly disparate results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Internal Controls" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Internal Controls" /><summary type="html">After the Enron scandal, Congress passed Sarbanes-Oxley (SOX) to improve the quality of financial reporting and deter fraud. One core reform was to require every company’s management team to annually assess and report on the effectiveness of the company’s disclosure controls.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Green%20Fields.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Green%20Fields.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Foreign Restatements and Securities Class Action Suits</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/foreign-restatements-and-securities-class-action-suits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Foreign Restatements and Securities Class Action Suits" /><published>2021-03-18T11:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-03-18T11:51:00-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/foreign-restatements-and-securities-class-action-suits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/foreign-restatements-and-securities-class-action-suits/">&lt;p&gt;Foreign companies have played an increasingly relevant role on the NYSE and NASDAQ over the last decade and currently comprise over 20% of those exchanges. We recently completed a report on the particular risks by foreign listings entitled Foreign Restatements and Securities Class Actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a summary of our report on Foreign Restatements and Securities Class Actions authored by Joseph Burke and John Cheffers. If you would like access to the complete report at no cost, please email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Securities class action suits against Chinese companies rose significantly in 2020, despite an overall decline in securities class action suits. We have &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-short-reports-fuel-lawsuits-against-chinese-companies/&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt; observed that nearly half of the suits filed against Chinese companies were the result of an activist short report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the proliferation of these short reports and resulting securities class action suits is due to &lt;em&gt;The Luckin Effect&lt;/em&gt;. In January 2020, Muddy Waters published an anonymous short report accusing the Luckin Coffee of fraud. Shortly afterwards, in April of 2020, Luckin admitted to an egregious fraud. Their stock lost over 90% of its value, most of it in a single day, with the result that the stock was later delisted and eventually declared bankruptcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckin Coffee was not Muddy Water’s first successful take down of a Chinese company, but the fraud revealed at Luckin was so brazen, and at such a large and well-known company, that it shook the confidence of the entire market. &lt;em&gt;The Luckin Effect&lt;/em&gt; occurs when the problems at a single company reveal systemic problems that are so pervasive in a sector of the market that it undermines the entire sector. Our research into foreign restatements (included in this report) indicates that investors already had less confidence in U.S. listed foreign companies than in U.S. companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an enormous fraud seems only to have been possible with serious systemic weaknesses in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;audit quality&lt;/a&gt;,  regulatory integrity, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing/&quot;&gt;corporate governance&lt;/a&gt;.  The systemic vulnerability to fraud in China has become so glaring that Congress has seen fit to pass the “&lt;a href=&quot;http://https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/senate-bill/945&quot;&gt;Holding Foreign Companies Accountable Act&lt;/a&gt;.”  This law could result in the delisting of every Chinese company from U.S. exchanges if the PCAOB is not permitted to inspect Chinese audit firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Luckin Effect&lt;/em&gt; has reduced investors’ confidence in the financial reporting of U.S. listed Chinese companies, making them a perfect target for activist short sellers. It is difficult to say just how long this effect will last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Foreign Listings Have Increased to an All-Time High&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last ten years, the overall number of companies listed on U.S. Exchanges has held relatively steady, but the portion of foreign companies has increased significantly.  In fact, foreign listings are at an all-time high. Foreign listings have increased rapidly, from 962 in 2017 to 1,064 in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This increase is primarily fueled by an increase in Chinese company listings. They account for 75% of new foreign listings between 2017 and 2020.  The Chinese listings on U.S. exchanges increased from 181 in 2017 to 260 in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increasing Litigation Risk for Foreign Listings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As foreign companies have listed in greater numbers, they have been named in an increasing number of securities class action suits. Foreign defendants in SCAs increased from a low of 29 in 2014 to a high of 67 in 2020. This holds true for Chinese companies as well; Chinese defendants in securities class actions increased from 5 in 2016 to 24 in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the litigation rate for Chinese companies has been increasing steadily since 2016. Here is a chart comparing the probability of being named in a securities class action suit for U.S. companies, foreign companies, and Chinese companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Probability%20for%20SCA%20Chinese.%20Foriegn.%20Overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Probability for SCA Chinese. Foriegn. Overall.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed in the introduction, the divergence of the rates of litigation for China from the overall trends is partly due to a proliferation of short reports against Chinese companies. After Luckin Coffee’s fraud was revealed in April 2020, more of the investing public became aware of systemic weaknesses in Chinese corporate governance, accounting quality, and regulatory enforcement. These weaknesses make Chinese companies more appetizing targets for short sellers and resulting securities class action litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Securities Class Actions Have a Larger Impact on Smaller Companies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We measure the impact of securities class actions and foreign restatements by looking at abnormal returns.  Abnormal returns are the average returns to the stock in the 60-day window around the event less average returns to the S&amp;amp;P 500 over the same period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Average abnormal returns to securities class action are -7.6% across all companies. Securities class actions tend to have a larger impact on smaller companies and a smaller impact on larger companies. Average abnormal returns are -2.4% for large cap companies, -5.2% for mid cap companies, and -12.4% for large cap companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20impact%20by%20size-1cd0ee.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA impact by size-1cd0ee.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Financial Restatements Have the Largest Impact on Chinese and Foreign Listings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of foreign financial restatements differs significantly those for U.S. companies. Average abnormal returns to financial restatements are -7.5% for foreign companies compared to -4.7% for U.S. companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of restatements on Chinese companies is even more pronounced. Their average abnormal returns are -9.4%.  This is due in no small part to Luckin Coffee, which had abnormal returns of -92% following their restatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Abnormal%20Returns%20for%20Restatements%20by%20country.png&quot; alt=&quot;Abnormal Returns for Restatements by country.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuing disparity in abnormal returns between U.S. companies and foreign companies may indicate a confidence deficit. It appears that investor confidence is more easily shaken by a foreign restatement than by a domestic one. This seems to be particularly true of Chinese companies, a situation that has been greatly exasperated by &lt;em&gt;The Luckin Effect&lt;/em&gt;. This confidence deficit help explain why foreign companies—especially Chinese companies—are more appetizing targets for short sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not sure how long &lt;em&gt;The Luckin Effect&lt;/em&gt; will last, but it seems possible that the mere passage of time will not restore confidence in Chinese companies. Confidence is more likely to be restored by some sort of event demonstrating that the systemic weaknesses revealed by the Luckin fraud are being seriously addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese companies make up nearly a quarter of all offshore U.S. listed companies and their probability for being named in a securities class action surpasses that any other country. In 2020, this increase appears to be largely due to &lt;em&gt;The Luckin Effect&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that U.S. and foreign companies trade seamlessly on U.S. exchanges, the truth is that these two types of companies operate in very different legal and regulatory environments. The risks associated with Chinese companies in particular are substantially different from U.S. companies, and investors, lenders, insurers and other financial professionals are wise to consider these differences when evaluating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This summary is based on our Foreign Restatements and Securities Class Actions report authored by Joseph Burke and John Cheffers. The source material for our research primarily comes from Audit Analytics, with share price data coming from Shardar. If you would like access to the complete report at no cost, please email jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. Watchdog Research generates independent research on overall trends, as well as company-specific reports.  If you want to learn more about us, visit our website, or email our President Brian Lawe via blawe@watchdogreseach.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Foreign Companies" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="China" /><category term="Financial Restatements" /><summary type="html">Foreign companies have played an increasingly relevant role on the NYSE and NASDAQ over the last decade and currently comprise over 20% of those exchanges. We recently completed a report on the particular risks by foreign listings entitled Foreign Restatements and Securities Class Actions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/China%20Flags.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/China%20Flags.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Impact of Securities Lawsuits</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-securities-lawsuits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Impact of Securities Lawsuits" /><published>2021-03-12T10:34:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-12T10:34:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-securities-lawsuits</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-impact-of-securities-lawsuits/">&lt;p&gt;In our research on securities class action lawsuits, we measure the impact of lawsuits by looking at abnormal returns over the 30-day period following a securities lawsuit. We calculate the abnormal returns by comparing how the company performed to how the S&amp;amp;P 500 performed on average over the same 30-day period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if the S&amp;amp;P 500 rose 10% in the 30-days following a lawsuit against company X, and the company X’s stock remained at the same price during that period, then we calculate an abnormal return of -10% for company X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a histogram for all the abnormal returns for all securities class actions from 2011-2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20Histogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA Histogram.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few things to note about this chart. Firstly, about one third of the time the company’s share value increases after a securities lawsuit is filed. Most people would consider getting named as a defendant in a lawsuit as bad news, so the most likely explanation for the modest increase we see in a about a third of cases comes from positive developments that cancel out the bad news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, about a third of the time the lawsuit coincides with a relatively modest underperformance by the company, with abnormal returns of zero to -10%. This is partially due to the fact that the impact of securities class actions on large companies tends to be significantly less than their impact on small companies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20impact%20by%20size.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA impact by size.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large cap companies have access to more resources that can help them mitigate the impact of a securities class action suit. Large companies can afford a PR firm and can take steps to change the media narrative. Additionally, investors may think that the lawsuit is immaterial if the company is large and wealthy enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final thing to note about the table is that it is skewed to the left. About a third of the time the company named as a defendant will have abnormal returns that are worse than -10%. In comparison, fewer than one-tenth of companies had positive returns that were better than 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data indicates that securities lawsuits pose a significant risk of intense losses for any given company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We specialize in researching accounting, legal, and regulatory issues that affect public companies. We produce reports on general trends, and granular reports on over 4,500 companies. If you want to learn more about what we do, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt; to start a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Impact Analysis" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Impact Analysis" /><summary type="html">In our research on securities class action lawsuits, we measure the impact of lawsuits by looking at abnormal returns over the 30-day period following a securities lawsuit. We calculate the abnormal returns by comparing how the company performed to how the S&amp;amp;P 500 performed on average over the same 30-day period.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SCA%20Histogram.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/SCA%20Histogram.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Restatements More Disruptive to Foreign Companies than U.S. Companies</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-more-disruptive-for-foreign-companies-than-us-companies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Restatements More Disruptive to Foreign Companies than U.S. Companies" /><published>2021-03-05T14:21:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-05T14:21:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-more-disruptive-for-foreign-companies-than-us-companies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-more-disruptive-for-foreign-companies-than-us-companies/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Investor Confidence in Foreign Companies is More Easily Shaken&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our regular readers are aware that we regularly put out reports on the impact that restatements, securities litigation, and material weaknesses have on public companies. Currently we are working on a report that will meld some of this analysis with a special focus on foreign companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our report, and this article, a foreign company is defined as a company that is incorporated outside the United States, but publicly traded the Nasdaq or NYSE. These companies have different filing requirements than publicly traded companies incorporated in the United States. They use different forms and are exempt from certain disclosure requirements (e.g. insiders only &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-insider-trading-and-stock-pledging/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; on ownership and trading activity once a year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past ten years restatements have had a far greater negative impact on foreign companies than on U.S. companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%20Returns%20by%20Region.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements Returns by Region.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Question of Confidence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Share prices reflect the confidence of investors and the market. When a company issues a restatement, that can undermine the confidence of investors and result in a decline in stock price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research shows that the reaction to a restatement by a foreign company is more severe than the reaction to a restatement by a domestic company. This leads us to believe that the confidence of investors in foreign companies is more easily shaken than for domestic companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it another way, investors are not as confident in the stability of foreign companies as they are in of U.S. companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Implications&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One implication is that foreign companies are a much more appetizing target for activist &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-short-reports-fuel-lawsuits-against-chinese-companies/&quot;&gt;short sellers&lt;/a&gt;. Our research indicates that investors lose confidence in foreign companies more easily, so a damaging short report is more likely to generate strong returns for the short seller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another implication is that foreign companies who file restatements are an easier target for plaintiff’s firms, which can use the price swings following an event like a restatement to establish damages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We provide independent research on public companies, ETFs, and portfolios.  Our clients include D&amp;amp;O insurers, buy-side analysts, and consultants.  Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Restatements" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Financial Restatements" /><category term="Foreign Companies" /><summary type="html">Investor Confidence in Foreign Companies is More Easily Shaken</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/globe.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/globe.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2020: U.S. Restatements Fall to 10-Year Low</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-us-restatements-fall-to-10-year-low/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2020: U.S. Restatements Fall to 10-Year Low" /><published>2021-02-26T12:32:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-26T12:32:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-us-restatements-fall-to-10-year-low</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-us-restatements-fall-to-10-year-low/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;U.S. companies filed 42 restatements in 2020, the fewest ever.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 was a difficult year for most companies. The coronavirus pandemic has ravaged industries and impacted how nearly every company does its business. One bright spot for U.S. public companies was that their probability of filing a restatement fell to an all-time low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Restatements%202020.png&quot; alt=&quot;Restatements 2020.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that these numbers do not include restatements from foreign companies, nor do they include “revisions” that are disclosed outside of the annual or quarterly filings. We are going to address those topics in a later report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is derived from “2020: Frequency and Impact of Restatements” a research report produced by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD, for Watchdog Research. If you are interested in accessing the entire report, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Restatements and Securities Class Action Suits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restatements are often followed by a securities class action suit. The reason is simple enough. A company usually files a restatement to correct mistakes that they made due to an internal control problem. This correction results in a loss of confidence and a drop in the share price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaintiff’s attorneys then file a lawsuit claiming that the management of the company intentionally made misrepresentations in the past (which have now been corrected in the restatement). The drop in share price helps establish damages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every restatement will result in a lawsuit for a variety of reasons, but there is a well-established pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year restatements and securities class action &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-short-reports-fuel-lawsuits-against-chinese-companies/&quot;&gt;lawsuits&lt;/a&gt; both declined. Securities lawsuits do not always follow the restatement trend considering that restatements have trended down over the past decade while securities class action lawsuits hit historic &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm/&quot;&gt;highs&lt;/a&gt; over the last three years. But the number of restatements remains a significant contributing factor to the overall number of securities class action lawsuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restatements were down significantly for U.S. companies in 2020, reaching a new low. It is not clear if this decline has something to do with the coronavirus, or if it is simply the continuation of a long-term trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decline in restatements has likely contributed to the decline in securities class action suits that also occurred in 2020, although restatements traditionally have minor impact on the overall securities class action trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We provide independent research on public companies, ETFs, and portfolios.  Our clients include D&amp;amp;O insurers, buy-side analysts, and consultants.  Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Restatements" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Financial Restatements" /><summary type="html">U.S. companies filed 42 restatements in 2020, the fewest ever.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size%20pic-6e1052.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Restatements%20by%20size%20pic-6e1052.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Biotech and Pharmaceutical Litigation in 2020</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/biotech-and-pharmaceutical-litigation-in-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biotech and Pharmaceutical Litigation in 2020" /><published>2021-02-17T11:13:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-17T11:13:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/biotech-and-pharmaceutical-litigation-in-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/biotech-and-pharmaceutical-litigation-in-2020/">&lt;p&gt;Companies sustained record-setting levels of securities class action suits in 2017, 2018, and 2019 after the Supreme Court’s decision in &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm/&quot;&gt;Cyan&lt;/a&gt; threw open the doors of the state courts to traditionally federal securities litigation. In 2020, the number of securities class action suits filed receded from these all-time highs, but it is unclear whether the reduction is a temporary departure from a new paradigm, or the beginning a of a return to the mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20Probability%202020.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA Probability 2020.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is partially derived from “2020: Frequency and Impact of Securities Class Actions” a research report produced by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD, for Watchdog Research. If you are interested in accessing the entire report, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trend of overall decline in 2020 does not apply to all types of cases. In a previous &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-short-reports-fuel-lawsuits-against-chinese-companies/&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; we looked at how cases against Chinese companies in 2020 bucked this trend and increased sharply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we will look at two industries, biotech, and pharmaceuticals. (Our classification system may vary slightly from others you are familiar with because we classify companies by NAICS codes.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/SCA%20biotech%20and%20pharma%202020.png&quot; alt=&quot;SCA biotech and pharma 2020.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see from the graph, suits against pharmaceuticals in 2020 declined, but remained in line with the average number of suits from 2016-2019. Suits against biotech companies remained almost identical to 2019, but the last two years are a significant downward departure from 2013-2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to draw too many conclusions from this data because the sample size is relatively small and subject to volatility. However, it is interesting that both industries were immune to whatever caused securities class actions suits to decline overall in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By our count, there were only 25 coronavirus related class action securities lawsuits in 2020. (There are some disagreements as to what should be considered a “coronavirus related” suit, which is why the count of “coronavirus cases” varies. We are shamelessly copying the count provided by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dandodiary.com/2020/07/articles/coronavirus/coronavirus-related-securities-suits-do-these-two-new-cases-count/&quot;&gt;Kevin Lacroix&lt;/a&gt;, whose blog the D&amp;amp;O Diary is a must read.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, several companies in the biotech and pharmaceutical industries were subject to coronavirus-related lawsuits. Our total was 8, accounting for a significant portion of the cases brought against pharmaceutical and biotech companies. If not for the coronavirus, these industries would have probably seen significant declines in litigation, paralleling the overall downward trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pattern may repeat again in 2021 as two of the three coronavirus-related lawsuits filed as of February 15th were against companies in the biotech and pharmaceutical industries. It appears that even if securities class actions continue to decline towards the long-term mean, there is a good chance that coronavirus-related lawsuits will keep biotech and pharmaceuticals at an elevated risk for litigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We provide independent research on public companies, ETFs, and portfolios.  Our clients include D&amp;amp;O insurers, buy-side analysts, and consultants.  Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Securities Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><category term="Pharmaceuticals" /><category term="Biotech" /><summary type="html">Companies sustained record-setting levels of securities class action suits in 2017, 2018, and 2019 after the Supreme Court’s decision in Cyan threw open the doors of the state courts to traditionally federal securities litigation. In 2020, the number of securities class action suits filed receded from these all-time highs, but it is unclear whether the reduction is a temporary departure from a new paradigm, or the beginning a of a return to the mean.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Legal-ec0bcb.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Legal-ec0bcb.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Review of 2020’s High-Risk Companies</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/review-of-2020-s-high-risk-companies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review of 2020’s High-Risk Companies" /><published>2021-02-15T09:27:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T09:27:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/review-of-2020-s-high-risk-companies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/review-of-2020-s-high-risk-companies/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Five large-cap companies that we categorized as “high-risk” struggled throughout the year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Watchdog Research, we provide independent reports on publicly traded companies. Each company has two reports, a Watchdog Report, and a Gray Swan Event Factor Report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Watchdog Reports use red, yellow, and green flags to make it easy to spot potential governance, accounting, legal, and oversight issues. Our Gray Swan Event Factor (GSEF) estimates what kind of negative impact a company’s past will have on their future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most companies have a relatively low GSEF score, in January 2020, only 5 large cap companies had scores over 5% (our threshold for considering a company “high-risk”). Here is a histogram of the GSEF scores for large cap companies. As you can see, even scoring above 2% is unusual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Histogram%20GSEF.png&quot; alt=&quot;Histogram GSEF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought it would be fun to revisit the high-risk companies after such an interesting year and see how they performed in 2020. When we look at each company, we will look at their GSEF on January 1, 2020, returns in 2020, any major red flags, and offer a brief analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the aggregate, the few companies that we categorized as high-risk performed abysmally in comparison to the S&amp;amp;P 500, which gained 16.26% in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/High%20Risk%20v.%20S&amp;amp;P.png&quot; alt=&quot;High Risk v. S&amp;amp;P.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Kraft Heinz (KHC)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11.15% GSEF: Extreme Risk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return in 2020: 9.65%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Red Flags:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019 Kraft Heinz issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-warren-buffets-dunkirk/&quot;&gt;restatement&lt;/a&gt; impairing $15.9 billion in goodwill and intangible assets and disclosing serious internal control issues. In response, share prices fell by approximately 25%. The chaos from this restatement continued into 2020 as KHC was subject to multiple lawsuits, including a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/kraft-heinz-complaint-alleges-fundamental-corporate-governance-problems-accounting-shenanigans-and-insider-trading/&quot;&gt;derivative suit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kraft Heinz has slowly been recovering from its catastrophic fall in 2019. KHC stated in its second quarterly report that they have addressed the material weaknesses in their internal controls. However, KHC also impaired an additional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1637459/000163745920000159/khc-20200926.htm&quot;&gt;$3.4 billion&lt;/a&gt; in goodwill and intangible assets in the first nine months of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kraft Heinz has survived 2020. Their survival may be due in part to the coronavirus. It was a good year to sell comfort food in grocery stores. Buying the familiar brands under the Kraft Heinz umbrella probably gave people a much-needed sense of normalcy in an otherwise abnormal year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible that 2020 could have been a tremendous year for Kraft Heinz, but their past accounting issues and ongoing impairments may have kept them from properly rebounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Bristol Myers Squibb (BMY)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6.81% GSEF: High Risk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return in 2020: -2.07%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Red Flags:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/bristol-myers-squibb-slash-celgene-merger/&quot;&gt;BMY merger&lt;/a&gt; with Celgene closed in 2019. When two companies of comparable size merge, the surviving company will typically underproduce in comparison to their peers for about &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/borgwarner-wants-to-dump-delphi-will-delphis-resistance-be-futile/&quot;&gt;two years&lt;/a&gt;. This is because the surviving company must attempt to integrate two completely different companies, each with their own set of problems and peculiarities. The “synergies” often are mere puffery that never materialize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting issues that arise out of a merger usually do not surface for at least a year. This is partly because accounting rules will allow companies to delay internal control assessments for the first year. So, it may take until 2022 to get a clear picture of the any challenges posed by BMY’s merger with Celgene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would also note that BMY has not had a comment letter with the SEC since late 2018. A company of that size is typically reviewed every year and the letters are not released until some weeks after the conversation ends, so it is possible that they are working on some complicated issues. A lack of comment letters can also be due to an undisclosed SEC investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BMY is suffering from the typical malaise that strikes companies post-merger. Since they do not produce vaccines and did not quickly develop a therapeutic for the coronavirus (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/14272/000001427221000066/bmy-20201231.htm&quot;&gt;currently&lt;/a&gt; they have a therapeutic in phase I of testing), they missed out on the government contracts and hype that so many other companies in the medical field benefitted from this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Baxter International Inc (BAX)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.24% GSEF: High Risk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return in 2020: -6.56%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Red Flags:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, BAX had to delay its 10-k for 2019 because of internal control issues and a pending restatement. That restatement was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/10456/000162828020003693/bax-20191231.htm&quot;&gt;issued&lt;/a&gt; shortly thereafter and restated figures from 2017, 2018, and 2019. It has led to several serious and ongoing problems, including a costly securities class action suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last comment letter from the SEC was in 2017, even though it is likely that BAX is reviewed every year because of its size. In 2018, BAX’s numbers did not conform to Benford’s law. The presence of Benford’s law anomalies and the absence of comment letters both can be associated with an undisclosed SEC investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After disclosing the restatement, BAX warned that they may be subject to SEC enforcement. They did not say if their disclosure was due to an ongoing investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baxter is the only company on this short list whose GSEF was higher at the end of 2020 than at the beginning. They have had a challenging year. It is &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/restatements-are-rare-but-can-pack-a-punch/&quot;&gt;typical&lt;/a&gt; for companies that issue a restatement to suffer stock declines has investor confidence plummets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BAX produces medical devices, which is a growing field, but many of their customers (hospitals and similar businesses) experienced slow-downs this year as people shied away from receiving non-emergency care during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Lumen Technologies (LUMN) (formerly CenturyLink)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.74% GSEF: High Risk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return in 2020: -17.36%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Red Flags:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lumen Technologies did not file their 10-k &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/18926/000119312519061757/d706860dnt10k.htm&quot;&gt;on time&lt;/a&gt; in 2019 due to a restatement. They also revealed internal control issues that were not fully resolved until the following year. As usually happens, the restatement resulted in a securities class action suit that is still ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lumen’s stock dropped during March, like every other company, but unlike many other companies, it did not recover. This is mysterious considering that the coronavirus did not appear to have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://seekingalpha.com/article/4396578-shedding-light-on-lumen-technologies&quot;&gt;material impact&lt;/a&gt; on operations. Their poor returns this year may have to do more with a lack of confidence in their attempt to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crn.com/news/networking/centurylink-changes-name-to-lumen-technologies-intros-smb-fiber-offering#:\~:text=and%20Technology%20Integrators-,CenturyLink%20Changes%20Name%20To%20Lumen%20Technologies%2C%20Intros%20SMB%20Fiber%20Offering,SMB%20services%2C%20the%20carrier%20said.&quot;&gt;revamp&lt;/a&gt; their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. TechnipFMC Plc. (FTI)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6.02% GSEF: High Risk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return in 2020: -55.93%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major Red Flags:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FTI issued a restatement in 2017 and had material weaknesses in 2017, 2018, and 2019. FTI also has made 11 changes to accounting estimates in the last three years. In 2020, changes in accounting estimates had a positive impact of over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/1681459/000168145919000104/technipfmc2019930-10q.htm#s31BD284795D659A194AE3E47EDF9B1B2&quot;&gt;$340 million&lt;/a&gt;. However, in 2019, the company also issued an impairment of $1.79 billion. FTI’s CFO departed in January 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their independent auditor’s critical audit matters disclosures highlighted risks in revenue recognition concerning long term contracts. FTI’s auditors warn that the estimates involved in these estimates require a lot of judgement and are subjective.  Uncertainty concerning revenue recognition is always a red flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FTI was removed from the S&amp;amp;P 500. This is partly because of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://seekingalpha.com/news/3649692-technipfmc-resumes-planned-split-via-energies-spinoff&quot;&gt;spinoff&lt;/a&gt;, but primarily because they were one of the worst performers in the S&amp;amp;P 500 during 2020. FTI’s industry, oil and gas, was hit particularly hard by a loss of demand due to the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stock prices reflect the confidence and enthusiasm of the market. Accounting, governance, regulatory and legal issues rarely have a significant impact on stock price, unless problems in those areas manifest themselves in a way that dashes the market’s confidence in a company. Our GSEF metric can serve as a proxy for evaluating potential challenges a company will have in keeping (or regaining) the confidence of the market.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Red Flags" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Gray Swan Event" /><category term="Returns" /><category term="coronavirus" /><summary type="html">Five large-cap companies that we categorized as “high-risk” struggled throughout the year.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Gray%20Swan.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Gray%20Swan.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">FINRA May Change Rules of the Game for Online Brokers</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finra-may-change-the-rules-of-the-game-for-online-brokers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FINRA May Change Rules of the Game for Online Brokers" /><published>2021-02-12T11:52:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T11:52:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finra-may-change-the-rules-of-the-game-for-online-brokers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finra-may-change-the-rules-of-the-game-for-online-brokers/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Recent guidance on “game-like” features from FINRA should concern every online broker.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many media stories, the GameStop saga loomed large and made people feel that everything was about to change. But the moment has passed, and the media has moved onto the next novelty. But for online brokers, this story may end up having a lasting impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting aspect of the GameStop saga was that many online brokers, most notably Robinhood, restricted their customer’s ability to buy certain volatile stocks, like GameStop. This exercise of direct control over the customers’ accounts was unusual and created an absolute uproar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a great deal of anger, some people even called for the brokers to be sent to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UaPgBtf5m6w&quot;&gt;prison&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to get into the weeds on why Robinhood halted trading, you should read Francine Mckenna’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedig.substack.com/p/robinhoods-capital-and-customer-fund&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finra.org/rules-guidance/guidance/reports/2021-finras-examination-and-risk-monitoring-program/communications-with-public&quot;&gt;guidance&lt;/a&gt; FINRA focused on online brokers who are attracting a great deal of interest from retail investors. They are primarily concerned by online apps that “include interactive and “game-like” features, as well as related forms of advertising and marketing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FINRA has expressed concern that these features, which may improve the customer’s experience, will increase risk for retail investors. In their guidance, FINRA tells brokers that they must evaluate these “game-like” features to see if they “&lt;em&gt;constitute a ‘recommendation’ that requires a broker-dealer to act in a retail customer’s ‘best interest.’&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guidance directly undermines a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/online-brokers-are-dot-dot-dot-not-brokers/&quot;&gt;key position&lt;/a&gt; held by online brokers. For years, these brokers have required customers to sign agreements stating that they do not rely on their brokers for advice or recommendations; these agreements create paper shields that protect the brokers from liability and leaves the customers bereft of the suitability protections traditionally granted by the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a case decided in 2006, online platforms are not required to provide suitable recommendations because they do not have “&lt;a href=&quot;https://casetext.com/case/williams-v-scottrade&quot;&gt;discretionary authority&lt;/a&gt;” over their customers accounts. That legal assessment was obliterated when Robinhood and other online brokers took control over their users accounts in the name of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cuCcchMOsKE&quot;&gt;protecting their customers&lt;/a&gt; from volatility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a somewhat related note, it is curious that the SEC allows ETF managers complete discretion to set an index and pick stocks without any consideration of whether the strategies or underlying are suitable for the ETF purchasers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FINRA’s focus on game-like features punches another hole in the online brokers’ paper shield. FINRA’s guidance explicitly expresses concern about the features that come with the mobile investing app that Robinhood pioneered and most online brokers shamelessly &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.crunchbase.com/news/robinhood-changed-online-trading-but-can-it-repeat-the-feat/&quot;&gt;copied&lt;/a&gt;. But FINRA’s concerns are not isolated to mobile investing, they are worried about how online brokers are influencing their customer’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finra.org/sites/default/files/2021-02/2021-report-finras-examination-risk-monitoring-program.pdf&quot;&gt;behavior&lt;/a&gt; with their features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Such &lt;strong&gt;features affect&lt;/strong&gt; … &lt;strong&gt;how firms interact and communicate with customers&lt;/strong&gt;, from initial advertisements through the opening of accounts, recommendations and the presentation of different investment choices.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this guidance FINRA is opening the door to examining the relationships formed between online brokers and their customers, regardless of what the registration agreement says. And the scope of that potential examination is exceptionally broad, covering advertisements, marketing materials, and the website interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FINRA may be contemplating some changes that will affect how every online broker does business. But instead of running from the legal obligation that brokers act in the best interests of their customers and provide suitable recommendations, they should find creative ways to meet these obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They could provide a suite of tools that allow investors to easily understand and evaluate the risks that come with investing in any investment vehicle, from single stocks to ETFs. If those risk profiles were the product of unbiased and independent research, then it would be easier to convince FINRA that their features were not unduly influential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We provide independent research on public companies, ETFs, and portfolios.  Our clients include D&amp;amp;O insurers, buy-side analysts, and consultants.  Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Online Brokers" /><category term="featured" /><category term="Online Brokers" /><category term="FINRA" /><summary type="html">Recent guidance on “game-like” features from FINRA should concern every online broker.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Online%20Brokerage.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/Online%20Brokerage.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2020: Short Reports Fuel Lawsuits Against Chinese Companies</title><link href="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-short-reports-fuel-lawsuits-against-chinese-companies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2020: Short Reports Fuel Lawsuits Against Chinese Companies" /><published>2021-02-08T14:38:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T14:38:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-short-reports-fuel-lawsuits-against-chinese-companies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/2020-short-reports-fuel-lawsuits-against-chinese-companies/">&lt;p&gt;There are more publicly traded companies from China on U.S. exchanges than from any other foreign country, including Canada. We have already covered how Chinese companies get &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/only-the-good-die-young-chinese-delistings-part-i/&quot;&gt;delisted&lt;/a&gt; at higher rates than companies from other countries. Here we will look at the dramatic increase in securities class action lawsuits filed against Chinese companies over the past five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is partially derived from “2020: Frequency and Impact of Securities Class Actions” a research report produced by Joseph Burke, PhD, and Joseph Yarborough, PhD, for Watchdog Research. If you are interested in accessing the entire report, email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&quot;&gt;jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/the-post-cyan-paradigm/&quot;&gt;Cyan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, there was a sharp increase in the number of securities lawsuits filed across the board, but that increase was not evenly distributed. In 2016, Chinese companies only had a 2.7% probability of being named as a defendant in a securities class action suit. From 2016-2019 that probability increased every year, but it remained less than the average probability for all companies, until 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, the overall probability that a company would be named in a securities class action suit fell below its historical high rates from 2017-2019. But the rates for Chinese companies moved in the opposite direction, shooting upwards to 9.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20SCAs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese SCAs.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short Reports Are Driving Litigation Against Chinese Issuers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone is familiar with the fall of Luckin Coffee, a Chinese unicorn purported to be the “Chinese Starbucks.” On January 31st, 2020, Muddy Waters announced it was short Luckin Coffee based on an anonymous 89-page short report. In April, Luckin Coffee &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-i/&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that up to a third of its revenues and a substantial portion of its expenses from 2019 were fabrications. Luckin was delisted shortly after these revelations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February, after Muddy Waters’ short report but before Luckin’s admission of fraud, the law firm Pomerantz LLP filed suit in the Southern District of New York against Luckin. Once Luckin disclosed the extensive fraud, another lawsuit was filed and eventually consolidated into the original suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This case is both emblematic and an exception to the symbiotic relationship that appears to have developed between short sellers and plaintiff’s attorneys. Short sellers will typically publish reports alleging fraud at a company, resulting in a panicked sell-off. Afterwards, a plaintiff’s firm will file a lawsuit against the company, using the facts alleged in the short report to assert some sort of misrepresentation and use the loss in share value from the sell-off to prove damages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of Luckin was an exception because the short report was rapidly followed up by an admission of fraud and complete collapse, ultimately resulting in Luckin’s delisting. Generally, short reports do not result in the delisting of the targeted company. The impact of Muddy Waters’ success has already had tremendous implications in 2020 and will continue to echo in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imitation as Flattery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exceptional result for Muddy Waters seems to have encouraged other short sellers to target Chinese listed companies. By the end of 2020, 12 of the 28 securities class action suits filed against Chinese companies were based on short reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Chinese%20SCAs%20reason.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese SCAs reason.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muddy Waters followed up its own success with a short report for GSX. Wolfpack Research filed four separate reports on four different Chinese issuers. Hindenburg Research, fresh off its victory over Nikola Motors, issued a report on the Chinese company Kandi Technology. All these reports (as well as several others filed by Grizzly Research and Marcus Aurelius Value) resulted in lawsuits against the companies targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the courts will attempt to sever the seemingly inseparable duo of short sellers and plaintiff’s firms, but such a dramatic change is unlikely if even possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have previously discussed many of the systemic problems in China: the lax &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-insider-trading-and-stock-pledging/&quot;&gt;foreign&lt;/a&gt; reporting requirements, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/divided-loyalty-something-is-rotten-in-beijing/&quot;&gt;corporate governance&lt;/a&gt; flaws, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/america-runs-from-luckin-clash-over-pcaob/&quot;&gt;lack&lt;/a&gt; of meaningful oversight for their auditors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems make it plausible that China has a serious and systemic &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/posts/finding-fraud-chinese-delistings-part-ii/&quot;&gt;fraud&lt;/a&gt; problem. To help factor in this risk for our clients, we penalize every Chinese company by automatically boosting their gray swan event risk factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While more investors are becoming skeptical of Chinese companies, Western capital continues to flow into China. This abundance of fear and greed creates an ideal environment for short sellers. We suspect that short sellers will continue to target Chinese companies at elevated levels in 2021 and that securities class actions will follow closely behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact Us&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;O insurers spend a lot of time on new bid requests. Our clients use our Watchdog Reports to quickly discover which bids they should pursue. Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec2-52-26-194-35.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com/x/d?c=10148055&amp;amp;l=8f486791-a4a8-4367-af11-bf1f39ebc6c7&amp;amp;r=dc393d8e-9c53-4da8-a628-9317a0b2abeb&quot;&gt;here &lt;/a&gt; to request a free demo. Special offers available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this blog, contact John Cheffers at jcheffers@watchdogresearch.com. For general or press inquires, contact our President Brian Lawe at blawe@watchdogresearch.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>john_cheffers</name></author><category term="Securities Litigation" /><category term="featured" /><category term="China" /><category term="Securites Litigation" /><summary type="html">There are more publicly traded companies from China on U.S. exchanges than from any other foreign country, including Canada. We have already covered how Chinese companies get delisted at higher rates than companies from other countries. Here we will look at the dramatic increase in securities class action lawsuits filed against Chinese companies over the past five years.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/China%20SCA.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.watchdogresearch.com/uploads/China%20SCA.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>